<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HTN_1</Tag>
		<English>I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE], and I come to the [CT_EMPIRE] in search of what is new and undiscovered!</English>
		<French>Je suis [OUR_NAME] de [OUR_EMPIRE], et je viens vers l'[CT_EMPIRE] à la recherche de ce qui est nouveau et inconnu!</French>
		<Polish>Jestem [OUR_NAME] z [OUR_EMPIRE], i przybywam do [CT_EMPIRE] w poszukiwaniu nieodrytego i niepoznanego!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HTN</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Henry the Navigator</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Henry le Navigateur</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Enrico il Navigatore</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>
			<Text>Henryk Żeglarz</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HTN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Henry the Navigator[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prince of the House of Aviz[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1394 - 1460[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]The Infante Henrique, Duke of Viseu was an infante (prince) of the Portuguese House of Aviz and an important figure in the early days of the Portuguese Empire, being responsible for the beginning of the European worldwide explorations. He is known in English as Prince Henry the Navigator.[PARAGRAPH:1]Prince Henry the Navigator was the third child of King John I of Portugal, the founder of the Aviz dynasty, and of Philippa of Lancaster, the daughter of John of Gaunt. Henry encouraged his father to conquer Ceuta (1415), the Muslim port on the North African coast across the Straits of Gibraltar from the Iberian peninsula, with profound consequences on Henry's worldview: Henry became aware of the profit possibilities in the Saharan trade routes that terminated there and became fascinated with Africa in general; he was most intrigued by the Christian legend of Prester John and the expansion of Portuguese trade.[PARAGRAPH:1]It is a common conception that Henry gathered at his Vila on the Sagres peninsula a school of navigators and map-makers. He did employ some cartographers to help him chart the coast of Mauritania in the wake of voyages he sent there, but for the rest there was no center of navigational science or any supposed observatory in the modern sense of the word, nor was there an organized navigational center. In “Crónica da Guiné” Henry is described as a person with no luxuries, not avaricious, speaking with soft words and calm gestures, a man of many virtues that never allowed any poor person leave his presence empty handed.[PARAGRAPH:1]Until Henry's time, Cape Bojador remained the most southerly point known to Europeans on the unpromising desert coast of Africa, although the Periplus of the Carthaginian Hanno the Navigator described a journey farther south about 2,000 years earlier.[PARAGRAPH:1]He functioned as a primary organizer of the Portuguese expedition to Tangier in 1437. This proved a disastrous failure; Henry's younger brother Fernando was given as a hostage to guarantee that the Portuguese would fulfill the terms of the peace agreement that had been made with Çala Ben Çala. The agreement was first broken by the Moors, who attacked the Portuguese and captured the Portuguese wounded when they were being carried to the ships, killing those who tried to resist. The Archbishop of Braga and the count of Arraiolos refused to approve the terms in the reunion of the Portuguese Cortes, thus condemning Fernando to remain in miserable captivity until his death eleven years later. Henry for most of his last twenty-three years concentrated on his exploration activities, or on Portuguese court politics.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Henryk Żeglarz[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Książę Rodu Aviz[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 1394 - 1460[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]infant, trzeci syn króla Portugalii Jana I Dobrego i Filipy Lancaster. Uważany za twórcę portugalskiego imperium kolonialnego. W 1415 otrzymał tytuł księcia Viseu i pana Covilha, a w 1417 został wielkim mistrzem Zakonu Rycerzy Chrystusa. Uważany jest za patrona rozwoju floty portugalskiej i odkryć geograficznych, założyciela uniwersytetu w Lizbonie oraz szkoły kartografii i astronomii w Sagres, uznawanej za pierwszą akademię morską na świecie. Przypisuje mu się także wynalazek karaweli, choć nie ma na to bezpośrednich dowodów. Przydomek Żeglarz nadano mu kilkaset lat po jego śmierci, chociaż nigdy nie pływał na statkach.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>