<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_HARUN_1</Tag>
		<English>Of course you can refuse me this favor if you want, but it you do, I wouldn't hang out at the markets tonight...</English>
		<French>Bien sûr, vous pouvez me refuser cette faveur, si vous voulez, mais il vous le faites, je vous conseille de ne pas traîner dans les rues le soir...</French>
		<Polish>Oczywiście możesz odwdzięczyć się mi za tą przysługę, ale jeśli nie chcesz to nie musisz...</Polish>
		<Russian>Конечно, вы можете отказать мне в этом одолжении, если хотите, но если вы это сделаете, я бы не стал торчать сегодня на базарах...</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_HARUN_1</Tag>
		<English>If you give this to me, I will not have to split your body in two. What do you say?</English>
		<French>Si vous donnez cela, je n'aurai pas à couper votre corps en deux. Qu'en dites-vous?</French>
		<Polish>Jeśli oddasz mi to czego chcę to nie rozrąbię Cie na pół. Co o tym sądzisz?</Polish>
		<Russian>Если ты отдашь это мне, мне не придется разрубать твое тело пополам. Каков твой ответ?</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_HARUN_1</Tag>
		<English>After all the lavish gifts I've given you, it wouldn't be much to return the favor with this tiny, insignificant gift, now would it?</English>
		<French>Après tous les cadeaux somptueux que je vous ai donnés, ce ne serait pas grand'chose pour vous de rendre la pareille avec ce petit cadeau insignifiant, n'est-ce pas?</French>
		<Polish>Po wszystkich drogocennych prezentach jakie Ci posłałem, miłym byłoby dostać coś od Ciebie.</Polish>
		<Russian>После всех щедрых даров, которые я тебе прислал, вы бы не понесли ущерба, если бы отплатили нам этим крошечным, незначительным подарком, не так ли?</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HARUN_1</Tag>
		<English>I've told my men what is coming... [CT_NAME], lord of [CT_CIV_SHORT], has come upon the [OUR_EMPIRE] to visit its ruler - I, [OUR_NAME]!</English>
		<French>J'ai dit à mes hommes ce qui suit ... [CT_NAME], seigneur de [CT_CIV_SHORT], est venu vers l'[OUR_EMPIRE] pour visiter son chef - Moi, [OUR_NAME]!</French>
		<Polish>[CT_NAME], lord of [CT_CIV_SHORT], has come upon the [OUR_EMPIRE] to visit its ruler - I, [OUR_NAME]!</Polish>
		<Russian>Мои приближенные донесли, что прибыл... [CT_NAME], властитель [CT_CIV_SHORT], пришел на землю [OUR_EMPIRE], чтобы посетить ее правителя - меня, [OUR_NAME]!</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_HARUN_1</Tag>
		<English>It's marvelous to see you again, [CT_NAME]. Take these white elephants home with you. They're all yours!</English>
		<French>C'est merveilleux de vous revoir, [CT_NAME]. Prenez ces éléphants blancs avec vous. Ils sont vôtres à présent!</French>
		<Polish>Cudownie jest znowu Cię zobaczyć, [CT_NAME]. Weź proszę w podarku te białe słonie. Są wszytkie Twoje!</Polish>
		<Russian>Рад видеть вас снова, [CT_NAME]. Прими в дар этих белых слонов. Отныне они все твои!</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_HARUN_1</Tag>
		<English>Oh, hello, [CT_NAME]. I wouldn't be surprised if it was you who stole my lute.</English>
		<French>Oh, bonjour, [CT_NAME]. Je ne serais pas surpris si c'était toi qui a volé mon luth.</French>
		<Polish>Oh, witam, [CT_NAME]. Nie zdziwił bym się, jeśli to ty byś był odpowiedzialny za kradzież mojej lutni.</Polish>
		<Russian>Мир тебе, [CT_NAME]. Не удивлюсь, если это ты украл мою лютню.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_HARUN_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace? Are you kidding around with me, [CT_NAME]?</English>
		<French>Paix? Vous vous moquez de moi, [CT_NAME]?</French>
		<Polish>Pokój? Raczysz sobie żartować, [CT_NAME]?</Polish>
		<Russian>Мир? Вы шутите надо мной, [CT_NAME]?</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_HARUN_1</Tag>
		<English>Kiss the sole of my foot, she-pig!</English>
		<French>Embrasse ma plante du pied, Bâtard!</French>
		<Polish>Całuj moje stopy, świnio!</Polish>
		<Russian>Поцелуй мою ногу, свинья!</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HARUN</Tag>
		<English>Harun al-Rashid</English>
		<Russian>Õàðóí àð-Ðàøèä</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HARUN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Harun al-Rashid[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]5th Abbasid Caliph[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 763 - 809[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2]Harun al-Rashid was the fifth and most famous of the Abbasid Caliphs, he was born near present day Tehran to al-Mahdi the Caliph of the Abbasid Empire and a slave girl from Yemen. While his mother came from quite humble beginnings she was very influential during the reign of her husband and for much of Harun's reign. Born into his position, Harun had developed quite an egotistical and arrogant attitude, however he was an apt and capable ruler. he began his reign by appointing very able ministers who were able to greatly improve the condition of his people. It was under Harun that Baghdad flourished into the most splendid city of its period, Harun's focus was on architecture, the arts adn a luxurious life at court. Harun gave great encouragement to learning, poetry and music. He was a scholar and poet himself and whenever he heard of learned men in his Empire, or in neighboring countries, he invited them to his court and treated them with great respect, regardless of their nationality or religious beliefs. He was known worldwide, he had diplomatic relations from Charlemagne's court in Europe to the farthest reaches of China. Harun is widely considered the greatest of the Abbasid caliphs, presiding over the Arab Empire at its political and cultural zenith. Consequently, Islamic literature has raised him to the level of an ideal figure, a great military and intellectual leader, even a paragon for future rulers to emulate. His best-known portrayal in the West, in the stories of the Thousand and One Nights, has little basis in historical fact, but does show the mythic stature he has attained over time.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Harun al-Rashid[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]5-ty Kalif Abbasydów[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 763 - 809[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2]Piąty i najbardziej znany kalif (od 786) z dynastii Abbasydów, ojciec kalifów Al Mamuna, Al-Amina i Al-Mutasima. Jeden z najwybitniejszych władców muzułmańskich, mecenas nauki i sztuki. W Europie zyskał popularność jako bohater Księgi tysiąca i jednej nocy. Był ostatnim kalifem, który brał osobisty udział w hadżdżu, pielgrzymce do Mekki i Medyny. Idealizowany (np. przez historyka Ibn Kasira) jako najzdolniejszy z władców abbasydzkich, u szczytu świetności kulturalnej i politycznej kalifatu. Na Zachodzie najlepiej znany jako bohater cyklu "Tysiąca i jednej nocy", baśni, wytworu naiwnej fantazji ludowej, który możny porównać z naszymi legendami o królu Kazimierzu Wielkim, jako "królu chłopskim".</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Харун ар-Рашид[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Пятый аббасидский халиф[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни: [\BOLD]763 - 809 гг.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Харун аль-Рашид был пятым и самым известным из аббасидских халифов, он родился около нынешнего Тегерана у аль-Махди, халифа Аббасидской империи и девушки-рабыни из Йемена. Хотя его мать происходила из довольно скромных семей, она была очень влиятельной во время правления своего мужа и на протяжении большей части правления Харуна. Родившись в этом положении, Харун развил довольно эгоистичное и высокомерное отношение, однако он был энергичным и способным правителем. Его правление началось с назначения очень способных визирей, которые смогли значительно улучшить положение его народа. Именно при Харуне Багдад превратился в самый великолепный город своего времени. Харун сосредоточился на архитектуре, искусстве и роскошной жизни при дворе. Харун очень поощрял просвещение, поэзию и музыку. Он сам был ученым и поэтом, и всякий раз, когда он слышал об образованных людях в своей Империи или в соседних странах, он приглашал их ко двору и относился к ним с большим уважением, независимо от их национальности или религиозных убеждений. Он был известен во всем мире, у него были дипломатические отношения от двора Карла Великого в Европе до самых отдаленных уголков Китая. Харун широко считается величайшим из халифов Аббасидов, правящим Арабской империей в период ее политического и культурного зенита. Следовательно, исламская литература подняла его до уровня идеальной фигуры, великого военного и интеллектуального лидера, даже образца для подражания будущим правителям. Его наиболее известное на Западе изображение в рассказах «Тысячи и одной ночи» имеет мало исторических фактов, но все же показывает мифический статус, которого он достиг с течением времени.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>