<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_EJE_SONG</Tag>
		<English>Eje Song</English>
		<French>Chant d'Eje</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Canto di Eje</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pieśń Eje</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_EJE_SONG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Eje is the goddess of fertility and virginity in Tengriism. Eje is similar in many ways to earth-mother goddesses found in various other world religions. Literally in the Mongolian language, "eje" means "mother." The earth was considered a "mother" symbolically. Eje symbolizes fertility and protector of children. From these it is understood that Eje Umay was accepted as a mother and a guide. Also, Khagans were thought to represent Kök Tengri. Khagan wives, katuns or hatuns, were thought as Umays, too. With the help of the Eje, Katuns have babies and these babies were the guarantee of the empire. It is clear that Eje is a female spirit related with the women, mothers and children. Today, Eje is defined as a protector of women and children. These belief is seen in Tungusic peoples, Southern Siberia and in Altaic Turks. Eje is always together with child, with rare exceptions. Then when Eje leaves child for a long time, the child gets ill and shamans are involved to call Eje. The smiling of a sleeping baby shows Eje is near it; unlike smiling, crying means that Eje has left.</English>
		<Italian>Eje è la dea della fertilità e della verginità nel tengriismo. Eje è in molti modi simile alle dee madri della terra che si trovano in varie altre religioni del mondo. Letteralmente in lingua mongola, "eje" significa "madre". La terra era considerata simbolicamente una "madre". Eje simboleggia la fertilità e protegge i bambini. Da questo si capisce che Eje Umay era venerata come una madre e una guida. Inoltre, si pensava che i Khagan rappresentassero Kök Tengri. Le mogli dei Khagan, katun o hatuns, venivano anch'esse considerate Umay. Con l'aiuto di Eje, le katun avevano bambini e questi bambini erano la garanzia dell'impero. È chiaro che Eje è uno spirito femminile in relazione con le donne, madri e bambini. Oggi, Eje è definita come protettrice delle donne e dei bambini. Questa convinzione è presente nei popoli di Tinguska, della Siberia meridionale e nei Turchi degli Altai. Eje è sempre insieme con il bambino, con rare eccezioni. Se Eje lascia il bambino per lungo tempo, il bambino si ammala e gli sciamani devono chiamare Eje. Il sorriso di un bambino addormentato mostra che Eje è vicino a lui; a differenza di sorridere, piangere significa che Eje ha lasciato il bambino.</Italian>
		<Polish>Eje to boginii płodności z panteonu ludów Azji Srodkowej.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_EJE_SONG_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build Eje Song to get a free promotion for your mounted units and to increase your cities culture.</English>
		<French>Construisez le Chant d'Eje pour obtenir une promotion gratuite pour vos unités montées. Ce bâtiment augmente la culture de votre ville.</French>
		<Italian>Costruisci il Canto di Eje per fornire una promozione gratuita alle tue unià montate e per incrementare la cultura della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KING_GESAR_SONG</Tag>
		<English>King Gesar Song</English>
		<French>Le Chant du Roi Gesar</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Canto di Re Gesar</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Epopeja o Królu Gesarze</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KING_GESAR_SONG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Epic of King Gesar is the central epic poem of Tibet and much of Central Asia. With about 140 Gesar ballad singers surviving today (including singers of Tibetan, Mongolian, Buryat and Tu ethnicities), it is prized as one of the few living epics. The epic, believed to be approximately 1000 years old, concerns the fearless king Gesar (Geser), who ruled the legendary Kingdom of Ling.The epic is considered the longest literary work in the world. Although there is no one definitive compilation, if completed it would fill some 120 volumes, containing over 20 million words in more than one million verses.</English>
		<Italian>Il poema di Re Gesar è il poema epico più diffuso in Tibet e nell'Asia centrale. Al giorno d'oggi esistono ancora 140 ballate di Gesar (diffuse anche nelle etnie Tibetane, Mongole, Buryat e Tu), e questo poema epico è ritenuto uno dei pochi ancora in vita. Il poema, che si ritiene esista da circa 1000 anni, riguarda il re senza paura Gesar (Geser), che guidò il leggendario Regno di Ling.Il poema è considerato il più lungo lavoro letterario del mondo. Anche se non esiste alcun testo ufficiale, se venisse scritto riempirebbe la bellezza di 120 volumi, usando 20 milioni di parole distribuite in più di un milione di versi.</Italian>
		<Polish>Epopeja o Królu Gesarze - poemat epicki Tybetańczyków, Mongołów i mniejszości Tu zamieszkujących zachodnie i północne Chiny. Uważany za ostatnią "żywą epopeję", jako że wśród Tybetańczyków i Mongołów znaleźć można ok. 140 pieśniarzy, którzy zajmują się tą balladą[potrzebne źródło]. Uważa się, że pieśń o nieustraszonym królu Gesarze, który rządził legendarnym Królestwem Ling, ma ponad 1000 lat. Opowiada ona dzieje życia legendarnych i historycznych bohaterów środkowej Azji. Korzenie tej legendy sięgają początków buddyzmu tybetańskiego, zawiera ona również wiele alegorii do nauk buddyzmu Wadżrajany.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KING_GESAR_SONG_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build the King Gesar Song to increase your cities culture.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci il Canto di Re Gesar per incrementare la cultura nella tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SHAMANS_YURTA</Tag>
		<English>Shaman's Yurta</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Yourte du Shaman</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Yurta dello sciamano</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Jurta Szamana</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SHAMANS_YURTA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Build the Shaman's Yurta to train the tengri missionary and to increase the military production of your city.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci la yurta dello sciamano per addestrare i missionari tengriisti e per incrementare la produzione militare della tua città.</Italian>
		<Polish>Jurta - najpopularniejsza nazwa dla namiotu koczowników Wielkiego Stepu. W rzeczywistości słowo to pochodzi z języków tureckich, więc dotyczy jedynie tych, które można zobaczyć od Morza Kaspijskiego po Ałtaj. Na stepach Mongolii, od Ałtaju Zachodniego po Wielki Chingan, namioty te nazywają się ger.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SHAMANS_YURTA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build the Shaman's Yurta to train the tengri missionary and to increase the military production of your city.</English>
		<French>Construisez la Yourte du Shaman pour entraîner des missionaires tengri et augmenter la production militaire de votre ville.</French>
		<Italian>Costruisci la yurta dello sciamano per addestrare i missionari tengriisti e per incrementare la produzione militare della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TENGRII_HORSE_BREEDER</Tag>
		<English>Tengrii Horse Trainer</English>
		<French>Elevage de Chevaux Tengrii</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Allevatore di cavalli tengriista</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Tengryjski Hodowca Koni</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TENGRII_HORSE_BREEDER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Horse Trainer is required to build Horse units.</English>
		<Italian>Quest'allevatore di cavalli permette di addestrare le unità di cavalleria, anche se non hai una fonte di cavalli nelle vicinanze della città.</Italian>
		<Polish>Stadnina koni prowadzona przez wyznawców Tengryzmu.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TENGRII_HORSE_BREEDER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Horse Trainer is required to build Horse units.</English>
		<Italian>Quest'allevatore di cavalli permette di addestrare le unità di cavalleria, anche se non hai una fonte di cavalli nelle vicinanze della città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TENGRI_SHRINE</Tag>
		<English>Khan Tengri</English>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Khan Tengri</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Chan Tengri</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TENGRI_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Khan Tengri ( translated as "Lord of the spirits", or "Lord of the sky"; or Turkic translated as "Ruler of Skies", "Ruler Tengri") is a mountain of the Tian Shan mountain range. It is located on the Kyrgyzstan-Kazakhstan border, east of lake Issyk Kul. Its geologic elevation is 6,995 m (22,949 ft), but its glacial cap rises to 7,010 m (22,999 ft). For this reason, in mountaineering circles, including for the Soviet Snow Leopard award criteria, it is considered a 7000-metre peak. It is also known as Khan Tangiri Shyngy, Kan-Too Chokusu, Pik Khan-Tengry, and Hantengri Feng.Khan Tengri is the second-highest mountain in the Tian Shan, surpassed only by Jengish Chokusu or Pik Pobedy (7,439 m) a few miles to the south. Khan Tengri is the highest point in Kazakhstan and the third-highest peak in Kyrgyzstan, after Jengish Chokusu (Pik Pobedy)and the Ibn Sina Peak, former Pik Lenina (7,134 m).</English>
		<Italian>Khan Tengri (tradotto come "Signore degli spiriti" o "Signore del cielo", mentre in turco viene tradotto come "Signore dei cieli" o "Signore Tengri") è una montagna nella catea montuosa del Tian Shan. Si trova sul confine tra Kyrghizistan e Kazakistan, ad est del lago Issyk Kul. È alto 6.995 m, ma tenendo conto anche della coltre nevosa raggiunge i 7.010 m. Per questo nei circoli alpinistici, inclusi i criteri per il premio sovietico "Leopardo delle nevi", viene considerato un Settemila. È noto anche come Khan Tangiri Shyngy, Kan-Too Chokusu, Picco Khan-Tengry e Hantengri Feng. Khan Tengri è la seconda montagna più alta nello Tian Shan, seconda solo al Jengish Chokusu, noto anche come Picco Pobedy (7.439 m), che si trova poche miglia a sud. Khan Tengri è il picco più alto del Kazakistan e il terzo del Kyrgyzstan, dopo il già citato Jengish Chokusu (Picco Pobedy) e il Picco Ibn Sina Peak, precedentemente noto come Picco Lenin (7.134 m).</Italian>
		<Polish>Chan Tengri - góra znajdująca się w centralnej części pasma górskiego Tienszan, o wysokości 7010 m n.p.m. (bez pokrywy śnieżnej i lodowej - 6995 m n.p.m.). Położona jest na granicy Kirgistanu (trzecia co do wysokości w tym kraju), Kazachstanu (najwyższy szczyt) oraz Chin (od 2009 roku po wprowadzeniu zmian przebiegu granicy kirgisko-chińskiej), na wschód od jeziora Issyk-kul. Zbudowana z marmuru, dzięki czemu w czasie zachodu słońca przybiera ona barwę purpurową. Jest to drugi co do wysokości szczyt Tienszanu (wyższy jest tylko położony od niego na południe Szczyt Zwycięstwa - 7439 m n.p.m.).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TENGRI_SHRINE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build the Khan Tengri to get gold and culture from every city in the world where Tengriism is spread.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci il Khan Tengri per ottenere oro e cultura da ogni città on cui è diffuso il tengriismo.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TENGRI_SONG</Tag>
		<English>Tengri Song</English>
		<French>Chant de Tengri</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Canto di Tengri</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pieśń Tengri</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TENGRI_SONG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Tengri is the supreme god of religion named Tengriism. It is analogous with the early Chinese concept of Tianli and derived Confucian concept of Tianli. The four direction symbols of Blue Dragon (East), White Tiger (West), Red Phoenix (South), Black Snake-Turtle (North) in Chinese cosmology is also analogous with the four direction symbol used in Tengriism.There are no official symbols of Tengriism, however the symbol of the World Tree and the four directions symbol are common. It is often confused with a sun-worshipping religion, but the sun is merely a symbol of Tengri. A dramatic pyramidal mountain peak, long believed to be the highest point on the border between Kazakhstan and Kyrgyzstan, is called "Khan Tengri".</English>
		<Italian>Tengri è il dio supremo nel Tengriismo. Esso è analogo all'antico concetto cinese di Tianli, da cui è derivato l'omonimo concetto confuciano. I quattro simboli direzionali del Dragone Blu (Est), Tigre Bianca (Ovest), Fenice Rossa (Sud) e Serpente-tartaruga Nero (Nord) nella cosmologia cinese sono analoghi ai quattro simboli direzionali usati nel Tengriismo. Non ci sono simboli ufficiali del Tengriismo, tuttavia il simbolo dell'Albero del Mondo e il simbolo a quattro direzioni sono comuni. È spesso confusa con una religione che adora il sole, ma il sole è solo un simbolo di Tengri. Un imponente vetta piramidale, a lungo ritenuta il punto più alto del confine tra Kazakistan e Kirghizistan, si chiama "Khan Tengri".</Italian>
		<Polish>Tengri - główne bóstwo w wierzeniach ałtajskich, mongolskich i tureckich. Wyraz tengri, oznaczający "bóg" i "niebo", był używany na przełomie er na obszarze od Chin do południowej Rosji oraz od Kamczatki do Morza Marmara na określenie zarówno naczelnego bóstwa, jak i bóstw pomniejszych. Również nazywano tak bóstwa w religiach, z którymi ludność turecko-mongolska zetknęła się podczas swojej ekspansji terytorialnej. Tengri to także określenie boskości. W II wieku p.n.e. lud Xiongnu nazywał tak wielkiego boga nieba, nadając mu przymioty "najwyższy", "biały", "niebiański", "wieczny", "potężny".</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TENGRI_SONG_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build Tengri Song to get a free promotion for your mounted units and to increse your cities culture.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci il Canto di Tengri per fornire una promozione gratuita alle tue unià montate e per incrementare la cultura della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_WIND_HORSE</Tag>
		<English>Wind Horse I</English>
		<French>Cheval de vent I</French>
		<Italian>Cavallo del vento I</Italian>
		<Polish>Wicher I</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_WIND_HORSE2</Tag>
		<English>Wind Horse II</English>
		<French>Cheval de vent II</French>
		<Italian>Cavallo del vento II</Italian>
		<Polish>Wicher II</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_TENGRIISM</Tag>
		<English>Tengriism</English>
		<French>Tengriisme</French>
		<Italian>Tengriismo</Italian>
		<Polish>Tengryzm</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_TENGRIISM_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Tengriist</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Tengriiste</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Tengriist</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter:Neuter:Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>tengriista:tengriista:tengriisti:tengriiste</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Tengriist</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Tengrystyczny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_TENGRIISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Tengriism is a fairly new term. It is conventionally used to describe a form of Tengri-centered shamanism that prevailed on the Eurasian steppes mostly among early Turkic and Mongol Khanates.[PARAGRAPH:2]Tengrism differs from Siberian shamanism in that the polities practicing it were not small bands of hunter gatherers like the Paleosiberians but a continuous succession of pastoral, semi-sedentarized Khanates and empires from the Xiongnu Empire (founded 209 BC) till the Mongol Empire (13th century).[PARAGRAPH:2]Tengrists view their existence as sustained by the eternal blue sky (Tengri), the fertile mother-earth spirit (Eje) and a ruler regarded as the holy spirit of the sky. Heaven, earth, spirits of nature and ancestors provide for every need and protect all humans. By living an upright, respectful life, a human will keep his world in balance and perfect his personal Wind Horse, or spirit. The Huns of the northern Caucasus reportedly believed in two gods: Tangri Han (or Tengri Khan), considered identical to the Persian Aspandiat and for whom horses were sacrificed, and Kuar (whose victims are struck by lightning).</English>
		<Italian>ATTENZIONE: il tengriismo non funziona come le altre religioni, ha qualche particolarità. La prima, e più importante, è che l'unico modo per diffonderla è usando gli sciamani (il tengriismo non si diffonde da solo) e l'unico modo per costruire gli sciamani è costruire prima una yurta degli sciamani, che può essere costruita solo se il tengriismo è presente in città, dandoti nessun'altra scelta che iniziare a diffondere il tengriismo dalla sua città santa. A parte la yurta degli sciamani il tengriismo non ha edifici, dato che nel mondo reale questa religione non ne aveva, perciò sono sostituiti dalla forma di trasmissione originale di questa religione... i canti. Il teengriism era la fede più diffusa tra i Mongoli e i popoli turchi prima che la stragrande maggioranza di essi aderisse alle religioni del mondo civilizzato. Si concentra intorno alla divinità celeste Tengri e incorpora elementi dello sciamanesimo, dell'animismo, del totemismo e del culto degli antenati. "Khukh" e "Tengri" letteralmente significano "blu" e "cielo" in lingua mongola, e i mongoli moderni ancora pregano "Munkh khukh Tengri" ("eterno cielo blu"). Pertanto la Mongolia è chiamaao come "terra dell'Eterno Cielo Blu" ("Munkh khukh tengriin oron" in mongolo). Oggi, ci sono ancora un gran numero di fedeli tengriisti che vivono in Asia centrale, come i Khakas e i Tuvani. Nel tengriismo, il senso della vita è visto come vivere in armonia con il mondo circostante. I credenti tengriisti vedono la loro esistenza come sostenuta dal Cielo eterno azzurro, Tengri, la Madre-Terra fertile, lo spirito Eje, e un dominatore che è considerato come lo spirito santo del Cielo. Cielo, Terra, gli spiriti della natura e degli antenati pensano a ogni tipo di esigenza e a proteggere tutti gli esseri umani. Vivendo una vita onesta e rispettosa, un essere umano non mancherà di tenere il suo mondo in equilibrio e massimizzare il suo potere personale a cavallo del vento. Gli sciamani hanno un ruolo importante nel ristabilire l'equilibrio quando viene turbato da disastri o da interferenze degli spiriti. È probabile che il tengriismo fosse la religione degli Unni; viene ancora praticato attivamente in Sakha, Buriazia, Tuva e Mongolia, assieme al buddismo tibetano e al Burkhanismo.</Italian>
		<Polish>Tengryzm to pradawna religia mająca związek przede wszystkim z ludami Azji Srodkowej, takimi jak Hunowie czy Mongołowie. Oparta głównie na wierze w Tengri, boga nieba, oraz Eje, Matkę Ziemię, wiara ta miała dość luźne ramy, nie posiadała duchownych ani kapłanów, a jej wyznawcy nie starali się nawracać innych. Tengryzm skupiał się na utrzymaniu harmonii z otaczającym środowiskiem. Wierni uznawali, że zasoby ziemi są święte, zwłaszcza woda, której ilość była skąpa na stepach Srodkowej Azji, na których żyła większość wyznawców. Choć twierdzi się, że w Azji nadal żyją przedstawiciele tej religii, nie próbowano określić ich liczby.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_TENGRIISM_QUOTE</Tag>
		<English>No one would hide oneself from him... Let everybody who wants to be saved express frankly one's devotion to Tangra.[PARAGRAPH:2]- Sandugach "Nightingale",[PARAGRAPH:1][SPACE][SPACE]"Chulman Tolgau, 53: 114-125" - Tengriism prayer</English>
		<French>"Personne ne peut se cacher de Lui... Laissez tout ceux qui souhaitent être sauvés, exprimer franchement leur dévotion à Tangra." - Prière Tengriiste</French>
		<Polish>"Nikt nie ukryje się przed nim... Niech każdy, kto chce być zbawiony odprawi szybko nabożeństwo dla Tengry." - Tengryjska modlitwa</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_TENGRIISM_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_TECH_TEXT]Tengriism[COLOR_REVERT] is a prehistoric era technology that founds said religion in the first civilization that researches it. Mechanically Tengriism works differently, first, and most important, it only spreads through the use of shamans, meaning that Tengriism isn't able to spread by itself. To construct shamans it is necessary to build a [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Shaman's Yurta[COLOR_REVERT] first (the religion's only building) in the founding city.</English>
		<French>Le Tengriisme permet d'entraîner des meilleures unités montées et cela dans toutes vos villes, à partir d'une seule ressource de chevaux.</French>
		<Italian>Il tengriismo permette di addestrare unità di cavalleria migliori; inoltre permette di addestrare unità di cavalleria anche nelle città che non hanno accesso diretto ai cavalli, sempre che sia disponibile almeno una fonte di cavalli nella tua nazione.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TENGRI_MISSIONARY</Tag>
		<English>Tengri Shaman</English>
		<French>Shaman Tengri</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Sciamano tengriista</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Szaman Tengryzmu</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TENGRI_MISSIONARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In Turkic mythology, Tengri is a pure, white goose that flies constantly over an endless expanse of water, which represents time. Beneath this water, Ak Ana ("White Mother") calls out to him saying "Create". To overcome his loneliness, Tengri creates Er Kishi, who is not as pure or as white as Tengri and together they set up the world. Er Kishi becomes a demonic character and strives to mislead people and draw them into its darkness. Tengri assumes the name Tengri Ülgen and withdraws into Heaven from which he tries to provide people with guidance through sacred animals that he sends among them. The Ak Tengris occupy the fifth level of Heaven. Shaman priests who want to reach Tengri Ülgen never get further than this level, where they convey their wishes to the divine guides. Returns to earth or to the human level take place in a goose-shaped vessel.</English>
		<Polish>Szaman - osoba pełniąca funkcję religijną, polegającą na sformalizowanej i instytucjonalnej więzi ekstatycznej z istotami nadludzkimi, duchami przodków lub demonami.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TENGRI_MISSIONARY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Use this missionary to actively spread [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Tengriism[COLOR_REVERT] in friendly cities (or rival cities with whom you have [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Open Borders[COLOR_REVERT]). This increases your income if you have the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Khan Tengri[COLOR_REVERT].</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>