<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CALIGULA_1</Tag>
		<English>Hate the [OUR_EMPIRE], if you must [CT_NAME]. Just so long as you fear as always.</English>
		<Polish>Moźesz nienawidieć [OUR_EMPIRE], a jeśli musisz to nawet [CT_NAME]. Póki będziesz się nas bał.</Polish>
		<Russian>Знай же,[CT_NAME]: я ненавижу [OUR_EMPIRE]. Посему трепещи перед нашей мощью.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CALIGULA</Tag>
		<English>Caligula</English>
		<Italian>Caligola</Italian>
		<Polish>Kaligula</Polish>
		<Russian>Êàëèãóëà</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CALIGULA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Caligula[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roman Emperor [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 12 - 41[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus, more commonly known by his nickname Caligula, was a Roman Emperor who reigned from 16 March 37 until his assassination on 24 January 41. Caligula was the third emperor of the Roman Empire, and a member of the Julio-Claudian dynasty which descended from Augustus.[PARAGRAPH:1]Caligula's father, Germanicus, was the adopted son of emperor Tiberius and one of Rome's most beloved generals. The young Gaius earned his nickname, meaning "little [soldier's] boots", while travelling with his father on military campaigns in Germania. When Germanicus died in Antioch in 19, his mother Agrippina the Elder returned to Rome with her six children, where she became entangled in an increasingly bitter feud with Tiberius. During the course of the 20s and 30s, many of Caligula's relatives, including Agrippina and two elder brothers, died in mysterious circumstances. Caligula withdrew to the island of Capri in 31, where Tiberius himself had retired since 26, and eventually succeeded his adoptive grandfather upon his death on 16 March 37.[PARAGRAPH:1]There are few surviving sources on the reign of Caligula, and although he is described as noble and moderate ruler during his first two years of reign, after this the sources focus upon his cruelty, extravagance and sexual perversity, presenting him as an insane tyrant. While the reliability of these sources has been difficult to assess, what is known is that during his brief reign, Caligula worked to increase the authority of the Principate, but struggled to maintain his position in the face of several conspiracies to overthrow him. He focused much of his attention on ambitious construction projects, and annexed Mauretania but failed to conquer Britain.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 38, Caligula focused his attention on political and public reform. He published the accounts of public funds, which had not been made public during the reign of Tiberius. He aided those who lost property in fires, abolished certain taxes and gave out prizes to the public and gymnastic events. He also allowed new members into the equestrian and senatorial orders. Perhaps most significantly, he restored the practice of democratic elections. Cassius Dio said that this act "though delighting the rabble, grieved the sensible, who stopped to reflect, that if the offices should fall once more into the hands of the many... many disasters would result".[PARAGRAPH:1]In 40, Caligula began implementing very controversial policies that introduced religion into his political role. Caligula began appearing in public dressed as various gods and demigods such as Hercules, Mercury, Venus and Apollo. Reportedly, he began referring to himself as a god when meeting with politicians and he was referred to as Jupiter on occasion in public documents. A sacred precinct was set apart for his worship at Miletus in the province of Asia and two temples were erected for worship of him in Rome. The Temple of Castor and Pollux on the Forum was linked directly to the Imperial residence on the Palatine and dedicated to Caligula. He would appear here on occasion and present himself as a god to the public.[PARAGRAPH:1]All surviving sources, except Pliny the Elder, characterize Caligula as insane. It is not known whether they are speaking figuratively or literally, though. Additionally, given Caligula's unpopularity among the surviving sources, it is difficult to separate fact from fiction. Recent sources are divided in attempting to ascribe a medical reason for Caligula's behavior, citing as possibilities encephalitis, epilepsy or meningitis. The question of whether or not Caligula was insane remains unanswered.[PARAGRAPH:1]On 24 January 41, Caligula was assassinated as the result of a conspiracy involving members of his own bodyguard and the Roman Senate. The conspirators' attempt to use the opportunity to restore the Roman Republic was thwarted, as the same day the Praetorian Guard declared Caligula's uncle Claudius emperor in his place.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Kaligula[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Cesarz Rzymski [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 12 - 41[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Urodził się w Ancjum (dziś Anzio), w pobliźu Rzymu. Jego ojciec Germanik, dowódca uwielbiany przez wojsko, zaraz po narodzinach syna znalazł się wraz ze swoją rodziną nad Renem, gdzie dowodził tamtejszą armią. Rodzice często pokazywali syna w stroju źołnierskim. Wkładali mu buty (sandały), które nazywały się caligae, stąd teź chłopiec otrzymał przydomek Caligula, czyli "Bucik", i był traktowany jako maskotka armii. Gajusz znalazł się na wyspie Capri w 31 roku, gdzie na stałe osiadł Tyberiusz, gdyź cesarz zapragnął mieć swych dwóch następców tronu blisko siebie. Byli to jego wnuk - Tyberiusz Gemellus oraz Gajusz. Stale otaczano ich, a szczególnie Gajusza, donosicielami podchwytującymi kaźde słowo. W 33 roku Tyberiusz przyznał Kaliguli honorowy kwestoriat. W 33 roku Kaligula poślubił Junię Klaudyllę, która zmarła podczas porodu razem z dzieckiem w 37 roku. Kaligula wszedł w porozumienie z prefektem pretorianów Makronem. Gajusz pragnął zostać cesarzem, a Makron zachować stanowisko u boku nowego cesarza. Gwarancją porozumienia była źona Makrona - Ennia, która za wiedzą męźa była kochanką Gajusza (źonatego wówczas z Junią). 16 marca cesarz zasłabł i zmarł. Po mieście krąźyły wszakźe plotki, źe do śmierci Tyberiusza przyczynili się Kaligula z Makronem. Zmarły w testamencie zalecił, by Gajusz i Tyberiusz Gemellus panowali razem. Jednak jego wola nie spełniła się. Za sprawą Makrona senat uniewaźnił jego wolę i ustanowił Gajusza cesarzem. Początki panowania nowego cesarza zapowiadały się wspaniale. Jednakźe w listopadzie 37 roku cesarz zapadł na dosyć powaźną chorobę, prawdopodobnie mózgu. Gdy Kaligula powrócił do zdrowia, był juź innym człowiekiem. Na początku wysłał źołnierzy z rozkazem zgładzenia Tyberiusza Gemmellusa, który mógł się upomnieć o ojcowiznę. Zmusił równieź do samobójstwa Marka Juniusza Silanusa (konsula zastępczego w 15 n.e.), ojca swojej pierwszej źony (Junii). W 38 roku odbyły się igrzyska, w trakcie których zmarła siostra cesarza Druzylla. Ogłoszono wtedy wielką źałobę publiczną. Kilka miesięcy po pogrzebie oźenił się z Lollią Pauliną, dotychczasową źoną Memmiusza Regulusa. W 38 r. ze światem poźegnał się m.in. Makron, który popełnił samobójstwo. W 39 roku znacznie pogorszyły się finanse państwa, poniewaź Kaligula lekkomyślnie roztrwonił pieniądze pozostawione przez gospodarnego Tyberiusza. Aby naprawić ten stan rzeczy, cesarz rozpoczął szeroko zakrojoną akcję konfiskat majątków. Gdy w połowie września Gajusz przygotował wielką wyprawę przeciw Germanom, odkryto spisek mający na celu zgładzenie cesarza. Jego senatorscy przywódcy (dowódca armii Getulik oraz Marek Emiliusz Lepidus, były mąź Druzylli) ponieśli śmierć, a zamieszane w spisek siostry cesarza, Agrypina Młodsza i Julia Młodsza, zostały wygnane na wyspy.</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Калигула[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Римский император[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни:[\BOLD]12 - 41 гг.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Гай Юлий Цезарь Август Германик, более известный под прозвищем Калигула, был римским императором, который правил с 16 марта 37 года до своего убийства 24 января 41 года. Калигула был третьим императором Римской империи из династии Юлиев-Клавдиев, которая берет начало от Октавиана Августа.[PARAGRAPH:1]Отец Калигулы, Германик, был приемным сыном императора Тиберия и одним из самых популярных военачальников Рима. Юный Гай получил свое прозвище, означающее «сапожок» (лат. Caligula, уменьшительно-ласкательное от caliga - «солдатский сапог»), путешествуя с отцом в военных кампаниях в Германии. Когда Германик умер в Антиохии в 19 году, его мать Агриппина Старшая вернулась в Рим со своими шестью детьми, где она оказалась вовлеченной в ожесточенную вражду с Тиберием. В течение 20-30-х годов многие из родственников Калигулы, включая Агриппину и двух старших братьев, погибли при загадочных обстоятельствах. Калигула удалился на остров Капри в 31 году, где сам Тиберий находился в добровольной изоляции с 26 года, и, в конце концов, сменил на троне своего приемного деда после его смерти 16 марта 37 года.[PARAGRAPH:1]Существует немного уцелевших источников о правлении Калигулы, и хотя его описывают как благородного и умеренного правителя в течение его первых двух лет правления, после этого источники сосредотачиваются на его жестокости, расточительности и сексуальных извращениях, представляя его как жестокого и сладострастного тирана. Хотя достоверность этих источников было трудно оценить, известно, что во время своего непродолжительного правления Калигула работал над повышением авторитета Принципата, но изо всех сил пытался сохранить свои позиции перед угрозой нескольких заговоров, направленных на его свержение. Он сосредоточил большую часть своего внимания на амбициозных строительных проектах и ??аннексировал Мавританию, однако не смог завоевать Британию.[PARAGRAPH:1]В 38 году Калигула сосредоточил свое внимание на политических и общественных реформах. Он опубликовал счета государственных фондов, которые не были обнародованы во времена правления Тиберия. Он помогал тем, кто утратил имущество в результате пожаров, отменил определенные налоги и раздавал щдрые пожертвования на различные общественные и спортивные мероприятия. Он также пополнил новыми членами Сенат и всадническое сословие. Пожалуй, самое главное, он восстановил практику демократических выборов. Римский историк Дион Кассий утверждал, что этот поступок «хотя и восхищал толпу, но огорчал опытныхплитиков, которые перестали задумываться, что если должности снова попадут в руки недостойных... это приведет ко многим бедствиям».[PARAGRAPH:1]В 40 году Калигула начал проводить очень противоречивую политику, пытаясь подкрепить свою власть религиозным авторитетом. Калигула начал появляться на публике в одеяниях различных богов и полубогов, таких как Геркулес, Меркурий, Венера и Аполлон. По сообщениям, он начал величать себя богом, когда встречался с римскими магистратами, и его иногда упоминали как Юпитера в публичных документах. Для его богослужения в Милете в провинции Азии был выделен священный участок, а для поклонения ему в Риме были возведены два храма. Храм Кастора и Поллукса на Форуме был напрямую связан с Императорской резиденцией на Палатине и посвящен Калигуле. Он иногда появлялся здесь и представлялся публике как бог.[PARAGRAPH:1]Во всех сохранившихся источниках, исключая сочинение Плиния Старшего, характеризуют Калигулу как безумца и деспота. Неизвестно, говорят ли они образно или буквально. Кроме того, учитывая непопулярность Калигулы среди авторов уцелевших источников, трудно отделить факты от вымысла. Недавние источники разделились в попытках объяснить причину изменения поведения Калигулы, ссылаясь на возможность энцефалита, эпилепсии или менингита. Вопрос о том, был ли Калигула безумным, остается дискуссионным.[PARAGRAPH:1]Так или иначе, 24 января 41 года Калигула был убит в результате заговора с участием его личных телохранителей и членов римского Сената. Попытка заговорщиков использовать возможность восстановить Римскую Республику была сорвана, так как в тот же день преторианская гвардия провозгласила императором Клавдия - родного дядю Калигулы.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>