<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LEONIDAS_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, oh leader of the [CT_EMPIRE]. Tonight we dine in hell. Care to join for dinner?</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, O Chef de l'[CT_EMPIRE]. Cette nuit nous dinons en enfer. Prêt à vous joindre à nous pour le repas?</French>
		<German>Willkommen, oh Anführer vom [CT_EMPIRE]. Heute Nacht speisen wir in der Hölle. Willst Du mit uns zu Abend essen?</German>
		<Spanish>Bienvenido, oh líder del [CT_EMPIRE]. Esta noche cenaremos en el infierno. ¿Quieres unirte a la cena?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Witam, przywódcę [CT_EMPIRE]. Dziś będziemy ucztować w piekle. Chcesz dołączyć do naszej uczty?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LEONIDAS</Tag>
		<English>Leonidas I</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Léonidas I</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Leonidas I.</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Leonidas I</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Leonidas I</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LEONIDAS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Leonidas I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Sparta[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.521 BC - August 11, 480 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Leonidas was a king of Sparta, the 17th of the Agiad line, one of the sons of King Anaxandridas II of Sparta, who was believed to be a descendant of Heracles. Leonidas was one of three: he had an older brother Dorieus and a younger brother Cleombrotus, who ruled as regent for a while on Leonidas' death before the regency was taken over by Pausanias, who was Cleombrotus' son. Leonidas succeeded his half-brother Cleomenes I, probably in 489 or 488 BC, and was married to Cleomenes' daughter, Gorgo. His name was raised to heroic status as a result of the events in the Battle of Thermopylae.[PARAGRAPH:1]In August 480 BC, Leonidas set out to meet the Xerxes' army at Thermopylae with 300 of his personal body guards, all with sons to carry on their names, where he was joined by forces from other Greek city-states, who put themselves under his command to form an army 4,200 strong. This force was assembled in an attempt to hold the pass of Thermopylae against hundreds of thousands of Persian soldiers who had invaded from the north of Greece under Xerxes I. Leonidas took only his personal bodyguards, and not the army, because the majority of the Spartan Army was coordinating with the massed naval forces of the Greeks against the Persian Navy. This is contrary to the belief that the army could not be sent because of religious restrictions.[PARAGRAPH:1]Leonidas and his men repulsed the Persians' frontal attacks for the first two days, killing roughly 20,000 of the enemy troops and losing very few of their own. The Persian elite unit known to the Greeks as "the Immortals" were held back, and two of Xerxes' brothers died in battle. On the third day, a Malian Greek traitor named Ephialtes led the Persian general Hydarnes by a mountain track to the rear of the Greeks. At that point Leonidas sent away all Greek troops and remained in the pass with his 300 Spartans, 900 Helots, and 700 Thespians who refused to leave. Another 400 Thebans were kept with Leonidas as hostages. The Thespians stayed entirely of their own will, declaring that they would not abandon Leonidas and his followers. Their leader was Demophilos, son of Diadromes, and as Herodotus writes: "Hence they lived with the Spartans and died with them."[PARAGRAPH:1]One theory provided by Herodotus is that Leonidas sent away the remainder of his men because he cared about their safety. The King would have thought it wise to preserve those Greek troops for future battles against the Persians, but he knew that the Spartans could never abandon their post on the battlefield. The soldiers who stayed behind were to protect their escape against the Persian cavalry. Herodotus himself believes that Leonidas gave the order because he perceived the allies to be out of heart and unwilling to encounter the danger to which his own mind was made up. He therefore chose to dismiss all troops except the Thespians and Helots and save the "glory" for the Spartans.[PARAGRAPH:1]The little Greek force, attacked from both sides, was cut down to a man except for the Thebans, who surrendered. Leonidas was killed, but the Spartans retrieved his body and protected it until their final defeat. Herodotus says that Xerxes' orders were to have Leonidas' head cut off and put on a stake and his body crucified. This was considered sacrilegious. The tomb of Leonidas lies today in the northern part of the modern town of Sparta.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Leonidas I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Król Sparty[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył: [\BOLD]ok. 521 p.n.e - 11 sierpnia 480 p.n.e [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Od około 490 p.n.e. król Sparty, syn Anaksandridasa II i jego pierwszej żony. Poślubił Gorgo - córkę swojego przybranego brata Kleomenesa I, z którą miał syna Plejstarchosa. W 480 p.n.e. dowodził obroną przesmyku termopilskiego, stojąc na czele 300 Spartan i kilku tysięcy żołnierzy z innych państw greckich. Przez trzy dni odpierał ataki wielotysięcznej armii króla Persji, Kserksesa I, która nie mogła w wąskim przejściu wykorzystać swojej przewagi liczebnej. W wyniku zdrady pasterza Efialtesa, wrogie oddziały zaszły od tyłu żołnierzy greckich. Leonidas odesłał wtedy wojska państw sprzymierzonych i wraz z trzystoma Spartanami, tyluż Helotami oraz siedmioma setkami Tespijczyków bronił wąwozu do końca. Poświęcenie Leonidasa i jego wojowników dało czas reszcie żołnierzy na wycofanie się. W bitwie pod Termopilami Spartanie stawiali zaciekły opór, jednak przeważająca liczba Persów zmiażdżyła niewielkie siły Leonidasa, który na koniec poległ w bitwie. Tebanie poddali się, wypalono im piętna, przed wojskami perskimi droga została otwarta.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
