<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_FRANCO_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I am responsible only to God and history!</English>
		<French>Salutations! Je suis [OUR_NAME] de l'[OUR_EMPIRE]. Je suis responsable uniquement devant Dieu et l'Histoire!</French>
		<German>Grüße, ich bin [OUR_NAME] vom [OUR_EMPIRE]. Meine Verantwortung gilt nur Gott und der Geschichte!</German>
		<Spanish>¡Saludos! Soy [OUR_NAME] del [OUR_EMPIRE]. ¡Yo solo respondo ante Dios y la historia!</Spanish>
		<Polish>Witam! Jestem [OUR_NAME] z [OUR_EMPIRE]. Odpowiadam tylko przed Bogiem i historią!</Polish>
		<Russian>Приветствую! Я [OUR_NAME] из [OUR_EMPIRE]. Я несу ответственность только перед Богом и историей!</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_FRANCO</Tag>
		<English>Francisco Franco</English>
		<Russian>Ôðàíêî</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_FRANCO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Francisco Franco[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Spanish Head of State[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1892 - 1975[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Francisco Paulino Hermenegildo Teódulo Franco y Bahamonde, commonly known as Francisco Franco or Francisco Franco y Bahamonde was the dictator and later formally became head of state of Nationalist Spain from October 1936, and of all of Spain from 1939 until his death in 1975. His state combined early 20th-century corporatism with nationalism and some aspects of fascism and a focus on traditional values. From 1947 to his death he was [i]de facto[/i] regent of Spain.[PARAGRAPH:1]Franco led a successful military career and reached the rank of General. He fought in Morocco and suppressed a strike in 1934 to defend the Republican government's stability. In February 1936, the left-wing Popular Front won the general election and formed a government. A period of severe instability and disarray followed the election, with escalating violence between left and right wing supporters. Anti-clerical violence against the Church by leftist militants further raised tensions. After the assassination of a major opposition figure, José Calvo Sotelo, by a commando unit of the Assault Guards in July 1936, Franco participated in a [i]coup d'etat[/i] against the elected Popular Front government. The coup failed and evolved into the Spanish Civil War during which he emerged as the leader of the Nationalists against the Popular Front. After winning the civil war, he dissolved the Spanish Parliament, establishing an authoritarian regime that lasted until 1978, when a new constitution was drafted. During the Second World War, Franco maintained a policy of neutrality, although he did assist Nazi Germany and Fascist Italy on a small scale against the Soviet Union, most famously by sending troops (known as the Blue Division) to aid Nazi Germany in fighting the USSR. Before the invasion of the Soviet Union by the German Army, Franco and Hitler met in Hendaye on October 23, 1940. During the Cold War, the United States established a diplomatic alliance with Franco, due to his strong anti-Communist policy. American President Richard Nixon toasted Franco, and after Franco's death, stated: «General Franco was a loyal friend and ally of the United States.» After his death Spain began a transition to democracy.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Francisco Franco[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Szef Rządu Hiszpanii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 1892 - 1975[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Hiszpański dyktator wojskowy. Przywódca antyrepublikańskiego przewrotu (1936-1939), szef państwa Hiszpanii (hiszp. Jefe del Estado Espanol, 1936-1975), regent Królestwa Hiszpanii (1947-1975), premier rządu, naczelny dowódca sił zbrojnych i przewodniczący organizacji politycznej - Falangi (FET y JONS, od 1958 roku Ruch Narodowy), tytułowany Przywódcą Ostatecznej Krucjaty i Hiszpańskiej Schedy, Liderem Wojny Wyzwoleńczej przeciw Komunizmowi i jego Współsprawcom (El Caudillo de la Ultima Cruzada y de la Hispanidad, El Caudillo de la Guerra de Liberacion contra el Comunismo y sus Complices).</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Франсиско Франко[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Каудильо Испании[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни: [\BOLD] 1892 - 1975[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Франсиско Паулино Эрменегильдо Теодуло Франко-и-Баамонде, широко известный как Франсиско Франко или Франсиско Франко-и-Баамонде, был диктатором, а затем формально стал главой государства националистической Испании с октября 1936 года и всей Испании с 1939 года до своей смерти в 1975 году. Его государство сочетал корпоративизм начала двадцатого века с национализмом, некоторыми аспектами фашизма и ориентацией на традиционные ценности. С 1947 года, когда была официально восстановлена монархия, он до своей смерти был де-факто регентом Испании.[PARAGRAPH:1]Франко вел успешную военную карьеру и достиг звания генерала. Он воевал в Марокко и подавил забастовку в 1934 году, чтобы защитить стабильность республиканского правительства. В феврале 1936 года левый Народный фронт победил на всеобщих выборах и сформировал правительство. После выборов последовал период серьезной нестабильности и беспорядка с эскалацией насилия между сторонниками левого и правого крыла. Антиклерикальное насилие против церкви со стороны левых боевиков еще больше усилило напряженность. После убийства крупного оппозиционера Хосе Кальво Сотело отрядом штурмовой гвардии в июле 1936 года Франко участвовал в государственном перевороте против избранного правительства Народного фронта. Переворот провалился и перерос в гражданскую войну в Испании, во время которой он стал лидером националистов против Народного фронта. После победы в гражданской войне он распустил испанский парламент, установив авторитарный режим, который просуществовал до 1978 года, когда была разработана новая конституция. Во время Второй мировой войны Франко придерживался политики нейтралитета, хотя он действительно помогал нацистской Германии и фашистской Италии в небольшом масштабе против Советского Союза, наиболее известный из которых - отправка войск (известных как Голубая дивизия) для помощи нацистской Германии в борьбе с СССР. Перед вторжением в Советский Союз немецкой армии Франко и Гитлер встретились в Андае 23 октября 1940 года. Во время холодной войны Соединенные Штаты заключили фактический союз с Франко из-за его решительной антикоммунистической политики. Американский президент Ричард Никсон произнес тост за Франко, а после смерти диктатора заявил: «Генерал Франко был верным другом и союзником Соединенных Штатов». После его смерти Испания начала переход к демократии.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>