<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HEKE_1</Tag>
		<English>KA MATE! KA ORA, KA MATE! KA ORA....</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HEKE</Tag>
		<English>Heke</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HEKE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Hone Heke[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Chief of the Maori[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1810 - 1850 [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Hone Wiremu Heke Pokai was a Maori chief and war leader in New Zealand. He is considered the principal instigator of the Flagstaff War. Born at Pakaraka south of Kerikeri in the Bay of Islands, Heke was a member of the Ngapuhi tribe but also had connections to Rahiri which added to his mana and gave him significant influence within the tribe. He grew up in the Kaikohe area, scarcely surviving the vicissitudes of tribal warfare. As a youth, he attended the mission school at Kerikeri and came under the influence of the missionary, Henry Williams. Subsequently he, his wife and children were converted to Christianity and Hone became a lay preacher.[PARAGRAPH:1]However, it was as a warrior that Hone Heke established his reputation. He took part in the first battle of Kororareka in 1830, in Titore's expedition to Tauranga, and fought with Titore against Pomare II in 1837. There are conflicting reports of when Heke signed the Treaty of Waitangi. It may have been with the other chiefs on February 6, 1840. Heke's doubts about signing the treaty were well grounded. The capital of the new colony was shifted from Kororareka to Auckland with the corresponding loss of revenue for the Bay of Islands. The imposition of customs duties, the banning of the felling of kauri trees and government control of the sale of land all contributed to an economic depression for the Maori. Furthermore it became clear that the British considered the authority of the chiefs to be subservient to that of the Crown although the treaty promised equal partnership.[PARAGRAPH:1]As a signal of his discontent, Hone Heke chopped down the flagpole carrying the British flag that flew over Kororareka. The British interpreted this as an act of rebellion and soon the two peoples were at war. In the time space of 6 months Hone Heke actually chopped the flagpole down three times. To prevent this happening yet again, Crown ordered in a battalion of British soldiers to defend it. Heke created a diversion with the help of Kawiti and, whilst the soldiers were fighting on the beach, Heke and a few others crept towards the flagpole and cut it down for the fourth time. This was the beginning of the Flagstaff War.[PARAGRAPH:1]Heke took an active part in the early phases of the conflict, but he was severely wounded during the Battle of Te Ahu Ahu and did not rejoin the fighting until the closing phase of the Siege of Ruapekapeka some months later. Shortly afterwards, Heke and his ally, Kawiti met with their principal Maori opponent, Tamati Waka Nene and negotiated a ceasefire, which they then imposed upon the British. This did not prevent the governor, George Grey from presenting it as a British victory. Despite this, Heke and George Grey were reconciled at a meeting in 1848.[PARAGRAPH:1]Hone Heke retired to Kaikohe where he died of tuberculosis two years later. He is still regarded as a great leader by the Ngapuhi and many of the Maori people. To this day, his burial place remains a secret known only to a few people although this is subject to considerable speculation.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Hone Heke[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Wódz Maorysów[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył: [\BOLD] 1810 - 1850 [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Po roku 1859 liczebność Europejczyków na Nowej Zelandii zaczęła szybko przerastać populację Maorysów. Ci drudzy, przede wszystkim z powodu nieznanych na wyspach chorób zakaźnych, zaczęli gwałtownie wymierać, do tego stopnia, że niektórym obserwatorom wydawało się, że są na drodze do ostatecznej zagłady. W tym samym czasie wyładowane imigrantami statki docierały do Auckland niemal co tydzień. Były i inne dysproporcje: brytyjskie siły imperialne były zaopatrywane i opłacane przez Koronę, nie przez niezbyt zasobnych osadników. W tej sytuacji Maorysi musieli walczyć z jednym z czołowych mocarstw świata. Na dodatek Maorysi bazowali na gospodarce agrarnej - wojownicy byli przede wszystkim rolnikami. Jako tacy mogli tylko dwa do trzech miesięcy w roku poświęcać na walkę, by rychło powrócić do swych domów i pól. Udało im się wprawdzie wypracować system zmian w odniesieniu do dłużej trwających zmagań, ale nigdy nie mogli rzucić do walki wszystkich swych sił. Podczas inwazji Waikato, która stanowiła najpoważniejszy z konfliktów, Brytyjczycy mieli do dyspozycji 18 000 żołnierzy (jednorazowo 14 000) uzbrojonych w działa, karabiny powtarzalne i granaty, podczas gdy Maorysi mogli liczyć na cztery do pięciu tysięcy wojowników, z czego do boju stawała połowa lub mniej ze strzelbami i sztucerami w ręku. Żadna z wojen nie była konfliktem wyłącznie dwóch stron. W niektórych przypadkach brały w nich udział aż cztery. Maorysi byli zawsze po obu stronach konfliktu, walcząc to po stronie Brytyjczyków, to przeciw nim. Podczas "wojny o maszt flagowy" maoryscy sprzymierzeńcy działali zupełnie niezależnie od brytyjskiego dowództwa; wódz Tamati Waka Nene uważał Hone Heke za swego osobistego wroga. Jedyna poważna bitwa pod Waimate Pa, kiedy to naprawdę walczono na śmierć i życie, obyła się bez najmniejszego udziału Brytyjczyków. W latach siedemdziesiątych XIX wieku, podczas wojny Te Kooti'ego, liczni Maorysi walczyli po stronie wojsk kolonialnych. Wódz Ngati Porou sformował swój własny regiment. Jednakże Maori byli sprzymierzeńcami tylko do czasu. Gdy ich interesy zaczynały kłócić się z interesami Pakeha, wybierali własną drogę i często przyłączali się do powstańców.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
