<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HENRY_VIII_1</Tag>
		<English>Warm greetings to the [CT_EMPIRE]. I, [OUR_NAME], seek a peace above all earthly dignities, and a still and quiet conscience. </English>
		<French>Salutations chaleureuses à l'[CT_EMPIRE]. Moi, [OUR_NAME], je cherche la paix auprès de toutes les dignités de la terre, et une conscience calme et paisible</French>
		<German>Herzliche Grüße dem [CT_EMPIRE]. Ich, [OUR_NAME], suche den Frieden mehr als alle irdischen Würden und ein ruhiges Gewissen.</German>
		<Italian>Warm greetings to the [CT_EMPIRE]. I, [OUR_NAME], seek a peace above all earthly dignities, and a still and quiet conscience.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos con cariño al [CT_EMPIRE]. Yo, [OUR_NAME], busco una paz por encima de todos los deseos terrenales, y una conciencia tranquila y sosegada.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Ciepłe pozdrowienia dla [CT_EMPIRE]. Ja, [OUR_NAME], szukam pokoju ponad wszystko na ziemi i cichej i spokojnej duszy.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HENRY_VIII</Tag>
		<English>Henry VIII</English>
		<Polish>Henryk VIII</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HENRY_VIII_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Henry VIII[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King and Lord Protector of England[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1491 - 1547[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Henry VIII was King of England and Lord of Ireland, later King of Ireland, from 21 April 1509 until his death. Henry was the second monarch of the House of Tudor, succeeding his father, Henry VII. Henry VIII is perhaps most famous for having been married six times. He wielded perhaps the most formidable power of any English monarch and brought about the English Reformation (including the creation of the Church of England as well as the Dissolution of the Monasteries) and the legal union of England and Wales.[PARAGRAPH:1]Many significant pieces of legislation were enacted during Henry VIII's reign. They included the several Acts which Created the Church of England by separating the English Catholic Church from the Roman Catholic Church, although he kept most Catholic traditions. He established the monarch as the Supreme Governor of the Church of England. In 1525, Henry's impatience with what he perceived to be Catherine's inability to produce the desired heir increased when he became attracted to a charismatic young woman in the Queen's entourage, Anne Boleyn. Henry ordered Cardinal Wolsey to begin formal proceedings with Rome to annul his marriage on the grounds that Catherine's brief marriage to the sickly Arthur had, indeed, been consummated. The king's secretary, William Knight, went to Rome to petition Pope Clement VII for the annulment, but the Pope was highly reluctant to grant the king’s request due to the influence of and pressure from Catherine's nephew, Emperor Charles V, whose troops had pillaged Rome and held the Pope prisoner. Wolsey's efforts to lobby for the annulment were unavailing.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Pope reacted by moving to excommunicate Henry in July 1533. Considerable religious upheaval followed. Urged by Cromwell, Parliament passed several acts that enforced the breach with Rome in the spring of 1534. The Statute in Restraint of Appeals prohibited appeals from English ecclesiastical courts to the Pope. It also prevented the Church from making any regulations without the King's consent. The Ecclesiastical Appointments Act 1534 required the clergy to elect bishops nominated by the Sovereign. The Act of Supremacy 1534 declared that the King was "the only Supreme Head in Earth of the Church of England".[PARAGRAPH:1]Henry was the quintessential Renaissance Man, and his court was a centre of scholarly and artistic innovation. The discovery of America or "The New World" set the stage for Henry's innovative attitude. Henry was among the first European rulers to learn about the true geography of the world, a revolutionary discovery. In 1507, the cartographers Martin Waldseemüller and Matthias Ringmann published the first "modern" map of the world, the first map to accurately depict the American continent and a separate Atlantic and Pacific Oceans, a radical thought for the time.This discovery developed an atmosphere of exploration and discovery in the arts and sciences of which Henry took full advantage in his court and daily life.[PARAGRAPH:1]Though mainly motivated by dynastic and personal concerns, and despite never really abandoning the fundamentals of the Roman Catholic church, Henry ensured that the greatest act of his reign would be one of the most radical and decisive of any English monarch. His break with Rome in 1533-34 was an act with enormous consequences for the course of modern English history beyond the Tudor dynasty. Henry's decision to entrust the regency of his son Edward's minor years to a decidedly Protestant regency council dominated by Edward Seymour most likely for the simple tactical reason that Seymour seemed likely to provide the strongest leadership for the kingdom ensured that the Protestant reformation would be consolidated and even furthered during his son's reign. Such ironies marked other aspects of his legacy. He fostered humanist learning and yet was responsible for the deaths of several outstanding English humanists. Obsessed with securing the succession to the throne, he left no legitimate heirs but a young son (who died before his sixteenth birthday) and two daughters devoted to mutually incompatible religions. The power of the state was magnified, yet so too (at least after Henry's death) were demands for increased political participation by the middle class. Henry worked with some success to once again make England a major player on the European scene but depleted his treasury in the course of doing so, a legacy that would remain an issue for English monarchs through the very end of the Tudor dynasty.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Henryk VIII[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Król i Lord Protektor Anglii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył: [\BOLD]1491 - 1547[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]  Król Anglii (od 21 kwietnia 1509 do końca życia), lord Irlandii (1494-1542), król Irlandii (1542-1547), drugi monarcha z dynastii Tudorów (po swoim ojcu, Henryku VII). Doprowadził w latach 20. i 30. XVI wieku do rozłamu z Kościołem rzymskokatolickim oraz ustanowienia Kościoła anglikańskiego, niezależnego od papieża i Watykanu, ale podporządkowanego królowi Anglii; za jego panowania dokonano kasaty klasztorów. Zasłynął z 6 małżeństw oraz ścinaniem głów niektórych swoich małżonek.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
