<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_LEADER_WRUB_1</Tag>
		<English>Good days and pleasant nights, what do you think about this?.</English>
		<French>Bons jours et nuits plaisantes, que pensez-vous de cela?.</French>
		<Spanish>Buenos dias y placenteras noches, que opinas de esto?.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dobrych dni i przyjemnych nocy, co o tym sądzisz?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_LEADER_WRUB_1</Tag>
		<English>Good days and pleasant nights, the neans dislike to take advantage of the weaks, but maybe you like to be in grace with the strongs...</English>
		<French>Bons jours et nuits plaisantes, nous n'aimons pas tirer avantage des faibles, mais peut-être que vous voulez être dans de bonnes graces avec les plus forts...</French>
		<Spanish>Buenos dias y placenteras noches, a los neans nos disgusta tomar ventaja de los debiles, pero quizas tu quieras estar en gracia con los fuertes...</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dobrych dni i przyjemnych nocy, Neandertalczycy nie lubią gnębić słabszych, ale może jednak chcesz być w sojuszu z silniejszymi... </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_LEADER_WRUB_1</Tag>
		<English>Good days and pleasant nights, may your mighty people help the neans when they are in need.</English>
		<French>Bons jours et nuits plaisantes, que votre brillant peuple puisse venir en aide à ceux dans le besoin.</French>
		<Spanish>Buenos dias y placenteras noches, podria tu fabuloso pueblo ayudar a los neans cuando lo necesitan.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dobrych dni i przyjemnych nocy, niech Twój silny lud pomoże nam kiedy potrzebujemy pomocy!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_WRUB_1</Tag>
		<English>Good days and pleasant nights, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Make no mistake, we are polite and kind people, apart from good-looking, wich is obvious, but if you are not as good as we are, our stones will taste your blood.</English>
		<French>Bons jours et nuits plaisantes, [CT_NAME]! Je suis [OUR_NAME] de [OUR_EMPIRE]. Ne vous méprenez pas, nous sommes un peuple poli et gentil, même si notre apparence est plutôt brutale. Mais si vous n'êtes pas assez bons avec nous, nos pierres goûterons le sang.</French>
		<Spanish>Buenos dias y placenteras noches, [CT_NAME]! Soy [OUR_NAME] de los [OUR_EMPIRE]. No te lleves a error, somos educados y amables, aparte de guapos, como es mas que obvio, pero si no resultas tan bueno como nosotros, nuestras piedras probaran tu sangre.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dobrych dni i przyjemnych nocy, [CT_NAME]! Jestem [OUR_NAME] z [OUR_EMPIRE]. Nie popełnij błedu, jesteśmy łagodnymi i miłymi ludźmi, jeśli jednak Ty nie będziesz dla mnie miły, to nasze kamienie skosztują Twojej krwi.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_WRUB_1</Tag>
		<English>Good days and pleasant nights, be welcome to our fires!</English>
		<French>Bons jours et nuits plaisantes, bienvenue devant nos feus!</French>
		<Spanish>Buenos dias y placenteras noches, se bienvenido a nuestros fuegos!</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dobrych dni i przyjemnych nocy, witamy przy naszych ogniskach!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_WRUB_1</Tag>
		<English>You again? Never enough sharp stones at hand when needed.</English>
		<French>Encore vous? Il n'y a jamais assez de pierres taillées lorsqu'on en a besoin.</French>
		<Spanish>Otra vez tu? Nuca hay bastantes piedras afiladas a mano cuando se necesitan de verdad.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Znowu Ty? Nigdy nie ma ostrych kamienie jak są potrzebne...</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_WRUB_1</Tag>
		<English>No place for peace here, just thirsty and sharp stones.</English>
		<French>Il n'y a pas de place pour la paix ici, juste des pierres aiguisées et assoiffées.</French>
		<Spanish>No hay sitio para la paz, solo caben piedras sedientas y afiladas</Spanish>
		<Polish>Nie ma miejsca na pokój tutaj, tylko ostre kamienie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_WRUB_1</Tag>
		<English>Don´t disturb, we have stones to sharp.</English>
		<French>Ne nous dérangez pas, nous avons des pierres à tailler.</French>
		<Spanish>No molestes, tenemos piedras que afilar.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Nie przeszkadzaj, mamy kamienie do zaostrzenia!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NEANDERTHAL_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Neanderthal</English>
		<French>Néanderthal</French>
		<Spanish>Neandertal</Spanish>
		<Polish>Neandertalski</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NEANDERTHAL_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Neanderthal</English>
		<French>Empire du Néanderthal</French>
		<Spanish>Imperio Neandertal</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Neandertalczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NEANDERTHAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Neanderthals or Neandertals are an extinct species of human in the genus Homo, possibly a subspecies of Homo sapiens. They are very closely related to modern humans, differing in DNA by only 0.3%, which however is twice that of the widest DNA gap found among contemporary humans. Remains left by Neanderthals include bones and stone tools, which are found from western Europe to central Asia. The species is named after Neandertal ("Neander Valley"), the location in Germany where it was first discovered.Neanderthals are generally classified by palaeontologists as the species Homo neanderthalensis, but a minority consider them to be a subspecies of Homo sapiens, (Homo sapiens neanderthalensis). The first humans with proto-Neanderthal traits are believed to have existed in Europe as early as 600,000–350,000 years ago.The exact date of their extinction is disputed. Fossils found in the Vindija Cave in Croatia have been dated to between 33,000 and 32,000 years old, and Neanderthal artifacts from Gorham's Cave in Gibraltar are believed to be less than 30,000 years old, but a recent study has redated fossils at two Spanish sites as 45,000 years old, 10,000 years older than previously thought, and may cast doubt on recent datings of other sites. Cro-Magnon (early-modern-human) skeletal remains showing some "Neanderthal traits" have been found in Lagar Velho (Portugal) and dated to 24,500 years ago, suggesting that there may have been an extensive admixture of the Cro-Magnon and Neanderthal populations in that region.Several cultural assemblages have been linked to the Neanderthals in Europe. The earliest, the Mousterian stone tool culture, dates to about 300,000 years ago. Late Mousterian artifacts were found in Gorham's Cave on the south-facing coast of Gibraltar. Other tool cultures associated with the Neanderthals include the Châtelperronian, the Aurignacian, and the Gravettian; their tool assemblages appear to have developed gradually within their populations, rather than being introduced by new population groups arriving in the region.With an average cranial capacity of 1600cc, Neanderthal's cranial capacity is known to be notably larger than the 1400cc average for all races of modern humans, indicating that their brain size was at least as large, if not larger. In 2008, a group of scientists produced a study using three-dimensional computer-assisted reconstructions of Neanderthal infants based on fossils found in Russia and Syria. The study indicated that Neanderthal and modern human brains were the same size at birth, but by adulthood, the Neanderthal brain was larger than the modern human brain. They were much stronger than modern humans, having particularly strong arms and hands. Males stood 164–168 cm (65–66 in) and females about 152–156 cm (60–61 in) tall.Genetic evidence published in 2010 suggests that Neanderthals contributed to the DNA of anatomically modern humans, probably through interbreeding between 80,000 and 50,000 years ago with the population of anatomically modern humans who had recently migrated from Africa. According to the study, by the time that population began dispersing across Eurasia, Neanderthals genes constituted as much as 1–4% of its genome (roughly equivalent to having one Neanderthal great-great-great-grandparent). Ötzi the iceman, Europe's oldest preserved mummy, was found to possess an even higher percentage of Neanderthal ancestry. Recent findings suggest there may be even more Neandarthal genes in human, non-African genes than previously expected, at about 20% of the human genome instead.In December 2013, researchers reported evidence that Neanderthals practiced burial behavior and intentionally buried their dead. In addition, scientists reported, for the first time, the entire genome of a Neanderthal. The genome was extracted from the toe bone of a 130,000-year-old Neanderthal found in a Siberian cave.</English>
		<Spanish>El hombre de Neandertal (Homo neanderthalensis) es una especie extinta del género Homo que habitó Europa y partes de Asia occidental desde hace 230 000 hasta 28 000 años atrás, durante el Pleistoceno medio y superior y culturalmente integrada en el Paleolítico medio. En un periodo de aproximadamente 5000 años se cree convivió paralelamente en los mismos territorios europeos con el Hombre de Cro-Magnon, primeros hombres modernos en Europa. Esta convivencia se ha demostrado por fósiles hallados en las cuevas de Châtelperron.Sus características definidoras, a partir de los huesos fósiles descubiertos hasta ahora (unos 400 individuos), son: esqueleto robusto, pelvis ancha, extremidades cortas y robustas, tórax en barril, arcos supraorbitarios resaltados, frente baja e inclinada, faz prominente, mandíbulas sin mentón y gran capacidad craneal —1550 cm³—. Vivían en grupos sociales organizados, formados por alrededor de unos treinta miembros casi todos con parentesco (clanes), dominaban el fuego y podían fabricar herramientas rústicas que incluían huesos y piedras.Los neandertales fueron una especie bien adaptada al frío extremo congruente con la cuarta y última glaciación. Tenían un cráneo alargado y amplio, baja estatura y complexión robusta, y nariz amplia de aletas prominentes; rasgos que denotan adaptación a climas fríos, como se puede observar actualmente en las poblaciones del Ártico, y muy probablemente dueños de un olfato más desarrollado que el hombre moderno. Su cerebro era igual o incluso más grande que el de los hombres modernos.Un neandertal medio podía alcanzar unos 1,65 m, era de contextura pesada, dentadura prominente y musculatura robusta. Si bien su estructura ósea no los hacía corredores de largo aliento, sí podían hacer cortas y rápidas carreras persecutorias o escapistas; eran sobre todo caminantes de largas distancias. Estudios anatómicos han determinado que el neandertal podía articular una fonética limitada respecto a la que actualmente posee el hombre moderno, debido a la ubicación de la laringe, situada más arriba que la de este. Otros estudios recientes indican que los neandertales podían dar grandes mascadas a su alimento gracias a una mayor apertura bucal.3 La expectativa de vida de un miembro adulto en un medio ambiente tan extremo, riguroso y hostil no sobrepasaba los 40 años en los hombres y 30 en las mujeres.El estilo de herramientas líticas utilizadas en el Paleolítico medio por los neandertales se conoce como la cultura Musteriense, así llamada por haber sido encontradas por primera vez en el yacimiento arqueológico Le Moustier. La cultura musteriense está caracterizada por la utilización de la técnica de talla Levallois. Estas herramientas fueron producidas usando martillos de percusión blandos, de hueso o madera. En los últimos tiempos de los neandertales aparece en el registro arqueológico el estilo Châtelperroniense, considerado como más "avanzado" que el musteriense.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Człowiek neandertalski, neandertalczyk - wymarły przedstawiciel rodzaju Homo (człowiek), znany z plejstocenu (ok. 400 000 do ok. 24 500 lat temu), w zależności od autorów klasyfikowany jako podgatunek człowieka rozumnego - Homo sapiens neanderthalensis - lub odrębny od niego gatunek - Homo neanderthalensis. Neandertalczyk prawdopodobnie ewoluował z Homo heidelbergensis lub formy z nim blisko spokrewnionej w środkowym plejstocenie. Pierwsze cechy neandertalskie pojawiły się u hominidów w Europie ok. 400 -350 tys. lat temu. Neandertalczycy rozprzestrzenili się po Europie (z wyjątkiem pokrytej lodowcem[potrzebne źródło] Skandynawii) i na Bliskim Wschodzie. W okresie dużych wahań klimatycznych wykazywali przystosowania do zimnego klimatu. Prawdopodobnie w tym czasie zaczęli używać odzieży (dla ochrony od zimna) oraz biżuterii. Nieliczne ślady wskazują na obecność podobnych form w południowej Syberii i północnej Afryce.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NEANDERTHAL_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Neanderthal</English>
		<French>Néanderthal</French>
		<Spanish>Neandertal</Spanish>
		<Polish>Neandertalczycy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_WRUB</Tag>
		<English>Wrub</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_WRUB_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Wrub sounds good for a Neanderthal leader, as, obviously, there are no records for any.</English>
		<Spanish>No suena mal Wrub como lider Neandertal, menos aún cuando no se puede decir nada en contra.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wrub to przypuszczalny wódz neandertalczyków.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
