<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PACHACUTI_1</Tag>
		<English>Ahh, the legendary [CT_NAME]. Pleased to welcome you to the lands of the Inca! Shall we make peace, or shall my Quechas bring your little kingdom into the Incan sphere?</English>
		<French>Ahh, le légendaire [CT_NAME]. Heureux de vous accueillir sur les terres des Incas! Allons-nous faire la paix, ou bien laisserez-vous à mes Quechuas intégrer votre petit royaume dans la sphère Inca?</French>
		<Polish>Ahh, legendarny [CT_NAME]. Witamy w kraju Inków! Czy podpiszemy pokój czy może moi wojownicy włączą Twój kraj do naszego imperium?</Polish>
		<Russian>Ах, легендарный [CT_NAME]. Рад приветствовать вас на землях инков! Должны ли мы заключить мир, или мои кеча перенесут ваше крохотное царство в сферу инков?</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PACHACUTI</Tag>
		<English>Pachacuti</English>
		<French>Pachacutec</French>
		<Russian>Ïà÷àêóòåê</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PACHACUTI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Pachacuti[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]9th Sapa Inca[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ruled:[\BOLD] 1438 - 1471[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]"He who remakes the world" was the ninth Sapa Inca of the Kingdom of Cuzco, which he transformed into an empire, Tawantinsuyu. He began the era of conquest that, within three generations, expanded the Inca dominion from the valley of Cuzco to nearly the whole of civilized South America. He was the fourth of the Hanan dynasty, and with his wife, whose name is given as Mama Anawarkhi or Coya Anahurque, he had two sons. After his father's death Pachacuti became sole ruler of the Incan empire. Immediately he initiated an energetic series of military campaigns which would transform the small state around Cuzco into a formidable nation. His conquests in collaboration with Tupac Yupanqui (Pachacuti's son and successor) were so successful that the ninth Incan emperor is sometimes referred to as "The Napoleon of the Andes." When Pachacuti died in 1471 the empire stretched from Chile to the south and Ecuador to the north also including the modern countries of Peru and Bolivia as well as most of northern Argentina.[PARAGRAPH:1]Pachacuti also reorganized the new empire, the Tahuantinsuyu or "the united four provinces." Under his system, there were four apos that each controlled one of four provinces (suyu). Below these governors were t'oqrikoq, or local leaders, who ran a city, valley, or mine. By the time of the Spanish conquest of Peru, each apo had around 15 t'oqrikoq below him, but we can assume there were fewer when Pachacuti first organized this system. He also established a separate chain of command for the army and priesthood to establish a system of checks and balances on power.[PARAGRAPH:1]Pachacuti rebuilt much of Cuzco, designing it to serve the needs of an imperial city, and indeed as a representation of the empire. There was a sector of the city for each suyu, centering on the road leading to that province; nobles and immigrants lived in the sector corresponding to their origin. Each sector was further divided into areas for the hanan (upper) and hurin (lower) moieties. The Inca and his family lived in the center, the most prestigious area. Many of the most renowned monuments around Cuzco, such as the great sun temple of Coricancha or the "fortress" of Sacsayhuamán, were constructed during Pachacuti's reign.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Pachacuti[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]9-ty Sapa Inca[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rządził:[\BOLD] 1438 - 1471[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]dziewiąty król Inków (Sapa Inka) od 1438 do 1471 roku, jeden z największych i najbardziej zasłużonych władców inkaskiego państwa, uznawany za twórcę jego imperialnej potęgi. Urodzony jako Cusi Yupanqui, do władzy doszedł ponoć, gdy jego ojciec Viracocha i jego prawowity następca opuścili Cuzco zaatakowane przez wrogie plemię Chanca. Po obronieniu stolicy i przejęciu władzy przyjął imię Pachacútec Inka Yupanqui co tłumaczy się na Reformator Swiata lub Zbawca Ziemi. Jako władca królestwa i wódz naczelny inkaskiej armii rozpoczął erę podboju obszarów między Limą i Jeziorem Titicaca, która w ciągu trzech pokoleń rozszerzyła państwo Inków z obszaru doliny Cuzco na znaczną część Andów, od dzisiejszego Ekwadoru po środkowe Chile. Jego żołnierze używali proc wykonanych z kamieni połączonych sznurkami, drewnianych dzid, mieczy i buzdyganów. W 1450 roku odbił krainę wokół jeziora Titicaca, a w 1463 roku rozpoczął wojnę przeciw tamtejszym plemionom Lupaca i Colla z grupy Ajmarów. W tymże roku przekazał dowodzenie wojskiem swemu synowi Topie (Tupac Yupanqui)</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Пачакутек[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Девятый Сапа Инка[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы правления: [\BOLD]1438 - 1471[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]«Изменивший мир» был девятым Сапа Инкой Королевства Куско, которое он превратил в империю Тавантинсуйу. Он начал эру завоеваний, которая за три поколения расширила владения инков от долины Куско до почти всей цивилизованной Южной Америки. Он был четвертым представителем династии Ханан, и вместе со своей женой, которую звали Мама Анавархи или Койя Анаурке, у него было двое сыновей. После смерти отца Пачакутек стал единоличным правителем империи инков. Сразу же он инициировал серию энергичных военных кампаний, которые обратили маленькое государство вокруг Куско в грозную державу. Его завоевания в соправлении с Тупаком Юпанки (сыном и преемником Пачакутек) были настолько успешными, что девятого императора инков иногда называют «Наполеоном Анд». Когда Пачакутек умер в 1471 году, империя простиралась от Чили на юг и Эквадора на севере, включая современные страны Перу и Боливию, а также большую часть северной Аргентины.[PARAGRAPH:1]Пачакутек также реорганизовал новую империю, Тауантинсуйу, или «объединенные четыре провинции». В его системе было четыре апо, каждый из которых контролировал одну из четырех провинций (суйю). Ниже этих правителей были токрикок, или местные лидеры, которые управляли городом, долиной или шахтой. Ко времени испанского завоевания Перу у каждого апо было около 15 токрикоков ниже его, но мы можем предположить, что их было меньше, когда Пачакутек впервые организовал эту систему. Он также установил отдельную цепочку командования для армии и духовенства, чтобы установить систему сдержек и противовесов власти.[PARAGRAPH:1]Пачакутек перестроил большую часть Куско, спроектировав его так, чтобы он служил потребностям имперского города и, по сути, представлял собой империю. На каждую суйю приходился сектор города с центром на дороге, ведущей в эту провинцию; дворяне и иммигранты жили в секторе, соответствующем их происхождению. Каждый сектор был далее разделен на области для частей ханан (верхний) и хурин (нижний). Инка и его семья жили в центре, самом престижном районе. Многие из самых известных памятников в окрестностях Куско, такие как великий храм солнца Кориканча или «крепость» Саксайуаман, были построены во время правления Пачакутека.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>