<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 Beyond the Sword -->
<!-- Modified by the Civ Gold Team -->
<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VENEZUELA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Venezuelan Empire</English>
		<French>Venezuelan Empire</French>
		<German>Venezuelan Empire</German>
		<Italian>Venezuelan Empire</Italian>
		<Spanish>Venezuelan Empire</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VENEZUELA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Venezuela</English>
		<French>Venezuela</French>
		<German>Venezuela</German>
		<Italian>Venezuela</Italian>
		<Spanish>Venezuela</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VENEZUELA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Venezuelan</English>
		<French>Venezuelan</French>
		<German>Venezuelan</German>
		<Italian>Venezuelan</Italian>
		<Spanish>Venezuelan</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VENEZUELA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Venezuela, officially the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela (Spanish: Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela), is a country on the northern coast of South America. The country comprises a continental mainland and numerous islands located off the Venezuelan coastline in the Caribbean Sea. The Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela possesses borders with Guyana to the east, Brazil to the south, and Colombia to the west. Trinidad and Tobago, Grenada, St. Lucia, Barbados, Curacao, Bonaire, Aruba, Saint Vincent and the Grenadines and the Leeward Antilles lie just north, off the Venezuelan coast. Falling within the tropics, Venezuela sits close to the equator, in the Northern Hemisphere. A former Spanish colony, which has been an independent republic since 1821, Venezuela holds territorial disputes with Guyana, largely concerning the Essequibo area, and with Colombia concerning the Gulf of Venezuela. In 1895, after the dispute over the Guyana border flared up, it was submitted to a neutral commission, which in 1899 decided it mostly in Guyana's favour. Today, the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela is known widely for its petroleum industry, the environmental diversity of its territory, and its natural features. Venezuela is considered to be among the world's 17 most biodiverse countries. Venezuela is among the most urbanized countries in Latin America; the vast majority of Venezuelans live in the cities of the north, especially in the capital Caracas which is also the largest city. Other major cities include Maracaibo, Valencia, Maracay, Barquisimeto, Ciudad Guayana and the popular tourist city of Merida. Venezuela is also home to a diversity of wildlife in a variety of protected habitats. The name "Venezuela" is believed to have originated from the cartographer Amerigo Vespucci who, along with Alonso de Ojeda, led a 1499 naval expedition along the northwestern coast's Gulf of Venezuela. On reaching the Guajira Peninsula, the crew observed villages (palafitos) that the people had built over the water. This reminded Vespucci of the city of Venice (Italian: Venezia), so he named the region "Venezuola", meaning "little Venice" in Italian. In Spanish, the suffix -zuela is used as a diminutive term (e.g., plaza / plazuela, cazo / cazuela); thus, the term's original sense would have been that of a "little Venice". Martin Fernandez de Enciso, a member of the Vespucci and Ojeda's crew, states in his work Summa de Geografia that the indigenous population they found were called "Veneciuela", suggesting that the name "Venezuela" may have evolved from a native word. The Vespucci story, however, remains the most popular and accepted version of the origin of the country's name. Human habitation of Venezuela is estimated to have commenced at least 15,000 years ago from which period leaf-shaped flake tools, together with chopping and plano-convex scraping implements, have been found exposed on the high riverine terraces of the Rio Pedregal in western Venezuela. Late Pleistocene hunting artifacts, including spear tips, have been found at a similar series of sites in northwestern Venezuela known as "El Jobo"; according to radiocarbon dating, these date from 13,000 to 7,000 BC. In the 16th century, when the Spanish colonization of Venezuela began, indigenous peoples such as the Mariches, themselves descendants of the Caribs, were systematically killed. Indian caciques (leaders) such as Guaicaipuro and Tamanaco attempted to resist Spanish incursions, but were ultimately subdued; Tamanaco himself, by order of Caracas' founder Diego de Losada, was also put to death. Venezuela was first colonized by Spain in 1522, when it hosted the Spanish Empire's first permanent South American settlement[citation needed] in what is now Cumaná. These portions of eastern Venezuela were incorporated into New Andalusia. Administered by the Audiencia of Santo Domingo since the early 16th century, most of Venezuela became part of the Viceroyalty of New Granada in the early 18th century, and was then reorganized as an autonomous Captaincy General starting in 1776. After a series of unsuccessful uprisings, Venezuela—under the leadership of Francisco de Miranda, a Venezuelan marshal involved in the French Revolution—declared independence on 5 July 1811. This began the Venezuelan War of Independence. However, a devastating earthquake that struck Caracas in 1812, together with the rebellion of the Venezuelan llaneros, helped bring down the first Venezuelan republic. A second Venezuelan republic, proclaimed on 7 August 1813, lasted several months before being crushed as well. Sovereignty was only attained after Simon Bolivar, aided by José Antonio Páez and Antonio José de Sucre, won the Battle of Carabobo on 24 June 1821. Jose Prudencio Padilla and Rafael Urdaneta's victory in the Battle of Lake Maracaibo on 24 July 1823 helped seal Venezuelan independence. New Granada's congress gave Bolívar control of the Granadian army; leading it, he liberated several countries and founded Gran Colombia. Sucre, who won many battles for Bolívar, went on to liberate Ecuador, and later become the second president of Bolivia. Venezuela remained part of Gran Colombia until 1830, when a rebellion led by Páez allowed the proclamation of a new Republic of Venezuela; Páez became its first president. Much of Venezuela's nineteenth century history was characterized by political turmoil and dictatorial rule. During first half of the 20th century, caudillos (military strongmen) continued to dominate, though they generally allowed for mild social reforms and promoted economic growth. Following the death of Juan Vicente Gómez in 1935 and the demise of caudillismo (authoritarian rule), pro-democracy movements eventually forced the military to withdraw from direct involvement in national politics in 1958. Since that year, Venezuela has had a series of democratically elected governments. The discovery of massive oil deposits, totaling some 400 million barrels,[citation needed] during World War I prompted an economic boom that lasted into the 1980s; by 1935, Venezuela's per capita GDP was Latin America's highest. After World War II the globalization and heavy immigration from Southern Europe (mainly from Spain, Italy, Portugal) and poorer Latin American countries markedly diversified Venezuelan society. The huge public spending and accumulation of internal and external debts by the government and private sector during the Petrodollar years of the 1970s and early 1980s, followed by the collapse of oil prices during the 1980s, crippled the Venezuelan economy. As the government devalued the currency in order to face its mounting local and non-local financial obligations, Venezuelans' real standard of living fell dramatically. A number of failed economic policies and increasing corruption in government and society at large, has led to rising poverty and crime and worsening social indicators and increasing political instability,[opinion needs balancing] resulting in two major coup attempts in 1992. In the February 1992 coup, Hugo Chavez, a former paratrooper, attempted to overthrow the government of President Carlos Andres Perez as anger grew against the President's economic austerity measures. Chavez was unsuccessful and landed in jail. In November of that year, another unsuccessful coup attempt occurred, organized by other revolutionary groups in the Venezuelan Armed Forces and those that remained from Chavez’s previous attempt. In 1998, Hugo Chavez (who led the first unsuccessful coup in 1992) was elected president as a reaction against the established political parties and the corruption and inequalities their policies created. He remains president today. Since coming to power, Chavez has attracted some controversy through his reforms of the Constitution, the implementation of his "Bolivarian Revolution", and in April 2002 (though now a democratically elected president) Chavez was temporarily ousted from power by right-wing elements in the army and the business sector. The venezuelan president is elected by a vote with direct and universal suffrage, and functions as both head of state and head of government. The term of office is six years, and a president may be re-elected to a single consecutive term. The president appoints the vice-president and decides the size and composition of the cabinet and makes appointments to it with the involvement of the legislature. The president can ask the legislature to reconsider portions of laws he finds objectionable, but a simple parliamentary majority can diminish these objections. The unicameral Venezuelan parliament is the National Assembly or Asamblea Nacional. Its 167 deputies, of which three are reserved for indigenous people, serve five-year terms and may be re-elected for a maximum of two additional terms. They are elected by popular vote through a combination of party lists and single member constituencies. The highest judicial body is the Supreme Tribunal of Justice or Tribunal Supremo de Justicia, whose magistrates are elected by parliament for a single twelve-year term. The National Electoral Council (Consejo Nacional Electoral, or CNE) is in charge of electoral processes; it is formed by five main directors elected by the National Assembly.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Venezuela, officially the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela (Spanish: Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela), is a country on the northern coast of South America. The country comprises a continental mainland and numerous islands located off the Venezuelan coastline in the Caribbean Sea. The Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela possesses borders with Guyana to the east, Brazil to the south, and Colombia to the west. Trinidad and Tobago, Grenada, St. Lucia, Barbados, Curacao, Bonaire, Aruba, Saint Vincent and the Grenadines and the Leeward Antilles lie just north, off the Venezuelan coast. Falling within the tropics, Venezuela sits close to the equator, in the Northern Hemisphere. A former Spanish colony, which has been an independent republic since 1821, Venezuela holds territorial disputes with Guyana, largely concerning the Essequibo area, and with Colombia concerning the Gulf of Venezuela. In 1895, after the dispute over the Guyana border flared up, it was submitted to a neutral commission, which in 1899 decided it mostly in Guyana's favour. Today, the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela is known widely for its petroleum industry, the environmental diversity of its territory, and its natural features. Venezuela is considered to be among the world's 17 most biodiverse countries. Venezuela is among the most urbanized countries in Latin America; the vast majority of Venezuelans live in the cities of the north, especially in the capital Caracas which is also the largest city. Other major cities include Maracaibo, Valencia, Maracay, Barquisimeto, Ciudad Guayana and the popular tourist city of Merida. Venezuela is also home to a diversity of wildlife in a variety of protected habitats. The name "Venezuela" is believed to have originated from the cartographer Amerigo Vespucci who, along with Alonso de Ojeda, led a 1499 naval expedition along the northwestern coast's Gulf of Venezuela. On reaching the Guajira Peninsula, the crew observed villages (palafitos) that the people had built over the water. This reminded Vespucci of the city of Venice (Italian: Venezia), so he named the region "Venezuola", meaning "little Venice" in Italian. In Spanish, the suffix -zuela is used as a diminutive term (e.g., plaza / plazuela, cazo / cazuela); thus, the term's original sense would have been that of a "little Venice". Martin Fernandez de Enciso, a member of the Vespucci and Ojeda's crew, states in his work Summa de Geografia that the indigenous population they found were called "Veneciuela", suggesting that the name "Venezuela" may have evolved from a native word. The Vespucci story, however, remains the most popular and accepted version of the origin of the country's name. Human habitation of Venezuela is estimated to have commenced at least 15,000 years ago from which period leaf-shaped flake tools, together with chopping and plano-convex scraping implements, have been found exposed on the high riverine terraces of the Rio Pedregal in western Venezuela. Late Pleistocene hunting artifacts, including spear tips, have been found at a similar series of sites in northwestern Venezuela known as "El Jobo"; according to radiocarbon dating, these date from 13,000 to 7,000 BC. In the 16th century, when the Spanish colonization of Venezuela began, indigenous peoples such as the Mariches, themselves descendants of the Caribs, were systematically killed. Indian caciques (leaders) such as Guaicaipuro and Tamanaco attempted to resist Spanish incursions, but were ultimately subdued; Tamanaco himself, by order of Caracas' founder Diego de Losada, was also put to death. Venezuela was first colonized by Spain in 1522, when it hosted the Spanish Empire's first permanent South American settlement[citation needed] in what is now Cumaná. These portions of eastern Venezuela were incorporated into New Andalusia. Administered by the Audiencia of Santo Domingo since the early 16th century, most of Venezuela became part of the Viceroyalty of New Granada in the early 18th century, and was then reorganized as an autonomous Captaincy General starting in 1776. After a series of unsuccessful uprisings, Venezuela—under the leadership of Francisco de Miranda, a Venezuelan marshal involved in the French Revolution—declared independence on 5 July 1811. This began the Venezuelan War of Independence. However, a devastating earthquake that struck Caracas in 1812, together with the rebellion of the Venezuelan llaneros, helped bring down the first Venezuelan republic. A second Venezuelan republic, proclaimed on 7 August 1813, lasted several months before being crushed as well. Sovereignty was only attained after Simon Bolivar, aided by José Antonio Páez and Antonio José de Sucre, won the Battle of Carabobo on 24 June 1821. Jose Prudencio Padilla and Rafael Urdaneta's victory in the Battle of Lake Maracaibo on 24 July 1823 helped seal Venezuelan independence. New Granada's congress gave Bolívar control of the Granadian army; leading it, he liberated several countries and founded Gran Colombia. Sucre, who won many battles for Bolívar, went on to liberate Ecuador, and later become the second president of Bolivia. Venezuela remained part of Gran Colombia until 1830, when a rebellion led by Páez allowed the proclamation of a new Republic of Venezuela; Páez became its first president. Much of Venezuela's nineteenth century history was characterized by political turmoil and dictatorial rule. During first half of the 20th century, caudillos (military strongmen) continued to dominate, though they generally allowed for mild social reforms and promoted economic growth. Following the death of Juan Vicente Gómez in 1935 and the demise of caudillismo (authoritarian rule), pro-democracy movements eventually forced the military to withdraw from direct involvement in national politics in 1958. Since that year, Venezuela has had a series of democratically elected governments. The discovery of massive oil deposits, totaling some 400 million barrels,[citation needed] during World War I prompted an economic boom that lasted into the 1980s; by 1935, Venezuela's per capita GDP was Latin America's highest. After World War II the globalization and heavy immigration from Southern Europe (mainly from Spain, Italy, Portugal) and poorer Latin American countries markedly diversified Venezuelan society. The huge public spending and accumulation of internal and external debts by the government and private sector during the Petrodollar years of the 1970s and early 1980s, followed by the collapse of oil prices during the 1980s, crippled the Venezuelan economy. As the government devalued the currency in order to face its mounting local and non-local financial obligations, Venezuelans' real standard of living fell dramatically. A number of failed economic policies and increasing corruption in government and society at large, has led to rising poverty and crime and worsening social indicators and increasing political instability,[opinion needs balancing] resulting in two major coup attempts in 1992. In the February 1992 coup, Hugo Chavez, a former paratrooper, attempted to overthrow the government of President Carlos Andres Perez as anger grew against the President's economic austerity measures. Chavez was unsuccessful and landed in jail. In November of that year, another unsuccessful coup attempt occurred, organized by other revolutionary groups in the Venezuelan Armed Forces and those that remained from Chavez’s previous attempt. In 1998, Hugo Chavez (who led the first unsuccessful coup in 1992) was elected president as a reaction against the established political parties and the corruption and inequalities their policies created. He remains president today. Since coming to power, Chavez has attracted some controversy through his reforms of the Constitution, the implementation of his "Bolivarian Revolution", and in April 2002 (though now a democratically elected president) Chavez was temporarily ousted from power by right-wing elements in the army and the business sector. The venezuelan president is elected by a vote with direct and universal suffrage, and functions as both head of state and head of government. The term of office is six years, and a president may be re-elected to a single consecutive term. The president appoints the vice-president and decides the size and composition of the cabinet and makes appointments to it with the involvement of the legislature. The president can ask the legislature to reconsider portions of laws he finds objectionable, but a simple parliamentary majority can diminish these objections. The unicameral Venezuelan parliament is the National Assembly or Asamblea Nacional. Its 167 deputies, of which three are reserved for indigenous people, serve five-year terms and may be re-elected for a maximum of two additional terms. They are elected by popular vote through a combination of party lists and single member constituencies. The highest judicial body is the Supreme Tribunal of Justice or Tribunal Supremo de Justicia, whose magistrates are elected by parliament for a single twelve-year term. The National Electoral Council (Consejo Nacional Electoral, or CNE) is in charge of electoral processes; it is formed by five main directors elected by the National Assembly.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Venezuela, officially the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela (Spanish: Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela), is a country on the northern coast of South America. The country comprises a continental mainland and numerous islands located off the Venezuelan coastline in the Caribbean Sea. The Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela possesses borders with Guyana to the east, Brazil to the south, and Colombia to the west. Trinidad and Tobago, Grenada, St. Lucia, Barbados, Curacao, Bonaire, Aruba, Saint Vincent and the Grenadines and the Leeward Antilles lie just north, off the Venezuelan coast. Falling within the tropics, Venezuela sits close to the equator, in the Northern Hemisphere. A former Spanish colony, which has been an independent republic since 1821, Venezuela holds territorial disputes with Guyana, largely concerning the Essequibo area, and with Colombia concerning the Gulf of Venezuela. In 1895, after the dispute over the Guyana border flared up, it was submitted to a neutral commission, which in 1899 decided it mostly in Guyana's favour. Today, the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela is known widely for its petroleum industry, the environmental diversity of its territory, and its natural features. Venezuela is considered to be among the world's 17 most biodiverse countries. Venezuela is among the most urbanized countries in Latin America; the vast majority of Venezuelans live in the cities of the north, especially in the capital Caracas which is also the largest city. Other major cities include Maracaibo, Valencia, Maracay, Barquisimeto, Ciudad Guayana and the popular tourist city of Merida. Venezuela is also home to a diversity of wildlife in a variety of protected habitats. The name "Venezuela" is believed to have originated from the cartographer Amerigo Vespucci who, along with Alonso de Ojeda, led a 1499 naval expedition along the northwestern coast's Gulf of Venezuela. On reaching the Guajira Peninsula, the crew observed villages (palafitos) that the people had built over the water. This reminded Vespucci of the city of Venice (Italian: Venezia), so he named the region "Venezuola", meaning "little Venice" in Italian. In Spanish, the suffix -zuela is used as a diminutive term (e.g., plaza / plazuela, cazo / cazuela); thus, the term's original sense would have been that of a "little Venice". Martin Fernandez de Enciso, a member of the Vespucci and Ojeda's crew, states in his work Summa de Geografia that the indigenous population they found were called "Veneciuela", suggesting that the name "Venezuela" may have evolved from a native word. The Vespucci story, however, remains the most popular and accepted version of the origin of the country's name. Human habitation of Venezuela is estimated to have commenced at least 15,000 years ago from which period leaf-shaped flake tools, together with chopping and plano-convex scraping implements, have been found exposed on the high riverine terraces of the Rio Pedregal in western Venezuela. Late Pleistocene hunting artifacts, including spear tips, have been found at a similar series of sites in northwestern Venezuela known as "El Jobo"; according to radiocarbon dating, these date from 13,000 to 7,000 BC. In the 16th century, when the Spanish colonization of Venezuela began, indigenous peoples such as the Mariches, themselves descendants of the Caribs, were systematically killed. Indian caciques (leaders) such as Guaicaipuro and Tamanaco attempted to resist Spanish incursions, but were ultimately subdued; Tamanaco himself, by order of Caracas' founder Diego de Losada, was also put to death. Venezuela was first colonized by Spain in 1522, when it hosted the Spanish Empire's first permanent South American settlement[citation needed] in what is now Cumaná. These portions of eastern Venezuela were incorporated into New Andalusia. Administered by the Audiencia of Santo Domingo since the early 16th century, most of Venezuela became part of the Viceroyalty of New Granada in the early 18th century, and was then reorganized as an autonomous Captaincy General starting in 1776. After a series of unsuccessful uprisings, Venezuela—under the leadership of Francisco de Miranda, a Venezuelan marshal involved in the French Revolution—declared independence on 5 July 1811. This began the Venezuelan War of Independence. However, a devastating earthquake that struck Caracas in 1812, together with the rebellion of the Venezuelan llaneros, helped bring down the first Venezuelan republic. A second Venezuelan republic, proclaimed on 7 August 1813, lasted several months before being crushed as well. Sovereignty was only attained after Simon Bolivar, aided by José Antonio Páez and Antonio José de Sucre, won the Battle of Carabobo on 24 June 1821. Jose Prudencio Padilla and Rafael Urdaneta's victory in the Battle of Lake Maracaibo on 24 July 1823 helped seal Venezuelan independence. New Granada's congress gave Bolívar control of the Granadian army; leading it, he liberated several countries and founded Gran Colombia. Sucre, who won many battles for Bolívar, went on to liberate Ecuador, and later become the second president of Bolivia. Venezuela remained part of Gran Colombia until 1830, when a rebellion led by Páez allowed the proclamation of a new Republic of Venezuela; Páez became its first president. Much of Venezuela's nineteenth century history was characterized by political turmoil and dictatorial rule. During first half of the 20th century, caudillos (military strongmen) continued to dominate, though they generally allowed for mild social reforms and promoted economic growth. Following the death of Juan Vicente Gómez in 1935 and the demise of caudillismo (authoritarian rule), pro-democracy movements eventually forced the military to withdraw from direct involvement in national politics in 1958. Since that year, Venezuela has had a series of democratically elected governments. The discovery of massive oil deposits, totaling some 400 million barrels,[citation needed] during World War I prompted an economic boom that lasted into the 1980s; by 1935, Venezuela's per capita GDP was Latin America's highest. After World War II the globalization and heavy immigration from Southern Europe (mainly from Spain, Italy, Portugal) and poorer Latin American countries markedly diversified Venezuelan society. The huge public spending and accumulation of internal and external debts by the government and private sector during the Petrodollar years of the 1970s and early 1980s, followed by the collapse of oil prices during the 1980s, crippled the Venezuelan economy. As the government devalued the currency in order to face its mounting local and non-local financial obligations, Venezuelans' real standard of living fell dramatically. A number of failed economic policies and increasing corruption in government and society at large, has led to rising poverty and crime and worsening social indicators and increasing political instability,[opinion needs balancing] resulting in two major coup attempts in 1992. In the February 1992 coup, Hugo Chavez, a former paratrooper, attempted to overthrow the government of President Carlos Andres Perez as anger grew against the President's economic austerity measures. Chavez was unsuccessful and landed in jail. In November of that year, another unsuccessful coup attempt occurred, organized by other revolutionary groups in the Venezuelan Armed Forces and those that remained from Chavez’s previous attempt. In 1998, Hugo Chavez (who led the first unsuccessful coup in 1992) was elected president as a reaction against the established political parties and the corruption and inequalities their policies created. He remains president today. Since coming to power, Chavez has attracted some controversy through his reforms of the Constitution, the implementation of his "Bolivarian Revolution", and in April 2002 (though now a democratically elected president) Chavez was temporarily ousted from power by right-wing elements in the army and the business sector. The venezuelan president is elected by a vote with direct and universal suffrage, and functions as both head of state and head of government. The term of office is six years, and a president may be re-elected to a single consecutive term. The president appoints the vice-president and decides the size and composition of the cabinet and makes appointments to it with the involvement of the legislature. The president can ask the legislature to reconsider portions of laws he finds objectionable, but a simple parliamentary majority can diminish these objections. The unicameral Venezuelan parliament is the National Assembly or Asamblea Nacional. Its 167 deputies, of which three are reserved for indigenous people, serve five-year terms and may be re-elected for a maximum of two additional terms. They are elected by popular vote through a combination of party lists and single member constituencies. The highest judicial body is the Supreme Tribunal of Justice or Tribunal Supremo de Justicia, whose magistrates are elected by parliament for a single twelve-year term. The National Electoral Council (Consejo Nacional Electoral, or CNE) is in charge of electoral processes; it is formed by five main directors elected by the National Assembly.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Venezuela, officially the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela (Spanish: Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela), is a country on the northern coast of South America. The country comprises a continental mainland and numerous islands located off the Venezuelan coastline in the Caribbean Sea. The Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela possesses borders with Guyana to the east, Brazil to the south, and Colombia to the west. Trinidad and Tobago, Grenada, St. Lucia, Barbados, Curacao, Bonaire, Aruba, Saint Vincent and the Grenadines and the Leeward Antilles lie just north, off the Venezuelan coast. Falling within the tropics, Venezuela sits close to the equator, in the Northern Hemisphere. A former Spanish colony, which has been an independent republic since 1821, Venezuela holds territorial disputes with Guyana, largely concerning the Essequibo area, and with Colombia concerning the Gulf of Venezuela. In 1895, after the dispute over the Guyana border flared up, it was submitted to a neutral commission, which in 1899 decided it mostly in Guyana's favour. Today, the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela is known widely for its petroleum industry, the environmental diversity of its territory, and its natural features. Venezuela is considered to be among the world's 17 most biodiverse countries. Venezuela is among the most urbanized countries in Latin America; the vast majority of Venezuelans live in the cities of the north, especially in the capital Caracas which is also the largest city. Other major cities include Maracaibo, Valencia, Maracay, Barquisimeto, Ciudad Guayana and the popular tourist city of Merida. Venezuela is also home to a diversity of wildlife in a variety of protected habitats. The name "Venezuela" is believed to have originated from the cartographer Amerigo Vespucci who, along with Alonso de Ojeda, led a 1499 naval expedition along the northwestern coast's Gulf of Venezuela. On reaching the Guajira Peninsula, the crew observed villages (palafitos) that the people had built over the water. This reminded Vespucci of the city of Venice (Italian: Venezia), so he named the region "Venezuola", meaning "little Venice" in Italian. In Spanish, the suffix -zuela is used as a diminutive term (e.g., plaza / plazuela, cazo / cazuela); thus, the term's original sense would have been that of a "little Venice". Martin Fernandez de Enciso, a member of the Vespucci and Ojeda's crew, states in his work Summa de Geografia that the indigenous population they found were called "Veneciuela", suggesting that the name "Venezuela" may have evolved from a native word. The Vespucci story, however, remains the most popular and accepted version of the origin of the country's name. Human habitation of Venezuela is estimated to have commenced at least 15,000 years ago from which period leaf-shaped flake tools, together with chopping and plano-convex scraping implements, have been found exposed on the high riverine terraces of the Rio Pedregal in western Venezuela. Late Pleistocene hunting artifacts, including spear tips, have been found at a similar series of sites in northwestern Venezuela known as "El Jobo"; according to radiocarbon dating, these date from 13,000 to 7,000 BC. In the 16th century, when the Spanish colonization of Venezuela began, indigenous peoples such as the Mariches, themselves descendants of the Caribs, were systematically killed. Indian caciques (leaders) such as Guaicaipuro and Tamanaco attempted to resist Spanish incursions, but were ultimately subdued; Tamanaco himself, by order of Caracas' founder Diego de Losada, was also put to death. Venezuela was first colonized by Spain in 1522, when it hosted the Spanish Empire's first permanent South American settlement[citation needed] in what is now Cumaná. These portions of eastern Venezuela were incorporated into New Andalusia. Administered by the Audiencia of Santo Domingo since the early 16th century, most of Venezuela became part of the Viceroyalty of New Granada in the early 18th century, and was then reorganized as an autonomous Captaincy General starting in 1776. After a series of unsuccessful uprisings, Venezuela—under the leadership of Francisco de Miranda, a Venezuelan marshal involved in the French Revolution—declared independence on 5 July 1811. This began the Venezuelan War of Independence. However, a devastating earthquake that struck Caracas in 1812, together with the rebellion of the Venezuelan llaneros, helped bring down the first Venezuelan republic. A second Venezuelan republic, proclaimed on 7 August 1813, lasted several months before being crushed as well. Sovereignty was only attained after Simon Bolivar, aided by José Antonio Páez and Antonio José de Sucre, won the Battle of Carabobo on 24 June 1821. Jose Prudencio Padilla and Rafael Urdaneta's victory in the Battle of Lake Maracaibo on 24 July 1823 helped seal Venezuelan independence. New Granada's congress gave Bolívar control of the Granadian army; leading it, he liberated several countries and founded Gran Colombia. Sucre, who won many battles for Bolívar, went on to liberate Ecuador, and later become the second president of Bolivia. Venezuela remained part of Gran Colombia until 1830, when a rebellion led by Páez allowed the proclamation of a new Republic of Venezuela; Páez became its first president. Much of Venezuela's nineteenth century history was characterized by political turmoil and dictatorial rule. During first half of the 20th century, caudillos (military strongmen) continued to dominate, though they generally allowed for mild social reforms and promoted economic growth. Following the death of Juan Vicente Gómez in 1935 and the demise of caudillismo (authoritarian rule), pro-democracy movements eventually forced the military to withdraw from direct involvement in national politics in 1958. Since that year, Venezuela has had a series of democratically elected governments. The discovery of massive oil deposits, totaling some 400 million barrels,[citation needed] during World War I prompted an economic boom that lasted into the 1980s; by 1935, Venezuela's per capita GDP was Latin America's highest. After World War II the globalization and heavy immigration from Southern Europe (mainly from Spain, Italy, Portugal) and poorer Latin American countries markedly diversified Venezuelan society. The huge public spending and accumulation of internal and external debts by the government and private sector during the Petrodollar years of the 1970s and early 1980s, followed by the collapse of oil prices during the 1980s, crippled the Venezuelan economy. As the government devalued the currency in order to face its mounting local and non-local financial obligations, Venezuelans' real standard of living fell dramatically. A number of failed economic policies and increasing corruption in government and society at large, has led to rising poverty and crime and worsening social indicators and increasing political instability,[opinion needs balancing] resulting in two major coup attempts in 1992. In the February 1992 coup, Hugo Chavez, a former paratrooper, attempted to overthrow the government of President Carlos Andres Perez as anger grew against the President's economic austerity measures. Chavez was unsuccessful and landed in jail. In November of that year, another unsuccessful coup attempt occurred, organized by other revolutionary groups in the Venezuelan Armed Forces and those that remained from Chavez’s previous attempt. In 1998, Hugo Chavez (who led the first unsuccessful coup in 1992) was elected president as a reaction against the established political parties and the corruption and inequalities their policies created. He remains president today. Since coming to power, Chavez has attracted some controversy through his reforms of the Constitution, the implementation of his "Bolivarian Revolution", and in April 2002 (though now a democratically elected president) Chavez was temporarily ousted from power by right-wing elements in the army and the business sector. The venezuelan president is elected by a vote with direct and universal suffrage, and functions as both head of state and head of government. The term of office is six years, and a president may be re-elected to a single consecutive term. The president appoints the vice-president and decides the size and composition of the cabinet and makes appointments to it with the involvement of the legislature. The president can ask the legislature to reconsider portions of laws he finds objectionable, but a simple parliamentary majority can diminish these objections. The unicameral Venezuelan parliament is the National Assembly or Asamblea Nacional. Its 167 deputies, of which three are reserved for indigenous people, serve five-year terms and may be re-elected for a maximum of two additional terms. They are elected by popular vote through a combination of party lists and single member constituencies. The highest judicial body is the Supreme Tribunal of Justice or Tribunal Supremo de Justicia, whose magistrates are elected by parliament for a single twelve-year term. The National Electoral Council (Consejo Nacional Electoral, or CNE) is in charge of electoral processes; it is formed by five main directors elected by the National Assembly.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Venezuela, officially the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela (Spanish: Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela), is a country on the northern coast of South America. The country comprises a continental mainland and numerous islands located off the Venezuelan coastline in the Caribbean Sea. The Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela possesses borders with Guyana to the east, Brazil to the south, and Colombia to the west. Trinidad and Tobago, Grenada, St. Lucia, Barbados, Curacao, Bonaire, Aruba, Saint Vincent and the Grenadines and the Leeward Antilles lie just north, off the Venezuelan coast. Falling within the tropics, Venezuela sits close to the equator, in the Northern Hemisphere. A former Spanish colony, which has been an independent republic since 1821, Venezuela holds territorial disputes with Guyana, largely concerning the Essequibo area, and with Colombia concerning the Gulf of Venezuela. In 1895, after the dispute over the Guyana border flared up, it was submitted to a neutral commission, which in 1899 decided it mostly in Guyana's favour. Today, the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela is known widely for its petroleum industry, the environmental diversity of its territory, and its natural features. Venezuela is considered to be among the world's 17 most biodiverse countries. Venezuela is among the most urbanized countries in Latin America; the vast majority of Venezuelans live in the cities of the north, especially in the capital Caracas which is also the largest city. Other major cities include Maracaibo, Valencia, Maracay, Barquisimeto, Ciudad Guayana and the popular tourist city of Merida. Venezuela is also home to a diversity of wildlife in a variety of protected habitats. The name "Venezuela" is believed to have originated from the cartographer Amerigo Vespucci who, along with Alonso de Ojeda, led a 1499 naval expedition along the northwestern coast's Gulf of Venezuela. On reaching the Guajira Peninsula, the crew observed villages (palafitos) that the people had built over the water. This reminded Vespucci of the city of Venice (Italian: Venezia), so he named the region "Venezuola", meaning "little Venice" in Italian. In Spanish, the suffix -zuela is used as a diminutive term (e.g., plaza / plazuela, cazo / cazuela); thus, the term's original sense would have been that of a "little Venice". Martin Fernandez de Enciso, a member of the Vespucci and Ojeda's crew, states in his work Summa de Geografia that the indigenous population they found were called "Veneciuela", suggesting that the name "Venezuela" may have evolved from a native word. The Vespucci story, however, remains the most popular and accepted version of the origin of the country's name. Human habitation of Venezuela is estimated to have commenced at least 15,000 years ago from which period leaf-shaped flake tools, together with chopping and plano-convex scraping implements, have been found exposed on the high riverine terraces of the Rio Pedregal in western Venezuela. Late Pleistocene hunting artifacts, including spear tips, have been found at a similar series of sites in northwestern Venezuela known as "El Jobo"; according to radiocarbon dating, these date from 13,000 to 7,000 BC. In the 16th century, when the Spanish colonization of Venezuela began, indigenous peoples such as the Mariches, themselves descendants of the Caribs, were systematically killed. Indian caciques (leaders) such as Guaicaipuro and Tamanaco attempted to resist Spanish incursions, but were ultimately subdued; Tamanaco himself, by order of Caracas' founder Diego de Losada, was also put to death. Venezuela was first colonized by Spain in 1522, when it hosted the Spanish Empire's first permanent South American settlement[citation needed] in what is now Cumaná. These portions of eastern Venezuela were incorporated into New Andalusia. Administered by the Audiencia of Santo Domingo since the early 16th century, most of Venezuela became part of the Viceroyalty of New Granada in the early 18th century, and was then reorganized as an autonomous Captaincy General starting in 1776. After a series of unsuccessful uprisings, Venezuela—under the leadership of Francisco de Miranda, a Venezuelan marshal involved in the French Revolution—declared independence on 5 July 1811. This began the Venezuelan War of Independence. However, a devastating earthquake that struck Caracas in 1812, together with the rebellion of the Venezuelan llaneros, helped bring down the first Venezuelan republic. A second Venezuelan republic, proclaimed on 7 August 1813, lasted several months before being crushed as well. Sovereignty was only attained after Simon Bolivar, aided by José Antonio Páez and Antonio José de Sucre, won the Battle of Carabobo on 24 June 1821. Jose Prudencio Padilla and Rafael Urdaneta's victory in the Battle of Lake Maracaibo on 24 July 1823 helped seal Venezuelan independence. New Granada's congress gave Bolívar control of the Granadian army; leading it, he liberated several countries and founded Gran Colombia. Sucre, who won many battles for Bolívar, went on to liberate Ecuador, and later become the second president of Bolivia. Venezuela remained part of Gran Colombia until 1830, when a rebellion led by Páez allowed the proclamation of a new Republic of Venezuela; Páez became its first president. Much of Venezuela's nineteenth century history was characterized by political turmoil and dictatorial rule. During first half of the 20th century, caudillos (military strongmen) continued to dominate, though they generally allowed for mild social reforms and promoted economic growth. Following the death of Juan Vicente Gómez in 1935 and the demise of caudillismo (authoritarian rule), pro-democracy movements eventually forced the military to withdraw from direct involvement in national politics in 1958. Since that year, Venezuela has had a series of democratically elected governments. The discovery of massive oil deposits, totaling some 400 million barrels,[citation needed] during World War I prompted an economic boom that lasted into the 1980s; by 1935, Venezuela's per capita GDP was Latin America's highest. After World War II the globalization and heavy immigration from Southern Europe (mainly from Spain, Italy, Portugal) and poorer Latin American countries markedly diversified Venezuelan society. The huge public spending and accumulation of internal and external debts by the government and private sector during the Petrodollar years of the 1970s and early 1980s, followed by the collapse of oil prices during the 1980s, crippled the Venezuelan economy. As the government devalued the currency in order to face its mounting local and non-local financial obligations, Venezuelans' real standard of living fell dramatically. A number of failed economic policies and increasing corruption in government and society at large, has led to rising poverty and crime and worsening social indicators and increasing political instability,[opinion needs balancing] resulting in two major coup attempts in 1992. In the February 1992 coup, Hugo Chavez, a former paratrooper, attempted to overthrow the government of President Carlos Andres Perez as anger grew against the President's economic austerity measures. Chavez was unsuccessful and landed in jail. In November of that year, another unsuccessful coup attempt occurred, organized by other revolutionary groups in the Venezuelan Armed Forces and those that remained from Chavez’s previous attempt. In 1998, Hugo Chavez (who led the first unsuccessful coup in 1992) was elected president as a reaction against the established political parties and the corruption and inequalities their policies created. He remains president today. Since coming to power, Chavez has attracted some controversy through his reforms of the Constitution, the implementation of his "Bolivarian Revolution", and in April 2002 (though now a democratically elected president) Chavez was temporarily ousted from power by right-wing elements in the army and the business sector. The venezuelan president is elected by a vote with direct and universal suffrage, and functions as both head of state and head of government. The term of office is six years, and a president may be re-elected to a single consecutive term. The president appoints the vice-president and decides the size and composition of the cabinet and makes appointments to it with the involvement of the legislature. The president can ask the legislature to reconsider portions of laws he finds objectionable, but a simple parliamentary majority can diminish these objections. The unicameral Venezuelan parliament is the National Assembly or Asamblea Nacional. Its 167 deputies, of which three are reserved for indigenous people, serve five-year terms and may be re-elected for a maximum of two additional terms. They are elected by popular vote through a combination of party lists and single member constituencies. The highest judicial body is the Supreme Tribunal of Justice or Tribunal Supremo de Justicia, whose magistrates are elected by parliament for a single twelve-year term. The National Electoral Council (Consejo Nacional Electoral, or CNE) is in charge of electoral processes; it is formed by five main directors elected by the National Assembly.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHAVEZ</Tag>
		<English>Chavez</English>
		<French>Chavez</French>
		<German>Chavez</German>
		<Italian>Chavez</Italian>
		<Spanish>Chavez</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHAVEZ_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela  [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD]July 28, 1954 - 5 March 2013[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias is the current President of Venezuela. As the leader of the Bolivarian Revolution, Chavez promotes a political doctrine of democratic socialism and Latin American integration. He is also a critic of neoliberalism, globalization and United States foreign policy. A career military officer, Chavez founded the left-wing Fifth Republic Movement after orchestrating a failed 1992 coup d'etat against former President Carlos Andres Perez. Chavez was elected President in 1998 with a campaign centering on promises of aiding Venezuela's poor majority, and was reelected in 2000 and in 2006. Domestically, Chavez has maintained nation wide Bolivarian Missions, whose goals are to combat disease, illiteracy, malnutrition, poverty, and other social ills. Abroad, Chávez has acted against the Washington Consensus by supporting alternative models of economic development, and has advocated cooperation among the world's poor nations, especially those in Latin America.

	Chavez's policies have evoked controversy in Venezuela and abroad, receiving anything from vehement criticism to enthusiastic support. The government of the United States claims that Chavez is a threat to democracy in Latin America. Others sympathize with his ideology or welcome his bilateral trade and reciprocal aid agreements. In 2005 and 2006 he was named one of Time magazine's 100 most influential people. After a two-year imprisonment, Chavez was pardoned by President Rafael Caldera in 1994. Upon his release, Chavez reconstituted the MBR-200 as the Fifth Republic Movement (MVR—Movimiento Quinta Republica, with the V representing the Roman numeral five). Later, in 1998, Chavez began to campaign for the presidency. In working to earn the trust of voters, Chavez drafted an agenda that drew heavily on his ideology of Bolivarianism. Chavez and his followers described their aim as "laying the foundations of a new republic" to replace the existing one, which they cast as "party-dominated"; the current constitution, they argued, was no more than the 'juridico-political embodiment of puntofijismo,' the country's traditional two-party patronage system.

	Chavez utilized his flamboyant public speaking style, which was noted for its abundance of colloquialisms and ribald manner—on the campaign trail to win the trust and favour of a primarily poor and working class following. By May 1998, Chavez's support had risen to 30% in polls, and by August he was registering 39%. Chavez went on to win the 1998 presidential election on December 6, 1998 with 56% of the votes. Chavez was sworn in as president on February 2, 1999. Among his first acts was the launching of Plan Bolivar 2000, which included road building, housing construction, and mass vaccination. Chavez also halted planned privatizations of, among others, the national social security system, aluminum industry holdings, and the oil sector.[26] Chavez also overhauled the formerly lax tax collection and auditing system—especially regarding major corporations and landholders.

	Responding to the stalling of his legislation in the National Assembly, Chavez scheduled two national elections for July 1999, including a referendum for and elections to fill a new constitutional assembly. The Constitutional Assembly was created when the referendum passed with a 72% "yes" vote, while the pro-Chávez Polo Patriotico ("Patriotic Pole") won 95% (120 of the total 131) of its seats. In August 1999, the Constitutional Assembly's "Judicial Emergency Committee" declared a "legislative emergency" whereby a seven-member committee conducted the National Assembly's functions; meanwhile, the National Assembly was prohibited from holding meetings. The Constitutional Assembly drafted the 1999 Venezuelan Constitution, which included an increase in the presidential term from five to six years, a new presidential two-term limit, a new provision for presidential recall elections, renaming of the country to Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela, expanded presidential powers, conversion of the bicameral National Assembly into a unicameral legislature, merit-based appointments of judges, and creation of the Public Defender, an office authorized to regulate the activities of the presidency and the National Assembly.

	In December 1999, the new constitution was approved. On December 15, after weeks of heavy rain, statewide mudslides claimed the lives of an estimated 30,000 people. Critics claim Chavez was distracted by the referendum and that the government ignored a civil defense report, calling for emergency measures, issued the day the floods struck. The government rejected these claims. Chavez personally led the relief effort afterwards. With respect to domestic policies, critics claim that both corruption and crime are rampant. They also cite a failing infrastructure and public hospitals. Criticism from Chavez supporters arises from reports that Chavez is not fulfilling his major campaign pledges with respect to labor and land reform. Critics charged that the Chávez government has engaged in "gigantic fraud" during the 2004 recall referendum, though all international observers and exit polls confirmed the official result. The United States government claims that his cooperation in their war on terror is negligible or purposely indifferent with regards to the FARC and ELN, who are engaged in a conflict with the US-backed Colombian government; nonetheless, the US government says there is no evidence of a direct link between violent groups opposed to its policies and Chavez.

	Several public figures have even gone so far as to call for the assassination of Chavez, most notably US Conservative Christian televangelist Pat Robertson. Other such requests have been expressed by Venezuelan actor Orlando Urdaneta and former president of Venezuela Carlos Andres Perez. The US Ambassador to Venezuela between 2001 and 2004, Charles Shapiro, also reported to the Chavez administration two potential assassination plots. Chavez has been accused of concentrating power of judicial and legislative branches. The leading business daily of Argentina, Ambito Financiero, predicted that Venezuela under Chavez in 2007 would have a "nationalized economy, out-of-control spending, government by decree, and perpetual re-election." The motion which included the provision to allow indefinite presidential re-election was voted down in national referendum in 2007. The daily also compared Chavez to King Louis XIV of France, stating his 2007 inauguration would mark "a concentration of power without precedent in Venezuela."
		</English>
		<French>[H1]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela  [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD]July 28, 1954 - 5 March 2013[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias is the current President of Venezuela. As the leader of the Bolivarian Revolution, Chavez promotes a political doctrine of democratic socialism and Latin American integration. He is also a critic of neoliberalism, globalization and United States foreign policy. A career military officer, Chavez founded the left-wing Fifth Republic Movement after orchestrating a failed 1992 coup d'etat against former President Carlos Andres Perez. Chavez was elected President in 1998 with a campaign centering on promises of aiding Venezuela's poor majority, and was reelected in 2000 and in 2006. Domestically, Chavez has maintained nation wide Bolivarian Missions, whose goals are to combat disease, illiteracy, malnutrition, poverty, and other social ills. Abroad, Chávez has acted against the Washington Consensus by supporting alternative models of economic development, and has advocated cooperation among the world's poor nations, especially those in Latin America.

	Chavez's policies have evoked controversy in Venezuela and abroad, receiving anything from vehement criticism to enthusiastic support. The government of the United States claims that Chavez is a threat to democracy in Latin America. Others sympathize with his ideology or welcome his bilateral trade and reciprocal aid agreements. In 2005 and 2006 he was named one of Time magazine's 100 most influential people. After a two-year imprisonment, Chavez was pardoned by President Rafael Caldera in 1994. Upon his release, Chavez reconstituted the MBR-200 as the Fifth Republic Movement (MVR—Movimiento Quinta Republica, with the V representing the Roman numeral five). Later, in 1998, Chavez began to campaign for the presidency. In working to earn the trust of voters, Chavez drafted an agenda that drew heavily on his ideology of Bolivarianism. Chavez and his followers described their aim as "laying the foundations of a new republic" to replace the existing one, which they cast as "party-dominated"; the current constitution, they argued, was no more than the 'juridico-political embodiment of puntofijismo,' the country's traditional two-party patronage system.

	Chavez utilized his flamboyant public speaking style, which was noted for its abundance of colloquialisms and ribald manner—on the campaign trail to win the trust and favour of a primarily poor and working class following. By May 1998, Chavez's support had risen to 30% in polls, and by August he was registering 39%. Chavez went on to win the 1998 presidential election on December 6, 1998 with 56% of the votes. Chavez was sworn in as president on February 2, 1999. Among his first acts was the launching of Plan Bolivar 2000, which included road building, housing construction, and mass vaccination. Chavez also halted planned privatizations of, among others, the national social security system, aluminum industry holdings, and the oil sector.[26] Chavez also overhauled the formerly lax tax collection and auditing system—especially regarding major corporations and landholders.

	Responding to the stalling of his legislation in the National Assembly, Chavez scheduled two national elections for July 1999, including a referendum for and elections to fill a new constitutional assembly. The Constitutional Assembly was created when the referendum passed with a 72% "yes" vote, while the pro-Chávez Polo Patriotico ("Patriotic Pole") won 95% (120 of the total 131) of its seats. In August 1999, the Constitutional Assembly's "Judicial Emergency Committee" declared a "legislative emergency" whereby a seven-member committee conducted the National Assembly's functions; meanwhile, the National Assembly was prohibited from holding meetings. The Constitutional Assembly drafted the 1999 Venezuelan Constitution, which included an increase in the presidential term from five to six years, a new presidential two-term limit, a new provision for presidential recall elections, renaming of the country to Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela, expanded presidential powers, conversion of the bicameral National Assembly into a unicameral legislature, merit-based appointments of judges, and creation of the Public Defender, an office authorized to regulate the activities of the presidency and the National Assembly.

	In December 1999, the new constitution was approved. On December 15, after weeks of heavy rain, statewide mudslides claimed the lives of an estimated 30,000 people. Critics claim Chavez was distracted by the referendum and that the government ignored a civil defense report, calling for emergency measures, issued the day the floods struck. The government rejected these claims. Chavez personally led the relief effort afterwards. With respect to domestic policies, critics claim that both corruption and crime are rampant. They also cite a failing infrastructure and public hospitals. Criticism from Chavez supporters arises from reports that Chavez is not fulfilling his major campaign pledges with respect to labor and land reform. Critics charged that the Chávez government has engaged in "gigantic fraud" during the 2004 recall referendum, though all international observers and exit polls confirmed the official result. The United States government claims that his cooperation in their war on terror is negligible or purposely indifferent with regards to the FARC and ELN, who are engaged in a conflict with the US-backed Colombian government; nonetheless, the US government says there is no evidence of a direct link between violent groups opposed to its policies and Chavez.

	Several public figures have even gone so far as to call for the assassination of Chavez, most notably US Conservative Christian televangelist Pat Robertson. Other such requests have been expressed by Venezuelan actor Orlando Urdaneta and former president of Venezuela Carlos Andres Perez. The US Ambassador to Venezuela between 2001 and 2004, Charles Shapiro, also reported to the Chavez administration two potential assassination plots. Chavez has been accused of concentrating power of judicial and legislative branches. The leading business daily of Argentina, Ambito Financiero, predicted that Venezuela under Chavez in 2007 would have a "nationalized economy, out-of-control spending, government by decree, and perpetual re-election." The motion which included the provision to allow indefinite presidential re-election was voted down in national referendum in 2007. The daily also compared Chavez to King Louis XIV of France, stating his 2007 inauguration would mark "a concentration of power without precedent in Venezuela."</French>
		<German>[H1]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela  [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD]July 28, 1954 - 5 March 2013[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias is the current President of Venezuela. As the leader of the Bolivarian Revolution, Chavez promotes a political doctrine of democratic socialism and Latin American integration. He is also a critic of neoliberalism, globalization and United States foreign policy. A career military officer, Chavez founded the left-wing Fifth Republic Movement after orchestrating a failed 1992 coup d'etat against former President Carlos Andres Perez. Chavez was elected President in 1998 with a campaign centering on promises of aiding Venezuela's poor majority, and was reelected in 2000 and in 2006. Domestically, Chavez has maintained nation wide Bolivarian Missions, whose goals are to combat disease, illiteracy, malnutrition, poverty, and other social ills. Abroad, Chávez has acted against the Washington Consensus by supporting alternative models of economic development, and has advocated cooperation among the world's poor nations, especially those in Latin America.

	Chavez's policies have evoked controversy in Venezuela and abroad, receiving anything from vehement criticism to enthusiastic support. The government of the United States claims that Chavez is a threat to democracy in Latin America. Others sympathize with his ideology or welcome his bilateral trade and reciprocal aid agreements. In 2005 and 2006 he was named one of Time magazine's 100 most influential people. After a two-year imprisonment, Chavez was pardoned by President Rafael Caldera in 1994. Upon his release, Chavez reconstituted the MBR-200 as the Fifth Republic Movement (MVR—Movimiento Quinta Republica, with the V representing the Roman numeral five). Later, in 1998, Chavez began to campaign for the presidency. In working to earn the trust of voters, Chavez drafted an agenda that drew heavily on his ideology of Bolivarianism. Chavez and his followers described their aim as "laying the foundations of a new republic" to replace the existing one, which they cast as "party-dominated"; the current constitution, they argued, was no more than the 'juridico-political embodiment of puntofijismo,' the country's traditional two-party patronage system.

	Chavez utilized his flamboyant public speaking style, which was noted for its abundance of colloquialisms and ribald manner—on the campaign trail to win the trust and favour of a primarily poor and working class following. By May 1998, Chavez's support had risen to 30% in polls, and by August he was registering 39%. Chavez went on to win the 1998 presidential election on December 6, 1998 with 56% of the votes. Chavez was sworn in as president on February 2, 1999. Among his first acts was the launching of Plan Bolivar 2000, which included road building, housing construction, and mass vaccination. Chavez also halted planned privatizations of, among others, the national social security system, aluminum industry holdings, and the oil sector.[26] Chavez also overhauled the formerly lax tax collection and auditing system—especially regarding major corporations and landholders.

	Responding to the stalling of his legislation in the National Assembly, Chavez scheduled two national elections for July 1999, including a referendum for and elections to fill a new constitutional assembly. The Constitutional Assembly was created when the referendum passed with a 72% "yes" vote, while the pro-Chávez Polo Patriotico ("Patriotic Pole") won 95% (120 of the total 131) of its seats. In August 1999, the Constitutional Assembly's "Judicial Emergency Committee" declared a "legislative emergency" whereby a seven-member committee conducted the National Assembly's functions; meanwhile, the National Assembly was prohibited from holding meetings. The Constitutional Assembly drafted the 1999 Venezuelan Constitution, which included an increase in the presidential term from five to six years, a new presidential two-term limit, a new provision for presidential recall elections, renaming of the country to Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela, expanded presidential powers, conversion of the bicameral National Assembly into a unicameral legislature, merit-based appointments of judges, and creation of the Public Defender, an office authorized to regulate the activities of the presidency and the National Assembly.

	In December 1999, the new constitution was approved. On December 15, after weeks of heavy rain, statewide mudslides claimed the lives of an estimated 30,000 people. Critics claim Chavez was distracted by the referendum and that the government ignored a civil defense report, calling for emergency measures, issued the day the floods struck. The government rejected these claims. Chavez personally led the relief effort afterwards. With respect to domestic policies, critics claim that both corruption and crime are rampant. They also cite a failing infrastructure and public hospitals. Criticism from Chavez supporters arises from reports that Chavez is not fulfilling his major campaign pledges with respect to labor and land reform. Critics charged that the Chávez government has engaged in "gigantic fraud" during the 2004 recall referendum, though all international observers and exit polls confirmed the official result. The United States government claims that his cooperation in their war on terror is negligible or purposely indifferent with regards to the FARC and ELN, who are engaged in a conflict with the US-backed Colombian government; nonetheless, the US government says there is no evidence of a direct link between violent groups opposed to its policies and Chavez.

	Several public figures have even gone so far as to call for the assassination of Chavez, most notably US Conservative Christian televangelist Pat Robertson. Other such requests have been expressed by Venezuelan actor Orlando Urdaneta and former president of Venezuela Carlos Andres Perez. The US Ambassador to Venezuela between 2001 and 2004, Charles Shapiro, also reported to the Chavez administration two potential assassination plots. Chavez has been accused of concentrating power of judicial and legislative branches. The leading business daily of Argentina, Ambito Financiero, predicted that Venezuela under Chavez in 2007 would have a "nationalized economy, out-of-control spending, government by decree, and perpetual re-election." The motion which included the provision to allow indefinite presidential re-election was voted down in national referendum in 2007. The daily also compared Chavez to King Louis XIV of France, stating his 2007 inauguration would mark "a concentration of power without precedent in Venezuela."</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela  [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD]July 28, 1954 - 5 March 2013[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias is the current President of Venezuela. As the leader of the Bolivarian Revolution, Chavez promotes a political doctrine of democratic socialism and Latin American integration. He is also a critic of neoliberalism, globalization and United States foreign policy. A career military officer, Chavez founded the left-wing Fifth Republic Movement after orchestrating a failed 1992 coup d'etat against former President Carlos Andres Perez. Chavez was elected President in 1998 with a campaign centering on promises of aiding Venezuela's poor majority, and was reelected in 2000 and in 2006. Domestically, Chavez has maintained nation wide Bolivarian Missions, whose goals are to combat disease, illiteracy, malnutrition, poverty, and other social ills. Abroad, Chávez has acted against the Washington Consensus by supporting alternative models of economic development, and has advocated cooperation among the world's poor nations, especially those in Latin America.

	Chavez's policies have evoked controversy in Venezuela and abroad, receiving anything from vehement criticism to enthusiastic support. The government of the United States claims that Chavez is a threat to democracy in Latin America. Others sympathize with his ideology or welcome his bilateral trade and reciprocal aid agreements. In 2005 and 2006 he was named one of Time magazine's 100 most influential people. After a two-year imprisonment, Chavez was pardoned by President Rafael Caldera in 1994. Upon his release, Chavez reconstituted the MBR-200 as the Fifth Republic Movement (MVR—Movimiento Quinta Republica, with the V representing the Roman numeral five). Later, in 1998, Chavez began to campaign for the presidency. In working to earn the trust of voters, Chavez drafted an agenda that drew heavily on his ideology of Bolivarianism. Chavez and his followers described their aim as "laying the foundations of a new republic" to replace the existing one, which they cast as "party-dominated"; the current constitution, they argued, was no more than the 'juridico-political embodiment of puntofijismo,' the country's traditional two-party patronage system.

	Chavez utilized his flamboyant public speaking style, which was noted for its abundance of colloquialisms and ribald manner—on the campaign trail to win the trust and favour of a primarily poor and working class following. By May 1998, Chavez's support had risen to 30% in polls, and by August he was registering 39%. Chavez went on to win the 1998 presidential election on December 6, 1998 with 56% of the votes. Chavez was sworn in as president on February 2, 1999. Among his first acts was the launching of Plan Bolivar 2000, which included road building, housing construction, and mass vaccination. Chavez also halted planned privatizations of, among others, the national social security system, aluminum industry holdings, and the oil sector.[26] Chavez also overhauled the formerly lax tax collection and auditing system—especially regarding major corporations and landholders.

	Responding to the stalling of his legislation in the National Assembly, Chavez scheduled two national elections for July 1999, including a referendum for and elections to fill a new constitutional assembly. The Constitutional Assembly was created when the referendum passed with a 72% "yes" vote, while the pro-Chávez Polo Patriotico ("Patriotic Pole") won 95% (120 of the total 131) of its seats. In August 1999, the Constitutional Assembly's "Judicial Emergency Committee" declared a "legislative emergency" whereby a seven-member committee conducted the National Assembly's functions; meanwhile, the National Assembly was prohibited from holding meetings. The Constitutional Assembly drafted the 1999 Venezuelan Constitution, which included an increase in the presidential term from five to six years, a new presidential two-term limit, a new provision for presidential recall elections, renaming of the country to Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela, expanded presidential powers, conversion of the bicameral National Assembly into a unicameral legislature, merit-based appointments of judges, and creation of the Public Defender, an office authorized to regulate the activities of the presidency and the National Assembly.

	In December 1999, the new constitution was approved. On December 15, after weeks of heavy rain, statewide mudslides claimed the lives of an estimated 30,000 people. Critics claim Chavez was distracted by the referendum and that the government ignored a civil defense report, calling for emergency measures, issued the day the floods struck. The government rejected these claims. Chavez personally led the relief effort afterwards. With respect to domestic policies, critics claim that both corruption and crime are rampant. They also cite a failing infrastructure and public hospitals. Criticism from Chavez supporters arises from reports that Chavez is not fulfilling his major campaign pledges with respect to labor and land reform. Critics charged that the Chávez government has engaged in "gigantic fraud" during the 2004 recall referendum, though all international observers and exit polls confirmed the official result. The United States government claims that his cooperation in their war on terror is negligible or purposely indifferent with regards to the FARC and ELN, who are engaged in a conflict with the US-backed Colombian government; nonetheless, the US government says there is no evidence of a direct link between violent groups opposed to its policies and Chavez.

	Several public figures have even gone so far as to call for the assassination of Chavez, most notably US Conservative Christian televangelist Pat Robertson. Other such requests have been expressed by Venezuelan actor Orlando Urdaneta and former president of Venezuela Carlos Andres Perez. The US Ambassador to Venezuela between 2001 and 2004, Charles Shapiro, also reported to the Chavez administration two potential assassination plots. Chavez has been accused of concentrating power of judicial and legislative branches. The leading business daily of Argentina, Ambito Financiero, predicted that Venezuela under Chavez in 2007 would have a "nationalized economy, out-of-control spending, government by decree, and perpetual re-election." The motion which included the provision to allow indefinite presidential re-election was voted down in national referendum in 2007. The daily also compared Chavez to King Louis XIV of France, stating his 2007 inauguration would mark "a concentration of power without precedent in Venezuela."</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela  [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD]July 28, 1954 - 5 March 2013[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Hugo Rafael Chavez Frias is the current President of Venezuela. As the leader of the Bolivarian Revolution, Chavez promotes a political doctrine of democratic socialism and Latin American integration. He is also a critic of neoliberalism, globalization and United States foreign policy. A career military officer, Chavez founded the left-wing Fifth Republic Movement after orchestrating a failed 1992 coup d'etat against former President Carlos Andres Perez. Chavez was elected President in 1998 with a campaign centering on promises of aiding Venezuela's poor majority, and was reelected in 2000 and in 2006. Domestically, Chavez has maintained nation wide Bolivarian Missions, whose goals are to combat disease, illiteracy, malnutrition, poverty, and other social ills. Abroad, Chávez has acted against the Washington Consensus by supporting alternative models of economic development, and has advocated cooperation among the world's poor nations, especially those in Latin America.

	Chavez's policies have evoked controversy in Venezuela and abroad, receiving anything from vehement criticism to enthusiastic support. The government of the United States claims that Chavez is a threat to democracy in Latin America. Others sympathize with his ideology or welcome his bilateral trade and reciprocal aid agreements. In 2005 and 2006 he was named one of Time magazine's 100 most influential people. After a two-year imprisonment, Chavez was pardoned by President Rafael Caldera in 1994. Upon his release, Chavez reconstituted the MBR-200 as the Fifth Republic Movement (MVR—Movimiento Quinta Republica, with the V representing the Roman numeral five). Later, in 1998, Chavez began to campaign for the presidency. In working to earn the trust of voters, Chavez drafted an agenda that drew heavily on his ideology of Bolivarianism. Chavez and his followers described their aim as "laying the foundations of a new republic" to replace the existing one, which they cast as "party-dominated"; the current constitution, they argued, was no more than the 'juridico-political embodiment of puntofijismo,' the country's traditional two-party patronage system.

	Chavez utilized his flamboyant public speaking style, which was noted for its abundance of colloquialisms and ribald manner—on the campaign trail to win the trust and favour of a primarily poor and working class following. By May 1998, Chavez's support had risen to 30% in polls, and by August he was registering 39%. Chavez went on to win the 1998 presidential election on December 6, 1998 with 56% of the votes. Chavez was sworn in as president on February 2, 1999. Among his first acts was the launching of Plan Bolivar 2000, which included road building, housing construction, and mass vaccination. Chavez also halted planned privatizations of, among others, the national social security system, aluminum industry holdings, and the oil sector.[26] Chavez also overhauled the formerly lax tax collection and auditing system—especially regarding major corporations and landholders.

	Responding to the stalling of his legislation in the National Assembly, Chavez scheduled two national elections for July 1999, including a referendum for and elections to fill a new constitutional assembly. The Constitutional Assembly was created when the referendum passed with a 72% "yes" vote, while the pro-Chávez Polo Patriotico ("Patriotic Pole") won 95% (120 of the total 131) of its seats. In August 1999, the Constitutional Assembly's "Judicial Emergency Committee" declared a "legislative emergency" whereby a seven-member committee conducted the National Assembly's functions; meanwhile, the National Assembly was prohibited from holding meetings. The Constitutional Assembly drafted the 1999 Venezuelan Constitution, which included an increase in the presidential term from five to six years, a new presidential two-term limit, a new provision for presidential recall elections, renaming of the country to Republica Bolivariana de Venezuela, expanded presidential powers, conversion of the bicameral National Assembly into a unicameral legislature, merit-based appointments of judges, and creation of the Public Defender, an office authorized to regulate the activities of the presidency and the National Assembly.

	In December 1999, the new constitution was approved. On December 15, after weeks of heavy rain, statewide mudslides claimed the lives of an estimated 30,000 people. Critics claim Chavez was distracted by the referendum and that the government ignored a civil defense report, calling for emergency measures, issued the day the floods struck. The government rejected these claims. Chavez personally led the relief effort afterwards. With respect to domestic policies, critics claim that both corruption and crime are rampant. They also cite a failing infrastructure and public hospitals. Criticism from Chavez supporters arises from reports that Chavez is not fulfilling his major campaign pledges with respect to labor and land reform. Critics charged that the Chávez government has engaged in "gigantic fraud" during the 2004 recall referendum, though all international observers and exit polls confirmed the official result. The United States government claims that his cooperation in their war on terror is negligible or purposely indifferent with regards to the FARC and ELN, who are engaged in a conflict with the US-backed Colombian government; nonetheless, the US government says there is no evidence of a direct link between violent groups opposed to its policies and Chavez.

	Several public figures have even gone so far as to call for the assassination of Chavez, most notably US Conservative Christian televangelist Pat Robertson. Other such requests have been expressed by Venezuelan actor Orlando Urdaneta and former president of Venezuela Carlos Andres Perez. The US Ambassador to Venezuela between 2001 and 2004, Charles Shapiro, also reported to the Chavez administration two potential assassination plots. Chavez has been accused of concentrating power of judicial and legislative branches. The leading business daily of Argentina, Ambito Financiero, predicted that Venezuela under Chavez in 2007 would have a "nationalized economy, out-of-control spending, government by decree, and perpetual re-election." The motion which included the provision to allow indefinite presidential re-election was voted down in national referendum in 2007. The daily also compared Chavez to King Louis XIV of France, stating his 2007 inauguration would mark "a concentration of power without precedent in Venezuela."</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHAVEZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome [CT_NAME].  I have found yet another friend here. And with such a friend we will together form a team, like a soccer team. This will be a fighting team.</English>
		<French>Welcome [CT_NAME].  I have found yet another friend here. And with such a friend we will together form a team, like a soccer team. This will be a fighting team.</French>
		<German>Welcome [CT_NAME].  I have found yet another friend here. And with such a friend we will together form a team, like a soccer team. This will be a fighting team.</German>
		<Italian>Welcome [CT_NAME].  I have found yet another friend here. And with such a friend we will together form a team, like a soccer team. This will be a fighting team.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Welcome [CT_NAME].  I have found yet another friend here. And with such a friend we will together form a team, like a soccer team. This will be a fighting team.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PAEZ</Tag>
		<English>Paez</English>
		<French>Páez</French>
		<German>Páez</German>
		<Italian>Páez</Italian>
		<Spanish>Páez</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PAEZ_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Jose Antonio Paez[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1790 - 1873[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Páez was born in Curpa, Portuguesa State in Venezuela. His paternal grandmother, Luisa Antonia de Mendoza and Mota, was daughter of Luís Rodríguez de Mendoza, a native of Icod de los Vinos, Tenerife (Canary Island). He was of humble origins, his father being a low level employee of the colonial government. As a boy he was forced to work like a slave. By the age of 20, his father already died, Páez was married and earning a living by trading cattle.  Late in 1810, he joined a cavalry squadron, led by a former employer, set up with the purpose of fighting the colonial government. In 1813, he asked for leave from his squadron with the intent of setting and leading his own, which he did, joining the Western Republican Army with the rank of sergeant. Páez had an ingratiating personality which made him very much liked amongst those who knew him. He was also looked up to for his skills as a horseman and for his physical capabilities.

Páez, a soldier at heart, started moving up the ranks by winning year after year several engagements against the royalists with his band of marauding llaneros (plainsmen). He came to be known by the nicknames of "El Centauro de los Llanos" (The Centaur of the Plains), and "El León de Payara" (The Lion of Payara) or (The Lion of Apure).  Páez had been leading the fighting in the plains while Simón Bolívar was busy with the eastern part of the country. Early in 1818, both men met to discuss better coordination of their efforts. After shortly fighting in the center of the country, Páez was ordered to go back to the western plains, where he took from the Spanish the city of San Fernando in Apure.  Páez won all of six major battles that he led by himself, the most celebrated one being the Battle of Las Queseras del Medio.  Late in 1820, an armistice had been signed with the Spanish commander and a temporary suspension of hostilities had taken place. However, ongoing developments were making difficult to maintain the armistice and, consequently, it was agreed it would lapse on 28 April 1821.  All five major fighting groups of the Venezuelan army were to start moving towards a central area. Some with the purpose of joining together in one single group and others with the intention of guarding the approach to that region to prevent royalists units from other far away areas from converging and reinforcing the main Spanish army stationed in the same area.  In early June 1821, the 6,500 men republican army was divided and organized in three divisions. The 1st division, made up of 2,500 men, was under Páez's command and formed by two battalions: Bravos de Apure (Apure Braves) and Cazadores Britanicos (British Hunters or as more often translated to English, the British Legion) and seven cavalry regiments.  By 20 June, all three republican divisions converge from different directions in the plain of Carabobo. With the royalists well entrenched in the center and the south, on the morning of 21 June, Páez was given command of an additional cavalry regiment and ordered to take it together with his own division through the hills on the north side and into the plain and to engage the Spanish, while the 2nd division would stay behind Páez and the 3rd would remain in a defensive position waiting to engage the enemy in the center.  On seeing Páez's men move, the Spanish commander, Miguel de la Torre, orders one of his elite battalions, the Burgos, to reinforce and defend the north flank. Initially, the Spanish so fiercely engage the Bravos de Apure battalion that it had to fall back on two occasions. Páez sent his Cazadores Britanicos to help the Bravos and together they fought back the Spanish, now reinforced themselves by two additional battalions. As the fighting intensified, de la Torre sent more troops to the north. Páez then sent his cavalry further north to outflank the Spanish and come down on the plain from behind. At this moment, the battle is obviously going against the Spanish, who in desperation kept sending reinforcements. In the meantime, Páez's men were gaining terrain and closing on falling Spanish from all sides. Some of the Spanish battalions supposed to join and reinforce the engagement in the north, on seeing how their comrades are faring, decide to disobey orders and retreat. As it becomes evident that the republicans were winning the battle, the other divisions moved forward, but by now the bulk of the work had already been done by Páez and his men.  With the Battle of Carabobo, the military fate of the Spanish army in Venezuela was sealed. The victory was carried by Páez. Bolívar promoted him on site to General in Chief of the republican army.  In the battle, the Spanish lost over 65% of their men; the survivors took refuge in the castle of Puerto Cabello, which, until it was taken by Páez and his men in 1823, was the last Spanish stronghold in Venezuela territory.

Following the Battle of Carabobo, Páez was named General Commander of the provinces of Caracas and Barinas (at the time they included the important regions of Caracas, Barquisimeto, Barinas and Apure).  It had been Bolivar's dream to unite the liberated Spanish provinces into a single great country: La Gran Colombia. It was made up of present-day Colombia, Venezuela, Ecuador, and Panama. As the war against Spain came to an end, federalist and regionalist sentiments began to arise once again.  While Bolívar was engaged in military campaigns in Peru, he was unable to carry on his duties as president of Gran Colombia. As a result, the center of power of the executive branch was in Bogotá under the leadership of Vice President Francisco de Paula Santander, from New Granada (modern-day Colombia and Panama). While some leaders saw Gran Colombia as only a military necessity, others saw it as a real administrative entity. Thus confusion arose between the central government in Bogotá and the provinces and the municipalities. This made Páez and some Venezuelan politicians uncomfortable. Then in 1826, after the Congress in Santa Fe de Bogotá under Santander found a Venezuelan hero from the independence war guilty of assassinating the French Colonel Emanuel Roergas Serviez in Colombia, Páez initiated and led a movement that became known as "La Cosiata" (a word that has never existed in Spanish language and that at the time was made up to refer to this movement and meaning something along the lines of "that weird thing without a name").  La Cosiata started in April 1826 as a quasi-spontaneous movement (as existing historical interpretations differ) of local politicians and personalities supporting Páez. There was pressure in favor of Páez's removal from his office by locals in Venezuela, who had accused him of abusing his authority in relation to implementing orders coming from Bogotá -orders which Páez himself allegedly did not agree much with-: the forced recruitment of men for the army. The Congress in Bogotá, including several of the Venezuelans among it, received the complaints coming from Venezuela, which alleged that Páez had not properly understood the extent of his orders and had exceeded them in his implementation. Congress decided that it alone could judge Páez for his actions, and ordered him to go to Bogotá for his trial.  Páez was initially willing to go. However, the irony now dictated that some of the same local personalities that were originally unhappy with Páez for implementing Santander's orders now felt insulted for their leader's having to go to Bogotá to be tried. After a few days of uncertainty and tension in the streets, the municipality of Valencia broke with Bogotá and submitted itself to Páez as military commander. In the following days, more municipalities would follow suit, including Caracas, which had been the one that first had accused Páez. Other municipalities and local officials did not join in this change of opinion.  In July, Santander declared that Páez was in open rebellion against the central government. While all this was happening, Páez wrote to Bolívar, asking him to come back to take charge and solve the imbroglio.  While Páez and his supporters were willing to have Bolívar as supreme leader, they were reluctant to follow Santander. While they wanted changes to be made to the constitution, they initially wanted to do it under Bolívar as part of the Gran Colombia.  Bolívar, finally returned from his campaigns in the south and took command of the executive towards the end of 1826 assuming the extraordinary powers granted to him by the Congress. Conflicting letters between Santander and Bolívar, and Bolívar and Páez, created a degree of uncertainty as to what his actions would be. He finally declared a general amnesty to all those that were involved in La Cosiata, notwithstanding from then on that any disobedience of his orders would be considered a crime against the state. Páez welcomed Bolívar and accepted his authority, and Bolívar named him Supreme Civil and Military Commander of Venezuela. This action confused and disappointed both Santander in Bogotá and the few local officials in Venezuela that had not supported the La Cosiata, who found themselves being removed or transferred to other posts while those that had backed Páez remained or were subsequently promoted.  Until La Cosiata, Páez had been mostly respected as a result of his military successes during the war. From now on he started to be seen as a politician with the power and the wit needed to pursue and defend any changes, or lack thereof, made under the constitutional order. Páez came out from La Cosiata with more power than he ever had before.

In 1830, Páez declared Venezuela independent from Gran Colombia and became president. Although he was not the first president of Venezuela (which declared its independence from Spain in 1811 and named Cristobal Mendoza as president) he was the first head of government after the dissolution of Gran Colombia. For more than thirty years from his accession to power in 1830 to his death in 1873, Páez was the greatest figure in Venezuela and would return to rule whenever the national government failed. The government ruled by the oligarchy in the country followed the Constitution of 1830. Páez and the conservative oligarchy were conveniently allied because the oligarchy controlled a great amount of their country's wealth but was not popular with the masses where as Páez was very much liked by the masses.  The 1830s to the 1860s are thought of by historians as a golden era in Venezuela's history, in contrast to previous and future dictatorships. It must be noted however that behind the constitution stood Páez, a military caudillo and that application of the law was only possible depending on his personal prestige. But he respected the law and was not interested in personal gain as demonstrated by the common conditions in which he lived. Between 1830-1848 under the power of Páez and the oligarchy, the economic power of the church was broken and its dominance destroyed and from then on the conflict between church and state ceased to exist unlike other countries in Latin America.  In 1842, Páez arranged to have the remains of Simon Bolivar repatriated from Santa Marta, Colombia, to the Liberator's hometown of Caracas. The procession was accompanied by exuberant funeral honors before Bolivar's remains were entombed in the Cathedral of Caracas.  In 1847 President José Tadeo Monagas, who was put into power by Páez, dispersed the Congress and proclaimed himself dictator. Páez led a rebellion against him but was defeated by General Santiago Mariño in the 'Battle of the Araguatos', imprisoned, and eventually exiled. He was exiled from the country in 1850 and did not return until 1858. In 1861, he became supreme dictator and ruled only for two years before again returning to exile. He lived in New York during his years in exile and died there in 1873. Páez served as president three times, once from 1831–1835, 1839–1842 and again from 1861-1863.</English>
		<French>[H1]José Antonio Páez[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1790 - 1873[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Páez was born in Curpa, Portuguesa State in Venezuela. His paternal grandmother, Luisa Antonia de Mendoza and Mota, was daughter of Luís Rodríguez de Mendoza, a native of Icod de los Vinos, Tenerife (Canary Island). He was of humble origins, his father being a low level employee of the colonial government. As a boy he was forced to work like a slave. By the age of 20, his father already died, Páez was married and earning a living by trading cattle.  Late in 1810, he joined a cavalry squadron, led by a former employer, set up with the purpose of fighting the colonial government. In 1813, he asked for leave from his squadron with the intent of setting and leading his own, which he did, joining the Western Republican Army with the rank of sergeant. Páez had an ingratiating personality which made him very much liked amongst those who knew him. He was also looked up to for his skills as a horseman and for his physical capabilities.

Páez, a soldier at heart, started moving up the ranks by winning year after year several engagements against the royalists with his band of marauding llaneros (plainsmen). He came to be known by the nicknames of "El Centauro de los Llanos" (The Centaur of the Plains), and "El León de Payara" (The Lion of Payara) or (The Lion of Apure).  Páez had been leading the fighting in the plains while Simón Bolívar was busy with the eastern part of the country. Early in 1818, both men met to discuss better coordination of their efforts. After shortly fighting in the center of the country, Páez was ordered to go back to the western plains, where he took from the Spanish the city of San Fernando in Apure.  Páez won all of six major battles that he led by himself, the most celebrated one being the Battle of Las Queseras del Medio.  Late in 1820, an armistice had been signed with the Spanish commander and a temporary suspension of hostilities had taken place. However, ongoing developments were making difficult to maintain the armistice and, consequently, it was agreed it would lapse on 28 April 1821.  All five major fighting groups of the Venezuelan army were to start moving towards a central area. Some with the purpose of joining together in one single group and others with the intention of guarding the approach to that region to prevent royalists units from other far away areas from converging and reinforcing the main Spanish army stationed in the same area.  In early June 1821, the 6,500 men republican army was divided and organized in three divisions. The 1st division, made up of 2,500 men, was under Páez's command and formed by two battalions: Bravos de Apure (Apure Braves) and Cazadores Britanicos (British Hunters or as more often translated to English, the British Legion) and seven cavalry regiments.  By 20 June, all three republican divisions converge from different directions in the plain of Carabobo. With the royalists well entrenched in the center and the south, on the morning of 21 June, Páez was given command of an additional cavalry regiment and ordered to take it together with his own division through the hills on the north side and into the plain and to engage the Spanish, while the 2nd division would stay behind Páez and the 3rd would remain in a defensive position waiting to engage the enemy in the center.  On seeing Páez's men move, the Spanish commander, Miguel de la Torre, orders one of his elite battalions, the Burgos, to reinforce and defend the north flank. Initially, the Spanish so fiercely engage the Bravos de Apure battalion that it had to fall back on two occasions. Páez sent his Cazadores Britanicos to help the Bravos and together they fought back the Spanish, now reinforced themselves by two additional battalions. As the fighting intensified, de la Torre sent more troops to the north. Páez then sent his cavalry further north to outflank the Spanish and come down on the plain from behind. At this moment, the battle is obviously going against the Spanish, who in desperation kept sending reinforcements. In the meantime, Páez's men were gaining terrain and closing on falling Spanish from all sides. Some of the Spanish battalions supposed to join and reinforce the engagement in the north, on seeing how their comrades are faring, decide to disobey orders and retreat. As it becomes evident that the republicans were winning the battle, the other divisions moved forward, but by now the bulk of the work had already been done by Páez and his men.  With the Battle of Carabobo, the military fate of the Spanish army in Venezuela was sealed. The victory was carried by Páez. Bolívar promoted him on site to General in Chief of the republican army.  In the battle, the Spanish lost over 65% of their men; the survivors took refuge in the castle of Puerto Cabello, which, until it was taken by Páez and his men in 1823, was the last Spanish stronghold in Venezuela territory.

Following the Battle of Carabobo, Páez was named General Commander of the provinces of Caracas and Barinas (at the time they included the important regions of Caracas, Barquisimeto, Barinas and Apure).  It had been Bolivar's dream to unite the liberated Spanish provinces into a single great country: La Gran Colombia. It was made up of present-day Colombia, Venezuela, Ecuador, and Panama. As the war against Spain came to an end, federalist and regionalist sentiments began to arise once again.  While Bolívar was engaged in military campaigns in Peru, he was unable to carry on his duties as president of Gran Colombia. As a result, the center of power of the executive branch was in Bogotá under the leadership of Vice President Francisco de Paula Santander, from New Granada (modern-day Colombia and Panama). While some leaders saw Gran Colombia as only a military necessity, others saw it as a real administrative entity. Thus confusion arose between the central government in Bogotá and the provinces and the municipalities. This made Páez and some Venezuelan politicians uncomfortable. Then in 1826, after the Congress in Santa Fe de Bogotá under Santander found a Venezuelan hero from the independence war guilty of assassinating the French Colonel Emanuel Roergas Serviez in Colombia, Páez initiated and led a movement that became known as "La Cosiata" (a word that has never existed in Spanish language and that at the time was made up to refer to this movement and meaning something along the lines of "that weird thing without a name").  La Cosiata started in April 1826 as a quasi-spontaneous movement (as existing historical interpretations differ) of local politicians and personalities supporting Páez. There was pressure in favor of Páez's removal from his office by locals in Venezuela, who had accused him of abusing his authority in relation to implementing orders coming from Bogotá -orders which Páez himself allegedly did not agree much with-: the forced recruitment of men for the army. The Congress in Bogotá, including several of the Venezuelans among it, received the complaints coming from Venezuela, which alleged that Páez had not properly understood the extent of his orders and had exceeded them in his implementation. Congress decided that it alone could judge Páez for his actions, and ordered him to go to Bogotá for his trial.  Páez was initially willing to go. However, the irony now dictated that some of the same local personalities that were originally unhappy with Páez for implementing Santander's orders now felt insulted for their leader's having to go to Bogotá to be tried. After a few days of uncertainty and tension in the streets, the municipality of Valencia broke with Bogotá and submitted itself to Páez as military commander. In the following days, more municipalities would follow suit, including Caracas, which had been the one that first had accused Páez. Other municipalities and local officials did not join in this change of opinion.  In July, Santander declared that Páez was in open rebellion against the central government. While all this was happening, Páez wrote to Bolívar, asking him to come back to take charge and solve the imbroglio.  While Páez and his supporters were willing to have Bolívar as supreme leader, they were reluctant to follow Santander. While they wanted changes to be made to the constitution, they initially wanted to do it under Bolívar as part of the Gran Colombia.  Bolívar, finally returned from his campaigns in the south and took command of the executive towards the end of 1826 assuming the extraordinary powers granted to him by the Congress. Conflicting letters between Santander and Bolívar, and Bolívar and Páez, created a degree of uncertainty as to what his actions would be. He finally declared a general amnesty to all those that were involved in La Cosiata, notwithstanding from then on that any disobedience of his orders would be considered a crime against the state. Páez welcomed Bolívar and accepted his authority, and Bolívar named him Supreme Civil and Military Commander of Venezuela. This action confused and disappointed both Santander in Bogotá and the few local officials in Venezuela that had not supported the La Cosiata, who found themselves being removed or transferred to other posts while those that had backed Páez remained or were subsequently promoted.  Until La Cosiata, Páez had been mostly respected as a result of his military successes during the war. From now on he started to be seen as a politician with the power and the wit needed to pursue and defend any changes, or lack thereof, made under the constitutional order. Páez came out from La Cosiata with more power than he ever had before.

In 1830, Páez declared Venezuela independent from Gran Colombia and became president. Although he was not the first president of Venezuela (which declared its independence from Spain in 1811 and named Cristobal Mendoza as president) he was the first head of government after the dissolution of Gran Colombia. For more than thirty years from his accession to power in 1830 to his death in 1873, Páez was the greatest figure in Venezuela and would return to rule whenever the national government failed. The government ruled by the oligarchy in the country followed the Constitution of 1830. Páez and the conservative oligarchy were conveniently allied because the oligarchy controlled a great amount of their country's wealth but was not popular with the masses where as Páez was very much liked by the masses.  The 1830s to the 1860s are thought of by historians as a golden era in Venezuela's history, in contrast to previous and future dictatorships. It must be noted however that behind the constitution stood Páez, a military caudillo and that application of the law was only possible depending on his personal prestige. But he respected the law and was not interested in personal gain as demonstrated by the common conditions in which he lived. Between 1830-1848 under the power of Páez and the oligarchy, the economic power of the church was broken and its dominance destroyed and from then on the conflict between church and state ceased to exist unlike other countries in Latin America.  In 1842, Páez arranged to have the remains of Simon Bolivar repatriated from Santa Marta, Colombia, to the Liberator's hometown of Caracas. The procession was accompanied by exuberant funeral honors before Bolivar's remains were entombed in the Cathedral of Caracas.  In 1847 President José Tadeo Monagas, who was put into power by Páez, dispersed the Congress and proclaimed himself dictator. Páez led a rebellion against him but was defeated by General Santiago Mariño in the 'Battle of the Araguatos', imprisoned, and eventually exiled. He was exiled from the country in 1850 and did not return until 1858. In 1861, he became supreme dictator and ruled only for two years before again returning to exile. He lived in New York during his years in exile and died there in 1873. Páez served as president three times, once from 1831–1835, 1839–1842 and again from 1861-1863.</French>
		<German>[H1]José Antonio Páez[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1790 - 1873[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Páez was born in Curpa, Portuguesa State in Venezuela. His paternal grandmother, Luisa Antonia de Mendoza and Mota, was daughter of Luís Rodríguez de Mendoza, a native of Icod de los Vinos, Tenerife (Canary Island). He was of humble origins, his father being a low level employee of the colonial government. As a boy he was forced to work like a slave. By the age of 20, his father already died, Páez was married and earning a living by trading cattle.  Late in 1810, he joined a cavalry squadron, led by a former employer, set up with the purpose of fighting the colonial government. In 1813, he asked for leave from his squadron with the intent of setting and leading his own, which he did, joining the Western Republican Army with the rank of sergeant. Páez had an ingratiating personality which made him very much liked amongst those who knew him. He was also looked up to for his skills as a horseman and for his physical capabilities.

Páez, a soldier at heart, started moving up the ranks by winning year after year several engagements against the royalists with his band of marauding llaneros (plainsmen). He came to be known by the nicknames of "El Centauro de los Llanos" (The Centaur of the Plains), and "El León de Payara" (The Lion of Payara) or (The Lion of Apure).  Páez had been leading the fighting in the plains while Simón Bolívar was busy with the eastern part of the country. Early in 1818, both men met to discuss better coordination of their efforts. After shortly fighting in the center of the country, Páez was ordered to go back to the western plains, where he took from the Spanish the city of San Fernando in Apure.  Páez won all of six major battles that he led by himself, the most celebrated one being the Battle of Las Queseras del Medio.  Late in 1820, an armistice had been signed with the Spanish commander and a temporary suspension of hostilities had taken place. However, ongoing developments were making difficult to maintain the armistice and, consequently, it was agreed it would lapse on 28 April 1821.  All five major fighting groups of the Venezuelan army were to start moving towards a central area. Some with the purpose of joining together in one single group and others with the intention of guarding the approach to that region to prevent royalists units from other far away areas from converging and reinforcing the main Spanish army stationed in the same area.  In early June 1821, the 6,500 men republican army was divided and organized in three divisions. The 1st division, made up of 2,500 men, was under Páez's command and formed by two battalions: Bravos de Apure (Apure Braves) and Cazadores Britanicos (British Hunters or as more often translated to English, the British Legion) and seven cavalry regiments.  By 20 June, all three republican divisions converge from different directions in the plain of Carabobo. With the royalists well entrenched in the center and the south, on the morning of 21 June, Páez was given command of an additional cavalry regiment and ordered to take it together with his own division through the hills on the north side and into the plain and to engage the Spanish, while the 2nd division would stay behind Páez and the 3rd would remain in a defensive position waiting to engage the enemy in the center.  On seeing Páez's men move, the Spanish commander, Miguel de la Torre, orders one of his elite battalions, the Burgos, to reinforce and defend the north flank. Initially, the Spanish so fiercely engage the Bravos de Apure battalion that it had to fall back on two occasions. Páez sent his Cazadores Britanicos to help the Bravos and together they fought back the Spanish, now reinforced themselves by two additional battalions. As the fighting intensified, de la Torre sent more troops to the north. Páez then sent his cavalry further north to outflank the Spanish and come down on the plain from behind. At this moment, the battle is obviously going against the Spanish, who in desperation kept sending reinforcements. In the meantime, Páez's men were gaining terrain and closing on falling Spanish from all sides. Some of the Spanish battalions supposed to join and reinforce the engagement in the north, on seeing how their comrades are faring, decide to disobey orders and retreat. As it becomes evident that the republicans were winning the battle, the other divisions moved forward, but by now the bulk of the work had already been done by Páez and his men.  With the Battle of Carabobo, the military fate of the Spanish army in Venezuela was sealed. The victory was carried by Páez. Bolívar promoted him on site to General in Chief of the republican army.  In the battle, the Spanish lost over 65% of their men; the survivors took refuge in the castle of Puerto Cabello, which, until it was taken by Páez and his men in 1823, was the last Spanish stronghold in Venezuela territory.

Following the Battle of Carabobo, Páez was named General Commander of the provinces of Caracas and Barinas (at the time they included the important regions of Caracas, Barquisimeto, Barinas and Apure).  It had been Bolivar's dream to unite the liberated Spanish provinces into a single great country: La Gran Colombia. It was made up of present-day Colombia, Venezuela, Ecuador, and Panama. As the war against Spain came to an end, federalist and regionalist sentiments began to arise once again.  While Bolívar was engaged in military campaigns in Peru, he was unable to carry on his duties as president of Gran Colombia. As a result, the center of power of the executive branch was in Bogotá under the leadership of Vice President Francisco de Paula Santander, from New Granada (modern-day Colombia and Panama). While some leaders saw Gran Colombia as only a military necessity, others saw it as a real administrative entity. Thus confusion arose between the central government in Bogotá and the provinces and the municipalities. This made Páez and some Venezuelan politicians uncomfortable. Then in 1826, after the Congress in Santa Fe de Bogotá under Santander found a Venezuelan hero from the independence war guilty of assassinating the French Colonel Emanuel Roergas Serviez in Colombia, Páez initiated and led a movement that became known as "La Cosiata" (a word that has never existed in Spanish language and that at the time was made up to refer to this movement and meaning something along the lines of "that weird thing without a name").  La Cosiata started in April 1826 as a quasi-spontaneous movement (as existing historical interpretations differ) of local politicians and personalities supporting Páez. There was pressure in favor of Páez's removal from his office by locals in Venezuela, who had accused him of abusing his authority in relation to implementing orders coming from Bogotá -orders which Páez himself allegedly did not agree much with-: the forced recruitment of men for the army. The Congress in Bogotá, including several of the Venezuelans among it, received the complaints coming from Venezuela, which alleged that Páez had not properly understood the extent of his orders and had exceeded them in his implementation. Congress decided that it alone could judge Páez for his actions, and ordered him to go to Bogotá for his trial.  Páez was initially willing to go. However, the irony now dictated that some of the same local personalities that were originally unhappy with Páez for implementing Santander's orders now felt insulted for their leader's having to go to Bogotá to be tried. After a few days of uncertainty and tension in the streets, the municipality of Valencia broke with Bogotá and submitted itself to Páez as military commander. In the following days, more municipalities would follow suit, including Caracas, which had been the one that first had accused Páez. Other municipalities and local officials did not join in this change of opinion.  In July, Santander declared that Páez was in open rebellion against the central government. While all this was happening, Páez wrote to Bolívar, asking him to come back to take charge and solve the imbroglio.  While Páez and his supporters were willing to have Bolívar as supreme leader, they were reluctant to follow Santander. While they wanted changes to be made to the constitution, they initially wanted to do it under Bolívar as part of the Gran Colombia.  Bolívar, finally returned from his campaigns in the south and took command of the executive towards the end of 1826 assuming the extraordinary powers granted to him by the Congress. Conflicting letters between Santander and Bolívar, and Bolívar and Páez, created a degree of uncertainty as to what his actions would be. He finally declared a general amnesty to all those that were involved in La Cosiata, notwithstanding from then on that any disobedience of his orders would be considered a crime against the state. Páez welcomed Bolívar and accepted his authority, and Bolívar named him Supreme Civil and Military Commander of Venezuela. This action confused and disappointed both Santander in Bogotá and the few local officials in Venezuela that had not supported the La Cosiata, who found themselves being removed or transferred to other posts while those that had backed Páez remained or were subsequently promoted.  Until La Cosiata, Páez had been mostly respected as a result of his military successes during the war. From now on he started to be seen as a politician with the power and the wit needed to pursue and defend any changes, or lack thereof, made under the constitutional order. Páez came out from La Cosiata with more power than he ever had before.

In 1830, Páez declared Venezuela independent from Gran Colombia and became president. Although he was not the first president of Venezuela (which declared its independence from Spain in 1811 and named Cristobal Mendoza as president) he was the first head of government after the dissolution of Gran Colombia. For more than thirty years from his accession to power in 1830 to his death in 1873, Páez was the greatest figure in Venezuela and would return to rule whenever the national government failed. The government ruled by the oligarchy in the country followed the Constitution of 1830. Páez and the conservative oligarchy were conveniently allied because the oligarchy controlled a great amount of their country's wealth but was not popular with the masses where as Páez was very much liked by the masses.  The 1830s to the 1860s are thought of by historians as a golden era in Venezuela's history, in contrast to previous and future dictatorships. It must be noted however that behind the constitution stood Páez, a military caudillo and that application of the law was only possible depending on his personal prestige. But he respected the law and was not interested in personal gain as demonstrated by the common conditions in which he lived. Between 1830-1848 under the power of Páez and the oligarchy, the economic power of the church was broken and its dominance destroyed and from then on the conflict between church and state ceased to exist unlike other countries in Latin America.  In 1842, Páez arranged to have the remains of Simon Bolivar repatriated from Santa Marta, Colombia, to the Liberator's hometown of Caracas. The procession was accompanied by exuberant funeral honors before Bolivar's remains were entombed in the Cathedral of Caracas.  In 1847 President José Tadeo Monagas, who was put into power by Páez, dispersed the Congress and proclaimed himself dictator. Páez led a rebellion against him but was defeated by General Santiago Mariño in the 'Battle of the Araguatos', imprisoned, and eventually exiled. He was exiled from the country in 1850 and did not return until 1858. In 1861, he became supreme dictator and ruled only for two years before again returning to exile. He lived in New York during his years in exile and died there in 1873. Páez served as president three times, once from 1831–1835, 1839–1842 and again from 1861-1863.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]José Antonio Páez[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1790 - 1873[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Páez was born in Curpa, Portuguesa State in Venezuela. His paternal grandmother, Luisa Antonia de Mendoza and Mota, was daughter of Luís Rodríguez de Mendoza, a native of Icod de los Vinos, Tenerife (Canary Island). He was of humble origins, his father being a low level employee of the colonial government. As a boy he was forced to work like a slave. By the age of 20, his father already died, Páez was married and earning a living by trading cattle.  Late in 1810, he joined a cavalry squadron, led by a former employer, set up with the purpose of fighting the colonial government. In 1813, he asked for leave from his squadron with the intent of setting and leading his own, which he did, joining the Western Republican Army with the rank of sergeant. Páez had an ingratiating personality which made him very much liked amongst those who knew him. He was also looked up to for his skills as a horseman and for his physical capabilities.

Páez, a soldier at heart, started moving up the ranks by winning year after year several engagements against the royalists with his band of marauding llaneros (plainsmen). He came to be known by the nicknames of "El Centauro de los Llanos" (The Centaur of the Plains), and "El León de Payara" (The Lion of Payara) or (The Lion of Apure).  Páez had been leading the fighting in the plains while Simón Bolívar was busy with the eastern part of the country. Early in 1818, both men met to discuss better coordination of their efforts. After shortly fighting in the center of the country, Páez was ordered to go back to the western plains, where he took from the Spanish the city of San Fernando in Apure.  Páez won all of six major battles that he led by himself, the most celebrated one being the Battle of Las Queseras del Medio.  Late in 1820, an armistice had been signed with the Spanish commander and a temporary suspension of hostilities had taken place. However, ongoing developments were making difficult to maintain the armistice and, consequently, it was agreed it would lapse on 28 April 1821.  All five major fighting groups of the Venezuelan army were to start moving towards a central area. Some with the purpose of joining together in one single group and others with the intention of guarding the approach to that region to prevent royalists units from other far away areas from converging and reinforcing the main Spanish army stationed in the same area.  In early June 1821, the 6,500 men republican army was divided and organized in three divisions. The 1st division, made up of 2,500 men, was under Páez's command and formed by two battalions: Bravos de Apure (Apure Braves) and Cazadores Britanicos (British Hunters or as more often translated to English, the British Legion) and seven cavalry regiments.  By 20 June, all three republican divisions converge from different directions in the plain of Carabobo. With the royalists well entrenched in the center and the south, on the morning of 21 June, Páez was given command of an additional cavalry regiment and ordered to take it together with his own division through the hills on the north side and into the plain and to engage the Spanish, while the 2nd division would stay behind Páez and the 3rd would remain in a defensive position waiting to engage the enemy in the center.  On seeing Páez's men move, the Spanish commander, Miguel de la Torre, orders one of his elite battalions, the Burgos, to reinforce and defend the north flank. Initially, the Spanish so fiercely engage the Bravos de Apure battalion that it had to fall back on two occasions. Páez sent his Cazadores Britanicos to help the Bravos and together they fought back the Spanish, now reinforced themselves by two additional battalions. As the fighting intensified, de la Torre sent more troops to the north. Páez then sent his cavalry further north to outflank the Spanish and come down on the plain from behind. At this moment, the battle is obviously going against the Spanish, who in desperation kept sending reinforcements. In the meantime, Páez's men were gaining terrain and closing on falling Spanish from all sides. Some of the Spanish battalions supposed to join and reinforce the engagement in the north, on seeing how their comrades are faring, decide to disobey orders and retreat. As it becomes evident that the republicans were winning the battle, the other divisions moved forward, but by now the bulk of the work had already been done by Páez and his men.  With the Battle of Carabobo, the military fate of the Spanish army in Venezuela was sealed. The victory was carried by Páez. Bolívar promoted him on site to General in Chief of the republican army.  In the battle, the Spanish lost over 65% of their men; the survivors took refuge in the castle of Puerto Cabello, which, until it was taken by Páez and his men in 1823, was the last Spanish stronghold in Venezuela territory.

Following the Battle of Carabobo, Páez was named General Commander of the provinces of Caracas and Barinas (at the time they included the important regions of Caracas, Barquisimeto, Barinas and Apure).  It had been Bolivar's dream to unite the liberated Spanish provinces into a single great country: La Gran Colombia. It was made up of present-day Colombia, Venezuela, Ecuador, and Panama. As the war against Spain came to an end, federalist and regionalist sentiments began to arise once again.  While Bolívar was engaged in military campaigns in Peru, he was unable to carry on his duties as president of Gran Colombia. As a result, the center of power of the executive branch was in Bogotá under the leadership of Vice President Francisco de Paula Santander, from New Granada (modern-day Colombia and Panama). While some leaders saw Gran Colombia as only a military necessity, others saw it as a real administrative entity. Thus confusion arose between the central government in Bogotá and the provinces and the municipalities. This made Páez and some Venezuelan politicians uncomfortable. Then in 1826, after the Congress in Santa Fe de Bogotá under Santander found a Venezuelan hero from the independence war guilty of assassinating the French Colonel Emanuel Roergas Serviez in Colombia, Páez initiated and led a movement that became known as "La Cosiata" (a word that has never existed in Spanish language and that at the time was made up to refer to this movement and meaning something along the lines of "that weird thing without a name").  La Cosiata started in April 1826 as a quasi-spontaneous movement (as existing historical interpretations differ) of local politicians and personalities supporting Páez. There was pressure in favor of Páez's removal from his office by locals in Venezuela, who had accused him of abusing his authority in relation to implementing orders coming from Bogotá -orders which Páez himself allegedly did not agree much with-: the forced recruitment of men for the army. The Congress in Bogotá, including several of the Venezuelans among it, received the complaints coming from Venezuela, which alleged that Páez had not properly understood the extent of his orders and had exceeded them in his implementation. Congress decided that it alone could judge Páez for his actions, and ordered him to go to Bogotá for his trial.  Páez was initially willing to go. However, the irony now dictated that some of the same local personalities that were originally unhappy with Páez for implementing Santander's orders now felt insulted for their leader's having to go to Bogotá to be tried. After a few days of uncertainty and tension in the streets, the municipality of Valencia broke with Bogotá and submitted itself to Páez as military commander. In the following days, more municipalities would follow suit, including Caracas, which had been the one that first had accused Páez. Other municipalities and local officials did not join in this change of opinion.  In July, Santander declared that Páez was in open rebellion against the central government. While all this was happening, Páez wrote to Bolívar, asking him to come back to take charge and solve the imbroglio.  While Páez and his supporters were willing to have Bolívar as supreme leader, they were reluctant to follow Santander. While they wanted changes to be made to the constitution, they initially wanted to do it under Bolívar as part of the Gran Colombia.  Bolívar, finally returned from his campaigns in the south and took command of the executive towards the end of 1826 assuming the extraordinary powers granted to him by the Congress. Conflicting letters between Santander and Bolívar, and Bolívar and Páez, created a degree of uncertainty as to what his actions would be. He finally declared a general amnesty to all those that were involved in La Cosiata, notwithstanding from then on that any disobedience of his orders would be considered a crime against the state. Páez welcomed Bolívar and accepted his authority, and Bolívar named him Supreme Civil and Military Commander of Venezuela. This action confused and disappointed both Santander in Bogotá and the few local officials in Venezuela that had not supported the La Cosiata, who found themselves being removed or transferred to other posts while those that had backed Páez remained or were subsequently promoted.  Until La Cosiata, Páez had been mostly respected as a result of his military successes during the war. From now on he started to be seen as a politician with the power and the wit needed to pursue and defend any changes, or lack thereof, made under the constitutional order. Páez came out from La Cosiata with more power than he ever had before.

In 1830, Páez declared Venezuela independent from Gran Colombia and became president. Although he was not the first president of Venezuela (which declared its independence from Spain in 1811 and named Cristobal Mendoza as president) he was the first head of government after the dissolution of Gran Colombia. For more than thirty years from his accession to power in 1830 to his death in 1873, Páez was the greatest figure in Venezuela and would return to rule whenever the national government failed. The government ruled by the oligarchy in the country followed the Constitution of 1830. Páez and the conservative oligarchy were conveniently allied because the oligarchy controlled a great amount of their country's wealth but was not popular with the masses where as Páez was very much liked by the masses.  The 1830s to the 1860s are thought of by historians as a golden era in Venezuela's history, in contrast to previous and future dictatorships. It must be noted however that behind the constitution stood Páez, a military caudillo and that application of the law was only possible depending on his personal prestige. But he respected the law and was not interested in personal gain as demonstrated by the common conditions in which he lived. Between 1830-1848 under the power of Páez and the oligarchy, the economic power of the church was broken and its dominance destroyed and from then on the conflict between church and state ceased to exist unlike other countries in Latin America.  In 1842, Páez arranged to have the remains of Simon Bolivar repatriated from Santa Marta, Colombia, to the Liberator's hometown of Caracas. The procession was accompanied by exuberant funeral honors before Bolivar's remains were entombed in the Cathedral of Caracas.  In 1847 President José Tadeo Monagas, who was put into power by Páez, dispersed the Congress and proclaimed himself dictator. Páez led a rebellion against him but was defeated by General Santiago Mariño in the 'Battle of the Araguatos', imprisoned, and eventually exiled. He was exiled from the country in 1850 and did not return until 1858. In 1861, he became supreme dictator and ruled only for two years before again returning to exile. He lived in New York during his years in exile and died there in 1873. Páez served as president three times, once from 1831–1835, 1839–1842 and again from 1861-1863.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]José Antonio Páez[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Venezuela[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1790 - 1873[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Páez was born in Curpa, Portuguesa State in Venezuela. His paternal grandmother, Luisa Antonia de Mendoza and Mota, was daughter of Luís Rodríguez de Mendoza, a native of Icod de los Vinos, Tenerife (Canary Island). He was of humble origins, his father being a low level employee of the colonial government. As a boy he was forced to work like a slave. By the age of 20, his father already died, Páez was married and earning a living by trading cattle.  Late in 1810, he joined a cavalry squadron, led by a former employer, set up with the purpose of fighting the colonial government. In 1813, he asked for leave from his squadron with the intent of setting and leading his own, which he did, joining the Western Republican Army with the rank of sergeant. Páez had an ingratiating personality which made him very much liked amongst those who knew him. He was also looked up to for his skills as a horseman and for his physical capabilities.

Páez, a soldier at heart, started moving up the ranks by winning year after year several engagements against the royalists with his band of marauding llaneros (plainsmen). He came to be known by the nicknames of "El Centauro de los Llanos" (The Centaur of the Plains), and "El León de Payara" (The Lion of Payara) or (The Lion of Apure).  Páez had been leading the fighting in the plains while Simón Bolívar was busy with the eastern part of the country. Early in 1818, both men met to discuss better coordination of their efforts. After shortly fighting in the center of the country, Páez was ordered to go back to the western plains, where he took from the Spanish the city of San Fernando in Apure.  Páez won all of six major battles that he led by himself, the most celebrated one being the Battle of Las Queseras del Medio.  Late in 1820, an armistice had been signed with the Spanish commander and a temporary suspension of hostilities had taken place. However, ongoing developments were making difficult to maintain the armistice and, consequently, it was agreed it would lapse on 28 April 1821.  All five major fighting groups of the Venezuelan army were to start moving towards a central area. Some with the purpose of joining together in one single group and others with the intention of guarding the approach to that region to prevent royalists units from other far away areas from converging and reinforcing the main Spanish army stationed in the same area.  In early June 1821, the 6,500 men republican army was divided and organized in three divisions. The 1st division, made up of 2,500 men, was under Páez's command and formed by two battalions: Bravos de Apure (Apure Braves) and Cazadores Britanicos (British Hunters or as more often translated to English, the British Legion) and seven cavalry regiments.  By 20 June, all three republican divisions converge from different directions in the plain of Carabobo. With the royalists well entrenched in the center and the south, on the morning of 21 June, Páez was given command of an additional cavalry regiment and ordered to take it together with his own division through the hills on the north side and into the plain and to engage the Spanish, while the 2nd division would stay behind Páez and the 3rd would remain in a defensive position waiting to engage the enemy in the center.  On seeing Páez's men move, the Spanish commander, Miguel de la Torre, orders one of his elite battalions, the Burgos, to reinforce and defend the north flank. Initially, the Spanish so fiercely engage the Bravos de Apure battalion that it had to fall back on two occasions. Páez sent his Cazadores Britanicos to help the Bravos and together they fought back the Spanish, now reinforced themselves by two additional battalions. As the fighting intensified, de la Torre sent more troops to the north. Páez then sent his cavalry further north to outflank the Spanish and come down on the plain from behind. At this moment, the battle is obviously going against the Spanish, who in desperation kept sending reinforcements. In the meantime, Páez's men were gaining terrain and closing on falling Spanish from all sides. Some of the Spanish battalions supposed to join and reinforce the engagement in the north, on seeing how their comrades are faring, decide to disobey orders and retreat. As it becomes evident that the republicans were winning the battle, the other divisions moved forward, but by now the bulk of the work had already been done by Páez and his men.  With the Battle of Carabobo, the military fate of the Spanish army in Venezuela was sealed. The victory was carried by Páez. Bolívar promoted him on site to General in Chief of the republican army.  In the battle, the Spanish lost over 65% of their men; the survivors took refuge in the castle of Puerto Cabello, which, until it was taken by Páez and his men in 1823, was the last Spanish stronghold in Venezuela territory.

Following the Battle of Carabobo, Páez was named General Commander of the provinces of Caracas and Barinas (at the time they included the important regions of Caracas, Barquisimeto, Barinas and Apure).  It had been Bolivar's dream to unite the liberated Spanish provinces into a single great country: La Gran Colombia. It was made up of present-day Colombia, Venezuela, Ecuador, and Panama. As the war against Spain came to an end, federalist and regionalist sentiments began to arise once again.  While Bolívar was engaged in military campaigns in Peru, he was unable to carry on his duties as president of Gran Colombia. As a result, the center of power of the executive branch was in Bogotá under the leadership of Vice President Francisco de Paula Santander, from New Granada (modern-day Colombia and Panama). While some leaders saw Gran Colombia as only a military necessity, others saw it as a real administrative entity. Thus confusion arose between the central government in Bogotá and the provinces and the municipalities. This made Páez and some Venezuelan politicians uncomfortable. Then in 1826, after the Congress in Santa Fe de Bogotá under Santander found a Venezuelan hero from the independence war guilty of assassinating the French Colonel Emanuel Roergas Serviez in Colombia, Páez initiated and led a movement that became known as "La Cosiata" (a word that has never existed in Spanish language and that at the time was made up to refer to this movement and meaning something along the lines of "that weird thing without a name").  La Cosiata started in April 1826 as a quasi-spontaneous movement (as existing historical interpretations differ) of local politicians and personalities supporting Páez. There was pressure in favor of Páez's removal from his office by locals in Venezuela, who had accused him of abusing his authority in relation to implementing orders coming from Bogotá -orders which Páez himself allegedly did not agree much with-: the forced recruitment of men for the army. The Congress in Bogotá, including several of the Venezuelans among it, received the complaints coming from Venezuela, which alleged that Páez had not properly understood the extent of his orders and had exceeded them in his implementation. Congress decided that it alone could judge Páez for his actions, and ordered him to go to Bogotá for his trial.  Páez was initially willing to go. However, the irony now dictated that some of the same local personalities that were originally unhappy with Páez for implementing Santander's orders now felt insulted for their leader's having to go to Bogotá to be tried. After a few days of uncertainty and tension in the streets, the municipality of Valencia broke with Bogotá and submitted itself to Páez as military commander. In the following days, more municipalities would follow suit, including Caracas, which had been the one that first had accused Páez. Other municipalities and local officials did not join in this change of opinion.  In July, Santander declared that Páez was in open rebellion against the central government. While all this was happening, Páez wrote to Bolívar, asking him to come back to take charge and solve the imbroglio.  While Páez and his supporters were willing to have Bolívar as supreme leader, they were reluctant to follow Santander. While they wanted changes to be made to the constitution, they initially wanted to do it under Bolívar as part of the Gran Colombia.  Bolívar, finally returned from his campaigns in the south and took command of the executive towards the end of 1826 assuming the extraordinary powers granted to him by the Congress. Conflicting letters between Santander and Bolívar, and Bolívar and Páez, created a degree of uncertainty as to what his actions would be. He finally declared a general amnesty to all those that were involved in La Cosiata, notwithstanding from then on that any disobedience of his orders would be considered a crime against the state. Páez welcomed Bolívar and accepted his authority, and Bolívar named him Supreme Civil and Military Commander of Venezuela. This action confused and disappointed both Santander in Bogotá and the few local officials in Venezuela that had not supported the La Cosiata, who found themselves being removed or transferred to other posts while those that had backed Páez remained or were subsequently promoted.  Until La Cosiata, Páez had been mostly respected as a result of his military successes during the war. From now on he started to be seen as a politician with the power and the wit needed to pursue and defend any changes, or lack thereof, made under the constitutional order. Páez came out from La Cosiata with more power than he ever had before.

In 1830, Páez declared Venezuela independent from Gran Colombia and became president. Although he was not the first president of Venezuela (which declared its independence from Spain in 1811 and named Cristobal Mendoza as president) he was the first head of government after the dissolution of Gran Colombia. For more than thirty years from his accession to power in 1830 to his death in 1873, Páez was the greatest figure in Venezuela and would return to rule whenever the national government failed. The government ruled by the oligarchy in the country followed the Constitution of 1830. Páez and the conservative oligarchy were conveniently allied because the oligarchy controlled a great amount of their country's wealth but was not popular with the masses where as Páez was very much liked by the masses.  The 1830s to the 1860s are thought of by historians as a golden era in Venezuela's history, in contrast to previous and future dictatorships. It must be noted however that behind the constitution stood Páez, a military caudillo and that application of the law was only possible depending on his personal prestige. But he respected the law and was not interested in personal gain as demonstrated by the common conditions in which he lived. Between 1830-1848 under the power of Páez and the oligarchy, the economic power of the church was broken and its dominance destroyed and from then on the conflict between church and state ceased to exist unlike other countries in Latin America.  In 1842, Páez arranged to have the remains of Simon Bolivar repatriated from Santa Marta, Colombia, to the Liberator's hometown of Caracas. The procession was accompanied by exuberant funeral honors before Bolivar's remains were entombed in the Cathedral of Caracas.  In 1847 President José Tadeo Monagas, who was put into power by Páez, dispersed the Congress and proclaimed himself dictator. Páez led a rebellion against him but was defeated by General Santiago Mariño in the 'Battle of the Araguatos', imprisoned, and eventually exiled. He was exiled from the country in 1850 and did not return until 1858. In 1861, he became supreme dictator and ruled only for two years before again returning to exile. He lived in New York during his years in exile and died there in 1873. Páez served as president three times, once from 1831–1835, 1839–1842 and again from 1861-1863.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PAEZ_1</Tag>
		<English>I am [OUR_NAME], a soldier through and through.  I will gladly fight for the independence of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</English>
		<French>I am [OUR_NAME], a soldier through and through.  I will gladly fight for the independence of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</French>
		<German>I am [OUR_NAME], a soldier through and through.  I will gladly fight for the independence of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</German>
		<Italian>I am [OUR_NAME], a soldier through and through.  I will gladly fight for the independence of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</Italian>
		<Spanish>I am [OUR_NAME], a soldier through and through.  I will gladly fight for the independence of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CARACAS</Tag>
		<English>Caracas</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Caracas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Caracas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Caracas</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Caracas</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MARACAIBO</Tag>
		<English>Maracaibo</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Maracaibo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Maracaibo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Maracaibo</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Maracaibo</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_VALENCIA</Tag>
		<English>Valencia</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Valencia</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Valencia</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Valencia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Valencia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_BARQUISIMETO</Tag>
		<English>Barquisimeto</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Barquisimeto</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Barquisimeto</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Barquisimeto</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Barquisimeto</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MARACAY</Tag>
		<English>Maracay</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Maracay</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Maracay</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Maracay</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Maracay</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CUIDAD_GUAYANA</Tag>
		<English>Ciudad Guayana</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Ciudad Guayana</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Ciudad Guayana</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Ciudad Guayana</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Ciudad Guayana</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_BARCELONA</Tag>
		<English>Barcelona</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Barcelona</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Barcelona</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Barcelona</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Barcelona</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MATURIN</Tag>
		<English>Maturín</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Maturín</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Maturín</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Maturín</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Maturín</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_TURMERO</Tag>
		<English>Turmero</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Turmero</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Turmero</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Turmero</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Turmero</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CIUDAD_BOLIVAR</Tag>
		<English>Ciudad Bolívar</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Ciudad Bolívar</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Ciudad Bolívar</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Ciudad Bolívar</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Ciudad Bolívar</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_BARINAS</Tag>
		<English>Barinas</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Barinas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Barinas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Barinas</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Barinas</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_LOS_TEQUES</Tag>
		<English>Los Teques</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Los Teques</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Los Teques</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Los Teques</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Los Teques</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CUMANA</Tag>
		<English>Cumaná</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Cumaná</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Cumaná</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cumaná</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Cumaná</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SAN_CRISTOBAL</Tag>
		<English>San Cristóbal</English>
		<French>
			<Text>San Cristóbal</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>San Cristóbal</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>San Cristóbal</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>San Cristóbal</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PUERTO_LA_CRUZ</Tag>
		<English>Puerto La Cruz</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Puerto La Cruz</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Puerto La Cruz</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Puerto La Cruz</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Puerto La Cruz</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MERIDA</Tag>
		<English>Mérida</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mérida</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Mérida</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Mérida</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Mérida</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CABIMAS</Tag>
		<English>Cabimas</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Cabimas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Cabimas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cabimas</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Cabimas</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CORO</Tag>
		<English>Coro</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Coro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Coro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Coro</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Coro</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_GUATIRE</Tag>
		<English>Guatire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Guatire</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Guatire</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guatire</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Guatire</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CUA</Tag>
		<English>Cúa</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Cúa</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Cúa</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cúa</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Cúa</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_GUARENAS</Tag>
		<English>Guarenas</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Guarenas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Guarenas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guarenas</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Guarenas</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_OCUMARE_DEL_TUY</Tag>
		<English>Ocumare del Tuy</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Ocumare del Tuy</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Ocumare del Tuy</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Ocumare del Tuy</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Ocumare del Tuy</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PUERTO_CABELLO</Tag>
		<English>Puerto Cabello</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Puerto Cabello</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Puerto Cabello</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Puerto Cabello</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Puerto Cabello</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_GUACARA</Tag>
		<English>Guacara</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Guacara</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Guacara</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guacara</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Guacara</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_EL_TIGRE</Tag>
		<English>El Tigre</English>
		<French>
			<Text>El Tigre</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>El Tigre</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>El Tigre</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>El Tigre</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_EL_LIMON</Tag>
		<English>El Limón</English>
		<French>
			<Text>El Limón</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>El Limón</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>El Limón</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>El Limón</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ACARIGUA</Tag>
		<English>Acarigua</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Acarigua</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Acarigua</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Acarigua</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Acarigua</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PUNTO_FIJO</Tag>
		<English>Punto Fijo</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Punto Fijo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Punto Fijo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Punto Fijo</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Punto Fijo</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CABUDARE</Tag>
		<English>Cabudare</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Cabudare</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Cabudare</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cabudare</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Cabudare</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CHARALLAVE</Tag>
		<English>Charallave</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Charallave</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Charallave</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Charallave</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Charallave</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CIUDAD_OJEDA</Tag>
		<English>Ciudad Ojeda</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Ciudad Ojeda</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Ciudad Ojeda</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Ciudad Ojeda</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Ciudad Ojeda</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PALO_NEGRO</Tag>
		<English>Palo Negro</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Palo Negro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Palo Negro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Palo Negro</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Palo Negro</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CAGUA</Tag>
		<English>Cagua</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Cagua</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Cagua</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cagua</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Cagua</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ANACO</Tag>
		<English>Anaco</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Anaco</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Anaco</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Anaco</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Anaco</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CALABOZO</Tag>
		<English>Calabozo</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Calabozo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Calabozo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Calabozo</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Calabozo</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_GUANARE</Tag>
		<English>Guanare</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Guanare</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Guanare</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guanare</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Guanare</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
