<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_CATHEDRAL</Tag>
		<English>Chram</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_CATHEDRAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The remains of several Slavic shrines have also been discovered. Some archeological excavations on the cape of Arkona on Rügen island have uncovered vestiges of a great temple and a city, identified with those described by Saxo. In Novgorod, at the ancient Peryn skete, archeologists discovered the remains of a pagan shrine likely dedicated to Perun. The shrine consisted of a wide circular platform centred around a statue. The platform was encircled by a trench with eight apses, which contain remains of sacrificial altars. Remains of a citadel with a more or less identical layout were discovered on a location with the suggestive name Pohansko (Paganic), near Breclav in the Czech Republic.</English>
		<Polish>Chram (także kącina, kupiszta; niepoprawnie: kontyna, gontyna) - przedchrześcijański typ budowli sakralnej u Słowian - miejsce spotkań, modlitw, nabożeństw i wróżb, którego rolę pierwotnie pełniły święte gaje. W językach ukraińskim, rosyjskim i białoruskim, czeskim, bułgarskim chram nadal jest powszechnie lub zamiennie używanym określeniem świątyni. Określenia chram w języku polskim używa się również w odniesieniu do świątyń shintoistycznych, dla odróżnienia od świątyń buddyjskich. Słowo gontyna jest wyrazem sztucznym, stworzonym ok. 1860, przez Bronisława Trentowskiego, fałszywie odtworzone przez adideację do słowa gont z kronik niemieckich z XII wieku.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_CATHEDRAL_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Chram[COLOR_REVERT] ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Rodnovery Cathedral[COLOR_REVERT]) greatly increases a city's cultural output. It makes a city's citizens happy (if [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Rodnovera[COLOR_REVERT] is the state religion).</English>
		<French>Cathédrale Rodnovère</French>
		<German>Rodnovery Cathedral</German>
		<Italian>La [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Cattedrale Rodnovery[COLOR_REVERT] incrementa notevolmente la produzione culturale di una città. Rende felice un cittadino, se il [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]RODNOVERYo[COLOR_REVERT] è la religione di stato ufficiale.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Rodnovery Cathedral</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_MONASTERY</Tag>
		<English>Idol</English>
		<French>Idole</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_MONASTERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Statues of several Slavic deities were discovered in 1848. On the banks of the Zbruch river, a tall stone statue was found, with four faces under a single stone hat. Because of its similarity to Saxo's description of the great image in the temple of Rügen, the statue was immediately proclaimed a representation of Svantevit, although it was clear it could not be the original Svantevit of Rügen. Several other multi-headed statues were discovered elsewhere. A tiny four-headed statue from the 10th century, carved out of bone, was unearthed among the ruins of Preslav, a capital of medieval Bulgarian tsars. A two-headed, human-sized wooden statue was discovered on an island in the Tollensesee lake near Neubrandenburg: in the Middle Ages, this was the land of the Slavic Dolenain tribe, whose name survives in the name of the lake. Furthermore, a three-headed statue was discovered in Dalmatia (Croatia) on the hill bearing the name of Suvid, not far from the peak of Mt. Dinara called Troglav.</English>
		<Polish>W religiach pierwotnych kult idola (idolatria) był wyrazem przeświadczenia, że pomiędzy wyobrażeniem bóstwa a nim samym istnieje bezpośrednia więź, granicząca czasem z tożsamością. Oddawanie religijnej czci idolowi było więc jednoczesną adoracją bóstwa. Podobny magiczny charakter miała też idolatria występująca w wielu religiach świata starożytnego (Babilon, Egipt, Grecja, częściowo Izrael i inne). Przyozdabianie idoli, namaszczanie, składanie im ofiar, obnoszenie w procesjach, okadzanie itp. były uważane za usługiwanie samym bóstwom.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_MONASTERY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Idols[COLOR_REVERT] provide culture, +1 health and a slight boost to research.</English>
		<French>Monastère Rodnovère</French>
		<German>Rodnovery Monastery</German>
		<Italian>I [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]monasteri rodnovery[COLOR_REVERT] forniscono cultura, +1 salute e un piccolo bonus alla ricerca.</Italian>
		<Polish>Rodnovery Monastery</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_SHRINE</Tag>
		<English>Arkona</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>From the 9th to the 12th centuries, Arkona was a cult site for the Rani, a Slavic tribe, which was dedicated to their god Svantevit. Located at the tip of the cape, it was protected on three sides by cliffs and from the land side by a 25-metre-high burgwall. The temple located within the ramparts grew in importance as a religious centre for the Slavs of Mecklenburg after the destruction of Rethra in 1068. In 1168, the Danish king Valdemar I conquered Rügen which then became Christian. Churches were established and the castle and its temple destroyed. From about the 9th century the Rani settled on Rügen; they probably built the sanctuary at this time and then erected the castle and fortifications in several stages. In the 11th century the rampart was raised further using soil from the inner area of the castle. The Rani dominated Rügen for some time and the temple increased in importance as a religious centre for the Slavs in the southern Baltic following the destruction of Rethra in 1068. The temple served as oracle site and received offerings from other peoples, not just the Slavs.</English>
		<Polish>Arkona była znanym ośrodkiem kultu słowiańskiego boga Swiętowita (połabskie: Svątevit, czytaj swantewit). Według Saxo Grammaticusa, świątyni Swiętowita (kąciny) strzegła stała załoga licząca 300 wojów, podległych arcykapłanowi. W świątyni znajdował się posąg i skarbiec Swiętowita, będący właściwie skarbcem państwa Rugian. Po splądrowaniu (1067/1068) a następnie zniszczeniu (1125) Radogoszczy, Arkona stała się najważniejszym miejscem kultu religijnego Słowian nadbałtyckich.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_SHRINE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Arkona[COLOR_REVERT] ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Rodnovery Shrine[COLOR_REVERT]) produces one gold each turn for every city in the world that practises [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Rodnovera[COLOR_REVERT]. It also spreads [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Rodnovera[COLOR_REVERT] thoughout the world and increases its city's chances of generating a [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Great Prophet[COLOR_REVERT].</English>
		<French>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Arkona[COLOR_REVERT] ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]L'Autel Rodnovère[COLOR_REVERT]) produit de l'or à chaque tour, pour chaque ville au monde qui pratique la [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Rodnoverie[COLOR_REVERT]. Propage également la [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Rodnoverie[COLOR_REVERT] à travers le monde, et augmente les chances pour la ville de donner naissance à un [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Prophète Illustre[COLOR_REVERT].</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_TEMPLE</Tag>
		<English>Gaj</English>
		<French>Gaj (Bosquet sacré)</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_TEMPLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>It is commonly claimed that worshiping among Slavic people often happened in the woods rather than in shrines. Such woods were called "gaje" in the Proto-Slavic language (compare Polish gaj 'small wood, thicket, bush, grove'; see: sacred grove), and were sometimes encircled by a fence, which created a sacred area, both a natural and social sphere. Sometimes they would be used as cemeteries as well (see Kleczanów Wood).</English>
		<Polish>Swięty gaj - święte miejsce poświęcone bóstwom, duchom przodków lub siłom natury. Swięte gaje występują w pierwotnych religiach Ariów, Irańczyków, Greków, Rzymian, Germanów, Słowian, Bałtów i Celtów. Istniały one zarówno w religiach starożytnych jak i w innych kulturach na świecie. W niektórych kulturach święte gaje poświęcone były bogom (jeden z nich stał się np. podstawą do powstania książki Jamesa Frazera Złota gałąź), w innych dodatkowo stanowiły symboliczną więź żywych ze zmarłymi przodkami, której naruszenie groziło poważnymi, negatywnymi konsekwencjami. Miejsca takie zachowały swoją funkcję religijną także współcześnie w wybranych nurtach religijnych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RODNOVERY_TEMPLE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Gaj[COLOR_REVERT] increase a city's happiness and culture. They are especially useful for expanding your civilization's borders during the early game.</English>
		<French>Les [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Gaj[COLOR_REVERT] améliorent le bonheur et la culture des villes. ils sont notamment utiles pour agrandir vos frontières culturelles au début du jeu.</French>
		<German>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Gaj[COLOR_REVERT] steigern die Zufriedenheit und Kultur einer Stadt. Sie eignen sich hervorragend, um Ihre Zivilisation bereits in der Frühphase des Spiels zu vergrößern.</German>
		<Italian>I [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Gaj[COLOR_REVERT] aumentano la felicità e la cultura della città. Sono particolarmente indicati per espandere i confini della tua civiltà durante le fasi iniziali della partita.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Los [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Gaj[COLOR_REVERT] aumentan la felicidad y cultura de la ciudad. Son especialmente útiles para expandir las fronteras de la civilización al principio de la partida.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_RODNOVERA</Tag>
		<English>Rodnovera</English>
		<French>Rodnoverie</French>
		<Polish>Rodzimowierstwo</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_RODNOVERA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Slavic mythology is the mythological aspect of the polytheistic religion that was practised by the Slavs prior to Christianisation. The religion possesses numerous common traits with other religions descended from the Proto-Indo-European religion. Archaeological remains of old Slavic idols and shrines have been found, though little can be yielded from them without proper knowledge of their contexts, other than confirming existing historical records. Fragments of old mythological beliefs and pagan festivals survive up to this day in folk customs, songs, and stories of all the Slavic nations.</English>
		<French>La mythologie slave est l'aspect mythologique de la religion polytheistic qui a été pratiquée par les Slaves avant la christianisation. La religion possède de nombreux traits communs avec d'autres religions descendues de la religion Proto-Indo-Européenne. Des restes archéologiques de vieux idoles et tombeaux slaves ont été trouvés, cependant petit peuvent être rapportés de eux sans connaissance appropriée de leurs contextes, autre que les disques historiques existants de confirmation. Les fragments de la vieille croyance mythologique et les festivals païens survivent jusqu'à ce jour à la douane, des chansons, et des histoires folkloriques de toutes les nations slaves.</French>
		<German>Slavicmythologie ist der mythologische Aspekt der polytheistic Religion, die von den Slawen vor Christianisierung geübt wurde. Die Religion besitzt zahlreiche allgemeine Merkmale mit anderen Religionen, die von der Proto-Indo-Europäischen Religion abgestiegen werden. Archäologische Überreste der alter Slavicidole und -Schreine sind gefunden worden, zwar klein können von ihnen ohne korrektes Wissen ihrer Zusammenhänge, anders als bestätigende vorhandene historische Rekorde erbracht werden. Fragmente des alten mythologischen Glaubens und heidnische Festivals überleben bis zu diesem Tag in den Volksgewohnheiten, in den Lieden und in den Geschichten aller Slavicnationen.</German>
		<Italian>La mitologia dello Slavic è la funzione mitologica della religione polytheistic che si è esercitata in dagli slavi prima di cristianizzazione. La religione possiede le numerose caratteristiche comuni con altre religioni discese dalla religione Proto-Indo-Europea. I resti Archaeological di vecchi idoli e santuari dello Slavic sono stati trovati, comunque piccolo possono essere resi da loro senza conoscenza adeguata dei loro contesti, tranne le annotazioni storiche esistenti di conferma. I frammenti di vecchia credenza mitologica ed i festival pagani sopravvivono a fino a questo giorno nelle abitudini, nelle canzoni e nelle storie pieghe di tutte le nazioni dello Slavic.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La mitología eslava es el aspecto mitológico de la religión politeísta que fue practicada por los eslavos antes de la cristianización. La religión posee rasgos comunes numerosos con otras religiones descendidas de la religión Proto-Indo-Europea. Los restos arqueológicos de ídolos y de capillas eslavos viejos se han encontrado, aunque pequeño se pueden rendir de ellas sin el conocimiento apropiado de sus contextos, con excepción de expedientes históricos existentes que confirmaban. Los fragmentos de la vieja creencia mitológica y los festivales paganos sobreviven hasta este día en aduanas, canciones, e historias populares de todas las naciones eslavas.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Rodzimowierstwo - system wierzeń etnicznych (zarówno minionych jak i współczesnych - w tym część rekonstrukcji - zawsze jednak nawiązujących do konkretnego systemu wierzeń etnicznych) odwołujących się zazwyczaj do tradycji przedchrześcijańskich. Zespół poglądów opartych na mitologii i wierzeniach lokalnej społeczności, w obrębie danej grupy kulturowej lub etnicznej (rodzimowierca - wyznawca wiary rodzimej, etnicznej).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_RODNOVERA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>"TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_RODNOVERA_QUOTE</Tag>
		<English>"Pjarun, nas bac'ka! Jasny boza gromu, Daruj nam! Zracy Hrysta nas asukal?" - Prayer to Perun (Slavic god of thunder)</English>
		<French>"Pjarun, nas bac'ka! Jasny boza gromu, Daruj nam! Zracy Hrysta nas asukal?" - Prière à Perun (Dieu slave du Tonnerre)</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_RODNOVERY_MISSIONARY</Tag>
		<English>Zerca</English>
		<Polish>Żerca</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_RODNOVERY_MISSIONARY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Use this missionary to actively spread [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Rodnovery[COLOR_REVERT] in friendly cities (or rival cities with whom you have [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Open Borders[COLOR_REVERT]). This increases your income if you have the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Arkona.[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>Utilisez le Missionnaire pour propager la [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Rodnoverie[COLOR_REVERT] dans les villes alliées (ou les villes rivales avec lesquelles vous avez un accord de [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Libre passage[COLOR_REVERT]). Cela augmente vos revenus si vous avez construit l'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Arkona[COLOR_REVERT].</French>
		<Italian>Usa questo missionario per diffondere velocemente l'[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Rodnovery[COLOR_REVERT] nelle tue città, o nelle città straniere nelle quali hai [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Arkona[COLOR_REVERT]).</Italian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>