<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_CATHEDRAL</Tag>
		<English>Cao Dai Cathedral</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_CATHEDRAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In Civilization IV, a cathedral is defined as an especially large and ornate religious building where the faithful worship. Only the most prosperous cities can afford to create cathedrals, as they require huge amounts of raw material and years of dedicated labor by skilled craftsmen. For example, the Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris, France, took over two centuries to complete.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_CATHEDRAL_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Mosque[COLOR_REVERT] ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]CaoDai Cathedral[COLOR_REVERT]) greatly increases a city's cultural output. It makes a city's citizens happy (if [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]CaoDai[COLOR_REVERT] is the state religion).</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_MONASTERY</Tag>
		<English>Cao Dai Monastery</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_MONASTERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A monastery is a building where monks can retreat from the world and concentrate upon the divine. Usually a monastery will have strict rules of conduct to protect its unworldly members from temptation. In some monasteries, the monks are totally silent; in others no visitors are allowed inside. Monasteries usually have many daily rituals and religious services.[PARAGRAPH:1]Throughout the ages monasteries have often been centers of learning. In remote areas the monks may be the only literate people for miles around. Monks have often been employed as scribes, copying out the words of their religion's sacred scripture. Monasteries frequently have extensive libraries, holding religious, scientific, medical and philosophical texts.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_MONASTERY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Monasteries[COLOR_REVERT] allow you to create [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Missionaries[COLOR_REVERT], who can spread the faith in other cities. They also provide culture and a slight boost to research.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_SHRINE</Tag>
		<English>Great Temple Tay Ninh</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Great Temple is 140 m long and 40 m wide. It has 4 towers each with a different name: Tam Dai, Hiep Thien Dai, Cuu Trung Dai, and Bat Quai Dai. The interior of the temple consists of a colonnaded hall and a sanctuary. The 2 rows of columns are decorated with dragons and are coated in white, red, and blue paint. The domed ceiling is divided into 9 parts similar to a night sky full of stars and symbolizing heaven. Under the dome is a giant star-speckled blue globe on which is painted the Divine Eye, the official symbol of Caodaism. Cao Dai followers worship Jesus Christ, Confucius, Taoism, and Buddha.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_SHRINE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Great Temple Tay Ninh[COLOR_REVERT] ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]CaoDai Shrine[COLOR_REVERT]) produces one gold each turn for every city in the world that practises [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]CaoDai[COLOR_REVERT]. It also spreads [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]CaoDai[COLOR_REVERT] thoughout the world and increases its city's chances of generating a [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Great Prophet[COLOR_REVERT].</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_TEMPLE</Tag>
		<English>Cao Dai Temple</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_TEMPLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In Civilization IV, a temple is defined as a building where the faithful come to worship. Christians call their temples "churches," while Muslims call theirs "mosques," and Jews call theirs, simply, "temples." Temples are far more common than cathedrals, but much less large and ornate. Even the smallest village can possess a temple.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAODAI_TEMPLE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Temples[COLOR_REVERT] increase a city's happiness and culture. They are especially useful for expanding your civilization's borders during the early game.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_CAO_DAI</Tag>
		<English>Cao Dai</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_CAO_DAI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[PARAGRAPH:0]Cao Dai (or "High Tower", a Taoist epithet for the supreme god) is a syncretist Vietnamese religious movement with a strongly nationalist political character. Cao Dai draws upon ethical precepts from Confucianism, occult practices from Taoism, theories of karma and rebirth from Buddhism, and a hierarchical organization (including a pope) from Roman Catholicism. Its pantheon of saints includes such diverse figures as the Buddha, Confucius, Jesus Christ, Muhammad, Pericles, Julius Caesar, Joan of Arc, Victor Hugo, and Sun Yat-sen. In Cao Dai, God is represented as an eye in a triangle, a symbol that appears on the facades of the sect’s temples. The religion’s organization is patterned after that of Roman Catholicism, with a pope, cardinals, and archbishops. Worship involves elaborate rituals and festivals.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1919 Ngo Van Chieu (q.v.), an administrator for the French in Indochina, received a communication from the supreme deity during a table-moving séance. Chieu became the prophet of the new religion, which was formally established in 1926. A Cao Dai army was established in 1943 during the Japanese occupation of Indochina. After the war the Cao Dai was an effective force in national politics; it first supported, then opposed, Premier Ngo Dinh Diem. In 1955–56 Diem disbanded the Cao Dai army and forced the sect’s pope, Pham Cong Tac, into exile. After the communist takeover in 1975, Cao Dai was reportedly repressed by the government. Centres of worship were established in Vietnamese refugee communities abroad, however, and by the early 1990s Cao Dai was reported to have some two million adherents in Vietnam, Cambodia, France, and the United States. Headquarters of the religion are at Tay Ninh (q.v.), near Ho Chi Minh City (formerly Saigon).[PARAGRAPH:2]- Encyclopaedia Britannica</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_CAO_DAI_QUOTE</Tag>
		<English>The ultimate goal of CaoDaists is to be reunified with the All That Is, to return home.[PARAGRAPH:2]- Hum Dac Bui,[PARAGRAPH:1][SPACE][SPACE]"Cao Dai: Faith of Unity"</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_CAO_DAI_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Research Cao Dai to found a religion.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAODAI_MISSIONARY</Tag>
		<English>Cao Dai Missionary</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAODAI_MISSIONARY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Use this missionary to actively spread [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]CaoDai[COLOR_REVERT] in friendly cities (or rival cities with whom you have [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Open Borders[COLOR_REVERT]). This increases your income if you have the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Masjid al-Haram[COLOR_REVERT].</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
