<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BISHOPS_STOREHOUSE</Tag>
		<English>Bishop's Storehouse</English>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Almacen del Obispo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BISHOPS_STOREHOUSE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A bishop's storehouse in The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (Mormonism) usually refers to a commodity resource center that is used by bishops (leaders of local-level congregations) of the church to provide goods to needy individuals. The storehouses stock basic foods and essential household items. Bishop's storehouses are not commercial entities and goods are generally not for sale to the public through them. Food and supplies stored at Welfare Square are distributed to central storehouses in other regions of the world. From these storehouses, food and materials are sent to more than 200 smaller bishops' storehouses in communities of those regions for distribution. Ecclesiastical leaders (bishops) of congregations in those communities are able to call in food and supply orders for their members who they determine are in need. Those members, in turn, have an opportunity to give volunteer service to pay for the goods received so that they are, in essence, given a hand up, not a hand out. The main function of the new central storehouse is to administer to the poor and needy through the Church's welfare system. On occasion, emergency equipment such as electrical generators, shovels, chain saws, picks, food and supplies are also dispatched to areas of the world where people have suffered the effects of natural disasters like Hurricane Katrina.</English>
		<Spanish>Se describe mejor un Almacén del Obispo como un supermercado sin cajas registradoras. El almacén ha sido diseñado intencionadamente para que parezca un supermercado, así las personas que acuden sienten como si estarían en un supermercado normal. Las personas que adquieren sus productos aquí se encuentran en necesidad de alimentos; por ejemplo, alguien puede estar desempleado y no tiene dinero para comprar los productos básicos necesarios en la vida, tales como alimentos. Le corresponde al Obispo de cada barrio mormón (congregación) determinar si una persona califica para obtener alimentos del Almacén del Obispo. Aunque este programa está dirigido principalmente a los miembros de la Iglesia, es posible que un no miembro obtenga ayuda del Almacén del Obispo, si el Obispo lo considera oportuno. Asimismo, en momentos de desastres como en el huracán Katrina, los Almacenes del Obispo más grandes conocidos como Almacenes Regionales del Obispo se abrieron para abastecer con alimentos y otros artículos a las víctimas del huracán Katrina. Muchas de las personas que recibieron ayuda en esta oportunidad no eran mormonas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MISSIONARY_TRAINING_CENTER</Tag>
		<English>Mormon Missionary Training Center</English>
		<French>Centre de formation de missionnaires Mormon</French>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Centro de Capacitación Misional</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MISSIONARY_TRAINING_CENTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Missionary Training Centers (or "MTCs") are centers devoted to training missionaries for The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (Mormonism). The largest MTC is located in Provo, Utah, USA, adjacent to the campus of Brigham Young University. At the beginning of their service, LDS missionaries usually spend 3-12 weeks at an MTC where they receive training in doctrine, conduct, proselyting methods, and when required, a foreign language. There are 15 MTCs located in nations throughout the world including Argentina, Brazil, Colombia, Mexico, South Africa, Spain, Philippines and the United Kingdom.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_CATHEDRAL</Tag>
		<English>Mormon Temple</English>
		<French>Temple Mormon</French>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Templo de los Mormones</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_CATHEDRAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, also called the LDS or Mormon Church, a temple is a building dedicated to be a House of The Lord, and they are considered by Church members to be the most sacred structures on earth. Upon completion, temples are usually open to the public for a short period of time (an "Open House"). During the Open House, the church conducts tours of the temple with missionaries and members from the local area serving as tour guides, and all rooms of the temple are open to the public. The temple is then dedicated as a "House of The Lord," after which only members in good standing are permitted entrance, thus they are not churches but rather places of worship. The LDS Church is a prolific builder of temples as temples hold a key place in LDS theology. Currently (August 2010) there are 131 operating temples, 7 under construction, and 14 announced (not yet under construction).[PARAGRAPH:2]At present, there are temples in many U.S. states, as well as in many countries across the world. Several temples have been built at holy sites of the LDS church, such as Nauvoo, Illinois; Winter Quarters, Nebraska; and Palmyra, New York. The importance of temples is often emphasized in weekly meetings, and regular participation in temple work is strongly encouraged of all Latter-day Saints (LDS).[PARAGRAPH:2]Within temples, members of the Church make covenants, receive instructions, and perform sacred ordinances, such as: baptism for the dead, washing and anointing (or "initiatory" ordinances), the "endowment," and eternal marriage sealing. Ordinances are a vital part of the theology of the church, which teaches that they were practiced by The Lord's covenant people in all dispensations. Additionally, members consider the temple a place to commune with God, seek God's aid, understand the will of God, and receive personal revelation.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_MONASTERY</Tag>
		<English>LDS Missionary Training Centre</English>
		<French>Centre de formation de missionnaires LDS</French>
		<Italian>Centro mormone di addestramento dei missionari</Italian>
		<Polish>Centrum Historii Rodziny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_MONASTERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Missionary Training Centers (or "MTCs") are centers devoted to training missionaries for The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.</English>
		<Italian>Missionary Training Centers ("MTCs") sono i centri in cui vengono addestrati i nuovi missionari mormoni.[PARAGRAPH:2]Fonte: Wikipedia</Italian>
		<Polish>Centrum Historii Rodziny - placówka badawcza, stworzona przez Kościół Jezusa Chrystusa Swiętych w Dniach Ostatnich (tzw. mormoni), której celem jest realizacja badań genealogicznych. Placówka taka zazwyczaj dysponuje materiałami źródłowymi w postaci mikrofilmów oraz sprzętem, który umożliwia ich przeglądanie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_SEMINARY</Tag>
		<English>Seminary (Mormon)</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Séminaire Mormon</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Priesterseminar Mormon</German>
		<Italian>Mormon Seminary</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Seminario de los Mormones</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_SEMINARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (LDS, Mormon), the Church Educational System (CES) provides Seminary instruction for high school age youth (usually 14 to 18). It is typically attended daily (Monday through Friday) and provides youth with instruction in the scriptures and in gospel principles. These courses are not for credit or degree purposes. Mormonism has no paid clergy, and seminary is not required for a call to the ministry. Instead, all LDS youth are encouraged to attend seminary for personal growth, and friends from other faiths are also welcomed. Every year the curriculum focuses on one of the standard works of the Church; the Old Testament, the New Testament, the Book of Mormon, and the Doctrine and Covenants. Released-time seminary is offered in areas where there are large populations of LDS students. Seminary classes are attended during school hours in a Church-owned seminary building near the school, and students take seminary classes in place of an elective. Seminary teachers are employed by the CES. Students do not receive any school credit for taking seminary. In other areas, students take early morning seminary (before school) or home study seminary in areas where LDS populations are very small. After high school, the CES offers Institute classes for college-age young men and women across the country (often near major colleges and universities).</English>
		<Spanish>En la Iglesia de Jesucristo de los Santos de los Últimos Días (SUD o Mormon), el Sistema Educativo de la Iglesia proporciona un Seminario para la juventud de la edad de preparatoria, (generalmente de 14 a 18 años). Regularmente se asiste diario y proporciona a la juventud instrucción en Las Escrituras y en principios del Evangelio de Jesucristo. Los que no son miembros de la Iglesia Mormona, también son bienvenidos a estas clases. Todos los años el plan de estudio se enfoca en uno de los Libros Canónicos de la Iglesia SUD, los cuales son El Antiguo Testamento, el Nuevo Testamento, el Libro de Mormón y la Doctrina y Convenios. El seminario de tiempo libre, se ofrece en áreas donde hay grandes poblaciones de estudiantes SUD y las leyes no prohíben estas reuniones. Estas reuniones de Seminario se llevan a cabo en horas de Escuela en un Edificio de la Iglesia o cerca de la Escuela. Los maestros en este caso son de jornada completa y el Sistema Educativo de la Iglesia les paga. Los estudiantes no reciben ningún crédito en la escuela por llevar Seminario. El seminario por las mañanas está disponible en la mayoría de las áreas que tienen un buen número de jóvenes SUD. El seminario de estudio en casa, está disponible en áreas donde en el seminario por las mañanas o el de tiempo libre, no está disponible. Toda la Juventud Mormona es alentada a completar y graduarse de Seminario si tienen la oportunidad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_SHRINE</Tag>
		<English>Hill Cumorah Pageant</English>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Festival del Cerro de Cumorah</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Hill Cumorah (also called Mormon Hill) is a drumlin in the Finger Lakes region in Western New York in Manchester, where Joseph Smith, Jr. said he found a set of ancient records, engraved on plates of gold, which he translated and published as the Book of Mormon in 1830. The hill is near Palmyra, New York, where Joseph Smith had a series of angelic and divine visitations leading up to the founding of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (Mormonism).[PARAGRAPH:2]Currently, the 283-acre (1.15 km2) site hosts the annual "Hill Cumorah Pageant." This large, outdoor theatrical and musical event typically occurs in early July and is free to the public. The pageant is a major tourist attraction for Mormons as well as a proselyting tool for spreading the Mormon faith. The pageant can trace its history back to 1935.</English>
		<Spanish>Fue en este cerro en Nueva York donde José Smith recobro los grabados antiguos de profetas de pueblos americanos. Guiado por un ángel de nombre Moroni, el último de los profetas en escribir en estas planchas de oro, José Smith recibió el llamado de traducir al Inglés los escritos de las planchas en lo que se conoce hoy como El Libro de Mormón: Otro Testamento de Jesucristo. En el presente, la vecindad del Cerro Cumorah en el pueblo de Palmyra, se encuentran establecidos una red de lugares históricos del área, en especial concerniente al origen de La Iglesia de Jesucristo de los Santos de los Últimos Días. Entre los puntos de interés renovados para guías turísticas se encuentran:[PARAGRAPH:2][TAB]La arboleda sagrada, lugar donde José Smith tuvo su primera visión.[PARAGRAPH:3][TAB]Centro de Visitantes del Cerro Cumorah[PARAGRAPH:4]Cabaña de la familia de José Smith[TAB][PARAGRAPH:5]Imprenta Grandin, donde se imprimió la primera edición del Libro de Mormón en el año 1829[TAB][PARAGRAPH:6][TAB]Templo de la ciudad de Palmyra[PARAGRAPH:7][TAB]The Hill Cumorah Pageant, una representación teatral de la historia del Libro de Mormon y de la Iglesia Restaurada.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_TEMPLE</Tag>
		<English>Mormon Meetinghouse</English>
		<French>Maison de Rencontre Mormon</French>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Capilla Mormona</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MORMON_TEMPLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (Mormonism), a meetinghouse typically housing LDS wards (congregations). A ward is presided over by a bishop, the equivalent of a pastor in other religions. As with all church leadership at the local level within a ward, the bishop is considered lay clergy and as such is not paid. A ward typically consists of 200 to 500 active church members within a set geographical area. In areas where there are greater numbers of active church members (such as urban and suburban areas in Utah), the area of a ward can be as small as one-fifth of a square mile.[PARAGRAPH:2]When a ward grows sufficiently in size, the ward will divide geographically. Generally, if both geographic divisions are in a reasonable distance of the meetinghouse, then they will meet at the same building, but at different times. Most ward meetinghouses are designed to house up to three or four wards. The Mormon Meetinghouse gives a small health benefit under the Church welfare civic, because in Mormonism it is the meetinghouse, not the missionary training center, that is the local hub for charitable efforts. The happiness effects of the meetinghouse represent LDS attitudes toward various civics, which tend to be conservative and libertarian. The LDS health code, which forbids consumption of coffee, tea, tobacco, and alcohol, explains the unhappiness effects of the Mormon Meetinghouse. Instead of alcohol, Mormon social functions typically feature breads and pastas, meat, fruit, vegetables, and plenty of desserts, among which ice cream is the perennial favorite.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TEMPLE_SQUARE</Tag>
		<English>Temple Square</English>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Temple Square</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TEMPLE_SQUARE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The headquarters of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (Mormonism) is a 50 acre complex consisting of four city blocks in the heart of Salt Lake City, Utah. It consists of the Salt Lake Temple, several visitors centers, the Church Office Building and other administration buildings, the Conference Center, and several museum and archive buildings, including the church's Family History Library, the world's largest genealogical library and a repository of research materials that is free and open to the public. The entire complex is sometimes called Temple Square.[PARAGRAPH:2][TAB]In 1847, when Mormon pioneers arrived in the Salt Lake Valley, prophet Brigham Young selected a plot of the desert ground and proclaimed, "Here we will build a temple to our God." The square also became the headquarters of the LDS Church. As the Church has grown, its headquarters has expanded into the surrounding area. The area has been termed the “Mormon Mecca” for its popularity as a Mormon tourist destination. Tens of thousands of Mormons gather there twice a year (in April and October) or tune in via radio, tv, satellite, or internet transmission, to listen to sermons by the faith's prophets, apostles, and other leaders at General Conference.</English>
		<Spanish>El centro religioso y espiritual es Salt Lake City, capital del estado de Utah, de manera análoga a Ciudad del Vaticano para los católicos. El Templo de Salt Lake City (Ciudad de Lago Salado) es uno de los templos construidos y operados por La Iglesia de Jesucristo de los Santos de los Últimos Días, el quinto construido por la iglesia, el tercero en Utah y uno de los más reconocidos del movimiento de los Santos de los Últimos Días, ubicado en el centro de Salt Lake City, capital del estado de Utah en los Estados Unidos. El templo de Salt Lake City es el cuarto templo que ha estado en operaciones desde el éxodo de los pioneros mormones desde Nauvoo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WELFARE_SQUARE</Tag>
		<English>Welfare Square</English>
		<Spanish>Cuadro de Bienestar</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WELFARE_SQUARE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Welfare Square is a complex in downtown Salt Lake City, Utah owned and operated by The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (LDS Church, or Mormonism), to provide material assistance to poor and otherwise needy individuals and families. Welfare Square is part of the LDS Church Welfare System. It includes a 178-foot, 318,000 bushel grain silo, fruit orchards, a milk-processing plant, a cannery, a bakery, a Deseret Industries thrift store, a private employment office, and the LDS Church's largest Bishop's storehouse, as well as associated administrative offices. Most of the assistance provided at Welfare Square goes to those who are members of the LDS Church. Fast offering donations from local LDS congregations fund its operations. Humanitarian assistance to worldwide disaster areas flows through a separate facility and is funded by LDS members' donations to the LDS Church's Humanitarian Fund. Welfare Square was created in 1938, under the direction of the General Welfare Committee of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (Mormonism). Throughout the 1930s and 1940s, as the United States was experiencing the Great Depression, Welfare Square became the flagship of Mormonism's Welfare Program. As part of the LDS Church's larger Welfare Program, all aid received at Welfare Square is based on personal responsibility, thrift, and work; recipients of aid may be asked to volunteer their time after receiving help.</English>
		<Spanish>Desde los primeros días de La Iglesia de Jesucristo de los Santos de los Últimos Días en los años 1800, los Almacenes del Obispo han formado parte de la Iglesia. Sin embargo, hasta la década de 1930, estos almacenes se mantuvieron sólo a nivel congregacional local. En 1936, la Iglesia anunció lo que ahora se conoce como el Programa de Bienestar de la Iglesia, el cual es un programa mundial dentro de la Iglesia Mormona. Este programa incluye al programa conocido como Almacenes del Obispo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_ENDOWMENT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Endowment</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_PRIESTHOOD_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Priesthood</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_MORMON</Tag>
		<English>Mormon</English>
		<Italian>Mormonismo</Italian>
		<Polish>Mormonizm</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_MORMON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (abbreviated as the LDS Church, and colloquially referred to as the Mormon Church) is a restorationist Christian church and the largest denomination originating from the Latter Day Saint movement founded by Joseph Smith, Jr. Founded in Upstate New York in 1830, the church is headquartered in Salt Lake City, Utah, and has established congregations (called wards or branches) worldwide.[PARAGRAPH:2]Adherents view faith in Jesus Christ as the central tenet of their religion. LDS Church theology includes the Christian doctrine of salvation only through Jesus Christ. The church has an open canon which includes four scriptural texts: the Bible (both Old and New Testaments), the Book of Mormon, the Doctrine and Covenants, and the Pearl of Great Price. Other than the Bible, the majority of the LDS canon constitutes revelation dictated by Joseph Smith and includes commentary and exegesis about the Bible, texts described as lost parts of the Bible, and other works believed to be written by ancient prophets. Together these are known to Latter-Day Saints as the Standard Works.[PARAGRAPH:2]Under the doctrine of revelation, Latter Day Saints believe that Jesus leads the church by revealing his will to the President of the Church, whom they sustain as a modern-day prophet, seer, and revelator. Individual members are expected to receive personal revelation from God for specifics in conducting their lives. The President heads a hierarchical structure with various levels reaching down to local congregations. Bishops, drawn from the laity, lead local congregations. Worthy male members, after age 12, may be ordained to the priesthood. Women do not hold positions within the priesthood but serve in an array of other leadership roles, including the Relief Society, the world's largest women's organization. Both men and women may serve as missionaries, and the church maintains a large missionary program which proselytizes and conducts humanitarian service worldwide. Faithful members adhere to laws regarding sexual purity, health, fasting, and Sabbath-day observance. Members also voluntarily tithe, donating 10 percent of their income to the church.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_MORMON_QUOTE</Tag>
		<English>Love is one of the chief characteristics of Deity... A man filled with the love of God is not content with blessing his family alone, but ranges through the whole world, anxious to bless the whole human race. (Joseph Smith, Jr., 1840)</English>
		<French>L'amour est l'une des principales caractéristiques de la Divinité... Un homme rempli de l'amour de Dieu ne doit pas se contenter de chercher le bien de sa famille. Il parcourt le monde entier, cherchant à faire du bien à tout le genre humain. (Joseph Smith, Jr., 1840)</French>
		<German>Liebe ist eine wesentliche Eigenschaft der Gottheit... Wer von der Liebe Gottes durchdrungen ist, der will nicht allein seiner Familie ein Segen sein, vielmehr will er überall, wo er ist, der ganzen Menschheit zum Segen gereichen. (Joseph Smith, Jr., 1840)</German>
		<Italian>L'amore è una delle caratteristiche principali della Divinità... Un uomo pieno dell'amore di Dio non si accontenta di benedire la sua famiglia soltanto, ma percorre tutto il mondo, ansioso di benedire tutta la razza umana. (Joseph Smith, Jr., 1840)</Italian>
		<Spanish>El amor es una de las características principales de la Deidad... El hombre que está lleno del amor de Dios no se conforma con bendecir solamente a su familia sino que va por todo el mundo, anheloso de bendecir a toda la raza humana. (Joseph Smith, Jr., 1840)</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MORMON_MISSIONARY</Tag>
		<English>Mormon Elders</English>
		<French>Aînés Mormons</French>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Los Elderes Mormones</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_RETURNED_MISSIONARY</Tag>
		<English>Mormon Returned Missionary</English>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Missionario Mormon Regressados</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_RETURNED_MISSIONARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>After serving an unpaid full-time mission for the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (Mormons), missionaries are "released" from their mission call and return to regular lives. Having gained valuable life experience while missionaries, most of these "returned missionaries" (RMs) are eager to put their experience to work. Marriage and building a family is usually a high priority for these young men and women, but there is also an unusually high percentage that pursue careers in government, the military, and law enforcement. In the USA, the FBI is remarkable for accepting a high proportion of candidates from the ranks of RMs. Their squeaky clean backgrounds, foreign language training, leadership experience, and commitment to law and order make them prime candidates for training to serve among law enforcement's elite.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>