<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KAMEHAMEHA</Tag>
		<Russian>Êàìåàìåà</Russian>
		<English>Kamehameha</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KAMEHAMEHA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<Russian>[H1]Êàìåàìåà Âåëèêèé[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Êîðîëü Ãàâàéè[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ãîäû æèçíè: [\BOLD]1758 - 1819[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Ãîäû æèçíè:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Рождение Камеамеа окружено легендами, и говорят, что гавайцы утверждали, что великий король однажды объединит острова, и комета станет знаком его рождения. Когда родился Камеамеа, комета Галлея была видна на Гавайях. Имя Камеамеа при рождении было Пай'еа, и он родился в семье Кеку'иапойва, вождя Коала на острове Гавайи, и в семье Кеуа. Кеоуа, его отец, был сыном Кеавейкекахиали'иокамоку, который был вождем значительной части Гавайев. Однако после его правления разразилась война за престолонаследие, и Алапаи одержал победу над своими братьями и их сыновьями, включая Кеуа. Когда родился Камеамеа, Алапаи приказал убить его и нервничал при мысли, что ребенок может в конечном итоге править Гавайями. Итак, Камеамеа была отдана другому дворянину, Наэ'оле, и таким образом исчезла из поля зрения. Алапаи, раскаявшись в своих действиях, пригласил ребенка жить при королевском дворе.[PARAGRAPH: 1]После кончины Алапаи ему наследовал его сын Кеавеа'опала, которому бросил вызов Калани'опу'у, внучатый племянник Алапаи, и которого поддержал Камеамеа. В битве в заливе Кеалакекуа Кеавеа'опала одержал победу и сделал Камеамеа своим соправителем. В 1779 году во время путешествия с Калани'опу'у в залив Кеалакекуа Камеамеа встретил капитана Кука. Кука ошибочно приняли за гавайского бога плодородия Лоно, и Камеамеа, возможно, некоторое время находился на борту его корабля. После смерти Калани'опу'у царство унаследовал его сын Кивала'о. Камеамеа по-прежнему занимал видное положение, но между двумя кузенами возник конфликт. Когда группа вождей предложила Камеамеа королевство вместо Кивала'о, он принял и позже победил Кивала'о в битве при Моку'охай.[PARAGRAPH: 1]В 1790 году Камеамеа сместил главу округа Пуна Кеавемаухили. В то же время Кеуа, сосланный к себе домой, возглавил восстание. Однако треть его воинов была убита, когда он бежал из возвращающегося Камеамеа мимо вулкана. Позже Камеамеа построил храм, чтобы принести в жертву Кеуа, так что Камеамеа стал главой всех Гавайев. У Камеамеа были другие амбиции, и он искал помощи у британских и американских торговцев, которые продавали Камеамеа оружие и боеприпасы. Когда Камеамеа вторгся на ослабленные острова Мауи и Оаху, он не думал, что его соперник, Каланикупуле, также обладал огнестрельным оружием.[PARAGRAPH: 1]В 1790 году Камеамеа сместил главу округа Пуна Кеавемаухили. В то же время Кеуа, сосланный к себе домой, возглавил восстание. Однако треть его воинов была убита, когда он бежал из возвращающегося Камеамеа мимо вулкана. Позже Камеамеа построил храм, чтобы принести в жертву Кеуа, так что Камеамеа стал главой всех Гавайев. У Камеамеа были другие амбиции, и он искал помощи у британских и американских торговцев, которые продавали Камеамеа оружие и боеприпасы. Когда Камеамеа вторгся на ослабленные острова Мауи и Оаху, он не думал, что его соперник, Каланикупуле, также обладал огнестрельным оружием.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Камеамеа был теперь полноправным правителем всех Гавайев к востоку от Оаху, но острова Кауаи и Ниихау постоянно ускользали от него. Первое вторжение Камеамеа было неудачным, а второе привело к болезни. Будучи запуганным новой сильной армией Камеамеа, Каумали, вождь Кауаи, согласился стать его вассалом. Как первый король Гавайев, Камеамеа сделал несколько шагов, чтобы убедиться, что острова остались едиными после его смерти. Он унифицировал правовую систему и не позволял иностранцам владеть землей. Это провозглашение гарантировало независимость островов, в то время как другие острова в Тихом океане подчинились колониальной власти[PARAGRAPH: 1]Камеамеа также известен тем, что ввел Мамалохое Канави или «Закон расколотого весла». Этот закон восходит к ранним битвам Камеамеа. Закон обеспечивал безопасность мирных жителей во время войны, и сегодня он остается в конституции штата Гавайи, являясь его первым законом. Когда Камеамеа умер в 1819 году, его тело было доверено его другу Хаопили. По сей день место его упокоения остается неизвестным.</Russian>
		<English>[H1]Kamehameha the Great[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Hawaii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1758 - 1819[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Kamehameha's birth is surrounded by legend, and it is said that the Hawaiians claimed that a great king would one day unite the islands, and a comet would be the sign of his birth. When Kamehameha was born, Halley's Comet was visible in Hawaii. Kamehameha's birth name was Pai'ea, and he was born to Keku'iapoiwa, chief of the Kohala on the island of Hawai'i, and to Keoua. Keoua, his father, was the son of Keaweikekahiali'iokamoku, who was the chief of a large portion of Hawai'i. However, after his reign a war over succession broke, and Alapa'i emerged victorious over his brothers and their sons, including Keoua. When Kamehameha was born, Alapa'i ordered that he be killed, and was nervous at the thought that the child might eventually rule over Hawai'i. So, Kamehameha was given to another noble, Nae'ole, and thus disappeared from sight. Alapa'i, in remorse for his actions, invited the child to live in the royal court. [PARAGRAPH: 1] When Alapa'i died, he was succeeded by his son Keawea'opala who was challenged by Kalani'opu'u, Alapa'i's great nephew, and was backed by Kamehameha. At a battle at Kealakekua Bay, Keawea'opala was victorious and made Kamehameha his aid. In 1779, on a trip with Kalani'opu'u to Kealakekua Bay, Kamehameha met Captain Cook. Cook was mistaken to be the Hawaiian god of fertility, Lono, and Kamehameha may have been onboard his ship for some time. After Kalani'opu'u's death, kingship was inherited by his son Kiwala'o. Kamehameha was still given a prominent position, but there was a conflict between the two cousins. When a group of chiefs offered Kamehameha the kingship instead of Kiwala'o, he accepted and later defeated Kiwala'o at the Battle of Moku'ohai. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In 1790, Kamehameha deposed the chief of the district of Puna, Keawema'uhili. At the same time Keoua, exiled to his home, led an uprising. However, a third of his warriors were killed when he fled from the returning Kamehameha past a volcano. Kamehameha built a temple to sacrifice Keoua later, so that Kamehameha became the chief of all of Hawai'i. Kamehameha had other ambitions, and sought the help from British and American traders, who sold guns and ammunition to Kamehameha. When Kamehameha invaded the weakened islands of Maui and O'ahu, he did not think that his rival, Kalanikupule, also possessed firearms. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In 1795, Kamehameha set sail with an astonishing 1,200 war canoes and 10,000 soldiers. He quickly captured the islands of Maui and Moloka'i, and then moved on to O'ahu. However, one of Kamehameha's best commanders defected to Kalanikupule. In a series of skirmishes, Kamehameha and his army pushed back Kalanukupule until he was trapped. After Kamehameha's troops faced heavy cannon fire advancing to Kalanikupule, he sent his best warriors to attack the cannons from behind, which proved to be successful. Thus, Kalanikupule's troops fell into disarray and were defeated, with Kalanikupule being sacrificed later. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha was now the complete ruler of all of Hawai'i east of O'ahu, but the islands of Kaua'i and Ni'ihau were continuously escaping him. Kamehameha's first invasion was unsuccessful, and his second resulted in disease. After being intimidated by Kamehameha's new strong army, Kaumali'i, chief of Kaua'i, agreed to become a vassal of Kamehameha. As the first king of Hawai’i, Kamehameha made several steps to make certain that the islands remained united after his death. He unified the legal system and didn't allow non-Hawaiians to own land. This proclamation guaranteed the islands' independence while other islands in the Pacific gave in to colonial authority. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha also instituted the Mamalohoe Kanawi, the Law of the Splintered Paddle. This law had origins in Kamehameha's early battles. The Law provided the safety of noncombatants during wartime, and remains in Hawaii's state constitution today, being its first law. When Kamehameha died in 1819, his body was trusted to his friend, Haopili. To this day, his resting place remains unknown.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KAMEHAMEHA_1</Tag>
		<Russian>Ïðèâåòñòâóþ! Ñïðîñè ìåíÿ, ÷òî åñòü âåëè÷àéøàÿ âåùü â ìèðå, ÿ îòâå÷ó: ýòî íàðîä, íàðîä è åùå ðàç íàðîä!</Russian>
		<English>Hello! Ask me what is the greatest thing in the world, I will reply: It is people, it is people, it is people!</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>