<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
	<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by XMLSPY 2004 Professional Ed. Release 2, Installed Multi + SMP for 3 users (Firaxis Games) -->
	<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
	<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
	<!-- -->
	<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CUBA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB] Cuba is the most populous nation in the Caribbean . Its people, culture and customs 
draw from several sources including the aboriginal peoples, the period of Spanish colonialism, African 
slaves, and its proximity to the United States. The recorded history of Cuba began on 17 October 1492, 
when Christopher Columbus sighted the island during his first voyage and claimed it for Spain. The island 
had been inhabited by Native American peoples known as the Taíno and Ciboney whose ancestors had come 
from South America and possibly North and Central America in a complex series of migrations perhaps 6,000 
to 8,000 years ago. The Spanish oppressed and enslaved the approximately 100,000 indigenous people that 
resisted conversion to Christianity on the island. Within a century, they had all but disappeared as 
a result of the combined effects of European-introduced disease, forced labor and other mistreatment. 
Cuba was in a Spanish possession for almost 400 years (circa 1511-1898). The economy was based on plantation 
agriculture and mining, the export of sugar, coffee and tobacco to Europe and later to North America.[PARAGRAPH:2]By 
the middle of the 18th century Havana, the capital city, had more than seventy thousand inhabitants, 
and was the third largest city in the Americas, ranking behind Lima and Mexico City but ahead of Boston 
and New York. There were regular proposals in the U.S. to buy Cuba from Spain. During the summer of 1848, 
President James K. Polk authorized his ambassador to Spain, Romulus Mitchell Saunders, to negotiate the 
purchase of Cuba and offer Spain up to $100 million, an astonishing sum of money at the time for one 
territory. Spain, however, refused. Trade in sugar and molasses was $18,000,000 in 1859 alone.[PARAGRAPH:2]A 
rebellion in 1868 led by Carlos Manuel de Céspedes, a wealthy lawyer landowner from Oriente province 
who freed his slaves, proclaimed a war and was named President of the Cuban Republic-in-arms, resulted 
in a prolonged conflict known as the Ten Years' War between pro-independence forces and the Spanish Army. 
In 1879-1880, Cuban patriot Calixto Garcia attempted to start another war, known in Cuban history as 
"la guerra chiquita" (the little war) but received little support. During the 1890s, pro-independence 
agitation revived, fueled by resentment of the restrictions imposed on Cuban trade by Spain and hostility 
to Spain's increasingly oppressive and incompetent administration of Cuba. In April 1895, a new war was 
declared, led by the writer and poet Jose Martí who had organized the war over a ten year period while 
in exile in the U.S. and proclaimed Cuba an independent republic. Martí was killed at Dos Rios shortly 
after landing in Cuba with the eastern expeditionary force. His death immortalized him and he has become 
Cuba's undisputed national hero.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Republic of Cuba gained formal independence on 20 May 
1902, with the independence leader Tomás Estrada Palma becoming the country's first president. During 
World War 1, Cuban pilots distinguished themselves fighting for France in the Lafayette Escadrille. In 
1934, after a series of coups, Batista and the army, took control of the government, and in 1940, Batista 
decided to run for President himself. With the support of the Communist-controlled labor unions, Batista 
was elected President and his administration carried out major social reforms. Several members of the 
Communist Party held office under his administration. Batista's administration formally took Cuba into 
World War II as a U.S. ally, declaring war on Japan on December 9, 1941, then on Germany and Italy on 
December 11, 1941; Cuba, however, did not significantly participate militarily in World War II hostilities. 
At the end of his term in 1944, in accordance with the constitution, Batista stepped down and Ramón Grau 
was elected to succeed him. Grau initiated increased government spending on health, education and housing. 
Grau's "Auténticos" (authentics) were bitter enemies of the Communists and Batista, which opposed most 
of Grau's program. Grau completed his presidential term. In 1948, Grau was succeeded by Carlos Prío Socarrás, 
who had been Grau's minister of labor and was particularly hated by the Communists. Corruption was believed 
to have increased under Prío's administration; however no accusations of corruption were ever proven, 
and Eduardo Chibás, leader of the Ortodoxo party to which Fidel Castro belonged, committed suicide when 
his allegations were not substantiated. The 1952 election was a three-way race. Roberto Agramonte of 
the Ortodoxos party led in all the polls, followed by Dr. Aurelio Hevia of the Auténtico party, and running 
a distant third was Batista, who was seeking a return to office. Both front runners, Agramonte and Hevia 
in their own camps, had decided to name Col. Ramon Barquin, then a diplomat in Washington, DC to head 
the Cuban Armed Forces after the elections. Barquin was a top officer who commanded the respect of the 
professional army and had promised to eliminate corruption in the ranks. Batista feared that Barquin 
would oust him and his followers, and when it became apparent that Batista had little chance of winning, 
he staged a coup on 10 March 1952.[PARAGRAPH:2]On April 4, 1956, a coup by hundreds of career officers 
led by Col. Barquin (then Vice Chairman of the Inter-American Defense Board in Washington and Cuban Military 
Attaché of Sea, Air and Land to the US) was betrayed by Rios Morejon. The coup broke the backbone of 
the Cuban Armed Forces. The officers were sentenced to the maximum terms allowed by Cuban Martial Law. 
Barquin was sentenced to solitary confinement for 8 years. "La Conspiración de los Puros" (the conspiracy 
of the pure) resulted in the imprisonment of the top commanding brass of the Armed Forces and the closing 
of the military academies. Barquin was the founder of La Escuela Superior de Guerra (Cuba's War College) 
and past director of La Escuela de Cadetes (Cuba's Military Academy). Without Barquin's officers the 
army's ability to combat the revolutionary insurgents was severely curtailed.[PARAGRAPH:2]On 2 December 
1956, a party of 82 revolutionaries, led by Fidel Castro, landed in a yacht named Granma with the intention 
of establishing an armed resistance movement in the Sierra Maestra. The yacht had come from Mexico, where 
Castro had been exiled to, and where his army was strengthened with the help of Ernesto Che Guevara. 
By late 1958, and after staging many terrorist attacks, the rebels had succeeded in breaking out of the 
Sierra Maestra and launched a general insurrection, joined by hundreds of students and others fleeing 
Batista's crackdown on dissent in the cities. When the rebels captured Santa Clara, east of Havana, Batista 
fled the country to exile in Portugal and later Spain.  Then began the summary executions of "suspected" 
Batista collaborators and members of the opposition through the "paredones" ( firing squad "wall") that 
took place after show trials. Coupled with the seizure of privately-owned businesses and the rapid demise 
of the independent press, these atrocities raised questions about the nature of the new government. Castro, 
along with the hitman for hire, murderous dog, Che Guevara, executed or jailed countless innocent land 
and bussiness owners for the sole purpose of consolidating power and eliminating opposition. Many who 
had initially supported the revolution fled the country to join a rapidly growing exile community in 
Miami.[PARAGRAPH:2]Castro has "successfully" transformed Cuba into a third world nation. His "educational" 
and "social" programs have led to lawyers and doctors working as waiters and cab drivers in order to 
get some tourist tips. Pre-teen girls resort to prostitution and those lucky enough to have family abroad, 
can "resolver" (make due) better than those who don't. Hotels, beaches and hospitals, but the native 
Cuban would be arrested for even voicing the wish to have rights to these locations. However, there is 
hope among the traumatized, brain-washed population; The National Lottery - and the prize.....a one-way 
ticket to MIAMI.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CUBA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Cuba</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CUBA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Cuba</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CUBA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Cuban</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CUBA_CASTRO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Fidel Castro[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Egomaniacal Dictator of Cuba[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Fidel Alejandro 
Castro Ruz (born August 13, 1926)[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Castro 
led the revolution overthrowing Fulgencio Batista in 1959. Shortly thereafter, Castro was sworn in as 
the Prime Minister of Cuba. Castro became First Secretary of the Communist Party of Cuba in 1965, and 
led the transformation of Cuba into a one-party socialist republic. In 1976 he became "president" of 
the Council of State as well as of the Council of Ministers. He also holds the supreme military rank 
of Comandante en Jefe ("Commander in Chief") of the Cuban armed forces. Since his assumption of power 
in 1959, he has evoked both praise and condemnation (at home and internationally). Opponents characterize 
Castro as a dictator, claiming that he has not risen to power through open, public elections, and some 
contend that his rule is illegitimate because the socialist system itself was not established through 
what they considered to be legal means. Supporters, on the other hand, see Castro as a charismatic leader 
whose "presidential authority" (AKA: dictatorial tyranny) has been acquired through legitimate elections. 
At home, Fidel Castro has overseen the implementation of various economic policies, leading to the rapid 
centralization of Cuba's economy, land reform, collectivization and mechanization of agriculture, and 
the expropriation of leading Cuban industries. These changes have had disastrous consequences and transformed 
Cuba into a third-world nation.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CUBA_MARTI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Jose Marti[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Intellectual, Poet and Martyr[\BOLD][NEWLINE]José Julián 
Martí Pérez (born: 28 January, 1853 died: 19 May 1895)[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2][TAB]Jose 
Marti was a leader of the Cuban independence movement from Spain and as well a renowned poet and writer. 
He is considered the national hero of Cuba and often referred to as the "Apostle of Cuban Independence".[PARAGRAPH:2]In 
1869, at the age of 16, he published his first political writings in the only edition of the newspaper 
El Diablo Cojuelo. That same year, he published "Abdala," a patriotic drama in verse form in the one-volume 
La Patria Libre.  Despite this success, in March of that year, colonial authorities shut down the school, 
interrupting Martí's studies. He came to resent Spanish rule of his homeland at a young age; likewise, 
he developed a hatred of slavery, which was still practiced in Cuba. On 21 October 1869, he was arrested, 
then incarcerated in the national jail following an accusation of treason from the Spanish government. 
More than four months later, Martí assumed responsibility of the charges and was condemned to six years 
in prison, although he was a 16 year old minor. Eventually Martí fell ill; his legs were severely lacerated 
due to the chains attached to him. Therefore, he was transferred to another part of Cuba known as Isla 
de Pinos instead of further imprisonment. Following that, they decided to repatriate him to Spain.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 
Spain, he studied law and wrote articles on the wrongs of Spanish rule in Cuba, including "El presidio 
político en Cuba" in 1871. Martí completed his studies, graduated with a bachelor of arts, and obtained 
his license in civil rights. He then traveled to France, where he spent some time before secretly returning 
to Cuba under an assumed name in 1877. He was unable to obtain any employment until he accepted a job 
as a professor of history and literature in Guatemala City. In 1878, he returned to Havana and found 
work there. His son, Jose Francisco was born there. However, the next year, he was arrested and deported 
to Spain again. His wife and son remained in Cuba. In 1880, Martí moved to New York City serving as a 
joint consul there for Uruguay, Paraguay, and Argentina. He mobilized the Cuban exile community, especially 
in Ybor City (Tampa area) and Key West, Florida, to revolution and independence from Spain, while lobbying 
to oppose U.S. annexation of Cuba, which some American politicians desired. In January 1892, he founded 
the Partido Revolucionario Cubano, the Cuban Revolutionary Party, with the purpose of gaining independence 
for both Cuba and Puerto Rico.[PARAGRAPH:2]On March 25, 1895, José Marti published the Manifesto of Montecristi 
together with Máximo Gómez, proclaiming Cuban independence, an end to all legal distinctions between 
the races, friendship with Spaniards who did not oppose the independence, and war with all who stood 
in the way of independence. On April 11, 1895, Martí landed in Cuba with a small force of rebel exiles, 
including the Generalísimo Máximo Gómez y Báez. Upon reuniting with the Ejercito Libertador (army of 
liberators), Martí was given the grade of Major General. José Martí was killed in battle with Spanish 
troops at the Battle of Dos Ríos on May 19, 1895. Gómez had recognized that the Spaniards had a strong 
position between palm trees, so he ordered to disengage. Martí was alone and seeing a young courier ride 
by, he said: "Joven, a la carga" meaning: "Young man, let's charge!" This was around midday, and he was, 
as always, dressed in a black jacket, riding a white horse, which made him an easy target for the Spanish. 
The young trooper, Angel de la Guardia,lost his horse and returned to report the loss. The Spanish took 
possession of the body, buried it close by, then exhumed the body upon realization of it's identity. 
They are said not to have burned him because they were scared that the ashes would get into their throats 
and asphyxiate them. Jose Marti is buried in Cementerio Santa Efigenia in Santiago de Cuba. Many have 
argued that Maceo and others had always spurned Martí for never participating in combat, which may have 
compelled Martí to that ill-fated suicidal two-man charge. Some of his "Versos sencillos" bore premonition: 
"Que no me entierren en lo oscuro, A morir como un traidor... Yo soy bueno y como bueno, Moriré de cara 
al sol." ("May they not bury me in darkness, to die like a traitor... I am good, and as a good man, I 
will die facing the sun.")</English>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- DIPLOMACY TEXT -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CASTRO_1</Tag>
		<English>What a surprise...I'm [OUR_NAME] of the powerful nation of Cuba, bend to my wishes or suffer the consequences.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_CASTRO_1</Tag>
		<English>No me jodas!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_CASTRO_1</Tag>
		<English>NO PEACE!!!...AAARGHAAHHH!!!!...I will destroy you with my trained flocks of infested pigeons!...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_CASTRO_1</Tag>
		<English>Tell me what you want [CT_NAME], what you really, really want?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_CASTRO_1</Tag>
		<English>MARIC....HIJO DE PUT...!, METETE EL DEDO POR EL CUL....!!!!!!!!!!.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_CASTRO_1</Tag>
		<English>I know that I am a filthy excuse for a human being [CT_NAME], but will you still let me take advantage of you?.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_CASTRO_1</Tag>
		<English>Give me what I want...because I say so!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_CASTRO_1</Tag>
		<English>Hand it over...Hand it over or we, with the blessings of my BABALAO, will crush you.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
