<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DIDO_1</Tag>
		<English>I greet you on behalf of the [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Pray that I do not grow to curse your progeny.</English>
		<French>Je vous salue au nom de [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Priez pour que je n'ai jamais à maudir votre progéniture.</French>
		<German>Du stehst vor dem großen [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Bete, dass ich mich nicht dazu entscheide, Deine Nachkommen zu verfluchen.</German>
		<Italian>Ti saluto a nome dell'impero [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Prega che io non arrivi a maledire la tua progenie.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Te recibo en nombre del [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Rezad por que jamás me vuelva para maldecir a vuestra descendencia.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Witamw imieniu [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Módl się, abym nie dorosła by przekląć Twoich następców.</Polish>
		<Russian>Приветствую вас, [CT_NAME], от имени [OUR_EMPIRE]. Молитесь, чтобы не выросло мое могущество, дабы вас не прокляли ваши потомки.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DIDO</Tag>
		<English>Dido</English>
		<French>Didon</French>
		<Russian>Äèäîíà</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DIDO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Dido[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Queen of Carthage[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates:[\BOLD] c. 790 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Dido, or Elisha/Elissa, was a Phoenician Queen, founder of Carthage. First-born from King of Tyre, her succession was disputed by her younger brother, Pumayyaton/Pygmalion, who murdered her husband and imposed his rule. At this point she left Tyre with a large following, starting a long voyage; main stages were Cyprus and, possibly, Malta. Landing on Libyan coasts, about 814 BC, she chose a place to found a new capital city for her Phoenician followers: Carthage. She peacefully obtained the land by an ingenious agreement with the local lord, today known as the "Theorem of Dido". During her widowhood, she was consistently sought in marriage by local kings; but if we accept Silius Italicus, she married again, probably with a Tyrian follower, from the Barca family.[PARAGRAPH:1]Dido promoted a significant religious reform and after a long and prosperous reign, she favored the formation of a Republic. After her death, she was deified by her people with the name of Tanit and assimilated to the Great Goddess Astarte.[PARAGRAPH:1]The cult of Tanit survived Carthage's destruction by the Romans; it was introduced to Rome itself by Emperor Septimius Severus, himself born in North Africa. It was extinguished completely with the Theodosian decrees of the late 4th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]Carthage was the Roman Republic's greatest rival and enemy, and Virgil's Dido in part symbolises this. Even though no Rome existed in her day, Virgil's Dido curses the future progeny of the Trojans. In Italy under the Fascist regime, her figure was demonized, perhaps not only as an anti-Roman figure but because she represented together at least three other unpleasant qualities: feminine virtue, Semitic ethnic origin, and African civilization. As an innocuous example: when Mussolini's regime named the streets of new quarters in Rome with the characters of Virgil's Aeneid, only the name Dido did not appear.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Dido[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Królowa Kartaginy[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Daty:[\BOLD] ok. 790 p.n.e.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Dydona (również Elissa; łac. Dido, poetycki przydomek Didona nadał jej Wergiliusz) - według Eneidy Wergiliusza legendarna założycielka Kartaginy i jej pierwsza królowa. Według innej legendy spisanej przez historyka sycylijskiego, Greka Timajosa, w IX w. p.n.e. oraz rzymskiego autora Pompejusza Trogusa, z dalekiego Tyru zbiegła garstka jego mieszkańców na północne wybrzeża Afryki, niedaleko fenickiej kolonii, Utyki. Przywódczynią kolonistów była Dydona (zwana też Eliszą, Elissą), która uciekła, ponieważ brat Pigmalion zabił jej męża Acharbasa. W jej otoczeniu znajdowali się bogaci Fenicjanie (nie jest wyjaśnione dlaczego, prawdopodobnie to oni uciekali), w drodze zatrzymali się na Cyprze, skąd zabrano arcykapłana i dużą grupę dziewcząt. Gdy wysiedli na ląd, otoczyli ich Numidyjczycy (autochtoni) i zaczęły się pertraktacje. Ostatecznie Dydonie użyczono takiego skrawka ziemi na wybrzeżu, jaki obejmie skóra wołu. Dydona pocięła ją na wąskie paski i objęła nimi miejsce, na którym wzniesiono Byrsę (łac. "skóra"), akropol Kartaginy. Imię Elissy zostało zmienione przez tubylców na Dydona, co oznacza wędrowniczka. Używane poprzednio imię pochodzi od fenickiego bóstwa El - być może więc Elissa była w Fenicji jego kapłanką. Gdy założone przez nią miasto rozkwitło, chciwy jej bogactw Jarbas (Iarbas, Hiarbas) poprosił o jej rękę, grożąc w razie odmowy wojną. Aby uniknąć małżeństwa z barbarzyńskim królem i pozostać wierną zamordowanemu mężowi, Dydona wstąpiła na zapalony stos i przebiła się sztyletem.</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Дидона[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Царица Карфагена[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни: [\BOLD] ок. 790 г. до н.э.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Дидона, или Елисей/Элисса, была финикийской царицей, основательницей Карфагена. Ее права на трон, как первенца князя Тира, оспаривались ее младшим братом Пумайятоном/Пигмалионом, который убил ее мужа и узурпировал власть. В этот момент она покинула Тир с большим количеством последователей, начав долгое путешествие; основными этапами были Кипр и, возможно, Мальта. Высадившись на побережье Ливии около 814 г. до н.э., она выбрала место, чтобы основать новую столицу для своих финикийских последователей, город Карт-Хадашт. Она мирно получила землю по гениальному соглашению с местным вождем, известному сегодня как «Теорема Дидоны». Во время ее вдовства местные царьки постоянно искали ее руки и сердца; но если мы примем свидетельства Силия Италика, она повторно вышла замуж, вероятно, за тирского последователя из семьи Барка.[PARAGRAPH:1]Дидона провела значительную религиозную реформу и после долгого и процветающего правления выступила за создание республики. После смерти она была обожествлена ??своим народом под именем Танит и позже была отождествлена с Великой Богиней Ашторет (Астартой).[PARAGRAPH:1]Культ Танит пережил разрушение Карфагена римлянами; в сам Рим его ввел император Септимий Север, сам родившийся в Северной Африке. Он был полностью уничтожен указами Феодосия в конце IV века.[PARAGRAPH:1]Карфаген был величайшим соперником и врагом Римской республики, и Дидона Вергилия отчасти символизирует это. Несмотря на то, что в ее дни не существовало Рима, Дидона Вергилия проклинает будущее потомство троянцев. В Италии при фашистском режиме ее фигура демонизировалась, возможно, не только как антиримская фигура, но и потому, что она представляла вместе по крайней мере три других неприятных качества: женскую добродетель, семитское этническое происхождение и африканскую цивилизацию. В качестве безобидного примера: когда режим Муссолини назвал улицы новых кварталов в Риме персонажами «Энеиды» Вергилия, только имя Дидоны отсутствовало среди них.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>