<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SEJONG_1</Tag>
		<English>I am honored to meet you. We will be watching you closely, [CT_NAME]. It is often darkest underneath the lampstand.</English>
		<French>Je suis honoré de vous rencontrer. Nous allons vous surveiller de près, [CT_NAME]. Il fait souvent plus sombre sous le chandelier.</French>
		<German>Ich fühle mich geehrt, Dir zu begegnen. Wir werden Dich genau beobachten, [CT_NAME]. Unter dem Ständer der Leuchte ist es oft am dunkelsten.</German>
		<Spanish>Es un honor conocerte. Te estaremos observando de cerca, [CT_NAME]. Normalmente lo más oscuro está debajo de la lámpara.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jestem zaszczycony, że Cię spotkałem. Będziemy uważnie Cię obserwować, [CT_NAME]. Często najciemniej jest pod latarnią.</Polish>
		<Russian>Для меня большая честь встретиться с вами. Мы будем внимательно наблюдать за вами, [CT_NAME]. Нередко самое темное бывает именно под светильником.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SEJONG</Tag>
		<English>Sejong</English>
		<Russian>Ñå÷æîí</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SEJONG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Sejong the Great[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Fourth ruler of the Joseon Dynasty[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1397 - 1450[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Sejong the Great, born Yi Do, was the fourth ruler of the Joseon Dynasty of Korea from 1418 to 1450. He was also a skilled linguist who apparently personally created the native Korean alphabet Hangul. Although there are circumstantial clues he may have been assisted by family members, most believe that he was the one who actually invented the alphabet, mainly due to the resistance he faced from the intellectuals of the day.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejong is also credited with the invention of a rain gauge, striking water clocks, and a sundial.[PARAGRAPH:1]Following the principles of Neo-Confucianism, Sejong was also a humanitarian who proclaimed that there must be three trials before a final judgment is reached, and he prohibited brutality in the punishment of criminals, such as flogging.[PARAGRAPH:1]He was an effective military planner. During his era, his army invaded Tsushima to reduce and eliminate heavy Japanese pirate activities along the southern coast line. On the northern border, he established 4 forts and 6 posts to safeguard his people from the hostile nomads living in Manchuria. He also created various military regulations and units to strengthen the safety of his kingdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejong is one of only two Korean rulers honored with the appellation "the Great," the other being Gwanggaeto the Great of Goguryeo.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejong was the third son of King Taejong. When he was ten, he became Grand Prince Chungnyeong and married a daughter of Sim On of Cheongsong, commonly known as Sim-ssi, who later was given the title Princess-Consort Soheon.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejong established the Hall of Worthies (Jiphyeonjeon) in 1420 in the royal palace, Sejong gathered intellectuals from around Korea. The scholars of the Hall of Worthies documented history, drafted documents and compiled books on various topics. Sejong's writings are also a highly regarded. He composed the famous Yongbi Eocheon Ga ("Songs of Flying Dragons", 1445), Seokbo Sangjeol ("Episodes from the Life of Buddha", July 1447), Worin Cheon-gang Jigok ("Songs of the Moon Shining on a Thousand Rivers", July 1447), and the reference Dongguk Jeong-un ("Dictionary of Proper Sino-Korean Pronunciation", September 1447). Sejong died at the age of 52 and was buried at the Yeong Mausoleum. His successor was his first son, Munjong.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejongno (a street) and the Sejong Center for the Performing Arts both located in central Seoul are named after King Sejong, and he is depicted on the South Korean 10,000 Won note.</English>
		<French>[H1]Sejong le Grand[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Quatrième souverain de la dynastie Joseon[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivait:[\BOLD] 1397 - 1450[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Contexte:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Sejong le Grand, né Yi Do, était le quatrième souverain de la dynastie Joseon de Corée de 1418 à 1450. Il était également un linguiste qualifié qui a apparemment créé personnellement l'alphabet coréen natif Hangul. Bien qu'il y ait des indices circonstanciels, il peut avoir été aidé par des membres de sa famille, la plupart pensent que c'est lui qui a réellement inventé l'alphabet, principalement en raison de la résistance qu'il a rencontrée de la part des intellectuels de l'époque.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejong est également crédité avec l'invention d'un pluviomètre, des horloges à eau frappantes et d'un cadran solaire.[PARAGRAPH:1]Suivant les principes du néo-confucianisme, Sejong était également un humanitaire qui a proclamé qu'il devait y avoir trois procès avant qu'un jugement définitif ne soit rendu, et il a interdit la brutalité dans la punition des criminels, comme la flagellation.[PARAGRAPH:1]Il était un planificateur militaire efficace. À son époque, son armée a envahi Tsushima pour réduire et éliminer les activités de pirates japonais lourds le long de la côte sud. À la frontière nord, il a établi 4 forts et 6 postes pour protéger son peuple des nomades hostiles vivant en Mandchourie. Il a également créé divers règlements et unités militaires pour renforcer la sécurité de son royaume.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejong est l'un des deux seuls dirigeants coréens honorés de l'appellation "le Grand", l'autre étant Gwanggaeto le Grand de Goguryeo.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejong était le troisième fils du roi Taejong. À l'âge de dix ans, il devint grand prince Chungnyeong et épousa une fille de Sim On de Cheongsong, communément appelé Sim-ssi, qui reçut plus tard le titre de princesse-consort Soheon.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejong fonda le Hall of Worthies ( Jiphyeonjeon) en 1420 au palais royal, Sejong a rassemblé des intellectuels de toute la Corée. Les érudits du Hall of Worthies ont documenté l'histoire, rédigé des documents et compilé des livres sur divers sujets. Les écrits de Sejong sont également très appréciés. Il a composé le célèbre Yongbi Eocheon Ga ("Chants de dragons volants", 1445), Seokbo Sangjeol ("Épisodes de la vie de Bouddha", juillet 1447), Worin Cheon-gang Jigok ("Chants de la lune qui brille sur mille rivières" ", Juillet 1447), et la référence Dongguk Jeong-un (" Dictionnaire de prononciation sino-coréenne ", septembre 1447). Sejong est décédé à l'âge de 52 ans et a été enterré au mausolée de Yeong. Son successeur était son premier fils, Munjong.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sejongno (une rue) et le Sejong Center for the Performing Arts, tous deux situés dans le centre de Séoul, portent le nom du roi Sejong, et il est représenté sur la note sud-coréenne de 10 000 won.</French>
		<Polish>[H1]Sejong Wielki[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Czwarty władca Dynastii Joseon[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 1397 - 1450</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Сечжон Великий[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Четвертый правитель династии Чосон[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни:[\BOLD] 1397 - 1450 гг.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Сечжон, также Седжон-тэван, носивший родовое имя Ли До был четвертым правителем корейской династии Чосон с 1418 по 1450 год. Он также был опытным лингвистом, который, очевидно, лично создал корейский алфавит хангыль. Хотя есть косвенные подсказки, что ему, возможно, помогали члены семьи, большинство считает, что именно он изобрел алфавит, главным образом из-за сопротивления, с которым он столкнулся со стороны интеллектуалов того времени.[PARAGRAPH:1]Сечжону также приписывают изобретение дождемера, водяных и солнечных часов.[PARAGRAPH:1]Следуя принципам неоконфуцианства, Сечжон был также гуманистом, постановив, что при судебных делах должно быть проведено три испытания, прежде чем будет принято окончательное решение, и он запретил излишнюю жестокость при наказании преступников, включая пытки и телесные наказания. [PARAGRAPH:1]Он был эффективным военным стратегом и полководцем. В его эпоху его армия вторглась на Цусиму с целью ликвидации разорительных набегов японских пиратов вдоль южной береговой линии. На северной границе он установил 4 крупные крепости и 6 аванпостов для защиты своего народа от враждебных кочевников, проживавших в Маньчжурии. Он также создал различные артикулы и реорганизовал войска, чтобы укрепить безопасность своего царства.[PARAGRAPH:1]Сечжон - один из двух корейских правителей, удостоенных звания «Великий», другим был Квангэтхо Тамдок (391-412 гг.) из династии Когуре.[PARAGRAPH:1]Сечжон был третьим сыном короля Тхэджона. Когда ему было десять лет, он стал наследником принца Чхуннен, третьего сына монарха, и женился на дочери Чонджу Ли, широко известной как Сохен-ванху, которой позже дали титул принцесса-консорт Сохеон.[PARAGRAPH:1]В 1420 году Сечжон учредил придворную академию Чипхенджон («Зал достойных»), учёные которой разработали слоговой алфавит хангыль, являющийся в настоящее время основой корейской письменности. Ученые из Чипхенджон документировали историю, составляли проекты документов и составляли книги на различные темы. Работы Сечжона также высоко ценятся. Он сочинил знаменитого Йонгби Еченга («Песни летающих драконов», 1445), Сэкбо Сангчжоль («Эпизоды из жизни Будды», июль 1447), Орин Чхонганг Чжидок («Песня Луны, сияющей в тысячи рек»). », Июль 1447 г.), и Дунгук чжон-ун («Словарь правильного китайско-корейского произношения», сентябрь 1447 г.). Сечжон умер в возрасте 52 лет и был похоронен в мавзолее Йонг. Его преемником стал его первый сын Мунджон.[PARAGRAPH:1]Седжонно (улица) и Центр прикладных видов искусства Сечжона, расположенные в центральной части Сеула, названы в честь короля Сечжона, также он изображен на южнокорейской купюре в 10 000 вон.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>