<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_CHARLES_V_1</Tag>
		<English>It would be diplomatically expedient to give us what we want, [CT_NAME]?</English>
		<French>Il serait diplomatiquement opportun de nous donner ce que nous voulons, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Es wäre in diplomatischer Hinsicht durchaus angebracht, unsere Forderung zu erfüllen, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Sarebbe diplomaticamente vantaggioso darci ciò che vogliamo, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿No sería más oportuno, diplomáticamente hablando, que nos dierais lo que queremos, [CT_NAME]?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dyplomatycznie byłoby zaakceptowanie naszych rządań, [CT_NAME]?</Polish>
		<Russian>Áûëî áû äèïëîìàòè÷íûì ïåðåäàòü íàì òî, ÷òî ìû çàõîòèì, [CT_NAME]?</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_CHARLES_V_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace is the biggest struggle, time to pay up, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Il est temps de payer l'ardoise, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Zeit, die Zeche zu zahlen, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>La pace è l'obiettivo più difficile, è tempo di pagare di pagare il conto, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es hora de pagar a quienes tienen la sartén por el mango, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pokój to największa udręka, czas w końcu ponieść karę, [CT_NAME].</Polish>
		<Russian>Ìèð åñòü íàèáîëüøàÿ áîðüáà, èáî ïðèøëî âðåìÿ çàïëàòèòü, [CT_NAME].</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_CHARLES_V_1</Tag>
		<English>Can you spare us this, [CT_NAME]? I would be extremely grateful for your assistance.</English>
		<French>Pouvez-vous nous donner ceci, [CT_NAME]? Je vous serais extrêmement reconnaissant de votre aide.</French>
		<German>Könnt Ihr das hier erübrigen, [CT_NAME]? Ich wäre Euch wirklich außerordentlich verbunden.</German>
		<Italian>Puoi darci ciò che chiediamo, [CT_NAME]? Sarei molto riconoscente per la tua assistenza.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Podrías darnos esto, [CT_NAME]? Os estaríamos tremendamente agradecidos por vuestra ayuda.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Czy mógłbyś wysłać nam to, [CT_NAME]? Byłbym bardzo wdzięczny za Twoją pomoc.</Polish>
		<Russian>Íå áóäåòå ëè âû ëþáåçíû óäåëèòü ìíå ýòî, [CT_NAME]? ß áûë áû ÷ðåçâû÷àéíî ïðèçíàòåëåí Âàì çà ýòó ïîìîùü.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHARLES_V_1</Tag>
		<English>I am honored to meet you, [CT_NAME]. I hope that our two nations will be able to live in peace and friendship.</English>
		<French>Je suis honoré de vous rencontrer, [CT_NAME]. J'espère que nos deux nations seront capables de vivre dans la paix et l'amitié.</French>
		<German>Es ist mir eine Ehre, [CT_NAME]. Ich hoffe, es wird Friede und Freundschaft zwischen unseren Völkern herrschen.</German>
		<Italian>È un onore incontrarti, [CT_NAME]. Spero che le nostre due nazioni riusciranno a vivere in pace e amicizia.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es un honor conoceros, [CT_NAME]. Espero que nuestras dos naciones sean capaces de vivir en paz y armonía.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jestem zaszczycony, źe Cię spotkałem, [CT_NAME]. Mam nadzieję, źe nasze narody będą mogły źyć razem w pokoju i przyjazni.</Polish>
		<Russian>ß ïîëüùåí ÷åñòüþ âèäåòü Âàñ, [CT_NAME]. ß íàäåþñü, ÷òî íàøè íàðîäû ñìîãóò áëàãîïîëó÷íî æèòü â ìèðå è äðóæáå.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_CHARLES_V_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, [CT_NAME]. I can always spare a few moments to converse with friends and allies.</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, [CT_NAME]. Je suis toujours disponible pour discuter avec mes amis et alliés.</French>
		<German>Willkommen, [CT_NAME]. Für Freunde und Verbündete habe ich doch immer ein paar Minuten Zeit.</German>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, [CT_NAME]. Ho sempre un momento da dedicare ad amici e alleati.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Siempre tengo un momento libre para charlar con amigos y aliados como vos.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Witam, [CT_NAME]. Zawsze znajdę chwilę czasu by porozmawiać z przyjacielem i sojusznikiem.</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïðèâåòñòâóþ, [CT_NAME]. Ó ìåíÿ âñåãäà åñòü íåñêîëüêî ñâîáîäíûõ ìèíóò ïåðåãîâîðèòü ñ äðóçüÿìè è ñîþçíèêàìè.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_CHARLES_V_1</Tag>
		<English>I'm listening.</English>
		<French>Je vous écoute.</French>
		<German>Ich höre!</German>
		<Italian>Sto ascoltando.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Os escuchamos.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Słucham.</Polish>
		<Russian>ß ñëóøàþ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_CHARLES_V_1</Tag>
		<English>Certainly not. The war will continue until I decide it is time to resume peace, or you are conquered!</English>
		<French>Certainement pas. La guerre continuera jusqu'à la victoire totale.</French>
		<German>Auf keinen Fall! Der Krieg wird so lange fortgeführt, bis wir den vollständigen Sieg erzielt haben!</German>
		<Italian>Certo che no. La guerra continuerà fino a quando io non deciderò di fare pace o tu sarai sconfitto totalmente!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Por supuesto que no. La guerra seguirá hasta que hayamos logrado la victoria total.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Napewno nie. Wojna będzie trwać do czasu zanim JA zdecyduję, źe czas na pokój, lub do czasu całkowitego podboju Twojego kraju.</Polish>
		<Russian>Êîíå÷íî íåò. Âîéíà áóäåò ïðîäîëæàòüñÿ ïîêà ÿ íå ðåøó âîçîáíîâèòü ìèðíûå ïåðåãîâîðû, ëèáî êîãäà âàøà ñòðàíà ìíå ïîêîðèòñÿ!</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_CHARLES_V_1</Tag>
		<English>No! Forget it! I have more important matters to tend to.</English>
		<French>Non!</French>
		<German>Nein!</German>
		<Italian>No! Scordatelo! Ho cose più importanti da fare.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No!</Spanish>
		<Polish>Nie! Zapomnij o tym! Mam waźniejsze sprawy do załatwienia.</Polish>
		<Russian>Íåò! Çàáóäü ýòî! ß ïðåäïî÷èòàþ îáñóæäàòü êäà áîëåå âàæíûå âåùè.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHARLES_V</Tag>
		<English>Charles V</English>
		<French>Charles Quint</French>
		<German>Karl V.</German>
		<Italian>Carlo V</Italian>
		<Spanish>Carlos I</Spanish>
		<Polish>Karol V</Polish>
		<Russian>Êàðë V</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHARLES_V_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Charles V[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Holy Roman Emperor, King of Spain[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1500 - 1558[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Charles V was Holy Roman Emperor from 1519 to his abdication in 1556. He was also King of Aragon and Castile as Charles I. As the heir of four of Europe's leading royal houses, he united in personal union extensive realms including the Holy Roman Empire, Spain, Naples, Sicily, the Burgundian Netherlands, and Spanish colonies in America. Upon his retirement, he divided his realms between his son Philip and his brother Ferdinand. Contents[PARAGRAPH:1]He was the son of Philip of Burgundy and Joanna the Mad of Castile. His paternal grandparents were Emperor Maximilian I and Mary of Burgundy, whose daughter Margarete of Austria raised him. His maternal grandparents were Ferdinand II of Aragon and Isabella I of Castile, whose marriage had first united their territories into what is now modern Spain, and whose daughter Catherine of Aragon was Queen of England and first wife of Henry VIII. His cousin was Mary I of England who married his son Philip.[PARAGRAPH:1]Combining the heritage of the German Habsburgs, the House of Burgundy, and the Spanish heritage of his mother, Charles transcended ethnic and national boundaries. His motto was Plus Ultra, Further Beyond.[PARAGRAPH:1]Charles was born in the Flemish city of Ghent in 1500. The culture and courtly life of the Burgundian Low Countries were an important influence in his early life. He spoke five different languages: Flemish, German, Spanish, French, and Italian. He spoke French as mother language and Flemish from his childhood years, later adding an acceptable Spanish (which was required by the Castilian Cortes as a condition for becoming king of Castile) and some German. Indeed, he claimed to speak "Spanish to God, Italian to women, French to men, and German to my horse."[PARAGRAPH:1]From his Burgundian ancestors, he inherited an ambiguous relationship with the Kings of France. Charles shared with France his mother tongue (together with Flemish) and many cultural forms. In his youth, he made frequent visits to Paris, then the largest city of Western Europe.[PARAGRAPH:1]In his words: "Paris is not a city, but a universe" (Lutetia non urbs, sed orbis). But Charles also inherited the tradition of political and dynastical enmity between the Royal and the Burgundian lines of the Valois Dynasty. This conflict was amplified by his accession to both the Holy Roman Empire and the kingdom of Spain.[PARAGRAPH:1]Though Spain was the core of his kingdom, he was never totally assimilated and especially in his earlier years felt like and was viewed as a foreign prince. He could not speak Spanish very well, as it was not his primary language. Nonetheless, he spent most of his life in Spain, including his final years in a Spanish monastery.[PARAGRAPH:1]In his youth, Charles was tutored by Adrian of Utrecht, later Pope Adrian VI. His three most prominent subsequent advisors were Lord Chièvres, Jean Sauvage and Mercurino Gattinara.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1506, Charles inherited his father's Burgundian territories, most notably the Low Countries and Franche-Comté, most of which were fiefs of the German empire, except his birthplace Flanders that was -on paper- still a French fief, a last remnant of what had been a powerful player in the hundred years war. As he was a minor, his aunt Margaret acted as regent until 1515 and soon she found herself in war with the regent of the king of France over the question whether Charles would have to do homage to the French king for Flanders as his father had done. The outcome was that France relinquished its ancient but empty claim on Flanders in 1528.[PARAGRAPH:1]Charles extended the Burgundian territory with the annexation of Tournai, Artois, Utrecht, Groningen and Guelders. The Seventeen Provinces had been unified by Charles' Burgundian ancestors, but nominally were fiefs of either France or the Holy Roman Empire. In 1549, Charles issued a Pragmatic Sanction, declaring the Low Countries to be a unified entity of which his family would be the heirs.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Low Countries held an important place in the Empire. For Charles V personally, they were the region where he spent his childhood. Because of trade and industry and the rich cities, they were also important for the treasury.[PARAGRAPH:1]With the death of his grandfather Ferdinand II on May 30, 1516, Charles inherited his grandfather's realm, which included Aragon, Naples, Sicily and Sardinia. He also became joint ruler of Castile with, and guardian of, his insane mother Joanna. With the Castilian crown he also gained Navarre, Granada, and the Spanish possessions in the New World.[PARAGRAPH:1]For the first time the crowns of Castile and Aragon were united in one person. Ferdinand and Isabella had each been sovereign in one kingdom, but only consort in the other.[PARAGRAPH:1]Charles arrived in his new kingdoms in autumn of 1517. His regent Jiménez de Cisneros came to meet him, but fell ill along the way, not without a suspicion of poison, and died before meeting the King.[PARAGRAPH:1]Negotiations with the Castilian Cortes proved difficult, and in the end Charles was accepted under the following conditions: he would learn to speak Castilian; he would not appoint foreigners; he was prohibited from taking precious metals from Castile; and he would respect the rights of his mother, Queen Joanna. The Cortes paid homage to him in Valladolid in 1518. In 1519, he was crowned before the Cortes of Aragon in Zaragoza, and the Corts of Catalonia followed.[PARAGRAPH:1]Charles was accepted as sovereign, even though the Spanish felt uneasy with the Imperial style. Spanish monarchs until then had been bound by the laws; the monarchy was a contract with the people. With Charles it would become more absolute, even though until his mother's death in 1555 Charles did not hold the full kingship of the country.[PARAGRAPH:1]Soon resistance against the Emperor rose, because of the heavy taxation (funds that were used to fight wars abroad, wars most Castilians had no interest in) and because Charles tended to select Flemings for high offices in Spain and America, ignoring Castilian candidates. The resistance culminated in the Castilian War of the Communities, which was suppressed by Charles. After this, Castile became integrated into the Habsburg empire, and would provide the bulk of the empire's military and financial resources.[PARAGRAPH:1]During Charles' reign, the territories in New Spain were considerably extended by conquistadores like Hernán Cortés and Francisco Pizarro, who caused the Aztec and Inca empires to fall in little more than a decade. Combined with the Magellan expedition's circumnavigation of the globe in 1522, these successes convinced Charles of his divine mission to become the leader of a Christian world that still perceived a significant threat from Islam. Of course, the conquests also helped solidify Charles' rule by providing the state treasury with enormous amounts of bullion. As the conquistador Bernal Diaz observed: "We came to serve God and our Majesty, and also to get rich." In 1550, Charles convened a conference at Valladolid in order to consider the morality of the force used against the indigenous populations of Spanish America.[PARAGRAPH:1]After the death of his paternal grandfather, Maximilian, in 1519, he inherited the Habsburg lands in Austria. He was also the natural candidate to succeed of the electors, but with the help of the wealthy Fugger family Charles could oust Francis and was elected on June 28, 1519. In 1530, he was crowned Holy Roman Emperor by Pope Clement VII in Bologna, the last Emperor to receive a papal coronation.[PARAGRAPH:1]Charles was Holy Roman Emperor over the German states, but his real power was limited by the princes. Protestantism gained a lot of support in Germany, and Charles was determined not to let this happen in the Netherlands. An inquisition was established as early as 1522. In 1550, the death penalty was introduced for all heresy. Political dissent was also firmly controlled, most notably in his place of birth, where Charles personally suppressed the Revolt of Ghent in 1539.[PARAGRAPH:1]Much of Charles's reign was taken up by conflicts with France, which found itself encircled by Charles's empire and still maintained ambitions in Italy. The first war with Charles's great nemesis Francis I of France began in 1521. Charles allied with England and Pope Leo X against the French and the Venetians, and was highly successful, driving the French out of Milan and defeating and capturing Francis at the Battle of Pavia in 1525. To gain his freedom, the French king was forced to cede Burgundy to Charles in the humiliating Treaty of Madrid (1526).[PARAGRAPH:1]When he was released, however, Francis had the Parlement of Paris denounce the treaty because it had been signed under duress. France then joined the League of Cognac that the Pope had formed with Henry VIII of England, the Venetians, the Florentines, and the Milanese to resist imperial domination of Italy. In the ensuing war, Charles's sack of Rome (1527) and virtual imprisonment of Pope Clement VII in 1527 prevented him from annulling the marriage of Henry VIII of England and Charles's aunt Catherine of Aragon, with important consequences. In other respects, the war was inconclusive. In the Treaty of Cambrai (1529), called the "Ladies' Peace" because it was negotiated between Charles's aunt and Francis's mother, Francis renounced his claims in Italy but retained control of Burgundy.[PARAGRAPH:1]A third war erupted in 1535, when, following the death of the last Sforza Duke of Milan, Charles installed his own son, Philip, in the duchy, despite Francis's claims on it. This war too was inconclusive. Francis failed to conquer Milan, but succeeded in conquering most of the lands of Charles's ally the Duke of Savoy, including his capital, Turin. A truce at Nice in 1538 on the basis of uti possidetis ended the war, but lasted only a short time. War resumed in 1542, with Francis now allied with Ottoman Sultan Suleiman I and Charles once again allied with Henry VIII. Despite the conquest of Nice by a Franco-Ottoman fleet, the French remained unable to advance into Milan, while a joint Anglo-Imperial invasion of northern France, led by Charles himself, won some successes but was ultimately abandoned, leading to another peace and restoration of the status quo ante in 1544.[PARAGRAPH:1]A final war erupted with Francis's son and successor, Henry II, in 1551. This war saw early successes by Henry in Lorraine, where he captured Metz, but continued failure of French offensives in Italy. Charles abdicated midway through this conflict, leaving further conduct of the war to his son, Philip II and his brother, Ferdinand I, Holy Roman Emperor.[PARAGRAPH:1]Charles fought continually with the Ottoman Empire and its sultan, Suleiman the Magnificent. The expeditions of the Ottoman force along the Mediterranean coast posed a threat to Habsburg lands and Christian monopolies on trade in the Mediterranean. In Central Europe, the Turkish advance was halted at Vienna in 1529. In 1535 Charles won an important victory at Tunis, but in 1536 Francis I of France allied himself with Suleiman against Charles. While Francis was persuaded to sign a peace treaty in 1538, he again allied himself with the Ottomans in 1542. In 1543 Charles allied himself with Henry VIII and forced Francis to sign the Truce of Crepy-en-Laonnois. Charles later signed a humiliating treaty with the Ottomans, to gain him some respite from the huge expenses of their war, although it wasn't over. However, the Protestant powers in the Holy Roman Empire Diet often voted against money for his Turkish wars, as many Protestants saw the Muslim advance as a counterweight to the Catholic powers. The great Hungarian defeat at the 1526 Battle of Mohács "sent a wave of terror over Europe".[PARAGRAPH:1]As Holy Roman Emperor, he called Martin Luther to the Diet of Worms in 1521, promising him safe conduct if he would appear. He initially dismissed Luther's idea of reformation as "An argument between monks". He later outlawed Luther and his followers in that same year but was tied up with other concerns and unable to try to stamp out Protestantism.[PARAGRAPH:1]1524 to 1526 saw the Peasants' Revolt in Germany and in 1531 the formation of the Lutheran Schmalkaldic League. Charles delegated increasing responsibility for Germany to his brother Ferdinand while he concentrated on problems abroad.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1545, the opening of the Council of Trent began the Counter-Reformation, and Charles won to the Catholic cause some of the princes of the Holy Roman Empire. He also attacked the Schmalkaldic League in 1546 and at the Battle of Mühlberg defeated John Frederick, Elector of Saxony and imprisoned Philip of Hesse in 1547. At the Augsburg Interim in 1548 he created a doctrinal compromise that he felt Catholics and Protestants alike might share. A more permanent settlement followed with the 1555 Peace of Augsburg.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1556, Charles abdicated his various titles, giving his Spanish empire (Spain, the Netherlands, Naples and Spain's possessions in the Americas) to his son, Philip II of Spain. He passed his dynastic Austrian lands and the Holy Roman Empire to his brother, Ferdinand. Charles retired to the monastery of Yuste in Extremadura, but continued to correspond widely and kept an interest in the situation of the empire. He suffered from severe gout and some scholars think Charles V decided to abdicate after a gout attack in 1552 forced him to postpone an attempt to recapture the city of Metz, where he was later defeated.[PARAGRAPH:1]Charles died on 21 September 1558. Twenty-six years later, his remains were transferred to the Royal Pantheon of The Monastery of San Lorenzo de El Escorial.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Karol V[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Cesarz Sw. Cesarstwa Rzymskiego, Król Hiszpanii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 1500 - 1558[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE] W 1506 r. zmarł ojciec Karola i formalnie władzę w nim pełniła nadal samodzielnie, matka Karola - Joanna. Faktycznie jednak regencję pełnił jej ojciec Ferdynand Aragoński. Po śmierci Ferdynanda w 1516 Joanna stała się równieź nominalnie królową Aragonii, będąc tym samym pierwszą prawdziwą władczynią zjednoczonych królestw Hiszpanii w jednej osobie. Jej połoźenie faktyczne niewiele się jednak zmieniło. Sprawujący regencję po śmierci Ferdynanda kardynał Cisneros wezwał najstarszego syna Joanny - Karola, by objął rządy w państwie. Został on w 1516 r. królem Kastylii i Leónu oraz Królem Aragonii (jako Karol I), w obu królestwach formalnie jako współwładca z matką, Joanną. Faktycznie jednak usunął w cień szaloną matkę. Karol ponownie zjednoczył Hiszpanię. Tym razem juź na stałe. Moment ten uznaje się za powstanie Królestwa Hiszpanii. Do swojego królestwa Karol przybył po raz pierwszy na jesieni 1517 r. Na jego spotkanie wyruszył regent, kardynał Francisco Jiménez de Cisneros, jednak zmarł podczas podróźy. Nie obyło się bez podejrzeń o otrucie. Negocjacje Karola z kastylijskimi Kortezami były trudne. Ostatecznie Karol obiecał nauczyć się kastylijskiego i nie obsadzać urzędów cudzoziemcami. 9 lutego 1518 Stany Kastylii uznały jego panowanie i złoźyły mu hołd w Valladolid. 29 lipca 1518 to samo zrobiły Kortezy aragońskimi w Saragossie. Hołd złoźyły mu teź Kortezy Katalonii (16 kwietnia 1519) i Walencji (16 maja 1528).</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Êàðë V[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ñâÿùåííàÿ Ðèìñêàÿ Èìïåðèÿ, Êîðîëü Èñïàíèè[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ãîäû æèçíè: [\BOLD]24 ôåâðàëÿ 1500 - 21 ñåíòÿáðÿ 1558[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Ïðåäûñòîðèÿ:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB] Êîðîëü Èñïàíèè (Êàñòèëèè è Àðàãîíà) ïîä èìåíåì Êàðë I (èñï. Carlos I) ñ 23 ÿíâàðÿ 1516 ãîäà, êîðîëü Ãåðìàíèè (ðèìñêèé êîðîëü) ñ 28 èþíÿ 1519 ïî 1556 ãîäû, èìïåðàòîð Ñâÿùåííîé Ðèìñêîé èìïåðèè ñ 1519 ãîäà (êîðîíîâàí 24 ôåâðàëÿ 1530 ãîäà â Áîëîíüå ïàïîé ðèìñêèì Êëèìåíòîì VII). Êðóïíåéøèé ãîñóäàðñòâåííûé äåÿòåëü Åâðîïû ïåðâîé ïîëîâèíû XVI âåêà, âíåñøèé íàèáîëüøèé âêëàä â èñòîðèþ ñðåäè ïðàâèòåëåé òîãî âðåìåíè. Áèîãðàôèÿ[PARAGRAPH:1]Êàðë áûë ñûíîì ãåðöîãà Ôèëèïïà Áóðãóíäñêîãî è èñïàíñêîé èíôàíòû Õóàíû. Îí ðîäèëñÿ âî âëàäåíèÿõ îòöà, â ãîðîäå Ãåíòå. Îòåö, ïûòàâøèéñÿ óíàñëåäîâàòü êàñòèëüñêóþ êîðîíó îò çíàìåíèòîé ñâîåé ò¸ùè, ïðîâîäèë ìíîãî âðåìåíè â èñïàíñêèõ âëàäåíèÿõ. Êàðë îñòàâàëñÿ æèòü â Íèäåðëàíäàõ. Åãî ðîäíûì ÿçûêîì áûë ôðàíöóçñêèé, çíàíèå äðóãèõ ÿçûêîâ â þíîñòè áûëè ñêðîìíûìè. Ïîñëå âñòóïëåíèÿ íà èñïàíñêèé ïðåñòîë îí âûó÷èë êàñòèëüñêèé. Ê êîíöó æèçíè îí óæå íåïëîõî âëàäåë ìíîãèìè ÿçûêàìè. Â 1506 ãîäó Ôèëèïï óìåð, à Õóàíà ñîøëà ñ óìà. Êàðë äî 17 ëåò æèë ïîä ïîêðîâèòåëüñòâîì òåòêè, Ìàðãàðèòû Àâñòðèéñêîé, ïðàâèòåëüíèöû Íèäåðëàíäîâ. Äî ñàìîé ñìåðòè îí ïîääåðæèâàë ñ íåé íåæíûå îòíîøåíèÿ. [PARAGRAPH:1]Íèêòî èç åâðîïåéñêèõ ìîíàðõîâ, íè äî, íè ïîñëå, íå èìåë òàê ìíîãî òèòóëîâ. Îäíèõ òîëüêî êîðîëåâñêèõ êîðîí ó Êàðëà áûëî ôîðìàëüíî áîëåå äåñÿòêà ? îí îäíîâðåìåííî áûë êîðîëåì Ëåîíà, Êàñòèëèè, Âàëåíñèè, Àðàãîíà, Ãàëèñèè, Ñåâèëüè, Ìàëüîðêè, Ãðàíàäû, Íàâàððû, îáåèõ Ñèöèëèé, Ñàðäèíèè, Êîðñèêè, Âåíãðèè, Õîðâàòèè è ïðî÷åå, à òàêæå êîðîëåì Ãåðìàíèè è Èòàëèè è òèòóëÿðíûì êîðîë¸ì Èåðóñàëèìà. Áëàãîäàðÿ ñêðåùåíèþ äèíàñòè÷åñêèõ ëèíèé Êàðë ïîëó÷èë â íàñëåäñòâî îãðîìíûå òåððèòîðèè â Çàïàäíîé, Þæíîé è Öåíòðàëüíîé Åâðîïå, äîíûíå íèêîãäà íå îáúåäèíÿâøèåñÿ. Êàê ÷àñòî îí ëþáèë ïîâòîðÿòü: "Ñ Áîãîì ÿ ãîâîðþ ïî-èñïàíñêè, ñ ìóæ÷èíàìè ïî-ôðàíöóçñêè, ñ æåíùèíàìè ïî-èòàëüÿíñêè, à ñ ìîèì êîíåì ïî-íåìåöêè."[PARAGRAPH:1]Â 1526 ãîäó Êàðë æåíèëñÿ íà Èçàáåëëå Ïîðòóãàëüñêîé. Îíà ïðèõîäèëàñü åìó äâîþðîäíîé ñåñòðîé (èõ ìàòåðè Õóàíà è Ìàðèÿ áûëè ñåñòðàìè). Ýòî áûë îäèí èç ïåðâûõ áëèçêîðîäñòâåííûõ áðàêîâ â äèíàñòèè, â êîíöå êîíöîâ, ïðèâåäøèõ ðîä èñïàíñêèõ Ãàáñáóðãîâ ê âûðîæäåíèþ è êðàõó. Â âîçðàñòå 36 ëåò Èçàáåëëà óìåðëà. Êàðë áîëüøå íå æåíèëñÿ, íî èìåë ìíîãî ëþáîâíèö, äâå èç êîòîðûõ ðîäèëè åìó äåòåé. Èç åãî çàêîííûõ äåòåé Ôèëèïï II óíàñëåäîâàë êîðîíó Èñïàíèè, Ñèöèëèè, Íèäåðëàíäîâ è àìåðèêàíñêèå âëàäåíèÿ, à åãî äî÷ü Ìàðèÿ âûøëà çàìóæ çà Ìàêñèìèëèàíà II, ïîçæå ñòàâøåãî èìïåðàòîðîì.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ôàêòè÷åñêè Èñïàíèÿ âïåðâûå îáúåäèíèëàñü èìåííî ïîä ñêèïåòðîì Êàðëà. Ïîêîëåíèåì ðàíüøå îíà áûëà ðàçäåëåíà íà êîðîëåâñòâà, ïðèíàäëåæàùèå äâóì ïðàâèòåëÿì Èçàáåëëå (êîðîëåâñòâî Êàñòèëèÿ) è Ôåðäèíàíäó II (êîðîëåâñòâî Àðàãîí). Áðàê ýòèõ äâóõ ìîíàðõîâ Èñïàíèþ íå îáúåäèíèë, êàæäàÿ ÷àñòü ñîõðàíèëà ñàìîñòîÿòåëüíîñòü, è êàæäûé ãîñóäàðü óïðàâëÿë åþ íåçàâèñèìî, íî ôóíäàìåíò áóäóùåãî îáúåäèíåíèÿ áûë çàëîæåí. Èçàáåëëà Êàñòèëüñêàÿ óìåðëà â 1504 ãîäó. Ïîñëå å¸ ñìåðòè Êàñòèëèÿ ïî çàâåùàíèþ îòîøëà ê å¸ äî÷åðè Õóàíå Áåçóìíîé ? ìàòåðè Êàðëà, îäíàêî ôàêòè÷åñêè Êàñòèëèåé óïðàâëÿë åãî äåä Ôåðäèíàíä II â êà÷åñòâå ðåãåíòà. Ôåðäèíàíä II ñêîí÷àëñÿ â 1516 ãîäó. Êàðë óíàñëåäîâàë îò äåäà Àðàãîí è îïåêó íàä Êàñòèëèåé (Õóàíà Áåçóìíàÿ áûëà âñå åù¸ æèâà. Îíà ñêîí÷àåòñÿ â ìîíàñòûðå âñåãî ëèøü íà òðè ãîäà ðàíüøå Êàðëà). Òåì íå ìåíåå, Êàðë íå ñòàë îáúÿâëÿòü ñåáÿ ðåãåíòîì Êàñòèëèè, à ïðåäïî÷¸ë âñþ ïîëíîòó âëàñòè. 14 ìàðòà 1516 îí ïðîâîçãëàñèë ñåáÿ êîðîëåì Êàñòèëèè è Àðàãîíà. Ïîïûòêà ïîñòàâèòü ñòðàíó ïåðåä ñâåðøèâøèìñÿ ôàêòîì ñïðîâîöèðîâàëà áóíò ? òàê íàçûâàåìîå âîññòàíèå êîìóíåðîñ â Êàñòèëèè â 1520?1522 ãã. Ñîáðàíèå êàñòèëüñêèõ êîðòåñîâ â Âàëüÿäîëèäå íàïîìíèëî åìó, ÷òî ó ìàòåðè, çàòî÷åííîé â ìîíàñòûðå, áîëüøå ïðàâ, ÷åì ó ñûíà. Â êîíöå êîíöîâ, Êàðë äîñòèã ñîãëàñèÿ â ïåðåãîâîðàõ ñ êîðòåñàìè. Õóàíà ôîðìàëüíî îñòàâàëàñü êîðîëåâîé Êàñòèëèè.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ñîñðåäîòî÷åíèÿ îãðîìíûõ òåððèòîðèé â ðóêàõ Êàðëà îïàñàëàñü Ôðàíöèÿ. Ñïîðíûõ âîïðîñîâ ó Êàðëà è êîðîëÿ Ôðàíöèè Ôðàíöèñêà I íàêîïèëîñü íåìàëî. Êàðë ïðåäúÿâëÿë ïðåòåíçèè íà ãåðöîãñòâî Áóðãóíäñêîå è òðåáîâàë âîçâðàùåíèÿ Ìèëàíà ñåìåéñòâó Ñôîðöà. Ôðàíöèñê ïîêðîâèòåëüñòâîâàë êîðîëþ Íàâàððû è íåîôèöèàëüíî ïîääåðæèâàë åãî â âîéíå çà óòðà÷åííûå íàâàððñêèå òåððèòîðèè. Âñå ýòè ÷àñòíûå âçàèìíûå ïðåòåíçèè, îäíàêî, ëèøü âûðàæàëè ñòðåìëåíèå îáåèõ ñòðàí ê ãåãåìîíèè íà åâðîïåéñêîì êîíòèíåíòå. Îòêðûòîå ïðîòèâîñòîÿíèå íà÷àëîñü â 1521 ãîäó, êîãäà èìïåðñêèå âîéñêà âòîðãëèñü â Ñåâåðíóþ Ôðàíöèþ, à ôðàíöóçû äâèíóëè ñâîè âîéñêà íà ïîìîùü íàâàððñêîìó êîðîëþ. Èñïàíñêàÿ àðìèÿ ðàçáèëà íàâàððöåâ è âåðíóëà Ïàìïëîíó. Íà ñåâåðå Ôðàíöèè ïîñëå ðàçîðåíèÿ íåñêîëüêèõ íåáîëüøèõ ãîðîäîâ è âçÿòèÿ Òóðíå ê êîíöó ãîäà Êàðëó âñ¸ æå ïðèøëîñü îòñòóïèòü. Ãëàâíûì äîñòèæåíèåì Êàðëà îäíàêî ñòàëà äèïëîìàòè÷åñêàÿ ïîáåäà: åìó óäàëîñü ñêëîíèòü ê ñîþçó ðèìñêîãî ïàïó è àíãëèéñêîãî êîðîëÿ. Â íîÿáðå 1521 ãîäà ôðàíöóçû áûëè âûáèòû èç Ìèëàíà, à â àïðåëå ñëåäóþùåãî ãîäà îíè áûëè íàãîëîâó ðàçáèòû ïðè Áèêîêêå. Â òî æå âðåìÿ àíãëè÷àíå àòàêîâàëè Áðåòàíü è Ïèêàðäèþ. Â 1523 ãîäó èç âîéíû âûøëà Âåíåöèÿ ? ñîþçíèê Ôðàíöèè. Ôðàíöóçñêîå êîðîëåâñòâî îêàçàëîñü â òÿæåëîì ïîëîæåíèè.[PARAGRAPH:1]Â 1524 ãîäó èìïåðñêèå âîéñêà ïåðåøëè ÷åðåç Àëüïû, âòîðãëèñü â Ïðîâàíñ è âçÿëè â îñàäó Ìàðñåëü. Â 1525 ãîäó ïðè Ïàâèè ? ê þãó îò Ìèëàíà ? ñîøëèñü äâå 30-òûñÿ÷íûå àðìèè. Êàðë ðàçáèë ôðàíöóçñêóþ àðìèþ è äàæå âçÿë â ïëåí ôðàíöóçñêîãî êîðîëÿ Ôðàíöèñêà I. Êàðë ïðèíóäèë ïëåíåííîãî êîðîëÿ ïîäïèñàòü Ìàäðèäñêèé äîãîâîð (14 ÿíâàðÿ 1526), ïî êîòîðîìó ïðèçíàâàëèñü ïðèòÿçàíèÿ Êàðëà íà Èòàëèþ, à òàêæå åãî ïðàâà ôåîäàëüíîãî ñþçåðåíà íà Àðòóà è Ôëàíäðèþ. Â çàëîæíèêàõ îñòàâàëèñü äâà ñûíà Ôðàíöèñêà. Îäíàêî, êàê òîëüêî êîðîëþ óäàëîñü ïîëó÷èòü ñâîáîäó, îí îáúÿâèë äîãîâîð íåäåéñòâèòåëüíûì è 22 ìàÿ 1526 ãîäà ñîçâàë ïðîòèâ Êàðëà Êîíüÿêñêóþ ëèãó (âîøëè Ôëîðåíöèÿ, Ìèëàí, Âåíåöèÿ, Ãåíóÿ, ïàïà è Àíãëèÿ). Ñíîâà êîíôëèêò ïðîèñõîäèë â Èòàëèè. Ïîñëå ïîáåä Êàðëà èìïåðàòîðñêàÿ àðìèÿ ðàçãðàáèëà Ðèì â ìàå 1527 ãîäà. Â 1528 ãîäó Êàðë çàêëþ÷èë ìèð ñ êîðîëåì Àíãëèè Ãåíðèõîì VIII, à ãåíóýçöû ïåðåøëè íà åãî ñòîðîíó, â 1529 ãîäó çàêëþ÷¸í Êàìáðåéñêèé ìèðíûé äîãîâîð ñ Ôðàíöèåé è ìèð ñ ïàïîé Êëèìåíòîì VII. Â 1530 ãîäó áûë ïîëíîñòüþ ðàçáèò ïîñëåäíèé ïðîòèâíèê Êàðëà ? Ôëîðåíòèéñêàÿ ðåñïóáëèêà. Ïî Êàìáðåéñêîìó ìèðíîìó äîãîâîðó àâãóñòà 1529 ãîäà ñóììà âûêóïà çà äâóõ ôðàíöóçñêèõ ïðèíöåâ íàçíà÷àëàñü â ðàçìåðå 2 ìëí çîëîòûõ ýêþ, èç êîòîðûõ 1,2 ìëí ñëåäîâàëî âûïëàòèòü íåìåäëåííî, à òàêæå Ãàáñáóðãè çàïîëó÷èëè Ìèëàí è âûòåñíèëè ôðàíöóçîâ ñ Àïåííèíñêîãî ïîëóîñòðîâà, óòâåðäèâ òàì ñâîå ïðèñóòñòâèå íà ìíîãèå âåêà. Ýòî, ïîæàëóé, áûëî îäíèì èç ãëàâíûõ äîñòèæåíèé Êàðëà, õîòÿ ðàçîðåííàÿ è îáíèùàâøàÿ Èòàëèÿ áûëà äàëåêî íå ñòîëü öåííûì òðîôååì, êàê ïðåæäå. Ôðàíöèñê çàòåÿë ïðîòèâ Êàðëà åù¸ äâå âîéíû (1536?1538 è 1542?1544), íî èçìåíèòü ïîëîæåíèå íå ñìîã.[PARAGRAPH:1]Â 1544 ã. áûë çàêëþ÷¸í ìèðíûé äîãîâîð â Êðåñïè, ïî êîòîðîìó Ôðàíöèñê I îòêàçàëñÿ îò ñâîèõ çàâîåâàíèé â Èòàëèè, â ÷àñòíîñòè îò Ìèëàíñêîãî ãåðöîãñòâà è ïðèíàäëåæàùåãî Èñïàíèè Íåàïîëèòàíñêîãî êîðîëåâñòâà. Êàðë V, â ñâîþ î÷åðåäü îòêàçàëñÿ îò ïðèòÿçàíèé íà Áóðãóíäèþ. Êðîìå ýòîãî Ôðàíöèñê îáåùàë Êàðëó âîåííóþ ïîìîùü â áîðüáå ïðîòèâ òóðîê. Çàêëþ÷åíèå äîãîâîðà ïîçâîëèëî Êàðëó ñêîíöåíòðèðîâàòü ñèëû â áîðüáå ïðîòèâ Øìàëüêàëüäåíñêîãî ñîþçà è òóðîê. [PARAGRAPH:1]Â îáðàçå çàùèòíèêà õðèñòèàíñòâà (çà ÷òî Êàðëà ïðîçâàëè «Áîæüèì çíàìåíîñöåì») îí âîåâàë ïðîòèâ Òóðöèè. Â êîíöå 1529 ãîäó òóðåöêèå âîéñêà îñàäèëè Âåíó, óæå èìåÿ çà ñïèíîé ïîêîðåííóþ Âåíãðèþ. Íî íàñòóïèâøàÿ çèìà çàñòàâèëà èõ îòñòóïèòü. Â 1532 ãîäó òàê æå íè ñ ÷åì òóðêè óøëè èç-ïîä êðåïîñòè Ê¸ñåã â çàïàäíîé Âåíãðèè. Èñïîëüçóÿ ïåðåðûâ â âîéíå, Êàðë â 1535 ãîäó îòïðàâëÿåò ôëîò ê áåðåãàì Òóíèñà. Ôëîò Êàðëà âçÿë ãîðîä è îñâîáîäèë òûñÿ÷è îáðàùåííûõ â ðàáñòâî õðèñòèàí. Çäåñü áûëà âîçâåäåíà êðåïîñòü è îñòàâëåí èñïàíñêèé ãàðíèçîí. Îäíàêî ýòà ïîáåäà áûëà ñâåäåíà íà íåò èñõîäîì ñðàæåíèÿ ïðè Ïðåâåçå (â Ýïèðå) â 1538 ãîäó, êîãäà õðèñòèàíàì ïðîòèâîñòîÿë çàíîâî âûñòðîåííûé ñóëòàíîì Ñóëåéìàíîì I Âåëèêîëåïíûì òóðåöêèé ôëîò. Òåïåðü òóðêè âíîâü ãîñïîäñòâîâàëè â Ñðåäèçåìíîì ìîðå (äî áèòâû ïðè Ëåïàíòî â 1571 ãîäó). Â 1541 ãîäó Êàðë ïûòàëñÿ ñ ïîìîùüþ ôëîòà âçÿòü Àëæèð, íî êîðàáëè ðàçìåòàëî ïî ìîðþ âíåçàïíîé áóðåé. Ïîëüçóÿñü òóðåöêî-ïåðñèäñêèì êîíôëèêòîì, â 1545 ãîäó Êàðë ïîäïèñàë ñ ñóëòàíîì ïåðåìèðèå, à çàòåì è ìèð (1547) ñðîêîì íà ïÿòü ëåò. Ãàáñáóðãàì ïðèøëîñü äàæå âûïëà÷èâàòü Ñóëåéìàíó äàíü, ïîñêîëüêó îí ïîñòîÿííî óãðîæàë âëàäåíèÿì Êàðëà â Èñïàíèè è Èòàëèè, à òàêæå â Àâñòðèè.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ïûòàÿñü âîññòàíîâèòü ðåëèãèîçíîå åäèíñòâî ñâîåé èìïåðèè (Ìàðòèí Ëþòåð âûñêàçàë ñâîè èäåè åù¸ â 1517 ãîäó), Êàðë àêòèâíî âìåøèâàëñÿ âî âíóòðåííèå äåëà ãåðìàíñêèõ ïðàâèòåëåé. Ïðèçíàêàìè ðàñïàäà I Ðåéõà áûëè: ò. í. Ðûöàðñêàÿ âîéíà 1522?1523 ãîäîâ, êîãäà ñîþç ëþòåðàíñêèõ àðèñòîêðàòîâ íàïàë íà çåìëè, ïðèíàäëåæàâøèå Òðèðñêîìó àðõèåïèñêîïó è êóðôþðñòó, è Êðåñòüÿíñêàÿ âîéíà 1524?1525 ãîäîâ. Êàðë âîåâàë ñ ëþòåðàíñêîé Øìàëüêàëüäåíñêîé ëèãîé. 24 àïðåëÿ 1547 ãîäà ? ÷åðåç ãîä ïîñëå ñìåðòè Ëþòåðà ? ïðè Ìþëüáåðãå (íà Ýëüáå) âîéñêà Êàðëà, êîòîðûìè êîìàíäîâàë Ôåðíàíäî Àëüâàðåñ äå Òîëåäî ãåðöîã Àëüáà, îäåðæàëè êðóïíóþ ïîáåäó.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ðàçî÷àðîâàâøèñü â èäåå ñòðîèòåëüñòâà âñååâðîïåéñêîé èìïåðèè, ïîñëå çàêëþ÷åíèÿ Àóãñáóðãñêîãî ðåëèãèîçíîãî ìèðà Êàðë 25 îêòÿáðÿ 1555 ãîäà îòêàçàëñÿ îò Íèäåðëàíäîâ â ïîëüçó ñûíà Ôèëèïïà. 16 ÿíâàðÿ 1556 ãîäà îí, òàêæå â ïîëüçó Ôèëèïïà, ñëîæèë ñ ñåáÿ èñïàíñêóþ êîðîíó, â òîì ÷èñëå îòäàë âëàäåíèÿ Èñïàíèè â Èòàëèè è Íîâîì Ñâåòå. Õîòÿ Êàðë èçúÿâëÿë æåëàíèå îòêàçàòüñÿ îò èìïåðàòîðñêîé âëàñòè åù¸ â 1556 ãîäó, êóðôþðñòû ïðèíÿëè åãî îòðå÷åíèå è èçáðàëè èìïåðàòîðîì Ôåðäèíàíäà ëèøü â ôåâðàëå 1558 ãîäà. Áûâøèé èìïåðàòîð óäàëèëñÿ â ìîíàñòûðü â Þñòå áëèç Êañåðåñà (Ýñòðåìàäóðà), ãäå è ïðîâ¸ë îñòàòîê æèçíè. Ïîõîðîíåí â êîðîëåâñêîé óñûïàëüíèöå Ýñêîðèàëà.[PARAGRAPH:1]Äå-ôàêòî Êàðë áûë ïåðâûì ïðàâèòåëåì åäèíîé Èñïàíèè â 1516?1556 ãîäàõ, õîòÿ òèòóë «êîðîëü Èñïàíèè» ïåðâûì ñòàë íîñèòü ëèøü åãî ñûí Ôèëèïï II. Ñàì Êàðë îôèöèàëüíî áûë êîðîë¸ì Àðàãîíà (êàê Êàðë I, èñï. Carlos I, 1516?1556), à â Êàñòèëèè áûë ðåãåíòîì ñâîåé ìàòåðè Õóàíû Áåçóìíîé, îáúÿâëåííîé íåäååñïîñîáíîé ïîñëå ñìåðòè îòöà Êàðëà ? êîðîëÿ-êîíñîðòà Ôèëèïïà (1504?1506) ? è çàòåì îäèí ãîä êîðîë¸ì Êàñòèëèè (1555?1556).[PARAGRAPH:1]Îí ñàì íàçûâàë ñåáÿ ñëîæíî: "Èçáðàííûé èìïåðàòîð õðèñòèàíñêîãî ìèðà è Ðèìñêèé, ïðèñíî Àâãóñò, à òàêæå êàòîëè÷åñêèé êîðîëü Ãåðìàíèè, Èñïàíèé è âñåõ êîðîëåâñòâ, îòíîñÿùèõñÿ ê íàøèì Êàñòèëüñêîé è Àðàãîíñêîé êîðîíàì, à òàêæå Áàëåàðñêèõ îñòðîâîâ, Êàíàðñêèõ îñòðîâîâ è Èíäèé, Àíòèïîäîâ Íîâîãî Ñâåòà, ñóøè â Ìîðå-Îêåàíå, Ïðîëèâîâ Àíòàðêòè÷åñêîãî Ïîëþñà è ìíîãèõ äðóãèõ îñòðîâîâ êàê êðàéíåãî Âîñòîêà, òàê è Çàïàäà, è ïðî÷àÿ; ýðöãåðöîã Àâñòðèè, ãåðöîã Áóðãóíäèè, Áðàáàíòà, Ëèìáóðãà, Ëþêñåìáóðãà, Ãåëüäåðíà è ïðî÷àÿ; ãðàô Ôëàíäðèè, Àðòóà è Áóðãóíäèè, ïôàëüöãðàô Ãåííåãàó, Ãîëëàíäèè, Çåëàíäèè, Íàìþðà, Ðóññèëüîíà, Ñåðäàíüè, Çþòôåíà, ìàðêãðàô Îðèñòàíèè è Ãîòöèàíèè, ãîñóäàðü Êàòàëîíèè è ìíîãèõ äðóãèõ êîðîëåâñòâ â Åâðîïå, à òàêæå â Àçèè è Àôðèêå ãîñïîäèí è ïðî÷àÿ".</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>