<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JOANOFARC_1</Tag>
		<English>Choose your words carefully, [CT_NAME]. Those of [OUR_EMPIRE] say that people are hanged sometimes for speaking the truth.</English>
		<French>Choisissez vos mots avec soin, [CT_NAME]. On raconte dans mon [OUR_EMPIRE] que les gens sont parfois pendus pour avoir dit la vérité.</French>
		<German>Wähle Deine Worte mit Sorgfalt, [CT_NAME]. Die Bewohner vom [OUR_EMPIRE] sagen, dass manchmal Leute aufgehängt werden, weil sie die Wahrheit sagen.</German>
		<Polish>Dobieraj swoje słowa ostrożnie, [CT_NAME]. Ludzie z [OUR_EMPIRE] powiadają, że czasami się wiesza za mówienie prawdy.</Polish>
		<Spanish>Elige bien tus palabras, [CT_NAME]. Aquellos del [OUR_EMPIRE] afirman que a veces se ahorca a la gente por decir la verdad.</Spanish>
		<Russian>Тщательно подбирайте слова, [CT_NAME]. В [OUR_EMPIRE] говорят, что людей порою вешают за то, что они говорят правду.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JOANOFARC</Tag>
		<English>Joan of Arc</English>
		<French>Jeanne d'Arc</French>
		<German>Johanna von Orléans</German>
		<Italian>Giovanna d'Arco</Italian>
		<Polish>Joanna d'Arc</Polish>
		<Russian>Æàííà ä'Àðê</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JOANOFARC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Joan of Arc[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Commander of the French Army[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1412 - 1431[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Joan of Arc, or Jeanne d'Arc in French, was a 15th century saint and national heroine of France. She was the only person ever recorded to have commanded the entire army of a nation at the age of seventeen; she was captured by the English and tried by an ecclesiastical court led by Bishop Pierre Cauchon, an English partisan, the court convicted her of heresy and she was burned at the stake by the English when she was nineteen years old. Twenty-four years later, the Vatican reviewed the decision of the ecclesiastical court, found her innocent, and declared her a martyr. She was beatified in 1909 and canonized as a saint in 1920.[PARAGRAPH:1]Joan asserted that she had visions from God that told her to recover her homeland from English domination late in the Hundred Years' War. The uncrowned King Charles VII sent her to the siege at Orléans as part of a relief mission. She gained prominence when she overcame the dismissive attitude of veteran commanders and lifted the siege in only nine days. Several more swift victories led to Charles VII's coronation at Reims and settled the disputed succession to the throne.[PARAGRAPH:1]The renewed French confidence outlasted her own brief career. She refused to leave the field when she was wounded during an attempt to recapture Paris that autumn. She defied the cautious strategy that had characterized French leadership. During the five months of siege before her arrival, the defenders of Orléans had attempted only one aggressive move and that had ended in disaster. On 4 May the French attacked and captured the outlying fortress of Saint Loup, which she followed on 5 May with a march to a second fortress called Saint Jean le Blanc. Finding it deserted, this became a bloodless victory. The next day she opposed Jean d'Orleans at a war council where she demanded another assault on the enemy. D'Orleans ordered the city gates locked to prevent another battle, but she summoned the townsmen and common soldiers and forced the mayor to unlock a gate. With the aid of only one captain she rode out and captured the fortress of Saint Augustins. That evening she learned she had been excluded from a war council where the leaders had decided to wait for reinforcements before acting again. Disregarding this decision, she insisted on assaulting the main English stronghold called "les Tourelles" on 7 May. Contemporaries acknowledged her as the heroine of the engagement after she sustained an arrow wound to her neck but returned wounded to lead the final charge.[PARAGRAPH:1]Hampered by court intrigues, she led only minor companies from then onward and fell prisoner at a skirmish near Compiègne the following spring. Joan's trial for heresy was politically motivated. The Duke of Bedford claimed the throne of France for his nephew Henry VI. She had been responsible for the rival coronation so to condemn her was to undermine her king's legitimacy. Legal proceedings commenced on 9 January 1431 at Rouen, the seat of the English occupation government. The procedure was irregular on a number of points. In 1456, Pope Callixtus III declared her innocent of the heresy charges brought against her. The trial record demonstrates her remarkable intellect. The transcript's most famous exchange is an exercise in subtlety. "Asked if she knew she was in God's grace, she answered: 'If I am not, may God put me there; and if I am, may God so keep me.'" The question is a scholarly trap. Church doctrine held that no one could be certain of being in God's grace. If she had answered yes, then she would have convicted herself of heresy. If she had answered no, then she would have confessed her own guilt. Notary Boisguillaume would later testify that at the moment the court heard this reply, "Those who were interrogating her were stupefied."[PARAGRAPH:1]The English regent John of Lancaster, 1st Duke of Bedford had her burnt at the stake in Rouen. She had been the heroine of her country at 17 and died when only 19 years old. Some 24 years later, Pope Callixtus III reopened the case, and a new finding overturned the original conviction. Her piety to the end impressed the retrial court. Pope Benedict XV canonized her on May 16, 1920.[PARAGRAPH:1]Joan has been a political symbol in France since the time of Napoleon. Liberals emphasized her humble origins. Early conservatives stressed her support of the monarchy. Later conservatives recalled her nationalism. During World War II, both the Vichy Regime and the French Resistance used her image: Vichy propaganda remembered her campaign against the English with posters that showed British warplanes bombing Rouen and the ominous caption: "They Always Return to the Scene of Their Crimes." The resistance emphasized her fight against foreign occupation and her origins in the province of Lorraine, which had fallen under Nazi control. Traditional Catholics, especially in France, also use her as a symbol of inspiration, often comparing the 1988 excommunication of Archbishop Marcel Lefebvre (founder of the Society of St. Pius X and a dissident against the Vatican II reforms) to Joan's excommunication. Three separate vessels of the French Navy have been named after her, including a helicopter carrier currently in active service. At present the controversial French far-right political party Front National holds rallies at her statues, reproduces her likeness in party publications, and uses a tricolor flame partly symbolic of her martyrdom as its emblem. This party's opponents sometimes satirize its appropriation of her image. The French civic holiday in her honor is the second Sunday of May.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Joanna d'Arc[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dowódca Armii Francji[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żyła:[\BOLD] 1412 - 1431[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Francuska bohaterka narodowa, święta Kościoła katolickiego, patronka Francji. Podczas wojny stuletniej poprowadziła armię francuską do kilku ważnych zwycięstw, twierdząc, że działa kierowana przez Boga. Pośrednio przyczyniła się do koronacji Karola VII. Została schwytana przez Burgundczyków i przekazana Anglikom, osądzona przez sąd kościelny i spalona na stosie w wieku 19 lat. 24 lata później papież Kalikst III dokonał rewizji decyzji sądu kościelnego. Uniewinnił ją i określił przeprowadzony w Rouen proces jako sprzeczny z prawem. Została beatyfikowana w 1909 roku i kanonizowana w 1920. Joanna twierdziła, że otrzymała widzenie od Boga, podczas którego dostała polecenie wyzwolenia ojczyzny spod panowania angielskiego. Chcąc wypróbować jej prawdomówność, niekoronowany król Karol VII wysłał ją do oblężonego Orleanu. Po doprowadzeniu do zniesienia oblężenia miasta w ciągu zaledwie dziewięciu dni uzyskała powszechny szacunek i przezwyciężyła lekceważącą postawę weteranów. Kilka kolejnych zwycięstw doprowadziło do koronacji Karola VII w Reims i rozstrzygnęło spór o sukcesję tronu Francji.</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Жанна д'Арк[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Французский полководец[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни: [\BOLD] 1412 - 1431[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Жанна д'Арк или Орлеанская дева - национальная героиня Франции, одна из командующих французскими войсками в Столетней войне. Попав в плен к бургундцам, была передана англичанам, осуждена как еретик церковным судом во главе с епископом Пьером Кошоном и сожжена на костре. Впоследствии в 1456 году была реабилитирована и в 1920 году канонизирована - причислена католической церковью к лику святых. Она была единственным человеком, когда-либо зарегистрированным, которая командовала всей армией страны в возрасте семнадцати лет.[PARAGRAPH:1]Жанна утверждала, что ей были видения от Бога, которые велели ей вернуть свою родину от английского господства в конце Столетней войны. Некоронованный дофин Карл VII послал ее на осаду Орлеана в рамках миссии по оказанию помощи. Она получила известность, когда преодолела пренебрежительное отношение старых военачальников и сняла осаду всего за девять дней. Несколько более быстрые победы привели к коронации Карла VII в Реймсе и таким образом поставила точку в спорах о престолонаследии.[PARAGRAPH:1]Возродившийся боевой дух французов пережил саму Жанну. Она отказалась покинуть поле боя, когда той осенью была ранена во время попытки вернуть Париж. Жанна бросила вызов осторожной стратегии, которая характеризовала французское руководство. За пять месяцев осады до ее прибытия защитники Орлеана предприняли только один решительный шаг, закончившийся катастрофой. 4 мая французы атаковали и захватили крепость Сен-Лу, за которой они последовали 5 мая маршем ко второй крепости Сен-Жан-ле-Блан. Когда он оказался заброшенным, победа стала бескровной. На следующий день она выступила против Жана д'Орлеана на военном совете, где потребовала еще одного нападения на врага. Д'Орлеан приказала запереть городские ворота, чтобы предотвратить новую битву, но она призвала горожан и простых солдат и заставила мэра открыть ворота. С помощью только одного капитана она выехала и захватила крепость святого Августина. В тот вечер она узнала, что ее исключили из военного совета, где лидеры решили дождаться подкрепления, прежде чем действовать снова. Игнорируя это решение, она настояла на нападении на главную английскую цитадель под названием «Ле Турель» 7 мая. Современники признали ее героиней сражения после того, как она получила ранение от стрелы в шею, но вернулась раненой, чтобы возглавить последнюю атаку.[PARAGRAPH:1]Из-за придворных интриг она с тех пор руководила лишь небольшими отрядами и следующей весной попала в плен в стычке под Компьеном. Суд над Жанной и обвинения в ереси были политически мотивированными. Герцог Бедфорд претендовал на трон Франции в пользу своего племянника Генриха VI. Она была ответственна за коронацию соперника, поэтому осудить ее значило подорвать легитимность ее короля. Судебное разбирательство началось 9 января 1431 года в Руане, резиденции английского оккупационного правительства. По ряду пунктов процедура была нерегулярной. В 1456 году папа Калликст III объявил ее невиновной в предъявленных ей обвинениях в ереси. Протокол судебного заседания демонстрирует ее недюжинный интеллект. Самый известный обмен стенограммой - это упражнение на тонкость. На вопрос, знает ли она, что она находится в Божьей благодати, она ответила: «Если я нахожусь вне благодати, пусть господь мне ее пошлет; если я пребываю в ней, пусть он меня в ней хранит». Вопрос представляет собой логическую ловушку. Согласно церковному учению, никто не может быть уверен в том, что находится в Божьей благодати. Если бы она ответила утвердительно, то осудила бы себя в ереси. Если бы она ответила «нет», то признала бы свою вину. Нотариус Буагийом позже засвидетельствовал, что в тот момент, когда суд услышал этот ответ: «Те, кто допрашивал ее, были ошеломлены».[PARAGRAPH:1]Английский регент Джон Ланкастер, 1-й герцог Бедфорд подписал приговор, после чего ее сожгли на костре в Руане. Она была героиней своей страны в 17 лет и погибла, когда ей было всего 19 лет. Примерно 24 года спустя папа Калликст III вновь открыл дело, и новый процесс отменило первоначальный приговор. Ее набожность до конца произвела впечатление на суд повторного рассмотрения. Папа Бенедикт XV канонизировал ее 16 мая 1920 года.[PARAGRAPH:1]Жанна сделалась олицетворенным знаменем Франции со времен Наполеона. Либералы подчеркивали ее скромное происхождение. Ранние консерваторы апеллировали к ее поддержке монархии. Позже консерваторы вспомнили о ее национализме. Во время Второй мировой войны и режим Виши, и французское Сопротивление использовали ее образ: пропаганда Виши вспоминала ее кампанию против англичан плакатами, на которых были изображены британские военные самолеты, бомбившие Руан, и зловещей надписью: «Они всегда возвращаются на место своих преступлений». Сопротивление подчеркнуло ее борьбу против иностранной оккупации и ее происхождение из провинции Лотарингия, которая попала под контроль нацистов. Традиционные католики, особенно во Франции, также используют ее как символ вдохновения, часто сравнивая отлучение от церкви в 1988 году архиепископа Марселя Лефевра (основателя Общества Святого Пия X и диссидента против реформ II Ватиканского собора) с отлучением Жанны. В честь нее были названы три отдельных корабля ВМС Франции, в том числе вертолетоносец, находящийся на действительной службе. В настоящее время скандальная французская крайне правая политическая партия «Национальный фронт» проводит митинги у ее статуй, воспроизводит ее образ в партийных публикациях и использует трехцветное пламя, отчасти символизирующее ее мученическую смерть, в качестве своей эмблемы. Противники этой партии иногда высмеивают присвоение ее имиджа. Французский гражданский праздник в ее честь - второе воскресенье мая.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>