<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ANIMAL_TOTEM_DEER</Tag>
		<English>Military Standard (Deer)</English>
		<French>Standards Militaires (Cervidés)</French>
		<Polish>Sztandar Wojskowy (Deer)</Polish>
		<Russian>Òîòåì «Îëåíü»</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ANIMAL_TOTEM_DEER_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Build Deer buildings and units faster in this city.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Construit les bâtiments et unités cervidés plus vite dans cette Ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DEER_TRAINER</Tag>
		<English>Animal Trainer (Deer)</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Dresseur de Cerf</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Allevatore di cervi</Italian>
		<Polish>Treser Jeleni</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïðèðó÷åíèå îëåíåé</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DEER_TRAINER_EFFECT</Tag>
		<English>Effect - Heritage - Deer</English>
		<French>Effet - Patrimoine (Cervidés)</French>
		<Polish>Efekt - Dziedzictwo Tresera Jeleni</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïèòîìíèê îëåíåé</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DEER_TRAINER_EFFECT_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]This free building is used to enable the building of the special deer units in all your cities.</English>
		<French>Ce bâtiment permet l'entraînement d'unités cervidés dans toutes vos villes.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DEER_TRAINER_HERITAGE</Tag>
		<English>Heritage - Deer</English>
		<French>Patrimoine (Cervidés)</French>
		<Polish>Dziedzictwo - Jeleń</Polish>
		<Russian>Ðàçâåäåíèå îëåíåé</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DEER_TRAINER_HERITAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Heritage building upgrades the Training Wonder to allow the special units to be built in all your cities.</English>
		<French>Le bâtiment du patrimoine améliore la merveille de la formation pour permettre la construction d'unités spéciales dans toutes vos villes.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DEER_TRAINER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>There is no evidence deer were ever trained for warfare. The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Deer Trainer[COLOR_REVERT] building is part of the [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]alternate timeline technologies[COLOR_REVERT]. Technologies that might have been.[PARAGRAPH:2]Strongest base early withdrawal - even battle hardened deer can be skittish creatures that can be tough to KEEP in the battle for long but makes them GREAT at wearing down opponents. They'd be perhaps the best at this get in/get out type of strategy so long as they can do some damage during their short fights.</English>
		<French>Il n'y a aucune preuve que les cerfs aient été formés pour la guerre. Le bâtiment [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT] Dresseur de cerfs [COLOR_REVERT] fait partie des [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT] technologies de chronologie alternatives [COLOR_REVERT]. Technologies qui auraient pu l'être.[PARAGRAPH:2]Retrait précoce de la base la plus forte - même les cerfs endurcis au combat peuvent être des créatures agiles qui peuvent être difficiles à GARDER dans la bataille pendant longtemps, mais les rendent EXCEPTIONNELS pour épuiser leurs adversaires. Ils seraient peut-être les meilleurs dans ce type de stratégie d'entrée / sortie tant qu'ils peuvent faire des dégâts pendant leurs combats courts.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DEERRIDER</Tag>
		<English>Deer Rider</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Chevaucheur de Cerf</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Cavalcatore di cervi</Italian>
		<Polish>Jeździec (Jeleń)</Polish>
		<Russian>Íàåçäíèê íà îëåíå</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DEERRIDER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Equivalent in style to the Horse Rider units. Strongest base early withdrawal - even battle hardened deer can be skittish creatures that can be tough to KEEP in the battle for long but makes them GREAT at wearing down opponents. They'd be perhaps the best at this get in/get out type of strategy so long as they can do some damage during their short fights.[PARAGRAPH:2]There is no evidence this unit was ever used. It is part of the [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]alternate timeline technologies[COLOR_REVERT]. Technologies that might have been.</English>
		<French>Équivalent en style aux unités Chevaucheurs (à cheval). Retrait précoce de la base la plus forte - même les cerfs endurcis au combat peuvent être des créatures agiles qui peuvent être difficiles à GARDER dans la bataille pendant longtemps, mais les rendent EXCEPTIONNELS pour épuiser leurs adversaires. Ils seraient peut-être les meilleurs dans ce type de stratégie d'entrée / sortie tant qu'ils peuvent faire des dégâts pendant leurs combats courts.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il n'y a aucune preuve que cette unité ait jamais été utilisée. Il fait partie des [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT] technologies de chronologie alternatives [COLOR_REVERT]. Technologies qui auraient pu l'être.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DEER_ARCHER</Tag>
		<English>Deer Archer</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Archer sur Cerf</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Arciere su cervo</Italian>
		<Polish>Jeleni Łucznik</Polish>
		<Russian>Ëó÷íèê íà îëåíå</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DEER_ARCHER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Equivalent in style to the Horse Archer units. Strongest base early withdrawal - even battle hardened deer can be skittish creatures that can be tough to KEEP in the battle for long but makes them GREAT at wearing down opponents. They'd be perhaps the best at this get in/get out type of strategy so long as they can do some damage during their short fights.[PARAGRAPH:2]There is no evidence this unit was ever used. It is part of the [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]alternate timeline technologies[COLOR_REVERT]. Technologies that might have been.</English>
		<French>Équivalent en style aux unités Archers sur cheval. Retrait précoce de la base la plus forte - même les cerfs endurcis au combat peuvent être des créatures agiles qui peuvent être difficiles à GARDER dans la bataille pendant longtemps, mais les rendent EXCEPTIONNELS pour épuiser leurs adversaires. Ils seraient peut-être les meilleurs dans ce type de stratégie d'entrée / sortie tant qu'ils peuvent faire des dégâts pendant leurs combats courts.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il n'y a aucune preuve que cette unité ait jamais été utilisée. Il fait partie des [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Technologies de chronologie alternatives[COLOR_REVERT]. Technologies qui auraient pu exister.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DEER_LIGHT</Tag>
		<English>Light Deer Cavalry</English>
		<French>Cavalier léger cervidé</French>
		<Polish>Lekka Kawaleria (Jeleń)</Polish>
		<Russian>Êàâàëåðèñò íà îëåíå</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DEER_LIGHT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Equivalent style to the Light Horse Cavalry units. Strongest base early withdrawal - even battle hardened deer can be skittish creatures that can be tough to KEEP in the battle for long but makes them GREAT at wearing down opponents. They'd be perhaps the best at this get in/get out type of strategy so long as they can do some damage during their short fights.[PARAGRAPH:2]There is no evidence this unit was ever used. It is part of the [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]alternate timeline technologies[COLOR_REVERT]. Technologies that might have been.</English>
		<French>Style équivalent aux unités de cavaliers légers à cheval. Retrait précoce de la base la plus forte - même les cerfs endurcis au combat peuvent être des créatures agiles qui peuvent être difficiles à GARDER dans la bataille pendant longtemps, mais les rendent EXCEPTIONNELS pour épuiser leurs adversaires. Ils seraient peut-être les meilleurs dans ce type de stratégie d'entrée / sortie tant qu'ils peuvent faire des dégâts pendant leurs combats courts.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il n'y a aucune preuve que cette unité ait jamais été utilisée. Il fait partie des [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Technologies de chronologie alternatives[COLOR_REVERT]. Technologies qui auraient pu exister.</French>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>