<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_ALBERTS2_1</Tag>
		<English>I come in peace to ask for assistance. What do you say?</English>
		<French>Je suis venu en paix vous demander de l'aide. Qu'avez-vous à répondre?</French>
		<German>Ich komme in Frieden und bitte um Unterstützung. Wie lautet Eure Antwort?</German>
		<Italian>Vengo in pace alla ricerca di aiuto. Cosa mi rispondi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vengo en son de paz a pedir ayuda. ¿Qué me decís?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_ALBERTS2_1</Tag>
		<English>I hold the fate of the [CT_EMPIRE] in my hand. Give me what I demand.</English>
		<French>Je tiens le destin de l'[CT_EMPIRE] dans ma main. Donnez-moi ce que j'exige.</French>
		<German>Ich halte das Schicksal vom [CT_EMPIRE:3] in meinen Händen. Gebt mir, was ich verlange.</German>
		<Italian>Ho nelle mani il destino di [CT_EMPIRE]. Dammi ciò che chiedo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tengo el destino del [CT_EMPIRE] en mis manos. Dadme lo que os exijo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_ALBERTS2_1</Tag>
		<English>My town folks are in need, can the [CT_EMPIRE] help?</English>
		<French>Ma personnes est dans le besoin, l'[CT_EMPIRE] peut-il nous aider?</French>
		<German>Mein Stamm ist in Not, kann uns das [CT_EMPIRE:2] helfen?</German>
		<Italian>I miei concittadini hanno bisogno di aiuto, potete aiutarci?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mi puebla está necesitada. ¿Podrá ayudarnos el [CT_EMPIRE]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ALBERTS2_1</Tag>
		<English>Hello. I am [OUR_NAME], Marshall of [OUR_CIV_ADJ] township. I consider you a friend. It is in your best interest that I never change that opinion.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_ALBERTS2_1</Tag>
		<English>It is good to hear from the [CT_EMPIRE]. To what do I owe this honor?</English>
		<French>Quel plaisir d'avoir de vos nouvelles! Que me vaut cet honneur?</French>
		<German>Es ist gut, etwas vom [CT_EMPIRE:3] zu hören. Womit haben wir diese Ehre verdient?</German>
		<Italian>È bello avere notizie da [CT_EMPIRE]. A cosa debbo quest'onore?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es un placer oír al [CT_EMPIRE]. ¿A qué debo este honor?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_ALBERTS2_1</Tag>
		<English>You have started down a path that will lead to your destruction. Feel free to try to explain yourself.</English>
		<French>Vous vous êtes engagé sur la voie qui menera à votre destruction. J'attends vos explications.</French>
		<German>Ihr habt begonnen, einen Pfad zu beschreiten, der zu Eurer Vernichtung führen wird. Wollt Ihr Euch möglicherweise rechtfertigen?</German>
		<Italian>Ti sei avviato lungo un cammino che porterà alla tua distruzione. Prova pure a cercare di spiegarti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Habéis hollado una senda que os llevará a la destrucción. Intentad explicaros como queráis.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_ALBERTS2_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace? Never!</English>
		<French>La paix? Jamais!</French>
		<German>Frieden? Niemals!</German>
		<Italian>Pace? Mai!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Paz? ¡Jamás!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_ALBERTS2_1</Tag>
		<English>You want to talk? It is a little too late for that.</English>
		<French>Vous voulez parler? C'est un peu tard pour ça.</French>
		<German>Ihr wollt reden? Dafür ist es etwas zu spät.</German>
		<Italian>Vuoi parlare? È un po' troppo tardi per farlo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Ahora queréis hablar? Es un poco tarde para eso.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ALBERTS2</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Alberts2</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ALBERTS2_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Alberts2[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Town Marshal[NEWLINE]Lived:[\BOLD] c. March 19, 1848 – January 13, 1929[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Alberts2 was a gambler, Pima County Deputy Sheriff, and Deputy Town Marshal in Tombstone, Arizona, and took part in the Gunfight at the O.K. Corral during which lawmen killed three outlaw Cowboys. Alberts2 moved constantly throughout most of his life from one boomtown to another.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>