<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AUGUSTA</Tag>
		<English>Augusta</English>
		<Russian>Îãàñòà</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_LOUISVILLE</Tag>
		<English>Louisville</English>
		<Russian>Ëóèñâèëë</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MOBILE</Tag>
		<English>Mobile</English>
		<Russian>Ìîáèë</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MONTGOMERY</Tag>
		<English>Montgomery</English>
		<Russian>Ìîíòãîìåðè</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_NASHVILLE</Tag>
		<English>Nashville</English>
		<Russian>Íàøâèëë</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_NORFOLK</Tag>
		<English>Norfolk</English>
		<Russian>Íîðôîëê</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PETERSBURG</Tag>
		<English>Petersburg</English>
		<Russian>Ïèòåðñáåðã</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SHREVEPORT</Tag>
		<English>Shreveport</English>
		<Russian>Øðèâïîðò</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_VICKSBURG</Tag>
		<English>Vicksburg</English>
		<Russian>Âèêñáåðã</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AMERICAN_CONFEDERACY_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Confederate</English>
		<French>Confédérés</French>
		<Polish>Konfederacki</Polish>
		<Russian>êîíôåäåðàòû</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AMERICAN_CONFEDERACY_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Confederate States of America</English>
		<French>Etats Confédérés d'Amérique</French>
		<Polish>Skonfederowane Stany Ameryki</Polish>
		<Russian>ÊØÀ</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AMERICAN_CONFEDERACY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Confederate States were formed on February 4, 1861, by six Southern slave states (South Carolina, Mississippi, Florida, Alabama, Georgia, and Louisiana) after confirmation of the election of Abraham Lincoln as President of the United States. Jefferson Davis was selected as its first President the next day.[PARAGRAPH:2]Texas joined the Confederacy on March 2 and then replaced its governor, Sam Houston, when he refused to take an oath of allegiance to the Confederacy. These seven states seceded from the United States and took control of military/naval installations, ports, and custom houses within their boundaries, triggering the American Civil War.[PARAGRAPH:2]A month after the Confederacy was formed, on March 4, 1861, Abraham Lincoln was sworn in as President of the United States. In his inaugural address, he argued that the Constitution was a more perfect union than the earlier Articles of Confederation and Perpetual Union, that it was a binding contract, and called the secession "legally void". He stated he had no intent to invade southern states, but would use force to maintain possession of federal property and collection of various federal taxes, duties and imposts. His speech closed with a plea for restoration of the bonds of union.[PARAGRAPH:2]On April 12 South Carolina troops fired upon the Federal troops stationed at Fort Sumter in Charleston, South Carolina until the troops surrendered. Following the Battle of Fort Sumter, Lincoln called for all remaining states in the Union to send troops to recapture Sumter and other forts, defend the capital, and preserve the Union. Most Northerners believed that a quick victory for the Union would crush the nascent rebellion, and so Lincoln only called for volunteers for 90 days. This resulted in four more states voting to secede: Virginia, Arkansas, Tennessee, and North Carolina joined the Confederacy for a total of 11. Once Virginia seceded, the Confederate capital was moved from Montgomery, Alabama to Richmond, Virginia.[PARAGRAPH:2]The government of Kentucky remained in the Union after a short-lived attempt at neutrality, but a rival faction from that state was also accepted as members of the Confederacy. A more complex situation surrounds the Missouri Secession, but in any event Missouri was also considered a member of the Confederate States. The number of Confederate states is thus sometimes considered to be 13.[PARAGRAPH:2]The five tribal governments of the Indian Territory - which became Oklahoma in 1907 - also mainly supported the Confederacy. The southern part of New Mexico Territory (including parts of the Gadsden Purchase) joined with the Confederacy as Arizona Territory. These first settlers petitioned the Confederate government for annexation of their lands, prompting an expedition in which territory south of the 34th parallel was governed by the Confederacy. Arizona troops were also officially recognized within the armies of the Confederacy.[PARAGRAPH:2]Preceding his New Mexico Campaign, General Sibley issued a proclamation to the people of New Mexico his intentions of taking possession of the territory in the name of the Confederate States. Confederate troops briefly occupied the territorial capital of Santa Fe between March 13 and April 8, 1862.[PARAGRAPH:2]Not all jurisdictions where slavery was still legal joined the Confederacy. In 1861 martial law was declared in Maryland (the state which borders the U.S. capital, Washington, D.C., on three sides) to block attempts at secession. Delaware, also a slave state, never considered secession, nor did the capital of the U.S., Washington, DC. In 1861, during the war, a unionist rump legislature in Wheeling, Virginia seceded from Virginia, claiming 48 counties, and joined the United States in 1863 as the state of West Virginia, with a constitution that would have gradually abolished slavery. Similar attempts to secede from the Confederacy in parts of other states (notably in eastern Tennessee) were held in check by Confederacy declarations of martial law.[PARAGRAPH:2]The surrender of the Army of Northern Virginia by General Lee at Appomattox Court House on April 9, 1865 is generally taken as the end of the Confederate States. President Davis was captured at Irwinville, Georgia on May 10 and the remaining Confederate armies surrendered by June 1865. The last Confederate flag was hauled down on CSS Shenandoah on November 6, 1865.</English>
		<Polish>Skonfederowane Stany Ameryki (ang. Confederate States of America, CSA) - południowe stany USA, potocznie zwane Konfederacją, próbujące dokonać secesji i biorące udział w wojnie secesyjnej. W latach 1861-1865 stworzyły one własne państwo. Zwycięstwo Abrahama Lincolna w wyborach prezydenckich, w kontekście narastającego od kilkudziesięciu lat konfliktu interesów między uprzemysłowioną Północą a rolniczym Południem USA, wywołało wzburzenie w stanach południowych, których legislatywy poczęły deklarować secesję z Unii. Pierwsza wystąpiła Karolina Południowa 20 grudnia 1860 roku, później dołączyły do niej Missisipi, Alabama, Floryda, Georgia, Luizjana, Teksas, a w trakcie trwania wojny także Wirginia, Tennessee, Arkansas i Karolina Północna. Ponadto w stanach: Missouri i Kentucky nastąpił rozłam i powstały tam zarówno rządy prounijne jak i prokonfederackie. Oficjalnie te dwa stany należały także do Konfederacji, co widać chociażby na przykładzie flagi nowo powstałego państwa, gdzie figurowało 13 gwiazdek, po jednej dla każdego stanu. Ponadto czynione były próby przyłączenia do Konfederacji innych terytoriów, np. Kalifornii. Utworzenie państwa ogłoszono 4 lutego 1861 roku. Cztery dni później uchwalona została konstytucja, w znacznej mierze wzorowana na dotychczasowej ustawie zasadniczej z 17 września 1787 roku. Wprowadzono do niej słowo niewolnicy zamiast dotychczasowego eufemizmu pozostałe osoby (other persons) przy obliczaniu podstaw reprezentacji parlamentarnej Kongresu (niewolnik liczony był za 3/5 człowieka), do zakazu stanowienia ustaw wymierzonych przeciw jednostce lub działających wstecz dodano zakaz podważania instytucji niewolnictwa (law denying or impairing the right of property in negro slaves). Kadencję prezydenta wydłużono z 4 do 6 lat, wprowadzając równocześnie jej jednorazowość. Prezydentem został gen. Jefferson Davis. Tymczasową stolicą stało się Montgomery w Alabamie, a później Richmond w Wirginii. Nowo utworzone państwo liczyło niecałe 2 mln km˛, zamieszkiwanych przez nieco ponad 9 mln ludzi, w tym ok. 4 mln czarnych niewolników i 133 tys. czarnych wyzwoleńców. Przystępując do wojny, Konfederacja liczyła na wsparcie mocarstw europejskich, szczególnie Wielkiej Brytanii i Francji. Kraje te jednakże odmówiły nawet oficjalnego uznania Skonfederowanych Stanów Ameryki; jedynym państwem świata, które to uczyniło, było księstwo Sachsen-Coburg-Gotha.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AMERICAN_CONFEDERACY_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Confederacy</English>
		<French>La Confédération</French>
		<Polish>Konfederacja</Polish>
		<Russian>Êîíôåäåðàòû</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DAVIS</Tag>
		<English>Davis</English>
		<French>J. Davis</French>
		<Russian>Äýâèñ</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DAVIS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Jefferson Davis[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President Confederate States[NEWLINE]Lived:[\BOLD] June 3, 1808 - Dec. 6, 1889[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Jefferson Davis was the only President ever of the Confederate States of America. As such, his largest challenge was to steer the Confederate States to victory over the Union and thus to independence. A native of Christian County, Ky., Davis was born on June 3, 1808. He was raised in Mississipi, attended a Roman Catholic school in Kentucky, and later studied at Transylvania University. He entered West Point at age 16 and graduated at 20, in 1828. He then proceeded to serve on the frontier and later in the Black Hawk War before resigning in 1835 to join the Confederacy.Davis's first wife, Sarah Knox Taylor, daughter of Zachary Taylor, died in September 1835, three months after their marriage. Heartbroken over her death, Davis moved to an isolated Mississippi plantation close to that owned by his brother Joseph. There he spent 10 years managing the plantation and studying. In 1845 he married Varina Howell, and in the same year he was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives as a Democrat. Davis soon left (1846) to command Mississippi troops in the Mexican War. He was prominent in the Battle of Buena Vista (February 1847), where he was wounded. After the war, he was appointed (August 1847) a U.S. senator from Mississippi, but he resigned in 1851 to make an unsuccessful campaign for governor of Mississippi. He was an outstanding secretary of war (1853-57) in the cabinet of Franklin Pierce, and then returned to the Senate, where he became a spokesman for the South.Basically a moderate, Davis favored Mississippi's secession and hoped to be made commander of the Southern army. Instead, he was elected president of the Confederacy and inaugurated on Feb. 18, 1861. For the next 4 years Davis gave his complete devotion to the Southern cause, but he was far from an ideal chief executive. He was in poor health (probably largely psychosomatic) for much of the war. He discouraged disagreement, and, as a result, many of those close to him were 'Yes-men'. He sometimes insisted on keeping loyal friends in office despite overwhelming evidence of their incompetence. Regarding all opposition as directed at him personally, he wasted valuable time and energy quarreling over unimportant matters, and he was unwilling to delegate authority. He has also been accused of neglecting the civil aspects of government to concentrate on the military.Many say Davis's greatest weakness was his inability to get along well with people. He was stiff and formal, unwilling to concede small points to win large objectives. As one Confederate official noted in 1864, Davis seemed "to possess a most unenviable facility for converting friends into enemies." As a result, he quarreled long and often with Confederate congressmen, generals, governors, and the press.Largely because of these limitations, Davis lacked popular appeal. He was unable to win wholehearted cooperation for such unpopular but necessary measures as conscription, the impressment of supplies, and suspension of the writ of habeas corpus. Nor was he able to deal with such problems as refugees, inflation, and the shortage of necessities. He became increasingly unpopular as the war continued.In fairness, it must be said that the winning of Southern independence was probably impossible and that Davis did not receive the support that he should have. Much of the opposition to him came from short-sighted men who put personal status or their state's interests above the cause of the Confederacy, or from honest men who were unable to understand that successful modern war demands the sacrifice of some state rights and personal liberties to the common cause.[PARAGRAPH:1]In April 1865, as the Confederacy was collapsing, Davis fled from Richmond, Va., hoping to continue the war from the Deep South or from west of the Mississippi, or to organize a government in exile. On May 10 he was captured by Federal cavalrymen in southern Georgia. For 2 years he was held in prison and threatened with trial for treason. His suffering during his imprisonment won him the affection of the Southern people, who came to regard him as a martyr to their lost cause.Although indicted, Davis was never brought to trial, and he was released on bond in 1867. His subsequent ventures into business were unsuccessful. Believing that he had done nothing to be pardoned for, he refused to seek a pardon and remained ineligible for public office. Davis retired to Beauvoir (now in Biloxi, Miss.), an estate that he inherited from a generous family friend, and devoted himself to writing in defense of the South in general and himself in particular. His Rise and Fall of the Confederate Government was published in 1881. Davis died on Dec. 6, 1889, in New Orleans.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Jefferson Davis[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prezydent Skonfederowanych Stanów[NEWLINE]Żył:[\BOLD] 3 Czerwca 1808 - 6 Grudnia 1889[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Cztery dni po swojej rezygnacji, Davis został mianowany generał majorem wojsk Missisipi, po czym wziął udział w konwencji stanów południowych, które wystąpiły z Unii. W czasie jej trwania, 9 lutego 1861 został obrany tymczasowym prezydentem nowo utworzonych Skonfederowanych Stanów Ameryki, na wniosek stanu Alabama. Urząd ten objął 18 lutego. Wkrótce powołał komisję pokojową, mającą rozstrzygnąć kwestie sporne między Konfederacją a Unią. Z drugiej strony, nakazał generałowi Pierre G.T. Beauregardowi sprowadzić wojska konfederackie w pobliże Charleston w Południowej Karolinie. W międzyczasie, zaczęta atakiem na Fort Sumter 12 kwietnia 1861, wybuchła amerykańska krwawa i długotrwała wojna secesyjna. W maju 1861 rząd Konfederacji z prezydentem przeniósł się do Richmond w stanie Wirginia. 6 listopada 1861 Davis został wybrany na 6-letnią kadencję jako Prezydent Skonfederowanych Stanów Ameryki. Nieprzypadkowo zaprzysiężenie miało miejsce dopiero 1862 r. w rocznicę urodzin Waszyngtona. Pełnił ten urząd do końca istnienia państwa. 31 maja wyznaczył generała Roberta Lee na dowódcę głównej Armii Północnej Wirginii. Przez cały okres swej prezydentury Davis musiał zmagać się z popularną na Południu ideą większej autonomii poszczególnych stanów. Davis uważał ją za szczególnie szkodliwą w warunkach tak ciężkiej wojny ze stanami Północy. Preferował więc istnienie scentralizowanego rządu konfederacji i łamał opór gubernatorów stanowych. 3 kwietnia 1865, gdy wojska Unii zwyciężające na całym froncie, zagroziły zdobyciem Richmond, Davis z rządem uciekł do Danville w stanie Wirginia, następnie do Greensboro w Północnej Karolinie. 10 maja 1865 został ujęty w okolicach miejscowości Irwinsville w stanie Georgia. Spędził dwa lata w areszcie w ciężkich warunkach. Dopiero w maju 1866 postawiono mu zarzut zdrady stanu. W 1867 roku został jednak zwolniony za poręczeniem grupy szanowanych obywateli południowych i północnych stanów. Ostatecznie w lutym 1869 odstąpiono od oskarżenia. Został m.in. prezesem kompanii ubezpieczeń na życie. Odwiedzał kilka razy Europę. W tym okresie napisał dzieło "Powstanie i upadek rządu Konfederacji" (The Rise and Fall of the Confederate Government) oraz, tuż przed śmiercią, "Krótką historię Skonfederowanych Stanów Ameryki" (A Short History of the Confederate States of America). Zmarł 6 grudnia 1889 w Nowym Orleanie. Pochowano go na cmentarzu Hollywood emetery w Richmond (Wirginia).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HOOD</Tag>
		<English>Hood</English>
		<French>J. Hood</French>
		<Russian>Õóä</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HOOD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]John Bell Hood[\H1][NEWLINE]Lived: June 29, 1831 - August 30, 1879[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]was a Confederate general during the American Civil War. Hood had a reputation for bravery and aggressiveness that sometimes bordered on recklessness. Arguably one of the best brigade and division commanders in the Confederate States Army, Hood became increasingly ineffective as he was promoted to lead larger, independent commands, and his career was marred by his decisive defeats leading an army in the Atlanta Campaign and the Franklin-Nashville Campaign.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]John Bell Hood[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Konfederacki generał z okresu wojny secesyjnej. Zyskał sobie reputację odważnego i brawurowego, a czasem wręcz lekkomyślnego dowódcy. Był jednym z najlepszych wodzów brygad i dywizji, jednakże okazał się wybitnie nieefektywny jako głowa większych formacji, co udowodnił dowodząc armią Tennessee podczas kampanii atlanckiej oraz kampanii Franklin-Nashville.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JACKSON</Tag>
		<English>Jackson</English>
		<Russian>Äæåêñîí</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JACKSON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Thomas Jonathan "Stonewall" Jackson[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]General Confederate States[NEWLINE]Lived:[\BOLD] January 21, 1824, May 10, 1863[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]was a Confederate general during the American Civil War, and probably the most revered Confederate commander after General Robert E. Lee. He is most famous for his audacious Valley Campaign of 1862 and as a corps commander in the Army of Northern Virginia under Robert E. Lee. His own troops accidentally shot him at the Battle of Chancellorsville, which the general survived, albeit with the loss of an arm to amputation. However, he died of complications of pneumonia several days later.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Thomas Jonathan "Stonewall" Jackson[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Generał Skonfederowanych Stanów[NEWLINE]Żył:[\BOLD] 21 Stycznia 1824 - 10 Maja 1863[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Konfederacki generał; brał udział w wojnie secesyjnej; prawdopodobnie najbardziej znany dowódca Południa, po generale Robercie E. Lee. Brał udział w kampanii w dolinie Shenandoah jako dowódca korpusu Armii Północnej Wirginii w 1862. Został postrzelony przypadkowo przez własnych ludzi pod Chancellorsville - przeżył, lecz amputowano mu rękę. Zmarł na zapalenie płuc osiem dni później. Jego śmierć była ciosem dla dowództwa Konfederacji, wpływając nie tylko na efektywność strategiczną, ale i morale zarówno wojsk, jak i ludności cywilnej. Historycy wojskowi uważają Jacksona za jednego z bardziej uzdolnionych przywódców w historii USA. Jego działania podczas kampanii w dolinie Shenandoah oraz działania prowadzące do zwyciężenia zaskoczonej armii federalnej pod Chancellorsville są studiowane na całym świecie i brane jako przykład innowacyjnego oraz odważnego dowództwa. Jego zasługi nie kończą się jednak na tym epizodzie: I bitwa nad Bull Run (gdzie otrzymał swój przydomek "Stonewall", czyli "Kamienny Mur"), II bitwa nad Bull Run, Antietam czy Fredericksburg. Jackson nie odnosił ciągłych sukcesów jako wódz, co można wywnioskować ze słabej postawy w bitwach siedmiodniowych oraz pod Richmond w 1862 r.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LEE</Tag>
		<English>Lee</English>
		<French>R. Lee</French>
		<Russian>Ëè</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LEE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Robert E. Lee[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]General[NEWLINE]Lived:[\BOLD] 1807-1870[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]US military leader, Confederate commander in the American Civil War, and military strategist. In 1859 he suppressed John Brown's raid on Harper's Ferry. Lee had freed his own slaves long before the war began, and he was opposed to secession, however his devotion to his native Virginia led him to join the Confederacy. At the outbreak of war he became military adviser to Jefferson Davis, president of the Confederacy, and in 1862 commander of the Army of Northern Virginia. Lee actually had been offered command of the Union armies, but he resigned his commission to return to Virginia. During 1862-63 he made several raids into Northern territory but after his defeat at Gettysburg was compelled to take the defensive; he surrendered 1865 at Appomattox.[PARAGRAPH:1]Lee graduated from West Point and distinguished himself in the Mexican War 1846-48. In 1861 he joined the army of the Confederacy of Southern states; in 1862 he received the command of the Army of Northern Virginia and won the Seven Days' Battle defending Richmond, Virginia, the Confederate capital, against General McClellan's Union forces. In 1863 Lee won victories at Fredericksburg and Chancellorsville, both in Virginia, and in 1864 at Cold Harbor, Virginia, but was besieged in Petersburg, Virginia, June 1864-April 1865. He surrendered to General Grant on April 9, 1865, at Appomattox Courthouse. Following the war he was paroled and served as president of Washington College (now Washington and Lee University). His home had been seized by Union forces and now is part of Arlington National Cemetery.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Robert E. Lee[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Generał[NEWLINE]Żył:[\BOLD] 1807-1870[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]23 kwietnia został głównodowodzącym armii i floty Wirginii i objął pod swą komendę Armię Północnej Wirginii. Przez rok był doradcą wojskowym prezydenta CSA Jeffersona Davisa. W lutym 1865 został wodzem naczelnym wszystkich sił wojskowych Konfederacji. Dwa miesiące później był zmuszony poddać się gen. Ulyssesowi S. Grantowi w miejscowości Appomattox Court House, co stanowiło zakończenie długotrwałych zmagań Północy i Południa. Najważniejsze bitwy, w których dowodził, to bitwa siedmiodniowa, bitwa nad Antietam, II bitwa nad Bull Run, Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, bitwa pod Gettysburgiem, Wilderness, Spotsylvania, Cold Harbour i Petersburg (oblężenie). Pod koniec wojny z powodzeniem (podobnie jak gen. J.E. Johnston) wprowadził taktykę umocnień polowych i walki w okopach, dzięki czemu przez wiele miesięcy blokował armię Granta oblegającą Petersburg. Będąc jednym z najwyższych dowódców Konfederacji, nie odsuwał od walki swych synów: W.H.F. Lee, Robina R. Lee - dowódców kawalerii. Geniusz wojskowy Lee uległ przewadze zasobów ludzkich i przemysłowych, które posiadała Unia. Prowadzone przez niego kampanie są przedmiotem badań we wszystkich akademiach wojskowych jako modelowa strategia i taktyka. Miał zdolność przewidywania ruchów swoich przeciwników i wykorzystywania ich słabości. Wykorzystywał umiejętnie linie zaopatrzeniowe wewnątrz własnego terytorium, jednocześnie osłaniając je frontem zwróconym na wrogie stanowiska. Dzięki temu jego posiłki, transport mogły docierać do punktu przeznaczenia najkrótszymi drogami. Mistrzowsko posługiwał się umocnieniami polowymi, ale też i prowadził działania manewrowe. Jego taktyka polegała na związaniu sił przeciwnika małymi oddziałami ukrytymi za umocnieniami, gdy główne siły próbowały oskrzydlić przeciwnika albo atakować jego mniejsze oddziały. Tym sposobem walki wyprzedzał swoje czasy o wiele lat. A strategia ta została dopiero w pełni zastosowana w XX wieku. Wiele zawdzięczał także swym utalentowanym podkomendnym: Thomasowi Stonewall Jacksonowi, Jamesowi L. Longstreetowi czy A.P. Hillowi.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LONGSTREET</Tag>
		<English>Longstreet</English>
		<French>J. Longstreet</French>
		<Russian>Ëîíãñòðèò</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LONGSTREET_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]James Longstreet[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]General Confederate States[NEWLINE]Lived:[\BOLD] January 8, 1821 – January 2, 1904[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]He was one of the foremost Confederate generals of the American Civil War and the principal subordinate to General Robert E. Lee, who called him his "Old War Horse." He served under Lee as a corps commander for many of the famous battles fought by the Army of Northern Virginia in the Eastern Theater, but also with Gen. Braxton Bragg in the Army of Tennessee in the Western Theater. Biographer and historian Jeffry D. Wert wrote that "Longstreet... was the finest corps commander in the Army of Northern Virginia; in fact, he was arguably the best corps commander in the conflict on either side."</English>
		<Polish>[H1]James Longstreet[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Generał Skonfederowanych Stanów[NEWLINE]Żył:[\BOLD]1821 - 1904[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Po wybuchu wojny domowej opowiedział się po stronie Konfederacji. Wystąpił w czerwcu 1861 z Armii Federalnej i walczył w Armii Północnej Wirginii pod generałem Robertem Lee i Armii Tennessee pod generałem Braxtonem Braggiem. Uważany za jednego z najlepszych dowódców korpusów w czasie wojny. Jego umiejętności dowódcze przyczyniły się do zwycięstw Konfederacji w bitwach pod Bull Run, Fredericksburgiem i Chickamauga. Wiele kontrowersji wzbudzają natomiast jego działania w bitwie pod Gettysburgiem, gdzie m.in. otwarcie kwestionował decyzje taktyczne generała Lee.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>