<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CETSHWAYO_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. We seek peace but will not give up strength. No partridge scratches the ground in search of food for another.</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, [CT_NAME]. Nous cherchons la paix, mais nous ne renoncerons pas à la force si nécessaire. Aucun perdrix de gratte le sol en quête de nourriture pour une autre.</French>
		<German>Grüße, [CT_NAME]. Wir suchen den Frieden aber werden unsere Stärke nicht aufgeben. Ein Rebhuhn scharrt den Boden auf der Suche nach Nahrung für sich, nicht für andere.</German>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Buscamos la paz pero no renunciamos a la fuerza. Ninguna perdiz escarba el terreno en busca de comida para otra.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Witam, [CT_NAME]. Szukamy pokoju, ale nie wyrzekniemy się siły. Kaźda kuropatwa szuka jedzenia dla siebie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CETSHWAYO</Tag>
		<English>Cetshwayo</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CETSHWAYO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Cetshwayo kaMpande[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of the Zulu [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1826 - 1884[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Cetshwayo was the king of the Zulu nation from 1872 to 1879 and their leader during the Zulu War. His name has also been transliterated as Cetawayo, Cetewayo, Cetywajo and Ketchwayo. Cetshwayo was born a son of Zulu king Mpande, who was a half-brother of Zulu king Shaka. In 1856 he defeated and killed in battle his younger brother Mbuyazi, Mpande's favorite, and became the effective ruler of Zulu tribe. However, he did not really ascend to the throne because his father was still alive.[PARAGRAPH:1]His other brother Umtonga was still a potential rival and he knew it. In 1861 Umtonga fled to the Boers' side of the border and Cetshwayo had to make deals with the Boers to get him back. In 1865 Umtonga did the same thing and apparently made Cetshwayo think that Umtonga could try replace him the similar way his father had replaced his predecessor Dingaan. [PARAGRAPH:1]Mpande died in 1873 and Cetshwayo became king on 1 September. As was customary he created a new capital for the nation and called it Ulundi (the high place). He expanded his army and readopted many methods of Shaka. He also equipped his impis with muskets. He banished European missionaries from his land. He might have incensed other native African peoples to rebel against Boers in Transvaal. [PARAGRAPH:1]In 1878 Sir Henry Bartle Frere, British Commissioner for South Africa, began to demand reparations for border infractions. They mainly angered Cetshwayo who kept his calm until Frere demanded that he should effectively disband his army. His refusal lead to Zulu War in 1879. After initial defeats, such as the infamous Battle of Isandlwana, the British eventually began to gain victories. After Cetshwayo's capital Ulundi was captured and torched on July 4 he was deposed and exiled to London, returning only in 1883. [PARAGRAPH:1]By 1882 differences between two Zulu factions - pro-Cetshwayo uSsutus and three rival chiefs UZibhebhu - had erupted into a blood feuds and civil war. In 1883, the British tried to restore Cetshwayo to rule at least part of his previous territory but the attempt failed. Chief UZibhebhu, started a war contesting the succession - with the aid of Boer cavalry mercenaries - and on July 22, 1883 he attacked Cetshwayo's new kraal in Ulundi. Cetshwayo was wounded but escaped to Nkandla forest. After pleas from the Resident Commissioner, Sir Melmoth Osborn, the king moved to Eshowe, where he died a few months later, possibly poisoned. His body was buried within sight of the forest, to the south near Nkunzane River. The remains of the wagon which carried his corpse to the site was placed on the grave, and its remains may be seen at Ondini Museum, near Ulundi. [PARAGRAPH:1]He died in February 1884 as the last king of an independent Zulu nation. Cetshwayo's son Dinizulu, as heir to the throne, was proclaimed king on 20 May 1884, supported by (other) Boer mercenaries.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Cetshwayo kaMpande[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Król Zulusów [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył: [\BOLD]1826 - 1884[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]ostatni władca niepodległego państwa Zulusów w latach 1872 - 1879, syn Mpande, kuzyn Czaki, ojciec Dinuzulu. Zgodnie z tradycją został królem po śmierci swego ojca w 1872 r. Był bardzo ceniony za umiejętność rządzenia oraz odwagę[potrzebne zródło]. Potrafił długo utrzymać niezaleźność swego państwa, broniąc go przed atakami Transwalu i Brytyjczyków. W 1877 r. Wielka Brytania zaanektowała Transwal i dwa lata pózniej wszczęli pierwszą wojnę z Zulusami. Mimo początkowych sukcesów oddziałów zuluskich Brytyjczycy pokonali je i zajęli państwo Zulusów. Cetshwayo zesłano do Kapsztadu, a jego państwo zostało podzielone na 13 niezaleźnych wodzostw. W 1882 r. przybył do Londynu i przekonał członków nowego rządu liberałów o swojej probrytyjskiej postawie, w efekcie czego w styczniu 1883 r. przywrócono go na tron. Decyzja ta nie spodobała się ani Brytyjczykom z południa Afryki, ani teź zuluskim przeciwnikom władzy, co doprowadziło do wybuchu wojny domowej w państwie Zulusów. Zakończyła się ona klęską Cetshwayo, który zmuszony został do ucieczki na tereny kontrolowane przez Natal. Tam zmarł na atak serca.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
