<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>Hmmm... erm, [CT_NAME], the great [OUR_EMPIRE] would like to ask a little favor. Helping the Middle Kingdom is in itself a great thing for a barbarian leader to do, showing his capability for civilization.</English>
		<French>Hmmm... erm, [CT_NAME], le grand [OUR_EMPIRE] voudrais demander une petite faveur. Aider l'Empire du Milieu est en soi une bonne chose pour un chef barbare, car il montre sa capacité à devenir civilisé.</French>
		<Polish>Hmmm... erm, [CT_NAME], Wielkie Imperium [OUR_EMPIRE] chciało by poprosić o małą przysługę. Państwo Srodka jest samo w sobie czymś niesamowitym dla barbarzyńcy takiego jak Ty.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>It is, unfortunately, time to pay tribute, [CT_NAME]. The Middle Kingdom doesn't like procrastinators.</English>
		<French>Il est malheureusement temps de payer le tribut, [CT_NAME]. L'Empire du Milieu n'aime pas la procrastination.</French>
		<Polish>Nadszedł czas, niestety, na zapłaceniu trybutu, [CT_NAME]. Państwo Srodka nienawidzi spóźnialskich.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>There is no shame in showing a little charity, [CT_NAME]. On the contrary, it is a very honorable thing for a ruler to do.</English>
		<French>Il n'y a aucune honte à montrer un peu de charité, [CT_NAME]. Au contraire, c'est une chose très honorable pour un dirigeant.</French>
		<Polish>Nie ma wstydu w okazaniu odrobiny miłosierdzia, [CT_NAME]. Wręcz przeciwnie, to jest dla każdego władcy rzecz honorowa.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME]! I am the supreme emperor, [OUR_NAME], son of heaven, ruler of the glorious Middle Kingdom, [OUR_CIV_SHORT]! You who come into our land - are you a civilized man, or a barbarian?</English>
		<French>[CT_NAME]! Je suis l'Empereur suprême, [OUR_NAME], Fils du ciel, dirigeant du glorieux Empire du Milieu, [OUR_CIV_SHORT]! Toi qui est venu en mes terres - es-tu un homme civilisé, ou un barbare?</French>
		<Polish>[CT_NAME]! Jestem najważniejszym z władców, [OUR_NAME], synem nieba, władcą wspaniałego Państwa Srodka, [OUR_CIV_SHORT]! Ty, który przybywasz na nasze ziemie - jesteś osobą cywilizowaną, czy może barbarzyńcą?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TAIZONG_2</Tag>
		<English>Greetings [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], emperor of all the lands below the heavens. With absolute power over numberless minions, do you dare hurt the divine ruler of mighty [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</English>
		<French>Salutations [CT_NAME]. Je suis [OUR_NAME], empereur de toutes les terres au-dessous des cieux. Avec le pouvoir absolu sur des foules innombrables, oseras-tu défie le dirigeant divin des puissants  [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</French>
		<German>Grüße [CT_NAME]. Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Kaiser aller Länder unterhalb der Himmel. Mit absoluter Macht über zahllosen Günstlingen, verletzen Sie Herausforderung die göttliche Lehre von mächtigem [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</German>
		<Italian>Saluti [CT_NAME]. Sono [OUR_NAME], imperatore di tutte le terre sotto i cieli. Con potere assoluto sopra i servi numberless, sfida danneggiate il righello divino di vigoroso [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos [CT_NAME]. Estoy [OUR_NAME], emperador de todas las tierras debajo de los cielos. ¿Con poder absoluto sobre subordinados innumerables, usted atrevimiento lastima la regla divina de poderoso [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Witam [CT_NAME]. Jestem [OUR_NAME], cesarzem wszystkich ziem podległych niebiosom. Posiadając władzę absolutną nad niezliczonymi rzeszami poddanych, czy odważysz się obrazić boskiego władcę [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME]! An auspicious time to visit... how are you doing? Your empire? Your spouse? Your heirs? Your economy? Well, all of mine are doing quite well.</English>
		<French>[CT_NAME]! Un moment propice pour une visite... comment allez-vous? Votre empire? Votre conjoint? Vos héritiers? Votre économie? Eh bien, de mon côté, tout se porte très bien.</French>
		<Polish>[CT_NAME]! Pomyślny czas na wizytę... co porabiasz? Jak tam Twoje imperium? A twója żona? Dzieci? A finanse? No, u mnie wszystko w porządku.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>With history as a mirror, one can understand the rise and fall of a nation, [CT_NAME]... and from what I can see, we can only hope the fall of yours comes soon.</English>
		<French>Avec l'histoire comme un miroir, on peut comprendre l'ascension et la chute d'une nation, [CT_NAME]... et à partir de ce que je vois, nous ne pouvons qu'espérer que la chute de la vôtre arrive bientôt.</French>
		<Polish>Historia jest zwierciadłem, jeden potrafi zrozumieć rozwój i upadek imperiów, [CT_NAME]... i z tego co widzę, miejmy nadzieję, że upadek Twojego nadziejedzie wkrótce.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>I shall not make peace with barbarians such as you, [CT_NAME], and your dirt-ragged [CT_CIV_ADJ], until you learn how to play civilization the RIGHT way!</English>
		<French>Je ne vais pas faire la paix avec les barbares comme vous, [CT_NAME], et vos [CT_CIV_ADJ] en haillons, jusqu'à ce que vous apprendre à jouer à civilisation dans le droit chemin!</French>
		<Polish>Nie zawieram pokoju z barbarzyńcami Twojego pokroju, [CT_NAME], i Twoim szmatławym kraikiem, zanim nie nauczycie się jak grać w cywilizację we właściwy sposób!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>You filthy barbarian. What right have you to talk with me?</English>
		<French>Immonde barbare. De quel droit ose-tu parler avec moi?</French>
		<Polish>Ty przebrzydły barbarzyńco. Jakim prawem do mnie przemawiasz?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_TAIZONG</Tag>
		<English>Taizong</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_TAIZONG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Taizong of Tang[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]2nd Emperor of the Tang Dynasty[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]599 - 649 CE[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Emperor Taizong of Tang (January 23, 599 – July 10, 649), personal name Li Shìmín, was the second emperor of the Tang Dynasty of China, ruling from 626 to 649. As he encouraged his father, Li Yuan (later Emperor Gaozu) to rise against Sui Dynasty rule at Taiyuan in 617 and subsequently defeated several of his most important rivals, he was ceremonially regarded as a cofounder of the dynasty along with Emperor Gaozu. He is typically considered one of the greatest, if not the greatest, emperor in all of Chinese history. Throughout the rest of Chinese history, Emperor Taizong's reign was regarded as the exemplary model against which all other emperors were measured, and his "Reign of Zhen'guan" was considered a golden age of Chinese history and required study for future crown princes. During his reign, Tang China flourished economically and militarily. For more than a century after his death, Tang China enjoyed peace and prosperity. In 630, Emperor Taizong sent his general Li Jing against Eastern Tujue -- to which Tang had once submitted -- defeating and capturing its Jiali Khan Ashina Duobi and destroying Eastern Tujue power. This made Tang the dominant power in East and Central Asia, and Emperor Taizong subsequently took the title of Tian Kehan ("Heavenly Khan"). Emperor Taizong was, in opposition to nobility of the time, a frank rationalist, openly laughing of superstitions and heaven's claimed signs, and modifying important rites in order to ease agricultural labour. The modern Chinese historian Bo Yang opined that Emperor Taizong achieved greatness by accepting criticism that others would find difficult to accept and trying hard not to abuse his absolute power (using Emperor Yang of Sui as a negative example), as well as employing capable chancellors Fang Xuanling, Du Ruhui, and Wei Zheng. Emperor Taizong's wife Empress Zhangsun served as a capable assistant to him as well.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Taizong z Tang[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Drug Cesarz z Dynastii Tang[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył: [\BOLD]599 - 649 n.e.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Tang Taizong - jego osobiste imię to Li Shěmin, był drugim cesarzem z chińskiej dynastii Tang, panującym od 626 do 649. Na ogół jest uważany za jednego z największych, o ile nie największego cesarza w całej chińskiej historii. Stanowił on miarę, do której porównywano wszystkich innych cesarzy. Za czasów jego rządów Chiny Tangów prosperowały ekonomicznie i militarnie. Pośmiertnie otrzymał imię Wen Huangdi.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
