<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PEDRO_II_1</Tag>
		<English>I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Shall we discuss our future together? If one does not look ahead, one remains behind.</English>
		<Italian>Io sono [OUR_NAME] dell'[OUR_EMPIRE]. Vogliamo discutere del nostro futuro insieme? Se non si guarda avanti, si rimane indietro.</Italian>
		<Polish>Jestem [OUR_NAME] z [OUR_EMPIRE]. Czy możemy przedyskutować naszą wspólną przyszłość?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PEDRO_II</Tag>
		<English>Dom Pedro II</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PEDRO_II_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Dom Pedro II[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of Brazil[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1825 - 1891[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]When he was a boy of five, Pedro became the emperor of Brazil. His father Pedro I abdicated the throne on April 7, 1831, after violent protests in Brazil against his careless handling of internal affairs, to fight a civil war in Portugal. The aim of the war in Portugal was to restore the throne of Portugal to Maria II, older sister of Pedro II. As a result of caring for his children's interests, in 1834, the warrior father Pedro I had a daughter of 15 on the throne of Portugal and a son of 9 Pedro II who was emperor of Brazil.[PARAGRAPH:1]Pedro II ruled Brazil for 49 years under the slogan "União e Indústria" (Union and Industry). The period saw the beginnings of industrialization, the first paved roads, the first steam-engine railway, a submarine telegraphy cable, and the introduction of the telephone. Liberal in outlook, Pedro II took steps to end slavery; the final abolition edict, the Golden Law, was signed in his absence by his daughter Princess Isabel, on May 13, 1888. Pedro II also took pains to learn Guarani, the most widely spoken indigenous language in nineteenth-century Brazil. He was widely respected by Brazilians of all social levels as an enlightened monarch who ruled in a principled, rational, moderate fashion.[PARAGRAPH:1]Though reputed to be an enlightened monarch, Pedro II nonetheless retained extensive power over the Brazilian government. Under the Brazilian Constitution of 1824, the emperor possessed Poder Moderator (Moderating Power), i.e. the power to temper the will of Brazil's representative government. In practice, this meant that Pedro II had the right to veto legislation, dissolve the lower house of the legislature (the only one that was elected), and call new elections at his pleasure. Pedro II generally respected the wishes of the electorate, but his favoritism towards the Conservative party in 1868 marred his reputation for even-handedness. The unexpectedly long and costly Paraguayan War of 1865-1870 also diminished his popularity.[PARAGRAPH:1]Pedro II died on December 5, 1891 in Paris, France. His and his wife's remains were taken to Brazil in 1922, and were reburied in Petropolis, their former summer residence, in 1939.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Dom Pedro II[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Cesarz Brazylii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 1825 - 1891[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Ostatni cesarz Brazylii, tam urodzony, co czyni go jedynym "rodowitym" monarchą brazylijskim. Piotr II rządził Brazylią przez 49 lat, jego mottem był: "Uniao e Industria" ("Unia i przemysł"). W okresie tym Brazylia wkroczyła na drogę państwa przemysłowego. Budowano pierwsze utwardzone drogi, koleje, kable podmorskie, fabryki. Wystąpiło także niekorzystne zjawisko uzależniania się gospodarki brazylijskiej od eksportu kawy, której wahania cenowe powodowały wielokrotnie kryzysy ekonomiczne w kraju. Prowadził ryzykowną politykę wewnętrzną, z powodzeniem kontrolując rywalizujące ze sobą regiony, poszerzając zakres władzy swego rządu oraz zapewniając cesarstwu długotrwałą stabilizację. Na arenie międzynarodowej prowadził działania znacznie bardziej kontrowersyjne, ingerując w politykę Argentyny, Paragwaju oraz Urugwaju, co doprowadziło do wybuchu trzech wojen w latach 1851-1870. Celem pierwszej (trwającej w 1851) było uzyskanie przez Brazylię swobodnego dostępu do strategicznej rzeki La Plata. Po szybkim zwycięstwie zyskał przychylny sobie rząd u południowego sąsiada, z którym zawarł później przymierze, by obalić argentyńskiego dyktatora Juana Manuela Rosasa (ta wojna również zakończyła się dla cesarza pomyślnie). Drugie wtargnięcie do Urugwaju (1864) doprowadziło do wybuchu długotrwałego konfliktu z Paragwajem. Podjął także pierwsze kroki w celu zniesienia niewolnictwa, które zostało ostatecznie zniesione dopiero w 1888 na mocy edyktu, który podpisała podczas jego nieobecności jego córka Izabela. Liberalizm cesarza wywołał jednak konflikt z bardziej konserwatywną częścią brazylijskiego społeczeństwa. W tym samym czasie bardziej radykalni liberałowie byli niezadowoleni z niezbyt zdecydowanych działań cesarza w celu zmodernizowania kraju. Mimo tego, że Piotr był bardzo lubiany przez swój naród, został zmuszony do ustąpienia z tronu przez juntę wojskową 15 listopada 1889 i wraz z rodziną udał się na wygnanie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>