<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SENNACHERIB_1</Tag>
		<English>Fear the goat from the front, the horse from the rear and man from all sides, [CT_NAME]. Now let us drink wine together!</English>
		<French>Méfiez-vous de la chèvre de face, du cheval de l'arrière et de l'homme de tous les côtés, [CT_NAME]. Maintenant, buvons un coup ensemble!</French>
		<Polish>Obawiaj się kozy z przodu, konia z tyłu, a człowieka z każdej strony, [CT_NAME]. A teraz napijmy się razem wina!</Polish>
		<Russian>Опасайтесь козла спереди, лошадь сзади и человека со всех сторон, [CT_NAME]. А теперь давайте вместе отведаем вина!</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SENNACHERIB</Tag>
		<English>Sennacherib</English>
		<Polish>Sennacheryb</Polish>
		<Russian>Ñèíàõõåðèá</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SENNACHERIB_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Sennacharib[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Assyria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ruled:[\BOLD] c. 704 - 681 BC[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Sennacherib was the son of Sargon II, whom he succeeded on the throne of Assyria. As a crown prince, Sennacherib was placed in charge of the empire while his father Sargon II was on campaign. Unlike his predecessors, the reign of Sennacherib was not marked as much by military campaigns as by building projects. After the violent death of Sargon, Sennacherib encountered some problems establishing his power. Still, he was able to carry out building projects. He moved the capital from his father's new city Dur-Sharrukin to the old city of Nineveh. It is striking that he not only left his father's city but also doesn’t name him in any official inscription.[PARAGRAPH:1]During his reign Sennacherib encountered various problems with Babylonia. His first campaign took place in 703 BC against Marduk-apla-iddina II who had seized the throne of Babylon and gathered an alliance supported by Chaldeans, Aramaeans, and Elam. We can date the visit of Babylonian ambassadors to Hezekiah of Judah in this period. The allies wanted to make use of the unrest that arose at the accession of Sennacherib. Sennacherib split his army and had one part attack the stationed enemy at Kish while he and the rest of the army proceeded to capture the city Cutha. After that was done the king returned swiftly to aid the rest of his army. The rebellion was defeated and Marduk-apla-iddina II fled. Babylon was taken, and its palace plundered but its citizens were left unharmed. The Assyrians searched for Marduk-apla-iddina II, especially in the southern marshes, but he was not found.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sennacherib first recounts several of his previous victories, and how his enemies had become overwhelmed by his presence. He was able to do this to Great Sidon, Little Sidon, Bit-Zitti, Zaribtu, Mahalliba, Ushu, Akzib and Akko. After taking each of these cities, Sennacherib installed a puppet leader named Ethbaal as ruler over the entire region. Sennacherib then turned his attention to Beth-Dagon, Joppa, Banai-Barqa, and Azjuru, cities that were ruled by Sidqia and also fell to Sennacherib.[PARAGRAPH:1]Egypt and Nubia then came to the aid of the stricken cities. Sennacherib defeated the Egyptians and, by his own account, single-handedly captured the Egyptian and Nubian charioteers. Sennacherib captured and sacked several other cities, including Lachish (the second most-strongly fortified city in the Kingdom of Judah). He punished the "criminal" citizens of the cities, and he reinstalled Padi, their leader, who had been held as a hostage in Jerusalem.[PARAGRAPH:1]During Sennacherib's reign, Nineveh evolved into the leading Metropolis of the empire. His building projects started almost as soon as he became king. Already in 703 BC he had built a palace complete with park and artificial irrigation he called his new home ‘The palace without rival’. For this ambitious project an old palace was torn down to make more room. In addition to his own large gardens, several small gardens were made for the citizens of Nineveh. He also constructed the first ever aqueduct, at Jerwan in 690 BCE, which supplied the large demand of water in Nineveh. The narrow alleys and squares of Nineveh were cleaned up and enlarged, and a royal road and avenue were constructed, which crossed a bridge on its approach to the park gate and which was lined on both sides with stelae. Temples were restored and built during his reign, as is the duty of the king. Most notable is his work on the Assur (god) and the new year (Akitu) temples. He also expanded the city defences which included a moat surrounding the city walls. Some of his city walls have been restored and can still be seen nowadays. The labour for his giant building project was performed by people of Que, Cilicia, Philistia, Tyre, and Chaldeans, Aramaeans, and Mannaeans who were there involuntarily.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Sennacheryb[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Król Asyrii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rządził:[\BOLD] ok. 704 - 681 p.n.e.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Większość swego życia spędził na walce z licznymi wrogami Asyrii. Po śmierci jego ojca wybuchły rebelie w Fenicji i Palestynie oraz w Babilonii, które krwawo tłumił. W celu zapobieganiu buntom stosował na masową skalę deportacje ludności podbitych krajów. Sytuacja w Babilonii była trudniejsza do opanowania. Sennacheryb odziedziczył jej koronę po swoim ojcu, ale już w 703 roku p.n.e. doszło tam do rebelii Marduk-apla-iddiny II, który przy pomocy elamickiego króla Szutruk-Nahhunte II przejął kontrolę nad Babilonem. Kilka miesięcy później rebelianci zostali pobici przez armię Sennacheryba pod Kisz. Marduk-apla-iddina II zdołał jednak zbiec na bagna w południowej Mezopotamii. Sennacheryb uprowadził do Asyrii 208 tysięcy ludzi, a na tronie Babilonii osadził niejakiego Bel-ibniego. Trzy lata później (700 p.n.e.) Marduk-apla-iddina II ponownie spróbował odzyskać Babilon. Asyryjczycy uniemożliwili mu to, ale Bel-ibni został zdetronizowany za nieudolność lub też współpracę z Chaldejczykiem. Jego miejsce zajął Aszur-nadin-szumi, najstarszy syn Sanheriba. W roku 694 p.n.e. Sennacheryb podjął wyprawę przeciwko Elamowi. Atakując z lądu i morza spustoszył kilka miast i powrócił z łupami. W odwecie król Elamu Halluszu-Inszuszinak wkroczył do Babilonu i zajął Sippar. Korzystając z sytuacji, Babilończycy zbuntowali się, pojmali Aszur-nadin-szumiego i wydali Elamitom, którzy wywieźli go do Elamu. Halluszu-Inszuszinak osadził na babilońskim tronie swojego protegowanego Nergal-uszeziba i wrócił do kraju. Kilka miesięcy później Sennacheryb odzyskał kontrolę nad Babilonem. Wkrótce mieszkańcy Babilonii znowu podnieśli bunt. W 691 p.n.e. doszło do bitwy pod Hallule nad Tygrysem. Roczniki asyryjskie przedstawiają bitwę jako wielkie zwycięstwo nad koalicją babiloński-elamicką, natomiast kronika babilońska mówi o odwrocie Asyryjczyków.</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Сеннахериб[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Царь Ассирии[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы правления: [\BOLD] ок. 704 - 681 гг. до н. э.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Сеннахериб был сыном Саргона II, от которого он унаследовал трон Ассирии. Как наследный принц, Сеннахериб был назначен ответственным за империю, в то время как его отец Саргон II руководил ведением военной кампании. В отличие от своих предшественников, правление Сеннахериба было отмечено не столько военными кампаниями, сколько строительными проектами. После насильственной смерти Саргона Сеннахериб столкнулся с некоторыми проблемами в установлении своей власти. Тем не менее, ему удалось реализовать строительные проекты. Он перенес столицу из нового города своего отца Дур-Шаррукин в старый город Ниневию. Поразительно, что он не только покинул город своего отца, но и не упоминает его ни в одной официальной надписи.[PARAGRAPH:1]Во время своего правления Сеннахериб столкнулся с различными проблемами в Вавилонии. Его первая кампания произошла в 703 г. до н.э. против Мардука-апла-иддина II, который захватил трон Вавилона и собрал союз, поддерживаемый халдеями, арамейцами и Эламом. Мы можем датировать визит вавилонских послов к Езекии Иудейскому в этот период. Союзники хотели использовать в своих интересах беспорядки, возникшие при восшествии на престол Сеннахериба. Сеннахериб разделил свою армию и приказал одной части атаковать расположенного в Кише врага, в то время как он и остальная часть армии приступили к захвату города Кута. После того, как это было сделано, царь быстро вернулся, чтобы помочь остальной части своей армии. Восстание было подавлено, и Мардук-апла-иддина II бежал. Вавилон был взят, а его дворец разграблен, но его граждане остались невредимыми. Ассирийцы искали Мардука-апла-иддину II, особенно в южных болотах, но его не нашли.[PARAGRAPH:1]Сеннахериб сначала рассказывает о нескольких своих предыдущих победах и о том, как его враги были подавлены его присутствием. Он смог сделать это с Великим Сидоном, Маленьким Сидоном, Бит-Зитти, Зарибту, Махаллиба, Ушу, Акзиб и Акко. После взятия каждого из этих городов Сеннахериб назначил марионеточного лидера по имени Этбаал правителем всего региона. Затем Сеннахериб обратил свое внимание на Бет-Дагон, Иоппию, Банай-Барку и Азджуру, города, которые находились под властью Сидкии и также попали под власть Сеннахериба.[PARAGRAPH:1]Тогда на помощь пострадавшим городам пришли Египет и Нубия. Сеннахериб победил египтян и, по его собственным словам, в одиночку захватил египетских и нубийских возниц. Сеннахериб захватил и разграбил несколько других городов, включая Лахис (второй по величине укрепленный город в Иудейском царстве). Он наказал «преступных» граждан городов и восстановил Пади, их лидера, который был оставлен заложником в Иерусалиме.[PARAGRAPH:1]Во время правления Сеннахериба Ниневия превратилась в ведущую метрополию империи. Его строительные проекты начались почти сразу после вступления на престол. Уже в 703 г. до н.э. он построил дворец с парком и искусственным орошением, назвав свой новый дом «Дворец без соперников». Для этого амбициозного проекта старый дворец был снесен, чтобы освободить место. В дополнение к его собственным большим садам для жителей Ниневии было разбито несколько небольших садов. Он также построил первый в истории акведук в Джерване в 690 г. до н.э., который обеспечил большую потребность в воде в Ниневии. Узкие переулки и площади Ниневии были расчищены и расширены, а также построена королевская дорога и проспект, которые пересекали мост на подходе к воротам парка и с обеих сторон были выложены стелами. Храмы были восстановлены и построены во время его правления, что является долгом короля. Наиболее примечательны его работы в храмах Ашшура (бога) и новогодних праздников (Акиту). Он также расширил городскую оборону, в том числе ров, окружавший городские стены. Некоторые из его городских стен были восстановлены, и их все еще можно увидеть в наши дни. Работу над его гигантским строительным проектом выполнили жители Квэ, Киликии, Филистии, Тира, а также халдеи, арамейцы и маннеи, которые оказались там невольно.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>