<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_HERD</Tag>
		<English>Herd (Mammoth)</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Troupeau de Mammouth</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Branco - Mammut</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Stado - Mamuty</Polish>
		<Russian>Òàáóí ìàìîíòîâ</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Only subdued mammoth can build the mammoth herd. It provides a mammoth resource. There can only be one per civ.</English>
		<Italian>Solo i mammut addomesticati possono costruire il Branco - Mammut; fornisce una risorsa di mammut.</Italian>
		<Polish>Mamut włochaty należał do ulubionej zwierzyny łownej człowieka w późnym plejstocenie, co znalazło swe odzwierciedlenie w zachowanych do dzisiaj licznych wyobrażeniach i malowidłach, pozostawionych głównie na ścianach jaskiń (np. w Rouffignac we Francji). Mamuty były źródłem pożywienia, ale dostarczały także materiałów do wyrobu okryć (skóry), sprzętów domowych, narzędzi i ozdób (kości, ciosy). Kości wykorzystywane były sporadycznie również do budowy paleolitycznych domostw, czego ślady odnaleziono w miejscowości Meziriczi na Ukrainie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_HERD_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Only subdued mammoths can build the Mammoth Herd. It provides an ivory resource.</English>
		<Italian>Solo i mammut addomesticati possono costruire un Branco - Mammut; quest'edificio fornisce una fonte di avorio.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_TRAINER</Tag>
		<English>Animal Trainer (Mammoth)</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Dresseur de Mammouth</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Allevatore di mammut</Italian>
		<Polish>Treser Mamutów</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïðèðó÷åíèå ìàìîíòîâ</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_TRAINER_EFFECT</Tag>
		<English>Effect - Heritage - Mammoths</English>
		<French>Effet - Patrimoine (Mammouth)</French>
		<Polish>Efekt - Dziedzictwo - Mamut</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïèòîìíèê ìàìîíòîâ</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_TRAINER_HERITAGE</Tag>
		<English>Heritage - Mammoth</English>
		<French>Patrimoine (Mammouth)</French>
		<Polish>Dziedzictwo - Mamut</Polish>
		<Russian>Ðàçâåäåíèå ìàìîíòîâ</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_TRAINER_HERITAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Instead of only being able to train Mammoth units in the city you built the wonder in this building allows them to be built in any of your cities. It can only be built in the ciy with the Mammothr Trainer World Wonder.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_TRAINER_HERITAGE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Allows the training of mammoth units in all cities. Requires Mammoth Trainer Wonder.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_TRAINER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The woolly mammoth was the last species of the genus. Most populations of the woolly mammoth in North America and Eurasia, as well all the Columbian mammoths in North America, died out around the time of the last glacial retreat, as part of a mass extinction of megafauna in northern Eurasia and the Americas.</English>
		<Italian>Il mammut peloso fu l'ultima specie del suo genere. La maggior parte dei mammut pelosi del Nordamerica e dell'Eurasia morirono surante l'ultima era glaciale, facendo parte di un'estinzione di massa della megafauna nell'emisfero settentrionale.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAMMOTH_TRAINER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a Mammoth Trainer to increase your cities production and happiness.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci un allevaore di mammut per incrementare la produzione e la felicità delle tue città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BALLISTA_MAMMOTH</Tag>
		<English>Ballista Mammoth</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mammouth Balliste</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Mammut con balista</Italian>
		<Polish>Mamut-Ballista</Polish>
		<Russian>Ìàìîíò ñ áàëëèñòîé</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BALLISTA_MAMMOTH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Great mammoths walk in northern tundras, some tribes hunt them for meat, skins and bones. But some hunt them them for beast of war. Capturing one alive and bending is no easy task, but if succeeded. Tribe have a warbeast that can crush down buildings and break a gates of strongholds. Mammoth can be used break down enemy troops.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BALLISTA_MAMMOTH_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Ballista Mammoth[COLOR_REVERT] - A well protected ballista that can bombard city fortifications. Effective against mounted units, siege engines and city defenders. It's more effective in arctic terrains and generally stronger than its elephant counterpart.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BOMBARD_MAMMOTH</Tag>
		<English>Bombard Mammoth</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mammouth Bombarde</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Mammut con bombarda</Italian>
		<Polish>Mamut-Bombard</Polish>
		<Russian>Ìàìîíò ñ ïóøêîé</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_NEANDERTHAL_MAMMOTH_RIDER</Tag>
		<English>Neanderthal Mammoth Rider</English>
		<Russian>Íåàíä. ìàìîíò</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SUBDUED_MAMMOTH</Tag>
		<English>Subdued Mammoth</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mammouth (App.)</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Gefangenes Mammut:Gefangenen Mammuts:Gefangenen Mammut:Gefangene Mammut:Gefangene Mammuts:Gefangenen Mammuts:Gefangenen Mammuts:Gefangenen Mammuts</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0:0:1:1:1:1</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Mammut addomesticato</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Poskromiony Mamut</Polish>
		<Russian>Ìàìîíò (ðó÷í.)</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TRAINED_MAMMOTH</Tag>
		<English>Mammoth Rider</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Chevaucheur de Mammouth</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Mammothreiter</German>
		<Italian>Cavalcatore di mammut</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Jinete de mamut</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jeździec (Mamut)</Polish>
		<Russian>Íàåçäíèê íà ìàìîíòå</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TRAINED_MAMMOTH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>You raised your own mammoth pup, broke it to the saddle and trained it for war. You might ride your massive mount on raids but your primary duty is to hunt down marauding raiders in your own clan's lands. Few will stand and face a 10' war-mammoth. Fewer will face that mammoth with a warrior on its back.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TRAINED_MAMMOTH_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Mammoth Riders[COLOR_REVERT] are early-game mounted units. This particular rider is using [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Mammoth[COLOR_REVERT] instead [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Horses[COLOR_REVERT] and its slower then rest of the Riders but much stronger. They have bonus in siege cities and when fighting in polar terrain and vs other mounted units and siege engines.</English>
		<French>Unité adaptée contre les autres unités montés et les unités de siège. Obtient un bonus lors de l'attaque de villes.</French>
		<Spanish>Una unidad adecuada contra unidades montadas y armas de asedio. Obtiene una bonificación al atacar una ciudad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WAR_MAMMOTH</Tag>
		<English>War Mammoth</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mammouth de Guerre</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Mammut da guerra</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Mamut de guerra</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Mamut Bojowy</Polish>
		<Russian>Áîåâîé ìàìîíò</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>