<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 Beyond the Sword -->
	<!-- Modified by the Civ Gold Team -->
	<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ATLANTIS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Atlantis[\H1][NEWLINE][TAB]Sometime presumably before 100,000 BC, Atlantis was simply 
another civilization in the world and the Atlanteans were a normal race like any other. One fateful day, 
a huge comet passed over the Earth. A single piece broke off and fell upon the landmass that was inhabited 
by the Atlanteans. To their astonishment, they managed to discover the great properties possessed by 
the comet fragment. Soon, they would use the fragment, which they called the Heart of Atlantis, as their 
source into becoming a more advanced civilization than any other before in history. But instead of using 
their new found technological powers for good, they exercised it to dominate other lands, establishing 
colonies all over the ancient world and subjugating the people there. They created a fearsome armada 
of flying machines called Ketaks and artificially-intelligent Leviathans that waged war with unmatched 
strength. However, their hubris would become their undoing when an accidental discharge caused a Great 
Flood that threatened to wipe out Atlantis as a whole. The crystal that had fueled their technology and 
gifted them with extended longevity, would save a part of the city, though it would be buried beneath 
the waters and deep into the Earth. Humbled by the result of their arrogance, the elder leaders of Atlantis, 
in particular its King Kashekim Nedakh, decided to keep the crystal secret, even from its people, forever 
so as not to repeat their actions. Kashekim went further by ordering all of Atlantis' history to be destroyed 
and hid the crystal deep within the city through the throne room. Overtime, their past glory had been 
all but forgotten. According to Plato, Atlantis is located somewhere beyond "the pillars of Heracles." 
The exact position has been debated by scholars for centuries with no theory being any better than the 
other. Many have even reasoned that it may not be in the Atlantic Ocean as has generally been believed.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ATLANTIS_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Atlantis Empire</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ATLANTIS_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Atlantis</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ATLANTIS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Atlantan</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_NEDAKH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]King Nedakh[\H1][NEWLINE][TAB]Kashekim Nedakh is the king and ruler of Atlantis at the 
height of its power. In his arrogance, he uses the Heart of Atlantis as a weapon and begins a campaign 
that sees him conquer and colonize other lands and cultures. This would end up bring about his downfall 
as his pride is carried over into his army, which results in the accidental weapons discharge that creates 
the Great Flood that sinks the city. Additionally, his wife is chosen by the crystal in an act to save 
the central city from being destroyed outright. However, she remains bonded to the crystal for so long 
that she is lost to it permanently, leaving their daughter Kidagakash without a mother. As if understanding 
of the situation, Kashekim looks directly at the crystal while it acts to save the central city, and 
is permanently blinded because of this.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_NEDAKH</Tag>
		<English>King Nedakh</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
