<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENTTRIGGER_KNOWLEDGE_INHERITANCE_1</Tag>
		<English>An old shaman from the %s1_civ_adjective tribe has reached an understanding of the changing reality. His new ideas will help their tribe to develop faster.</English>
		<French>Un vieux shaman de la tribu %s1_civ_adjective a réussi à comprendre la réalité de certains changements. Ses nouvelles idées aident la tribu à se développer plus vite.</French>
		<Italian>Un vecchio sciamano della tribù %s1_civ_adjective ha raggiunto la comprensione della realtà in cambiamento. Le sue nuove idee aiuteranno la tribù a svilupparsi più velocemente.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Un viejo chamán de la tribu %s1_civ_adjective ha alcanzado un grado de comprensión de la realidad cambiante sin parangón. Sus nuevas ideas guiarán a la tribu a un mejor desarrollo.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Stary szaman z plemienia %s1_civ_adjective zrozumial zmieniajaca sie rzeczywistosc. Jego nowa wiedza przyda sie plemieniu w rozwoju.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_KNOWLEDGE_INHERITANCE_1</Tag>
		<English>A thinker? Let's see what interesting ideas he has.</English>
		<French>Un penseur? Voyons quelles idées intéressantes il a.</French>
		<Italian>Un pensatore? Vediamo quali idee interessanti ha.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Un pensador? Veamos qué ideas interesantes tiene.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Mysliciel? Zobaczmy jakie interesujace idee glosi.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_KNOWLEDGE_INHERITANCE_2</Tag>
		<English>Just what we needed. Let him tell the entire tribe his ideas and make sure they pass from generation to generation.</English>
		<French>Juste ce dont nous avions besoins. Demandez-lui de propager ses idées à toute la tribu, qu'elles se transmettent de génération en génération.</French>
		<Italian>Proprio ciò di cui avevamo bisogno. Lasciategli insegnare le sue idee a tutta la tribù, e fate in modo che passino di generazione in generazione.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Justo lo que necesitábamos. Dejemos que le cuente a toda la tribu sus ideas, y asegúraos de que pasen de generación en generación.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Tego potrzebowalismy. Przekazmy calemu plemienu jego idee i upewnijmy sie, ze beda przekazywane z pokolenia na pokolenie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_KNOWLEDGE_INHERITANCE_OBSOLETE_HELP_1</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Every [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Knowledge Inheritance[COLOR_REVERT] in our empire will become obsolete.</English>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ogni [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Trasmissione della conoscenza[COLOR_REVERT] in tutto il nostro impero diventa obsoleta.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]Toda [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Herencia del saber[COLOR_REVERT] en nuestro imperio quedará obsoleta.</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Kazde [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Dziedzictwo Wiedzy[COLOR_REVERT] w naszym imperium niedlugo przestaje istniec.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_OBSOLETE_KNOWLEDGE_INHERITANCE_1</Tag>
		<English>I see.</English>
		<Italian>Capisco.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ya veo.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Rozumiem.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_TRIGGER_KNOWLEDGE_INHERITANCE_1</Tag>
		<English>An old shaman from our tribe seems to have reached an understanding of the changing reality. He says he has new ideas that can help the tribe develop faster.</English>
		<French>Un vieux shaman votre tribu a réussi à comprendre la réalité de certains changements. Ses nouvelles idées aident la tribu à se développer plus vite.</French>
		<Italian>Un vecchio sciamano della nostra tribù sembra aver raggiunto una comprensione della realtà in cambiamento. Dice di avere nuove idee che possono aiutare la tribù a svilupparsi più velocemente.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Un viejo chamán de nuestra tribu parece haber alcanzado un grado de comprensión de la realidad cambiante sin parangón. Asimismo, dice tener nuevas ideas que ayudarán a la tribu desarrollarse más rápido.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Stary szaman z naszego plemienia zrozumial zmieniajaca sie rzeczywistosc. Jego nowa wiedza przyda sie plemieniu w rozwoju.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_TRIGGER_OBSOLETE_KNOWLEDGE_INHERITANCE_1</Tag>
		<English>Our current Sedentary Lifestyle has made obsolete our Knowledge Inheritance all over our empire. We will have to find other ways to increase our science rate from now.</English>
		<Italian>La nostra attuale Vita sedentaria ha reso obsoleta la nostra Trasmissione della conoscenza in tutto l'impero. Dovremo trovare un altro modo per incrementare la nostra ricerca d'ora in poi.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nuestro actual estilo de vida sedentario ha dejado obsoletos nuestras costumbres de Herencia del saber por todo el imperio. Tendremos que encontrar otros modos de incrementar nuestra razón de investigación a partir de ahora.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Nasz osiadly sposób zycia spowodowal, ze Dziedzictwo Wiedzy przestalo byc potrzebne w naszym imperium. Musimy znalezc lepszy sposób na przyspieszenie naszego rozwoju.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>