<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings. I am [OUR_NAME]. Always be pleasant, [CT_NAME], and your reputation will be fragrant and pervasive within the [OUR_EMPIRE].</English>
		<French>Salutations. Je suis [OUR_NAME]. Soiyez toujours poli, [CT_NAME], et votre réputation sera ressentie et omniprésente dans [OUR_EMPIRE].</French>
		<German>Grüße. Ich bin [OUR_NAME]. Sei stets freundlich, [CT_NAME], und Dein Ansehen wird wohlriechend und durchdringend sein im [OUR_EMPIRE].</German>
		<Spanish>Saludos. Soy [OUR_NAME]. Sé siempre amable, [CT_NAME], y te forjarás una reputación duradera ante el [OUR_EMPIRE].</Spanish>
		<Polish>Witam. Jestem [OUR_NAME]. Zawsze bądź zadowolony, [CT_NAME], a Twoja reputacja będzie wonna i dominująca w Twoim Imperium.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN</Tag>
		<English>Jayavarman VII</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Jayavarman VII[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of the Khmer Empire[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c. 1125 - 1215[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Jayavarman VII was a king of the Khmer Empirein present day Cambodia. He was the son of Dharanindravarman II and his wife Sri Jayarajacudamani.[PARAGRAPH:1]Jayavaraman became king in 1181 after having driven out the Cham conquerors of Yashodharapura, the city of Angkor Wat and many other temple complexes. We know that the city had been burned and that after his conquest Jayavarman led an almost unparalled programme of building. Famously Buddhist rather than a Hindu, he did not rely solely on royal obeisance to the gods to protect the city. Instead he built a huge wall around it for the first time. The wall remains in place today.[PARAGRAPH:1]Angkor Thom (Big Angkor) was a new city centre, called in its day Indrapattha. At the centre of the new city stands one of his most massive achievements -- the temple now called the Bayon, a multi-faceted, multi-towered temple that mixes Buddhist and Hindu iconography. Its outer walls have startling bas reliefs not only of warfare but the everyday life of the Khmer army and its followers. These reliefs show camp followers on the move with animals and oxcarts, hunters, women cooking, female traders selling to Chinese merchants, and celebrations of common footsoldiers.[PARAGRAPH:1]The reliefs also depict a naval battle on the great lake, the Tonle Sap, which as it shows Cham and Khmer, may well depict the retaking of Yashodharapura. Jayavarman lived for a time in the lands of the Cham, in what is now middle Vietnam, though it is not clear in what circumstances. There is another Jayavarman-style temple complex very remote and hard to reach now called Preah Kahn at Kompong Svay. As portraiture of him has been found there, some people feel he may have lived there before becoming the Chakravatin, or Khmer emperor.[PARAGRAPH:1]What is known is that King Suryavarman (Sun Shield) II, builder of the great Angkor Wat died some time in the early 1150s. He was succeeded by Yashovarman II who was himself overthrown by Tribhuvanadityavarman (Protegee of the Three Suns) assumed to be an usurper. Most dates are a matter of debate or conjecture. One date that is certain is that in 1177 the Chams who had themselves been subjected to numerous Khmer invasions, took the city of Yashodharapura in 1177. A Cham king took the title of Jaya-Indravarman. In 1181 Jayavarman VII became King after leading the Khmer forces and driving out the Chams.[PARAGRAPH:1]Jayavarman VII remains a potent symbol of national pride for present day Cambodians. As a Buddhist King in a now Buddhist country he is regarded with great respect. He built and repaired many 'firehouses' across the Empire, which are thought of as places for travellers to rest and many buildings which are now called hospitals in translation. This has contributed to a legend of the Buddharaja, the King-Buddha, who privileged compassion in ruling. This view of Jayavarman and his reign is supported by some beautiful portrait sculpture of him in meditation.[PARAGRAPH:1]Jayavarman died in about 1215, at an advanced age ranging from 85 to 90. Of these dates we cannot be certain. There is a minority view, quite cynical, that the current biography of Jayavarman is imaginary and that the evidence could just as easily support the view that he was the usurper. What is not imaginary is the size and scale of the building programme, the fact of his Buddhism, or the unusual focus on everyday life that is found on the walls of the Bayon.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Jayavarman VII[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Król Khmerów[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] ok. 1125 - 1215[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Jayavarman VII was a king of the Khmer Empirein present day Cambodia. He was the son of Dharanindravarman II and his wife Sri Jayarajacudamani.[PARAGRAPH:1]Jayavaraman became king in 1181 after having driven out the Cham conquerors of Yashodharapura, the city of Angkor Wat and many other temple complexes. We know that the city had been burned and that after his conquest Jayavarman led an almost unparalled programme of building. Famously Buddhist rather than a Hindu, he did not rely solely on royal obeisance to the gods to protect the city. Instead he built a huge wall around it for the first time. The wall remains in place today.[PARAGRAPH:1]Angkor Thom (Big Angkor) was a new city centre, called in its day Indrapattha. At the centre of the new city stands one of his most massive achievements -- the temple now called the Bayon, a multi-faceted, multi-towered temple that mixes Buddhist and Hindu iconography. Its outer walls have startling bas reliefs not only of warfare but the everyday life of the Khmer army and its followers. These reliefs show camp followers on the move with animals and oxcarts, hunters, women cooking, female traders selling to Chinese merchants, and celebrations of common footsoldiers.[PARAGRAPH:1]The reliefs also depict a naval battle on the great lake, the Tonle Sap, which as it shows Cham and Khmer, may well depict the retaking of Yashodharapura. Jayavarman lived for a time in the lands of the Cham, in what is now middle Vietnam, though it is not clear in what circumstances. There is another Jayavarman-style temple complex very remote and hard to reach now called Preah Kahn at Kompong Svay. As portraiture of him has been found there, some people feel he may have lived there before becoming the Chakravatin, or Khmer emperor.[PARAGRAPH:1]What is known is that King Suryavarman (Sun Shield) II, builder of the great Angkor Wat died some time in the early 1150s. He was succeeded by Yashovarman II who was himself overthrown by Tribhuvanadityavarman (Protegee of the Three Suns) assumed to be an usurper. Most dates are a matter of debate or conjecture. One date that is certain is that in 1177 the Chams who had themselves been subjected to numerous Khmer invasions, took the city of Yashodharapura in 1177. A Cham king took the title of Jaya-Indravarman. In 1181 Jayavarman VII became King after leading the Khmer forces and driving out the Chams.[PARAGRAPH:1]Jayavarman VII remains a potent symbol of national pride for present day Cambodians. As a Buddhist King in a now Buddhist country he is regarded with great respect. He built and repaired many 'firehouses' across the Empire, which are thought of as places for travellers to rest and many buildings which are now called hospitals in translation. This has contributed to a legend of the Buddharaja, the King-Buddha, who privileged compassion in ruling. This view of Jayavarman and his reign is supported by some beautiful portrait sculpture of him in meditation.[PARAGRAPH:1]Jayavarman died in about 1215, at an advanced age ranging from 85 to 90. Of these dates we cannot be certain. There is a minority view, quite cynical, that the current biography of Jayavarman is imaginary and that the evidence could just as easily support the view that he was the usurper. What is not imaginary is the size and scale of the building programme, the fact of his Buddhism, or the unusual focus on everyday life that is found on the walls of the Bayon.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>