<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Soren Johnson (Firaxis Games) -->
	<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
	<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
	<!-- -->
	<!---->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_LIBYA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Libyan Empire</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_LIBYA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Libya</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_LIBYA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Libyan</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_LIBYA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD]Strategy:[\BOLD]Libya is a dangerous civ to face in the early game militarily, since 
it has great offensive capabilities; it also boasts clean and healthy cities. Shoshenq is Aggressive, 
which, combined with the Meshwesh Warrior - an excellent field unit - makes the Libyans unstoppable in 
open battles. Shoshenq is also Expansive, which, combined with the Olive Grove, makes Libyan cities the 
hygenic envy of the world early on. Certainly, with their clean cities and powerful field armies, the 
Libyans are not a military might to be toyed with in the early game![PARAGRAPH:1][NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Compared 
with the History of Egypt, historians know little about the history of Libya, as there are few surviving 
written records. Archaeological evidence indicates that from at least the eighth millennium BC. Libya's 
coastal plain shared in a Neolithic culture, skilled in the domestication of cattle and cultivation of 
crops, that was common to the whole Mediterranean littoral. To the south, in what is now the Sahara Desert, 
nomadic hunters and herders roamed a far, well-watered savanna that abounded in game and provided pastures 
for their stock. Their culture flourished until the region began to desiccate after 2000 BC. Scattering 
before the encroaching desert and invading horsemen, the savanna people migrated into the Sudan or were 
absorbed by the Berbers.[PARAGRAPH:2]The origin of the Berbers is a partial mystery, the investigation 
of which has produced an abundance of educated speculation but no solution. Archaeological and linguistic 
evidence strongly suggests southwestern Asia as the point from which the ancestors of the Berbers may 
have begun their migration into North Africa early in the third millennium BC. Over the succeeding centuries 
they extended their range from Egypt to the Niger Basin. Caucasians of predominantly Mediterranean stock, 
the Berbers present a broad range of physical types and speak a variety of mutually (un)intelligible 
Berber dialects that belong to the Berber family of the Afro-Asiatic language family. They rarely developed 
a sense of a full Berber nationhood (as we understand it today). They have historically identified themselves 
in terms of their tribes, clans, or kingdoms. Collectively, Berbers referred to themselves simply as 
imazighen, to which has been attributed the meaning "free men".[PARAGRAPH:2]Inscriptions found in Egypt 
dating from the Old Kingdom (ca. 2700–2200 BC) are the earliest known recorded testimony of the Berber 
migration and also the earliest written documentation of Libyan history. At least as early as this period, 
troublesome Berber tribes, one of which was identified in Egyptian records as the Levu (or "Libyans"), 
were raiding eastward as far as the Nile Delta and attempting to settle there. During the Middle Kingdom 
(ca. 2200-1700 BC) the Egyptian pharaohs succeeded in imposing their overlordship on these eastern Berbers 
and extracted tribute from them. Many Berbers served in the army of the pharaohs, and some rose to positions 
of importance in the Egyptian state. One such Berber officer seized control of Egypt in about 950 BC 
and, as Shishonk I, ruled as pharaoh. His successors of the twentysecond and twenty-third dynasties—the 
so-called Libyan dynasties (ca. 945–730 BC)—are also believed to have been Berbers.[PARAGRAPH:2]After 
the Egyptians, Greeks, Romans, and Byzantines mentioned various other tribes in Libya. Later tribal names 
differ from the Egyptian ones but, probably, some tribes were named in the Egyptian sources and the later 
ones, as well. The Meshwesh-tribe represents this assumption. Scholars believe it would be the same tribe 
called Mazyes by Hektaios and Maxyes by Herodotus, while it was called "Mazaces" and "Mazax" in Latin 
sources. All those names are similar to the name used by the Berbers for themselves, Imazighen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Late 
period sources give more detailed descriptions of Libya and its inhabitants. The ancient historian Herodotus 
describes Libya and the Libyans in his fourth book, known as The Libyan Book. Pliny the Elder, Diodorus 
Siculus, and Procopius also contributed to what is now primary source material on ancient Libya and the 
Libyans.[PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SHOSHENQ</Tag>
		<English>Shoshenq</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SHOSHENQ_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Shoshenq I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Libyan Pharaoh of Egypt[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]? 
- 922 BC[NEWLINE]Shoshenq came from a line of princes or sheikhs of Libyan tribal descent whose title 
was “great chief of the Meshwesh” and who appear to have settled in Bubastis in the eastern Nile River 
delta. He was a general under Psusennes II, the last king of the 21st dynasty (1075–c. 950 BCE), and 
probably ascended the throne without a struggle, making Bubastis his residence and marrying his son Osorkon 
to a daughter of Psusennes II. As king, Shoshenq chose his eldest son, Osorkon I, as his successor and 
consolidated his authority over Egypt through marriage alliances and appointments. He assigned his second 
son, Iuput , the prominent position of High Priest of Amun at Thebes as well as the title of Governor 
of Upper Egypt and Commander of the Army to consolidate his authority over the Thebaid. Finally, Shoshenq 
I designated his third son, Nimlot, as the "Leader of the Army" at Herakleopolis in Middle Egypt.[PARAGRAPH:2]He 
pursued an aggressive foreign policy in the adjacent territories of the Middle East, towards the end 
of his reign. This is attested, in part, by the discovery of a statue base bearing his name from the 
Lebanese city of Byblos, part of a monumental stela from Megiddo bearing his name, and a list of cities 
in the region comprising Syria, Philistia, Phoenicia, the Negev and the Kingdom of Israel, among various 
topographical lists inscribed on the walls of temples of Amun at al-Hibah and Karnak. Because of this, 
Sheshonq is oftentimes associated with the Biblical Shishak, who invaded Judah during the fifth year 
of the reign of king Rehoboam, taking with him most of the treasures of the temple created by Solomon. 
While the names are similar, the Canaan campaigns of the historical Shoshenq I are difficult to correlate 
with the outline of events in the Book of Kings and Chronicles. As there were multiple "Shoshenqs," it 
is possible that a subsequent Egyptian ruler matches the times and activity of the biblical "Shishaq." 
Unfortunately there is no mention of either an attack nor tribute from Jerusalem, which has led some 
to suggest that Shoshenq was not the Biblical Shishak. The fragment of a stela bearing his cartouche 
from Megiddo has been interpreted as a monument Shoshenq erected there to commemorate his victory.[PARAGRAPH:2]He 
was succeeded by his son Osorkon I after a reign of 21 Years. According to the British Egyptologist Aidan 
Dodson, no trace has yet been found of the tomb of Shoshenq I; the sole funerary object linked to Shoshenq 
I is a canopic chest of unknown provenance. This may indicate his tomb was looted in antiquity, but this 
hypothesis is unproven. Egyptologists differ over the location of Sheshonq I's burial and speculate that 
he may have been buried somewhere in Tanis—perhaps in one of the Anonymous royal tombs here—or in Bubastis. 
It is also possible that he is buried in another city in the Egyptian delta, such as Memphis. [PARAGRAPH:2]In 
later times, Shoshenq became an important and pivotal figure not to the Egyptians, but to the Berbers, 
who regard him as their first important historical personage. Shoshenq, after all, was almost certainly 
of Libyan Berber ancestry. Thus, this is why the modern-day Berber calendar (distinct from the Georgian 
calendar) begins to compute its years from 950 BCE, the approximate date of Shoshenq's ascension to the 
throne of Egypt, thus becoming the first Libyan pharaoh. With the passage of time, what could seem a 
bizarre innovation has been adopted with conviction by many supporters of the Berber culture and is now 
a part of the cultural heritage of this people, fully integrated in the system of traditional customs 
related the North-African calendar.		[PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KADDAFI</Tag>
		<English>Kaddafi</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KADDAFI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Mu’ammar al-Kaddafi[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Libyan revolutionary and politician[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: 
[\BOLD]1 September 1969 – 23 August 2011[NEWLINE]		The son of an impoverished Bedouin goat herder, Gaddafi 
became involved in politics while at school in Sabha, subsequently enrolling in the Royal Military Academy, 
Benghazi. Founding a revolutionary cell within the military, in 1969 they seized power from the absolute 
monarchy of King Idris in a bloodless coup. Becoming Chairman of the governing Revolutionary Command 
Council (RCC), he abolished the monarchy and proclaimed the Republic. Ruling by decree, he implemented 
measures to remove what he viewed as foreign imperialist influence from Libya, and strengthened ties 
to Arab nationalist governments. Intent on pushing Libya towards "Islamic socialism", he introduced sharia 
as the basis for the legal system and nationalized the oil industry, using the increased revenues to 
bolster the military, implement social programs and fund revolutionary militants across the world. In 
1973 he initiated a "Popular Revolution" with the formation of General People's Committees (GPCs), purported 
to be a system of direct democracy, but retained personal control over major decisions. He outlined his 
Third International Theory that year, publishing these ideas in The Green Book.		In 1977, he dissolved 
the Republic and created the Jamahiriya, a "state of the masses" part-governed by GPCs. Officially adopting 
a symbolic role in governance, he retained power as military commander-in-chief and head of the Revolutionary 
Committees responsible for policing and suppressing opponents. Overseeing unsuccessful border conflicts 
with Egypt and Chad, Gaddafi's support for foreign militants and alleged responsibility for the Lockerbie 
bombing led to Libya's label of "international pariah". A particularly hostile relationship developed 
with the United States and United Kingdom, resulting in the 1986 U.S. bombing of Libya and United Nations-imposed 
economic sanctions. Rejecting his earlier ideological commitments, from 1999 Gaddafi encouraged economic 
privatization and sought rapprochement with Western nations, also embracing Pan-Africanism and helping 
to establish the African Union. Amid the Arab Spring, in 2011 an anti-Gaddafist uprising led by the National 
Transitional Council (NTC) broke out, resulting in civil war. NATO intervened militarily on the side 
of the NTC, bringing about the government's downfall. Retreating to Sirte, Gaddafi was captured and killed 
by NTC militants.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SHOSHENQ</Tag>
		<English>I am a god among mortals, having defeated many enemies with my mighty armies. Should I count you among those enemies, [CT_NAME], or perhaps you have come to pay tribute?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SHOSHENQ</Tag>
		<English>I refuse to listen to your mad ramblings, [CT_NAME]. You shall deceive me no longer, fool!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SHOSHENQ</Tag>
		<English>No! Not while I still have the upper hand!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SHOSHENQ</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, mighty leader of [CT_CIV_SHORT]. I am eager to hear of your newest conquests and exploits over lesser states.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SHOSHENQ</Tag>
		<English>The other day I comissioned a stone relief depicting me smiting your skull. Perhaps we should try the real thing?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SHOSHENQ</Tag>
		<English>I once was an impoverished [OUR_CIV_ADJ] chieftain, so I know when I must be humble. [CT_NAME], please bestow some generosity upon us.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SHOSHENQ</Tag>
		<English>Think about it, [CT_NAME]: [OUR_NAME] and [CT_NAME], allies forever! And allies share their gifts with one another, do they not?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SHOSHENQ</Tag>
		<English>Imagine it, depicted on a stone relief: the cities of [CT_CIV_SHORT] being raided and razed by the glorious armies of [OUR_NAME]. Or perhaps would you prefer it like this: [CT_NAME] and [CT_CIV_ADJ]'s envoys paying a little tribute to [OUR_NAME]?</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
