<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ATOMPUNK_EMBASSY</Tag>
		<English>Culture (Atompunk)</English>
		<Polish>Kultura (Atompunk)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ATOMPUNK_EMBASSY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Atompunk relates to the pre-digital period of 1945-1965, including mid-century Modernism, the Atomic Age and Space Age, Communism and concern about it exaggerated as paranoia in the USA along with Neo-Soviet styling, underground cinema, Googie architecture, the Sputnik programme, superhero fiction, the rise of the US military/industrial powers and the fall-out of Chernobyl. Its aesthetic tends toward Populuxe and Raygun Gothic, which describe a retro-futuristic vision of the world.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ATOMPUNK_EMBASSY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build Culture (Atompunk) to gain access to unique buildings and units.</English>
		<French>Construisez la Culture (Atompunk) pour avoir accès à des bâtiments et unités uniques.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLEAN_NUCLEAR_REACTOR</Tag>
		<English>Clean Nuclear Reactor</English>
		<French>Réacteur nucléaire propre</French>
		<Polish>Czysty Reaktor Jądrowy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLEAN_NUCLEAR_REACTOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>After the discovery of clean and save nuclear energy, many reactors were built to produce incredebly amounts of energy.</English>
		<Polish>Z uwagi na istotną rolę neutronów w pracy reaktora jądrowego, w teorii sterowania reaktorem wyróżnia się cykl życia neutronu jako jeden z elementów opisujących działanie reaktora. Cykl opisuje "historię życia" neutronów, od chwili ich powstania do wychwytu (pochłonięcia przez jądro) albo ucieczki z rdzenia. Cykl życia neutronu opisywany jest różnymi formułami.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLEAN_NUCLEAR_REACTOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a Clean Nuclear Reactor to increase your cities Production.</English>
		<French>Construisez un [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Réacteur nucléaire propre[COLOR_REVERT] pour améliorer la production de votre ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GOOD_ATOM</Tag>
		<English>Power (Nuclear)</English>
		<French>Energie (Nucléaire)</French>
		<Polish>Energia (Nuklearna)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GOOD_ATOM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>With the discovery of clean and save nuclear power and the developement of large reactor complexes, Energy becomes available in such a big amount, that energy-intensive  facilities are not an issue</English>
		<Polish>Energetyka jądrowa - zespół zagadnień związanych z uzyskiwaniem na skalę przemysłową energii z rozszczepienia ciężkich jąder pierwiastków (głównie uranu 235).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GOOD_ATOM_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>A Building Produced Good.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HIGH_ENERGY_LAB</Tag>
		<English>High Energy Lab</English>
		<French>Laboratoire à haute énergie</French>
		<Polish>Laboratorium Wysokich Energii</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HIGH_ENERGY_LAB_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>High Energy Labs use the immense amounts of energy produced by nuclear reactors.</English>
		<Polish>Instytut dysponuje siedmioma laboratoriami poświęconym różnym dziedzinom: fizyce teoretycznej, fizyce wysokich energii, fizyce ciężkich jonów, fizyce fazy skondensowanej, reakcjom jądrowym, neutronom i technikom informatycznym. Istnieją również wydziały zajmujące się badaniami nad promieniowaniem i radiobiologią oraz zespoły badawcze poświęcone konkretnym eksperymentom.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HIGH_ENERGY_LAB_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a High Energy Lab to increase your cities Science.</English>
		<French>Construisez un [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Laboratoire à haute énergie[COLOR_REVERT] pour améliorer la science de votre ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HI_TECH_NUCLEAR_REACTOR</Tag>
		<English>Hi-Tech Nuclear Reactor</English>
		<French>Réacteur nucléaire Hi-Tech</French>
		<Polish>Nowoczesny Reaktor Jądrowy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HI_TECH_NUCLEAR_REACTOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>After the discovery of clean and save nuclear energy, many reactors were built to produce incredebly amounts of energy. With advanced technology, the efficiency of reactors increased even more.</English>
		<Polish>W przyszłości planuje się wykorzystywać jako paliwo jądrowe tor. W wyniku rozszczepienia toru powstają jądra atomowe o mniejszej masie niż przy rozszczepieniu uranu lub plutonu i jest wśród nich więcej jąder trwałych. Rozszczepienie toru wytwarza zbyt mało neutronów by uzyskać stan krytyczny, w związku z tym do reaktora takiego trzeba by wstrzeliwać neutrony pochodzące z zewnątrz. W celu uzyskania dużej ilości neutronów naukowcy pracują nad zastosowaniem zjawiska spalacji. W zjawisku tym jądra ciężkich pierwiastków np. ołowiu są bombardowane wiązką protonów o dużej energii (rzędu 1 GeV), w wyniku czego ulegają wzbudzeniu. Jądra pozbywają się energii wzbudzenia wyrzucając z siebie nukleony w tym i neutrony. Zjawisko spalacji może być stosowane w celu uczynienia bezpiecznymi i przedłużenia pracy paliwa obecnych reaktorów jądrowych, a także pomóc w utylizacji radioaktywnych odpadów.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HI_TECH_NUCLEAR_REACTOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a Hi-Tech Nuclear Reactor to increase your cities Production.</English>
		<French>Construisez un [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT] Réacteur nucléaire Hi-Tech[COLOR_REVERT] pour améliorer la production de votre ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MID_CLASS_SKYPAD_APARTMENTS</Tag>
		<English>Housing (Mid Class Skypad Apartments)</English>
		<French>Habitations (Appartements à ciel ouvert)</French>
		<Polish>Domostwa (Sredniej Klasy Apartamenty Podniebne)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MID_CLASS_SKYPAD_APARTMENTS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Another architectural marvel from famed architect Mr. Elroy Jetson, these space age apartments rise into the clouds above all the muss and fuss and most of the weather of the world below. Convenient parking for your hovercars are found on the lowest level.</English>
		<Polish>Jetsonowie żyją w odległej przyszłości. Według pierwotnego zamysłu producentów akcja miała się rozgrywać dokładnie 100 lat od premiery serialu, czyli w roku 2062.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MID_CLASS_SKYPAD_APARTMENTS_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Autobuild Housing in the early Atompunk.</English>
		<French>Construit automatiquement du début de l'ère Atompunk.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NUCLEAR_POWERCOMPLEX</Tag>
		<English>Nuclear Powercomplex</English>
		<French>Complexe de Production Nucléaire</French>
		<Polish>Kompleks Nuklearny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NUCLEAR_POWERCOMPLEX_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>With advanced technology and longtime expierience with nuclear reactors, it was possible to build a centralized, huge complex of tousends of reactors.</English>
		<Polish>Potężna elektrownia jądrowa składająca się z tysięcy reaktorów.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NUCLEAR_POWERCOMPLEX_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a Nuclear Powercomplex to increase your city Production and supply your empire with energy.</English>
		<French>Construisez un [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Complexe de Production Nucléaire[COLOR_REVERT] pour augmenter votre production et procurer de l'électricité.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PUSHBUTTON_AUTOMAT</Tag>
		<English>Pushbutton Automat</English>
		<French>Distributeurs Automatiques</French>
		<Polish>Automat Sprzedający</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PUSHBUTTON_AUTOMAT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Insert money, push a button and out pops a meal. Where does it come from? Nobody knows! Aren't modern conveniences grand! Most people wouldn't even consider moving into a house if it didn't have it's very own Pushbutton Automat nearby.</English>
		<Polish>Automat sprzedający (automat vendingowy, ang. vending machine) - urządzenie służące do sprzedaży samoobsługowej. Można wyróżnić automaty sprzedające towary i usługi. Do pierwszych należą różnego rodzaju maszyny do sprzedaży batonów, kanapek, zabawek, napojów, prezerwatyw, papierosów itp. Natomiast w drugiej grupie znajdują się np. parkometry, automaty piorące, automaty biletowe, automaty telefoniczne czy fotograficzne.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PUSHBUTTON_AUTOMAT_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a Pushbutton Automat to increase your cities Food.</English>
		<French>Construisez des [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Distributeurs Automatiques[COLOR_REVERT] pour améliorer la nourriture de votre ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SMALL_REACTOR_FACTORY</Tag>
		<English>Small Reactor Factory</English>
		<French>Usine de réacteurs miniatures</French>
		<Polish>Fabryka Małych Reaktorów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SMALL_REACTOR_FACTORY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Nuclear Reactors were only used in buildings to produce enough energy for a whole city for a long time. Now it is possible to make them small enough to be installed in Aircrafts, Cars and Tanks.</English>
		<Polish>Fabryka przydomowych elektrowni atomowych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SMALL_REACTOR_FACTORY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a Small Reactor Factory to increase your cities production and equip your troops with better engines.</English>
		<French>Construisez une [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Usine de réacteurs miniatures[COLOR_REVERT] pour accroître la production et votre ville, et équiper les véhicules de meilleurs moteurs.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VENTURE_INDUSTRIES</Tag>
		<English>Venture Industries</English>
		<French>Les Industries Venture</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VENTURE_INDUSTRIES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Venture Industries is the privately owned company of the Venture family. Once world renowned for its innovations in technology and science, it has fallen from grace since Jonas' passing. The Venture Compound is home base and headquarters of the team. It was seemingly built as a large research and manufacturing campus by Jonas himself with his many scientific inventions' profits, large government contracts and business acumen. It evolved to become an enormous set of buildings, with a large fountain and a giant stone statue of Jonas holding a young Rusty on his shoulder up front, the two shadowing a beautifully-designed white compound. The compound would seem at one time to have had a large workforce, but is now practically empty. It is large enough that Dr. Orpheus and his daughter Triana can actually rent out a portion as their own home. Currently, it is being run rather into the ground by Thaddeus Venture, who fulfills mainly government contracts rather than make any major new discoveries. Venture Industries at one point had its corporate business headquarters in New York City. At some point, the building was sold and became '1 Impossible Plaza', headquarters of Impossible Industries. A private compound belonging to Venture Industries, which was gained after the original Team Venture foiled a scheme by Scaramantula's Fraternity of Torment, also exists on Spider Skull Island, and is being run (rather successfully) by Jonas Venture, Jr..</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VENTURE_INDUSTRIES_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build the Venture Industries to increase your cities Science.</English>
		<French>Construisez les [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Industries Venture[COLOR_REVERT] pour améliorer la science de votre ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VIDEOPHONE_NETWORK</Tag>
		<English>Videophone Network</English>
		<French>Réseau de Vidéophones</French>
		<Polish>Sieć Wideofoniczna</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VIDEOPHONE_NETWORK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A videophone is a telephone with a video display, capable of simultaneous video and audio for communication between people in real-time. Videophone service provided the first form of videotelephony, later to be followed by videoconferencing, webcams, and finally high-definition telepresence. At the dawn of its commercial deployment from the 1950s through the 1990s, videotelephony also included 'image phones' which would exchange still images between units every few seconds over conventional POTS-type telephone lines, essentially the same as slow scan TV systems. The development of advanced technology video codecs and high bandwidth Internet telecommunication services allowed videophones to provide high quality colour service between users almost anyplace in the world that the Internet is available, often at low or nominal costs.</English>
		<Polish>Wideofon (nazwa pełna: wideotelefon) - aparat telefoniczny wyposażony w mały monitor ekranowy. W czasie prowadzenia rozmowy, rozmówcy widzą się nawzajem na monitorach znajdujących się przy aparatach telefonicznych. Urządzenie pozwala na wymianę informacji audio-wizualnych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VIDEOPHONE_NETWORK_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a Videophone Network to increase your cities Trade.</English>
		<French>Construisez un [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Réseau de Vidéophones[COLOR_REVERT] pour améliorer le commerce de votre ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
