<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLYNESIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Polynesian Empire</English>
		<French>Empire polynésien</French>
		<German>Polynesische Reich</German>
		<Italian>Impero Polinesiano</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polinesiano Imperio</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Polinezji</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLYNESIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Polynesia</English>
		<French>Polynesie</French>
		<German>Polynesien</German>
		<Italian>Polinesia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polinesia</Spanish>
		<Polish>Polinezja</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLYNESIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Polynesian</English>
		<French>Polynesien</French>
		<German>Polynesische</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Polinesiano:Polinesiana:Polinesiani:Polinesiane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polinesiano</Spanish>
		<Polish>Polinezyjski</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLYNESIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Polynesia comprises of the island groups of Samoa, the Cook Islands, French Polynesia, and Niue, the islands of Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis, Futuna, Hawaii, and Pitcairn Island.  The original inhabitants of New Zealand, the Maori, are also considered Polynesian.  The island of Fiji is sometimes included in Polynesia because of its high percentage of Polynesian inhabitants.  Archaeological evidence supports that Polynesia was settled by migration from Melanesia beginning about 3,000 to 4,000 years ago.  The Samoans are believed to have settled the Marquesas perhaps as early as 300 AD, and Easter Island may have been settled from the Marquesas as early as 400 AD.  Hawaii was also settled by these voyagers during the second half of the first millennium AD, and then the Society Islanders, who were the point of origin for the Polynesians who settled on Cook Island.  Around 1000 AD, these cultures also inhabited Polynesia. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Prior to European contact, Polynesian settlements were either in hamlets or villages.  Houses were clustered in small groups, and villages contained 30 or more houses.  These villages were primarily found on the islands of Samoa and New Zealand and were often fortified by walls of stone or wooden palisades.  Both of these types of settlements relied on family oriented organization.  The most common type of organization was that power passed from the first born son to firstborn son and so on.  In Polynesian societies, chiefs would be revered as equals to others.  However, they could usually trace their family line back to the creator gods.  In societies where the chief was protected and separate from the people, warfare was common.  Christian missionaries succeeded in overthrowing ancient religious practices only after they had converted the chiefs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Religion and magic played an important role in Polynesian culture.  Each of the gods had their own rituals, which were carried out by the priests.  Among these practices were sacrifice, chanting, feasting, and fertility rites.  Magic was also enveloping, and countless rituals regarding love, war, revenge, agriculture, and fishing were practiced.  Polynesian culture was a largely marine based.  In addition to fish, mollusks and crustaceans were an important source of food.  Fishing was usually a group activity, and Polynesian fishermen explored the vast expanses of ocean around their homes.  Other food could be provided by various plants. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Food plants also provided materials for various reasons.  Breadfruit wood was used in canoe making, for instance, and leaves of some plants were used in weaving mats, clothing, sails, and other household goods.  Both single and double canoes were equipped with mat sails.  Some boats were large enough to transport families, domesticated animals, and plants over long stretches of ocean.  Over time, cultures developed distinct artistic skills.  Ruined stone temples can be found in the Society Islands, Easter Island, and the Marquesas culture.  Good such as canoes, war clubs, shields, and fish hooks were elaborately decorated.  Feather cloaks showed an enormous amount of effort in gathering rare feathers and arranging them in intricate designs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Contact with European culture began in the late 1700s and radically changed Polynesia.  Spanish explorers were eager to search for riches and spread Christianity.  The Dutch and British also explored areas such as New Zealand and the Samoan islands.  Resistance to European intervention occurred in almost all of the Polynesian islands, but such movements were brief.  For much time to come, Polynesia would go under the power of European powers and the United States.  Polynesian culture, however, always remained in these islands.</English>
		<French>Polynésie est composée de groupes de l'île de Samoa, les îles Cook, la Polynésie française, et Niue, les îles de Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis, Futuna, à Hawaii, et l'île de Pitcairn. Les premiers habitants de la Nouvelle-Zélande, les Maoris, les Polynésiens sont également considérés. L'île des Fidji est parfois inclus dans la Polynésie en raison de son fort pourcentage d'habitants polynésiens. Témoignages archéologiques soutient que la Polynésie a été réglée par la migration à partir de début Mélanésie environ 3.000 à 4.000 ans. Les Samoans sont soupçonnés d'avoir réglé les Marquises peut-être dès 300 après J.-C., et l'île de Pâques ont pu être réglées depuis les Marquises dès 400 après Jésus Christ. Hawaii a aussi été réglé par les voyageurs au cours de la seconde moitié du premier millénaire après JC, puis la Société Islanders, qui ont été le point d'origine de l'Polynésiens qui se sont installés sur des îles Cook. Environ 1000 AD, ces cultures aussi habitée Polynésie. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Avant le contact avec les Européens, les Polynésiens colonies étaient soit en hameaux ou villages. Des maisons ont été regroupés en petits groupes, et les villages contient 30 ou plusieurs maisons. Ces villages ont été trouvés principalement sur les îles Samoa et la Nouvelle-Zélande, et sont souvent enrichis par des murs de pierre ou de bois palissades. Ces deux types d'établissements invoqué organisation familiale. Le type le plus courant de l'organisation était que le pouvoir est passé depuis le premier fils né à fils premier-né et ainsi de suite. Dans les sociétés polynésiennes, les chefs serait considéré comme égal aux autres. Toutefois, ils pourraient retrouver leur famille généralement retour à la ligne créateur dieux. Dans les sociétés où le chef était protégé et à l'écart de la population, la guerre était commun. Missionnaires chrétiens ont réussi à renverser les anciennes pratiques religieuses uniquement après avoir converti les chefs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La religion et la magie jouent un rôle important dans la culture polynésienne. Chacun des dieux avaient leurs propres rites, qui ont été perpétrés par des prêtres. Parmi ces pratiques sont le sacrifice, le chant, de fête, de rites et de la fertilité. Magic était aussi enveloppant, et d'innombrables rituels concernant l'amour, la guerre, la vengeance, l'agriculture et la pêche ont été pratiquées. Culture polynésienne était largement fondée marines. En plus des poissons, mollusques et crustacés ont été une source importante de nourriture. La pêche est souvent une activité de groupe, et les pêcheurs polynésiens ont exploré les vastes étendues de l'océan autour de leur maison. Autres produits alimentaires pourraient être fournies par diverses plantes. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Food plantes a également fourni du matériel pour des raisons diverses. Breadfruit bois a été utilisé en canot rendant, par exemple, et les feuilles de certaines plantes ont été utilisés dans le tissage de tapis, les vêtements, voiles, et d'autres biens d'équipement ménager. Les deux simples et doubles canots étaient équipés d'un tapis de voiles. Certains bateaux ont été assez grands pour le transport des familles, les animaux domestiques et les plantes sur de grandes étendues de l'océan. Au fil du temps, développé des cultures distinctes compétences artistiques. Les temples en pierre en ruine peut être trouvée dans les Îles de la Société, l'île de Pâques, les Marquises et de la culture. Bon tels que canots, de la guerre des clubs, des boucliers et des hameçons ont été minutieusement décorés. Plume mantos montré une énorme quantité d'efforts pour recueillir des rares plumes et arrangeant dans les modèles complexes. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Le contact avec la culture européenne a commencé à la fin des années 1700 et radicalement changé la Polynésie. Explorateurs espagnols étaient impatients de recherche de la richesse et à la propagation du christianisme. Le néerlandais et britannique a également étudié des domaines tels que la Nouvelle-Zélande et les îles des Samoa. Résistance à l'intervention européenne a eu lieu dans presque toutes les îles polynésiennes, mais ces mouvements ont été brève. Pour beaucoup de temps à venir, la Polynésie se retrouvera dans le pouvoir des puissances européennes et des états-Unis. Culture polynésienne, cependant, toujours restés dans ces îles.</French>
		<German>Polynesien besteht aus Gruppen von der Insel Samoa, die Cook Inseln, Französisch Polynesien, Niue, die Inseln Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis, Futuna, Hawaii, und Pitcairn Island. Die Ureinwohner Neuseelands, die Maori, sind ebenfalls als polynesischen. Die Insel Fidschi ist manchmal in Polynesien wegen seiner hohen Anteil der polynesischen Einwohner. Archäologische Belege, dass Polynesien wurde von Migration von Melanesien ab etwa 3.000 bis 4.000 Jahren. Die Samoaner sind der Ansicht, dass sich die Marquesas vielleicht so früh wie 300 n. Chr., und Osterinsel Mai geklärt sind von den Marquesas so früh wie 400 n.Chr. Hawaii war auch durch diese Reisenden in der zweiten Hälfte des ersten Jahrtausends n. Chr., und dann der Gesellschaft Islanders, die als Ausgangspunkt für die Polynesier, die sich auf Cook Island. Um 1000 n. Chr., diese Kulturen auch bewohnt Polynesien. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Vor dem Europäischen Kontakt, polynesische Siedlungen wurden entweder in Weiler oder Dörfer. Die Häuser wurden gebündelt in kleinen Gruppen, und Dörfer mit 30 oder mehr Wohnungen. Diese Dörfer waren vor allem auf den Inseln von Samoa und Neuseeland und waren oft von befestigten Mauern aus Stein oder hölzernen Palisaden. Beide Arten von Siedlungen auf Familie ausgerichtete Organisation. Die häufigste Art der Organisation war, dass die Macht vom ersten Sohn geboren Erstgeborenen Sohn, und so weiter. In polynesischen Gesellschaften, Häuptlinge wäre verehrt und gleichberechtigt mit anderen. Allerdings könnten sie meist den Spuren ihrer Familie zurück in die Zeile Schöpfer Götter. In Gesellschaften, in denen der Chef war geschützt und getrennt von den Menschen, Kriegsführung war häufig. Christlichen Missionaren gelang es den Sturz alten religiösen Praktiken nur, nachdem sie konvertiert war die Chefs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Religion und Magie spielte eine wichtige Rolle in der polynesischen Kultur. Jeder der Götter hatten ihre eigenen Rituale, die durchgeführt wurden, indem die Priester. Zu diesen Praktiken waren Opfer, Deklamieren, Schlemmen, Riten und Fruchtbarkeit. Magie war auch Kuvertierung, und zahllose Rituale über Liebe, Krieg, Rache, Landwirtschaft und Fischerei wurden geübt. Polynesischen Kultur war ein weitgehend marinen beruht. Zusätzlich zu Fisch, Muscheln und Krebse waren eine wichtige Quelle von Lebensmitteln. Angeln in der Regel eine Gruppe, und polynesische Fischer erkundet die große Weiten des Ozeans rund um ihr Zuhause. Andere Lebensmittel werden könnten, die von verschiedenen Pflanzen. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Essen Pflanzen auch Materialien für die verschiedenen Gründen. Brotfruchtbaum Holz verwendet wurde im Kanu machen, zum Beispiel, und einige Blätter von Pflanzen wurden in die Weberei Matten, Bekleidung, Segel, und andere Haushaltsgeräte. Sowohl Einzel- und Doppelzimmer Kanus wurden mit Matte Segel. Einige Boote waren groß genug, um Verkehr Familien, domestizierten Tiere und Pflanzen über weite Strecken des Ozeans. Im Laufe der Zeit entwickelte Kulturen unterschiedliche künstlerische Fähigkeiten. Steinruine Tempel finden sich in der Gesellschaft Inseln, die Osterinsel, und die Marquesas Kultur. Gute wie Kanus, Krieg Clubs, Schilde, und Fisch Haken waren aufwendig gestaltet. Feather Mäntel zeigte eine enorme Anstrengungen bei der Erfassung seltener Federn und Vermittlung in komplexen Designs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Kontakt mit der europäischen Kultur begann in den späten 1700er und radikal verändert Polynesien. Spanische Forscher waren eifrig bei der Suche nach Reichtum und der Verbreitung des Christentums. Die niederländischen und britischen auch erkundet Bereichen wie Neuseeland und den samoanischen Inseln. Widerstand der europäischen Intervention in fast allen der polynesischen Inseln, aber solche Bewegungen waren kurz. Für viel Zeit zu kommen, Polynesien würde unter der Macht der europäischen Mächte und die Vereinigten Staaten. Polynesische Kultur, jedoch immer noch in diesen Inseln.</German>
		<Italian>Polinesia comprende l'isola di gruppi di Samoa, Isole Cook, Polinesia francese, e Niue, le isole di Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis, Futuna, Hawaii, e Pitcairn Island. Gli abitanti originari della Nuova Zelanda, i Maori, anche in considerazione della Polinesia. L'isola delle Figi è talvolta inclusi nella Polinesia a causa della sua elevata percentuale di abitanti della Polinesia. Archeologico prove sostiene che la Polinesia è stata regolata dalla migrazione Melanesia iniziate da circa 3.000 a 4.000 anni fa. Il Samoans si ritiene di aver risolto il Marquesas forse già nel 300 dC, e Isola di Pasqua potrebbe essere stata risolta dal Marquesas già nel 400 dC. Hawaii è stata risolta anche da questi viaggiatori durante la seconda metà del primo millennio dC, e poi la società Islanders, che sono stati il punto di origine per i Polinesiani che insediati sul Cook Island. Intorno al 1000 dC, queste culture anche abitato Polinesia. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Prima di contatto europeo, polinesiani erano insediamenti o in frazioni o villaggi. Case sono state raggruppate in piccoli gruppi, e villaggi conteneva 30 o più case. Questi villaggi sono stati trovati soprattutto sulle isole di Samoa e la Nuova Zelanda e sono stati spesso fortificato da mura di pietra o di legno palizzate. Entrambi questi tipi di insediamenti valere famiglia orientata organizzazione. Il tipo più comune di organizzazione di potere che è stato superato dal primo figlio a figlio primogenito, e così via. In Polinesia società, capi sarebbe riverito come uguale agli altri. Tuttavia, di solito si potrebbe risalire la loro famiglia torna alla linea il creatore dei. Nelle società in cui il capo è stato protetto e separato dal popolo, la guerra è stata comune. Missionari cristiani sono riusciti a rovesciare antiche pratiche religiose solo dopo aver convertito capi. [PARAGRAPH: 2] religione e la magia svolto un ruolo importante nella cultura polinesiana. Ciascuno di loro ha avuto dei propri rituali, che sono stati effettuati dai sacerdoti. Tra queste pratiche erano sacrificio, canto, festa, e di riti di fertilità. Magic è stato anche avvolgente, e innumerevoli rituali per quanto riguarda l'amore, la guerra, la vendetta, l'agricoltura, la pesca e sono state praticate. Polinesia cultura è stato un gran marini fonda. Oltre a pesci, molluschi e crostacei sono state un'importante fonte di cibo. La pesca è stata generalmente di un gruppo di attività, e la Polinesia pescatori esplorato il vasto oceano intorno distese di loro case. Altri alimenti possono essere forniti da varie piante. [PARAGRAPH: 2] alimentare impianti anche fornito materiali per vari motivi. Pane di legno è stato usato in canoa fare, per esempio, e le foglie di alcuni impianti sono stati utilizzati in tessitura tappeti, vestiti, vele, e di altri beni. Entrambe le singole e doppie canoe erano equipaggiate con vele tappetino. Alcune imbarcazioni sono state abbastanza grande per il trasporto di famiglie, animali addomesticati, e di impianti per lunghi tratti di mare. Nel corso del tempo, di culture distinte sviluppato capacità artistiche. Rovinato pietra templi si trovano nella Società Isole, Isola di Pasqua, e la cultura Marquesas. Buona come canoe, club di guerra, scudi, e di pesce ganci erano elaboratamente decorato. Piume cloaks mostrato un enorme sforzo nella raccolta di rari piume e organizzare in intricati disegni. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Il contatto con la cultura europea ha avuto inizio alla fine del 1700 e ha cambiato radicalmente la Polinesia. Esploratori spagnoli erano desiderosi di ricerca per la ricchezza e la diffusione del cristianesimo. Gli olandesi e britannici anche esplorare settori come la Nuova Zelanda e le isole Samoa. Resistenza agli europei intervento è avvenuto in quasi tutte le isole della Polinesia, ma tali movimenti sono stati brevi. Per molto tempo a venire, Polinesia andrebbe sotto il potere di potenze europee e gli Stati Uniti. Polinesia cultura, tuttavia, è rimasta sempre in queste isole.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polinesia comprende grupos de la isla de Samoa, las Islas Cook, la Polinesia Francesa, y Niue, las Islas de Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis y Futuna, Hawaii, y la isla de Pitcairn. Los habitantes originarios de Nueva Zelanda, los maoríes, también se consideran de Polinesia. La isla de Fiji veces se incluyen en la Polinesia, debido a su alto porcentaje de habitantes polinesios. Archaeological pruebas apoyan que la Polinesia fue resuelta por la migración de Melanesia inicio unos 3.000 a 4.000 años atrás. Los samoanos se cree que se han asentado las Marquesas quizás ya en 300 dC, y la Isla de Pascua puede haber sido resuelta de las Marquesas ya en 400 DC. Hawaii fue también reiterada por esas viaje durante la segunda mitad del primer milenio dC, y luego la Sociedad de los isleños, que fueron el punto de origen de los polinesios que se establecieron en las Islas Cook. Alrededor de 1000 DC, estas culturas también habitada Polinesia. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Antes del contacto europeo, de Polinesia fueron los asentamientos, ya sea en aldeas o caseríos. Casas se agruparon en grupos pequeños, y los pueblos que figuran 30 o más viviendas. Estas aldeas se encuentran principalmente en las islas de Samoa y Nueva Zelandia y son a menudo fortificadas por muros de piedra o empalizadas de madera. Ambos de estos tipos de asentamientos se basó en la organización orientada a la familia. El tipo más común de organización es que el poder pasa de la primera a hijo nacido hijo primogénito, etc. En las sociedades de Polinesia, jefes sería venerado como iguales a los demás. Sin embargo, por lo general pueden localizar a sus familiares de nuevo a la línea de dioses creadores. En las sociedades en que el jefe estaba protegida y separada del pueblo, la guerra era común. Misioneros cristianos tenido éxito en derrocar a antiguas prácticas religiosas sólo después de que se habían convertido los jefes. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Religión y magia desempeñado un papel importante en la cultura polinesia. Cada uno de los dioses tienen sus propios rituales, que fueron llevados a cabo por los sacerdotes. Entre estas prácticas se sacrificio, cantando, banquete, y los ritos de la fertilidad. Magic también fue envolviendo, y un sinnúmero de rituales en relación con el amor, la guerra, la venganza, la agricultura y la pesca se practica. Cultura polinesia era un gran marino basada. Además de los peces, moluscos y crustáceos son una fuente importante de alimento. La pesca es generalmente una actividad de grupo, y los pescadores polinesios explorar vastas extensiones de los océanos alrededor de sus hogares. Otros alimentos podría ser proporcionada por diversas plantas. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Alimentación plantas también proporcionó materiales por diversas razones. Pan madera se utiliza en la canoa, por ejemplo, y las hojas de algunas plantas se han utilizado en el tejido de alfombras, ropa, velas, y otros artículos para el hogar. Las dos canoas individuales y dobles equipadas con colchoneta velas. Algunos barcos eran lo suficientemente grandes como para el transporte de las familias, los animales domesticados, plantas y más largas extensiones de océano. Con el tiempo, las culturas desarrolladas aptitudes artísticas distintas. Templos de piedra en ruinas se pueden encontrar en la sociedad de las Islas, la Isla de Pascua, la cultura y las Marquesas. Bueno, como canoas, clubes de la guerra, escudos, y los peces se ganchos elaboradamente decorado. Feather mantos mostró una enorme cantidad de esfuerzo en la recopilación y organización de plumas raras en intrincados diseños. [PARAGRAPH: 2] contacto con la cultura europea comenzó a fines de 1700 y cambió radicalmente la Polinesia. Exploradores españoles que estaban deseosos de búsqueda de la riqueza y difundir el cristianismo. Los holandeses y británicos también se exploraron áreas tales como Nueva Zelanda y las islas de Samoa. La resistencia a la intervención europea se produjo en casi todas las islas de la Polinesia, pero esos movimientos fueron breves. Por mucho tiempo, la Polinesia iría bajo el poder de las potencias europeas y los Estados Unidos. Cultura polinesia, sin embargo, siempre se mantuvo en esas islas.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Polinezja - wschodnia część Oceanii, położona w środkowej części Oceanu Spokojnego, po obu stronach równika i po obu stronach linii zmiany daty. Wyspy Polinezji są pochodzenia wulkanicznego lub koralowego. Klimat wysp jest gorący i wilgotny; porasta je bujna roślinność międzyzwrotnikowa. Języki polinezyjskie - grupa języków oceanicznych (wschodnioaustronezyjskich) z rodziny języków austronezyjskich, którymi posługuje się ok. 1 mln rdzennych mieszkańców wysp Oceanii. Większość z nich używana jest w obrębie tzw. trójkąta polinezyjskiego, którego zasięg wyznaczają Hawaje, Nowa Zelandia i Wyspa Wielkanocna, niektóre jednak, klasyfikowane jako języki peryferyjne (ang. outlier) geograficznie pozostają poza trójkątem, na terenie Mikronezji i Melanezji.Hawaje zostały zaludnione w IV wieku przez Polinezyjczyków z Tahiti, którzy dotarli tutaj po mniej więcej 4 wiekach wypraw podejmowanych śladami lecących w tym kierunku ptaków. Dla Europy odkryte zostały przez Jamesa Cooka w 1778. Początkowo Polinezyjczycy potraktowali Cooka jak bóstwo, które przybyło do nich na ogromnym statku. Kiedy jednak Cook opuścił wyspę i musiał na nią powrócić po parodniowym sztormie, uznali, że jest to świadectwo tego, iż nie jest on bogiem. Podczas zbrojnego starcia zginął wtedy Cook i kilku jego marynarzy.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>