<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_WORLD_VIEW</Tag>
		<English>World View</English>
		<French>Vision du Monde</French>
		<Italian>Concezioni del mondo</Italian>
		<German>Weltanschauung</German>
		<Polish>Swiatopogląd</Polish>
		<Russian>Ìèðîâîççðåíèÿ</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_WORLD_VIEW_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The World Views are like civics, but they only have two states on and off. They are an experiment and are implemented as buildings rather than civics due to the number we are thinking of having. Current World Views are:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Cannibalism[\BOLD] - allows the butchering of captives like animals.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Human Sacrifice[\BOLD] - allows the sacrifice of captives.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Slavery[\BOLD] - allows selling or settling captives as slaves.</English>
		<French>Les Visions du monde sont comme les doctrines, mais en étant soit activés ou non. Il s'agit d'un essai expérimental, et sont implémentées en tant que batiment. Les visions du monde actuelles sont:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Cannibalisme[\BOLD] - Permet de manger les prisonniers comme des animaux.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Sacrifice Humain[\BOLD] - Permet le sacrifice des prisonniers.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Esclavage[permet la vente des prisonnier comme esclaves.</French>
		<Italian>Le concezioni del mondo sono come forme di governo, e come tali possono essere attive o no. Sono ancora in fase sperimentale e sono state introdotte come edifici dato che sono poche in confronto alle forme di governo. Le attuali concezioni sono:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Cannibalismo[\BOLD] - permette di uccidere e macellare i prigionieri coome gli animali.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Sacrifici umani[\BOLD] - permette di sacrificare i prigionieri.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Schiavismo[\BOLD] - permette di vendere o utilizzare i prigionieri come schiavi.</Italian>
		<German>Weltanschauung sind wie Gesellschaftsformen, außer das es nur zwei Zustände gibt, aktiv und inaktiv. Diese sind ein Experiment und eher als Gebäude umgesetzt statt als Gesellschaftsformen aufgrund der Anzahl welche wir erwarten. Aktuelle Weltanschauungen sind:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Kannibalismus[\BOLD] - Erlaubt das Schlachten von Gefangenen wie Tiere.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Menschenopfer[\BOLD] - Erlaubt das Opfern von Gefangenen.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Sklaverei[\BOLD] - Erlaubt das Verkaufen oder Ansiedeln von Gefangenen als Sklaven.</German>
		<Polish>Swiatopogląd jest podobny do ustroju. Obecnie istnieją 3 światopoglądy w grze: Kanibalizm, Ofiary z ludzi oraz Niewolnictwo.</Polish>
		<Russian>Мировоззрения в чем-то похожи на Парадигмы, но в них только два состояния - принятие или запрет. Они являются экспериментом и реализованы в виде зданий, а не Парадигм, из-за количественных ограничений. Ниже приведены текущие мировоззрения:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Каннибализм[\BOLD] - позволяет убивать пленных как животных.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Человеческие жертвоприношения[\BOLD] - позволяет приносить пленников в жертву богам и духам в обмен на прирост культуры и счастливые лица.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Рабовладение[\BOLD] - позволяет захватывать, продавать или заселять пленных как рабов.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
