<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB</Tag>
		<English>Air Bomb</English>
		<French>Bombardement aérien</French>
		<German>Luftbombardierung</German>
		<Italian>Bombardamento aereo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bombardeo aéreo</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB1</Tag>
		<English>Airbomb Defenses</English>
		<French>Bombardement des Défenses</French>
		<German>Luftbombardierung Verteidigungen</German>
		<Italian>Bombarda difese</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bombardear defensas</Spanish>
		<Polish>Obrona przed bombardowaniem</Polish>
		<Russian>Укрепления</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB1_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Select an air unit that can airbomb, select the airbomb defense mission, then click on the target city to reduce defense, or target an Improvement to destroy it.</English>
		<French>Sélectionnez une unité aérienne capable de bombarder, puis la mission de bombardement de défenses. Cliquez ensuite sur la cible pour réduire son pourcentage de défense ou ciblez une amélioration de terrain pour la détruire.</French>
		<German>Wählen Sie eine Lufteinheit, die Luftbombardierungen durchführen kann, aktivieren Sie die Mission "Luftbombardierung Verteidigungen" und klicken Sie dann auf die Zielstadt, um deren Verteidigung zu schwächen, oder auf eine Modernisierung, um diese zu zerstören.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Seleziona "bombarda difese" e poi una città per abbatterne le difese oppure seleziona un miglioramento per distruggerlo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Selecciona una unidad que pueda realizar bombardeos aéreos, selecciona la misión "Bombardear defensas" y haz clic en la ciudad objetivo (para reducir su defensa) o en la mejora objetivo (para destruirla).</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wybierz jednostk&#234; powietrzn&#185;, kt&#243;ra mo&#191;e wykona&#230; bombardowanie, wybierz misj&#234; bombardowania umocnie&#241;, a nast&#234;pnie kliknij na mie&#156;cie aby zredukowa&#230; jego obron&#234; lub na udoskonaleniu aby je zniszczy&#230;.</Polish>
		<Russian>Выберите воздушный юнит, который может осуществлять бомбардировку, поручите ему бомбардировку укреплений, а затем щелкните либо город, чтобы уменьшить его показатель защиты, либо объект, чтобы уничтожить его.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB2</Tag>
		<English>Airbomb Buildings</English>
		<French>Bombardement des Bâtiments</French>
		<German>Luftbombardierung Gebäude</German>
		<Italian>Bombarda edifici</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bombardear edificios</Spanish>
		<Polish>Bombardowanie budynk&#243;w</Polish>
		<Russian>Здания</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB2_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Select an air unit that can airbomb, select the airbomb building mission, then click on the target city to attempt to destroy one civil building.</English>
		<French>Sélectionnez une unité aérienne capable de bombarder, puis la mission de bombardement de bâtiments civils. Cliquez ensuite sur la cible pour tenter de détruire un bâtiment civil.</French>
		<German>Wählen Sie eine Lufteinheit, die Luftbombardierungen durchführen kann, wählen Sie die Mission "Luftbombardierung Gebäude" und klicken Sie dann auf die Zielstadt, um zu versuchen, dort ein ziviles Gebäude zu zerstören.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Seleziona "bombarda edifici" e poi clicca su una città per cercare di distruggere un edificio civile.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Selecciona una unidad que pueda realizar bombardeos aéreos, selecciona la misión "Bombardear edificios" y haz clic en la ciudad objetivo para intentar destruir un edificio civil.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wybierz jednostk&#234; powietrzn&#185;, kt&#243;ra mo&#191;e wykona&#230; bombardowanie, wybierz misj&#234; bombardowania budynku, a nast&#234;pnie kliknij na mie&#156;cie aby zniszczy&#230; w nim jeden budynek cywilny.</Polish>
		<Russian>Выберите воздушный юнит, который может осуществлять бомбардировку, поручите ему бомбардировку зданий, а затем щелкните город, в котором нужно уничтожить здание мирного назначения.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB3</Tag>
		<English>Airbomb Factories</English>
		<French>Bombardement d'usines</French>
		<German>Luftbombardierung Fabriken</German>
		<Italian>Bombarda fabbriche</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bombardear fábricas</Spanish>
		<Polish>Bombardowanie fabryk</Polish>
		<Russian>Заводы</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB3_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Select an air unit that can airbomb, select the airbomb production mission, then click on the target city to attempt to destroy one factory.</English>
		<French>Sélectionnez une unité aérienne capable de bombarder, puis la mission de bombardement d'infrastructure de production. Cliquez ensuite sur la cible pour tenter de détruire une usine.</French>
		<German>Wählen Sie eine Lufteinheit, die Luftbombardierungen durchführen kann, aktivieren Sie die Mission "Luftbombardierung Produktion" und klicken Sie dann auf die Zielstadt, um zu versuchen, dort eine Fabrik zu zerstören.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Seleziona "bombarda fabbriche" e poi clicca su una città per cercare di distruggere una fabbrica.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Selecciona una unidad que pueda realizar bombardeos aéreos, selecciona la misión "Bombardear fábricas" y haz clic en la ciudad objetivo para intentar destruir una fábrica.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wybierz jednostk&#234; powietrzn&#185;, kt&#243;ra mo&#191;e wykona&#230; bombardowanie, wybierz misj&#234; bombardowania fabryki, a nast&#234;pnie kliknij na mie&#156;cie aby zniszczy&#230; w nim jeden budynek produkcyjny.</Polish>
		<Russian>Выберите воздушный юнит, который может осуществлять бомбардировку, поручите ему бомбардировку заводов, а затем щелкните город, в котором нужно уничтожить производственную структуру.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB4</Tag>
		<English>Port Airbomb</English>
		<French>Bombardement du Port</French>
		<German>Luftbombardierung Häfen</German>
		<Italian>Bombarda porto</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bombardear puerto</Spanish>
		<Polish>Bombardowanie portu</Polish>
		<Russian>Порты</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB4_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Select an air unit that can airbomb, select the port airbomb mission, then click on the target city to damage and attempt to sink a ship.</English>
		<French>Sélectionnez une unité aérienne capable de bombarder, puis la mission de bombardement du port. Cliquez ensuite sur la ville ciblée et essayer de couler un navire.</French>
		<German>Wählen Sie eine Lufteinheit, die Luftbombardierungen durchführen kann, aktivieren Sie die Mission "Luftbombardierung Häfen" und klicken Sie dann auf die Zielstadt, um zu versuchen, dort ein Schiff zu beschädigen oder zu versenken.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Seleziona "bombarda porto" e poi clicca su una città per cercare di danneggiare o affondare una nave.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Selecciona una unidad que pueda realizar bombardeos aéreos, selecciona la misión "Bombardear puerto" y haz clic en la ciudad objetivo para intentar dañar o hundir un navío.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wybierz jednostk&#234; powietrzn&#185;, kt&#243;ra mo&#191;e wykona&#230; bombardowanie, wybierz misj&#234; bombardowania portu, a nast&#234;pnie kliknij na mie&#156;cie aby uszkodzi&#230; lub zatopi&#230; znajduj&#185;cy si&#234; w nim statek.</Polish>
		<Russian>Выберите воздушный юнит, который может осуществлять бомбардировку, поручите ему бомбардировку портов, а затем щелкните город, в порту которого стоит корабль.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB5</Tag>
		<English>Strategic Airbomb</English>
		<French>Bombardement Stratégique</French>
		<German>Strategische Luftbombardierung</German>
		<Italian>Bombardamento strategico</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bombardeo estratégico</Spanish>
		<Polish>Bombardowanie strategiczne</Polish>
		<Russian>Стратегические цели</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB5_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Select an air unit that can airbomb, select the strategic airbomb mission, then click on the target city to damage the current production project.</English>
		<French>Sélectionnez une unité aérienne capable de bombarder, puis la mission de bombardement stratégique. Cliquez ensuite sur la ville ciblée pour tenter de détruire son projet de construction actuel.</French>
		<German>Wählen Sie eine Lufteinheit, die Luftbombardierungen durchführen kann, aktivieren Sie die Mission "Strategische Luftbombardierung" und klicken Sie dann auf die Zielstadt, um zu versuchen, dort die aktuelle Produktion zu zerstören.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Seleziona "bombardamento strategico" e poi clicca su una città per cercare di danneggiarne la produzione.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Selecciona una unidad que pueda realizar bombardeos aéreos, selecciona la misión "Bombardeo estratégico" y haz clic en la ciudad objetivo para dañar la producción en curso.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wybierz jednostk&#234; powietrzn&#185;, kt&#243;ra mo&#191;e wykona&#230; bombardowanie, wybierz misj&#234; bombardowania strategicznego, a nast&#234;pnie kliknij na mie&#156;cie aby uszkodzi&#230; jego aktualn&#185; produkcj&#234;.</Polish>
		<Russian>Выберите воздушный юнит, который может осуществлять бомбардировку, поручите ему бомбардировку стратегических целей и щелкните город, в котором создается важный объект.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRBOMB_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Destroys city fortifications and tile Improvements.</English>
		<French>Détruire les fortifications de la ville et les aménagements des cases.</French>
		<German>Zerstören Sie Befestigungen und Modernisierungen.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Distrugge le fortificazioni della città e i miglioramenti delle casella.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Destruye fortificaciones de ciudades y mejoras de casillas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRLIFT</Tag>
		<English>Airlift</English>
		<French>Transport aérien</French>
		<German>Lufttransport</German>
		<Italian>Trasporto aereo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Aerotransportar</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AIRLIFT_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Airlifts the unit to another city.</English>
		<French>Transport aérien de l'unité vers une autre ville.</French>
		<German>Fliegen Sie die Einheit in eine andere Stadt.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Trasporta un'unità verso un'altra città per via aerea.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Para aerotransportar a la unidad a otra ciudad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AMBUSH</Tag>
		<English>Ambush enemy units on the same tile!</English>
		<French>Tendre une Embuscade aux ennemis sur la même case!</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Tendi un'imboscata (sulla stessa casella)</Italian>
		<Russian>Устройте засаду вражеским отрядам на этой клетке!</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AMBUSH_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Attacks the best defender of enemy target(s) on the same plot. WARNING: You should only have one unit selected at a time for this or else it will always choose the first available unit to attack with and will not show an accurate odds assessment.</English>
		<French>Attaque le meilleur défenseur ennemi sur la même case. ATTENTION: Action à exécuter avec une seule unité sélectionnée. Sinon le combat sera lancé avec la première unité dans la liste!</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Attacca l'unità nemica con la migliore difesa sulla stessa casella. ATTENZIONE: seleziona solo un'unità alla volta o il sistema sceglierà la prima unità disponibile per attaccare.</Italian>
		<Russian>Атакует лучшего защитника среди вражеской цели(ей) на той же клетке. ВНИМАНИЕ: для этого нужно выбирать лишь один отряд за раз, иначе он всегда будет выбирать первый доступный отряд для атаки и покажет точную оценку шансов.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_ASSASSIN</Tag>
		<English>Assassinate Unit</English>
		<French>Assassiner Unité</French>
		<German>Einheit ermorden</German>
		<Italian>Assassina unità</Italian>
		<Spanish>Asesinar unidad</Spanish>
		<Polish>Skrytob&#243;jstwo</Polish>
		<Russian>Убить подразделение</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_ASSASSINATE</Tag>
		<English>Assassinate enemy units on the same tile!</English>
		<French>Assassiner une unité ennemie de la même case!</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Assassina unità nemiche (sulla stessa casella)</Italian>
		<Russian>Убить вражеские единицы на этой клетке.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_ASSASSINATE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Attacks the best defender of enemy target(s), prioritizing unit types this unit will targets first in a stack, on the same plot. Works inside a city. WARNING: You should only have one unit selected for this action.</English>
		<French>Attaque le meilleur défenseur de la cible ennemie présente sur la même case. Utilisable dans une ville. ATTENTION: ne sélectionner qu'une seule unité pour cette action.</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Attacca l'unità nemica con la migliore difesa sulla stessa casella, tra i tipi di unità che questa unità può attaccare per primi. Funziona all'interno di una città. ATTENZIONE: seleziona solo un'unità alla volta per questa azione.</Italian>
		<Russian>Атакует лучшего защитника среди вражеской цели(ей) (из числа однородных с ним отрядов в стеке) на той же клетке. Работает внутри города. ВНИМАНИЕ: для этого действия у вас должен быть выбран лишь один отряд.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_ASSASSINATE_CHOICE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Choices and Attacks one defender on the same plot. Works inside a city. WARNING: You should only have one unit selected for this action.</English>
		<French>Attaque au choix un des défenseurs présents sur la même case. Utilisable dans une ville. ATTENTION: ne sélectionner qu'une seule unité pour cette action.</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Attacca l'unità nemica con la migliore difesa sulla stessa casella, tra i tipi di unità che questa unità può attaccare per primi. Funziona all'interno di una città. ATTENZIONE: seleziona solo un'unità alla volta per questa azione.</Italian>
		<Russian>Атакует лучшего защитника среди вражеской цели(ей) (из числа однородных с ним отрядов в стеке) на той же клетке. Работает внутри города. ВНИМАНИЕ: для этого действия у вас должен быть выбран лишь один отряд.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AUTO_BUILDUP</Tag>
		<English>Automate Build Ups</English>
		<French>Automatise les retranchements</French>
		<German>Training (automatisiert)</German>
		<Italian>Allenamento automatico</Italian>
		<Russian>Автоматизировать действия</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_AUTO_BUILDUP_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Automate build up selections for all units selected.</English>
		<French>Automatise les retranchements pour toutes les unités sélectionnées.</French>
		<German>Automatisches Training der ausgewählten Einheiten.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Automatizza gli allenamenti per tutte le unità selezionate.</Italian>
		<Russian>Все выбранные единицы будут сами решать, что делать.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BOMBARD</Tag>
		<English>Bombard</English>
		<French>Bombardement</French>
		<German>Bombardierung</German>
		<Italian>Bombardamento</Italian>
		<Spanish>Cañonear</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BOMBARD_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Destroys fortifications and reduces the cities defensive bonus.</English>
		<French>Détruire les fortifications de la ville et réduire ses bonus de défense.</French>
		<German>Zerstören Sie die Befestigungen einer Stadt und senken Sie deren Defensivbonus.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Distrugge le fortificazioni e riduce i bonus difensivi delle città.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Destruye las fortificaciones y reduce la bonificación defensiva de las ciudades.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BRIBE</Tag>
		<English>Bribe Unit</English>
		<French>Corrompre Unité</French>
		<German>Einheit bestechen</German>
		<Italian>Corrompi unità</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sobornar unidad</Spanish>
		<Polish>Przekup jednostk&#234;</Polish>
		<Russian>Подкупить отряд</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BUILDUP</Tag>
		<English>Build Up</English>
		<French>Retranchement</French>
		<Italian>Allenamenti</Italian>
		<German>Training</German>
		<Polish>Koncentracja</Polish>
		<Russian>Концентрация</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BUILDUP_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Select a Promotion Line. For each turn the unit remains stationary, it gains an  additional automatic Promotion from the next level in that line. Unit loses all Build Up Promotions when it next moves. (An alternative form of Fortification.)</English>
		<French>Permet de cumuler le retranchement tout en choisissant une Spécialisation permettant de développer des compétences (sous forme de promotion) à chaque tour tant que l'unité reste sur place. (Il s'agit d'une alternative à 'Se retrancher F'.)</French>
		<German>Einheit zum Training in einer bestimmten Beförderungsreihe abstellen. Pro Runde Training erhält die Einheit eine Zusatzbeförderung (maximal 5 Runden lang). Diese Beförderungen sind nicht dauerhaft. Sie gehen verloren, sobald sich die Einheit bewegt.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Auto-promozione sulla linea selezionata (max 5 turni). Muovere l'unità fa perdere tutti i vantaggi dell'allenamento.</Italian>
		<Polish>Wybierz Lini&#234; Promocji i otrzymaj dodatkow&#185; auto-promocj&#234; z nast&#234;pnego poziomu tej linii promocji za ka&#191;da tur&#234; Koncentracji na danym terenie (max 5 promocji). Jednostka traci Koncentracj&#234; kiedy si&#234; poruszy. (To jest alternatywa do Fortyfikacji jednostek).</Polish>
		<Russian>Выберите линейку Квалификации и получите возможность для доп. автоматического продвижения на следующий уровень в этой строке на каждый ход (до 5), т.е. прокачать навык для отряда. Юнит игнорирует все альт. линии прокачки, весь следующий ход. (Альтер. форма фортификации.)</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BUILD_CITY</Tag>
		<English>Build City</English>
		<French>Fonder une ville</French>
		<German>Stadt gründen</German>
		<Italian>Fonda una città</Italian>
		<Spanish>Construir ciudad</Spanish>
		<Russian>Основать город</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BUILD_CITY_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order causes the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Settler[COLOR_REVERT] to build a city in its current location. The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Settler[COLOR_REVERT] is consumed in the process.</English>
		<French>Ordonne au [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]colon[COLOR_REVERT] de s'installer et de fonder une ville. Le [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]colon[COLOR_REVERT] s'autodétruit dans l'opération.</French>
		<German>Opfern Sie einen [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Siedler[COLOR_REVERT], damit dieser an seinem aktuellen Standort eine Stadt gründet.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]unità colonizzatore[COLOR_REVERT] fonda una città sulla casella su cui si trova e viene sacrificata nel processo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta orden hace que el [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Colono[COLOR_REVERT] construya una ciudad en el lugar en que se encuentre. El [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Colono[COLOR_REVERT] se consumirá en el proceso.</Spanish>
		<Russian>Создать город на текущей позиции [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]градостроителя[COLOR_REVERT]. Подразделение будет потеряно.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BUILD_IMPROVEMENT</Tag>
		<English>Build Improvement</English>
		<French>Construire aménagement</French>
		<German>Modernisierung errichten</German>
		<Italian>Costruisci miglioramento</Italian>
		<Spanish>Construir mejora</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BUTCHER</Tag>
		<English>Butcher Animal</English>
		<French>Abattre l'Animal</French>
		<Italian>Macella l'animale</Italian>
		<Spanish>Descuartizar animal</Spanish>
		<Polish>Zabij zwierz&#234;</Polish>
		<Russian>Разделка животного</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_BUTCHER_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Butchers a Subdued Animal, gives resources in friendly territory and even more in city.</English>
		<French>Abattre un animal apprivoisé donne davantage de ressources en territoire ami, et encore plus dans la ville.</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Produce più risorse se si è in territorio amico e ancora di più nelle città.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Descuartiza un animal domado; dará más recursos en el territorio propio, y aún más en una ciudad.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Zabijanie oswojonych zwierz&#185;t, daje wi&#234;cej surowc&#243;w na swoim terytorium i jeszcze wi&#234;cej w mie&#156;cie.</Polish>
		<Russian>Забивает прирученное животное и дает больше средств на дружественной территории и еще больше в городе.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CLAIM_TERRITORY</Tag>
		<English>Claim territory</English>
		<French>Revendiquer le Territoire</French>
		<German>Territorium beanspruchen</German>
		<Italian>Reclama territorio</Italian>
		<Spanish>Reclamar territorio</Spanish>
		<Polish>Przejmij terytorium</Polish>
		<Russian>Спорная территория</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CLAIM_TERRITORY_CIV_SUCCESS</Tag>
		<English>%s1_civ_adjective units occupied a part of your territory!</English>
		<French>Des unités %s1:3_civ_adjective occupent une partie de votre Territoire!</French>
		<German>%s1_civ_adjective Einheiten besetzten einen Teil Deines Territoriums!</German>
		<Italian>Delle unità %s1_civ_adjective hanno occupato una parte del tuo territorio!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Unidades %s1:4_civ_adjective han ocupado parte de tu territorio.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jednostki z %s1_civ_adjective okupuj&#185; cz&#234;&#156;&#230; Twojego terytorium!</Polish>
		<Russian>Отряды %s1_civ_adjective заняли часть вашей территории!</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CLAIM_TERRITORY_CIV_SUCCESS_NEAR</Tag>
		<English>%s1_civ_adjective units occupied a part of your territory near %s2_city</English>
		<French>Des Unités %s1:3_civ_adjective occupent une partie de votre territoire près de %s2_city</French>
		<German>%s1_civ_adjective Einheiten besetzten einen Teil Deines Territoriums in der Nähe von %s2_city</German>
		<Italian>Delle unità %s1_civ_adjective hanno occupato una parte del tuo territorio vicino alla città di %s2_city</Italian>
		<Spanish>Unidades %s1:4_civ_adjective han ocupado parte de tu territorio cercano a %s2_city.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jednostki z %s1_civ_adjective okupuj&#185; cz&#234;&#156;&#230; Twojego terytorium blisko miasta %s2_city</Polish>
		<Russian>Отряды %s1_civ_adjective заняли часть вашей территории около города %s2_city</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CLAIM_TERRITORY_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit will occupy the tile it is on and adjoin it to your empire. Effects will be visible next turn.</English>
		<French>L'unité va occuper la case sur laquelle elle se trouve et la revendiquer pour qu'elle rejoigne votre Empire. Les effets seront visibles au tour suivant.</French>
		<German>Die Einheit wird das Geländefeld besetzen und es Deinem Imperium hinzufügen. Die Effekte werden in der nächsten Runde sichtbar sein.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità occuperà annetterà la casella su cui si trova al tuo impero. Gli effetti saranno visibili dal prossimo turno.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad ocupará la casilla en la que está y la anexionará a tu imperio. Los efectos serán apreciables el próximo turno.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jednostka b&#234;dzie okupywa&#230; pole na kt&#243;rym stoi i przy&#179;&#185;czy go do Twego imperium. Efekty b&#234;d&#185; widoczne w nast&#234;pnej turze.</Polish>
		<Russian>Отряд займет клетку, на которой он находится, и присоединит ее к вашей державе. Эффекты будут видны на следующем ходу.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CONDUCT_TRADE_MISSION</Tag>
		<English>Conduct Trade Mission</English>
		<French>Mission commerciale</French>
		<German>Handelsmission ausführen</German>
		<Italian>Conduci una missione commerciale</Italian>
		<Spanish>Realizar misión comercial</Spanish>
		<Russian>Провести торговую миссию</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CONDUCT_TRADE_MISSION_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Conduct a Trade Mission in this city. The amount of Gold created is relative to the size of the city and the distance to the city the unit was trained in, as well as if the city is foreign. It consumes a Great Person, but sends regular merchants and criminals back to the capital. Criminals, attempting to trade their contraband, may fail an investigation check for this mission and thus fail to derive the Gold, and they may lose their movement for the turn and become 'Wanted'.</English>
		<French>Effectuez une mission commerciale dans cette ville. La quantité d'or générée dépend de la taille de la ville, de la distance à la ville où l'unité a été formée, ainsi que du fait que la ville soit étrangère. Cela "consomme" un Personnage Illustre, mais renvoie les marchands ordinaires et les criminels à la capitale. Les criminels tentant de commercer leur contrebande peuvent échouer le contrôle d'enquête de cette mission, échouant ainsi à générer de l'or, et peuvent perdre leur mouvement pour le tour et devenir «recherchés».</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Inizia una missione commerciale in questa città. La quantità di oro creata dipende dalle dimensioni e dalla distanza dalla città in cui l'unità è stata addestrata o in cui è nata, e dipende anche dal fatto che la città sia straniera. Consuma un gran personaggio, ma rimanda alla capitale mercanti e criminali regolari.</Italian>
		<Russian>Проведите торговую миссию в этом городе. Количество полученного золота зависит от размера города, в котором отряд был обучен, а также размера и расстояния до города в пункте назначения, и от того, является ли город иностранным. При этом тратится Великий человек, но отправляет в столицу обычных торговцев и преступников. Преступники, пытающиеся продать свою контрабанду, могут не пройти проверку правоохранителей в этой миссии и, таким образом, не получить золото, потерять очки движения на ход и оказаться в розыске.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CONSTRUCT</Tag>
		<English>Construct</English>
		<French>Construire</French>
		<German>Bauen</German>
		<Italian>Costruisci edificio speciale</Italian>
		<Spanish>Erigir</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CONSTRUCT_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This will have the Great Person create their special building. It consumes the Great Person.</English>
		<French>Ordonner au personnage illustre de construire son édifice spécial. Le personnage illustre est alors détruit.</French>
		<German>Opfern Sie die Große Persönlichkeit, damit diese ihr Spezialgebäude errichtet.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Il gran personaggio costruisce un edificio speciale. L'unità viene sacrificata nel processo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hace que el gran personaje cree su edificio especial, consumiéndose en el proceso.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CREATE_GREAT_WORK</Tag>
		<English>Create Great Work</English>
		<French>Créer un chef d'oeuvre</French>
		<German>Großes Bauwerk errichten</German>
		<Italian>Crea un'opera d'arte</Italian>
		<Spanish>Crear gran obra</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CREATE_GREAT_WORK_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order will have the Great Artist create a Great Work in the city they are currently in. It consumes the Great Person.</English>
		<French>Ordonner à l'artiste illustre de créer un chef d'oeuvre dans la ville où il se trouve. Ceci détruit le personnage illustre.</French>
		<German>Opfern Sie die Große Persönlichkeit, damit ein Großer Künstler in der aktuellen Stadt ein großes Kunstwerk erschafft.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Il gran artista crea un' opera d'arte nella città in cui si trova. L'unità viene sacrificata nel processo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta orden hace que el gran artista cree una gran obra en la ciudad en la que se encuentre, consumiéndose en el proceso.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CURE</Tag>
		<English>Cure Next Unit in Stack of a Curable Affliction</English>
		<French>Guérir la prochaine unité dans la pile d'une affection curable</French>
		<Italian>Cura la prossima unità presente nel gruppo di un'afflizione curabile</Italian>
		<Polish>Leczy nast&#234;pn&#185; jednostk&#234; w grupie</Polish>
		<Russian>Вылечить указанный отряд в стеке от повреждений</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_CURE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order will cause the healer to improve the condition of one Affliction from the first of your units sharing the same plot that is beset by an Affliction that the healer can cure.</English>
		<French>Cet ordre amènera le guérisseur à améliorer l'état d'affliction de la première de vos unités partageant le même groupe, si elle est victime d'une Affliction que le guérisseur peut guérir.</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Il guaritore migliora la condizione di un afflizione della prima unità presente nella stessa casella se l'afflizione è curabile.</Italian>
		<Polish>Ten rozkaz spowoduje, &#191;e Lekarz wyleczy jedn&#185; dolegliwo&#156;&#230;, kt&#243;r&#185; potrafi wyleczy&#230;, pierwszej jednostce z grupy na tym samym polu.</Polish>
		<Russian>Эта команда заставит медика исцелить от ранений один из ваших отрядов, расположенных на одном с лекарем участке, или от болезни, от которой медик может вылечить.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_DESTROY</Tag>
		<English>Destroy Production</English>
		<French>Saboter la production</French>
		<German>Produktion zerstören</German>
		<Italian>Distruggi produzione</Italian>
		<Spanish>Destruir producción</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_DESTROY_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Spy[COLOR_REVERT] will attempt to destroy the city's current production.</English>
		<French>L'[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]espion[COLOR_REVERT] tentera de saboter la production en cours de la ville.</French>
		<German>Der [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Spion[COLOR_REVERT] versucht, die aktuelle Produktion der Stadt zu zerstören.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]La [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]spia[COLOR_REVERT] tenterà di distruggere la produzione attuale della città.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Espía[COLOR_REVERT] intentará destruir la producción que haya en ese momento en la ciudad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_DISCOVER_TECH</Tag>
		<English>Discover Technology</English>
		<French>Découvrir une technologie</French>
		<German>Technologie entdecken</German>
		<Italian>Scopri tecnologia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Descubrir tecnología</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_DISCOVER_TECH_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This will have the Great Person help research a Technology. It consumes the Great Person.</English>
		<French>Ordonner au personnage illustre de découvrir automatiquement une nouvelle technologie. Le personnage illustre est alors détruit.</French>
		<German>Opfern Sie die Große Persönlichkeit, damit diese automatisch eine Technologie entdeckt.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Il gran personaggio aiuta a scoprire una tecnologia. L'unità viene sacrificata nel processo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hace que el gran personaje descubra automáticamente una tecnología, consumiéndose en el proceso.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_ESPIONAGE_SLEEP</Tag>
		<English>Gather Intel</English>
		<French>Récolte d'Infos</French>
		<German>Sammle Informationen</German>
		<Italian>Raccogli informazioni</Italian>
		<Spanish>Recopilar información</Spanish>
		<Polish>Zgromad&#159; Dane</Polish>
		<Russian>Собирать разведданные</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_ESPIONAGE_SLEEP_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This unit will gather intelligence and not awaken until it reaches the maximum Espionage bonus</English>
		<French>Cette Unité va récolter des Informations et devenir à nouveau active lorsqu'elle aura atteint son bonus maximum d'espionnage.</French>
		<German>Diese Einheit wird Informationen sammeln und nicht aufwachen bis sie ihr Maximum an Spionagepunkten erreicht hat</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità raccoglierà informazioni e non si riattiverà finché non avrà raggiunto il massimo bonus di spionaggio.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta unidad recopilará información y no se activará hasta que alcance la máxima bonificación por espionaje.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jednostka b&#234;dzie zbiera&#230; dane i nie obudzi si&#234; dop&#243;ki nie zbierze kompletnych danych(maksymalnego bonusu do szpiegostwa).</Polish>
		<Russian>Этот юнит соберет сведения и не проснется, пока не достигает максимального бонуса шпионажа</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_FENGAGE</Tag>
		<English>Fighter Engagement</English>
		<French>Engagement Aérien</French>
		<German>Jägereinsatz</German>
		<Italian>Battaglia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Combate</Spanish>
		<Polish>Anga&#191;owanie my&#156;liwc&#243;w</Polish>
		<Russian>Бой истребителей</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_FENGAGE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Select a fighter unit, select the fighter engagement mission and then select the enemy unit to attack.</English>
		<French>Sélectionner un avion de chasse, puis l'action 'Engagement Aérien', et enfin la cible à attaquer.</French>
		<German>Wählen Sie eine Jägereinheit, wählen Sie die Jägereinsatzmission und anschließend die feindliche Einheit, die angegriffen werden soll.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Selezione l'unità nemica da attaccare.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Selecciona un caza, selecciona la misión "Combate" y haz clic en la unidad enemiga para atacarla.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wybierz jednostk&#234; my&#156;liwca, wybierz misj&#234; anga&#191;owania my&#156;liwc&#243;w i wybierz jednostk&#234; wroga do zaatakowania.</Polish>
		<Russian>Выберите истребитель, отдайте ему приказ вступить в бой истребителей и укажите цель.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_FORTIFY</Tag>
		<English>Fortify</English>
		<French>Se retrancher</French>
		<German>Verschanzen</German>
		<Italian>Fortificazione</Italian>
		<Spanish>Fortificar</Spanish>
		<Russian>Укрепиться</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_FORTIFY_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit "digs in" to better withstand enemy attack. A unit gets a cumulative 5% defensive bonus (plus it's Dig In ability) for each turn it is fortified, capping out after 5 turns. Note that on Hide and Seek games, Fortified units automatically lose all invisibility.</English>
		<French>L'unité s'installe et profite du terrain pour mieux résister aux attaques ennemies. Une unité obtient un bonus défensif cumulatif de 5%% (plus sa capacité de retranchement) pour chaque tour où elle est fortifiée, plafonnant à 5 tours. Notez qu'avec le mode de combat cache-cache, les unités fortifiées perdent automatiquement toute invisibilité.</French>
		<German>Einheit in Befestigungsmodus versetzen zur besseren Verteidigung im Falle eines Angriffs. Pro befestigter Runde erhält die Einheit einen zusätzlichen Verteidigungsbonus von 5%%, bis zu einem Maximum von 25%%. Befestigte Einheiten verlieren im "Versteckspiel" jegliche Unsichtbarkeit.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Bonus difensivo del 5% (più i vantaggi della sua abilità) per ogni turno (max 5 turni). Con l'opzione "nascondino" attiva, le unità fortificate perdono l'invisibilità</Italian>
		<Russian>Поздразделение «окапается» для лучшего противодействия вражеской атаке. Оно будет получать накопительный 5%-ный бонус к защите (плюс способность «Окапывание») за каждый ход (но не более пяти), пока стоит на месте. Обратите внимание, что с включенной игровой опцией «Игра в прятки» укрепившиеся единицы автоматически теряют всю маскировку.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GOTO</Tag>
		<English>Go To City</English>
		<French>Aller à la Ville</French>
		<German>Zielstadt</German>
		<Spanish>Ir a ciudad</Spanish>
		<Italian>Via a una città</Italian>
		<Polish>Id&#159; do Miasta</Polish>
		<Russian>Идти к городу</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GOTO_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Select a city to send this unit to. The city does not need to be inside the current Viewport.</English>
		<French>Sélectionner une ville où envoyer l'unité (n'a pas besoin d'être dans la fenêtre de vue).</French>
		<German>Ausgewählte Einheit zu einer beliebigen Zielstadt (auch außerhalb des aktuellen Sichtfelds) beordern.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Manda l'unità a una città specifica.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Selecciona una ciudad a la que enviar la unidad. No es necesario que dicha ciudad se encuentre dentro de la Vista parcial actual.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wybierz miasto do kt&#243;rego si&#234; ma uda&#230; jednostka. Miasto nie musi znajdowa&#230; si&#234; na bie&#191;&#185;cym Viewporcie.</Polish>
		<Russian>Выберите город, куда нужно отправить данную единицу. Города не должны быть внутри текущего обзорного экрана.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_CISLUNAR</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Cislunar Space</English>
		<French>Voyager vers l'espace cislunaire</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa dello spazio cislunare</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_DISTANT_COSMOS</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Distant Cosmos</English>
		<French>Voyager vers le cosmos lointain</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa dello spazio distante</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_EARTH</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Earth</English>
		<French>Voyager vers la Terre</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa della Terra</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_INNER_SOLAR_SYSTEM</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Inner Solar System</English>
		<French>Voyager vers le système solaire intérieur</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa del sistema solare interno</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_LOCAL_GROUP</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Local Group</English>
		<French>Voyager vers le Groupe local</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa del gruppo locale di galassie</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_MARS</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Mars</English>
		<French>Voyager vers Mars</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa di Marte</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_MILKY_WAY</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Milky Way</English>
		<French>Voyager vers la Voie lactée</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa della via lattea</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_MOON</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Moon</English>
		<French>Voyager vers la Lune</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa della luna</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_NEARBY_STARS</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Nearby Stars</English>
		<French>Voyager vers des étoiles proches</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa delle stelle vicine</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_ORION_ARM</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Orion Arm</English>
		<French>Voyager vers le Bras d'Orion</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa del braccio di Orione</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_OUTER_SOLAR_SYSTEM</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Outer Solar System</English>
		<French>Voyager vers le système solaire extérieur</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa del sistema solare esterno</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_SUBTERRAIN</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Earth Underground</English>
		<French>Voyager sous la surface de la Terre</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa del sottosuolo terrestre</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_TITAN</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Titan</English>
		<French>Voyager vers Titan</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa di Titano</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_TRANSNEPTUNIAN</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Kuiper Belt</English>
		<French>Voyager vers la ceinture de Kuiper</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa della fascia di Kuiper</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_UNIVERSE</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Universe</English>
		<French>Voyager vers l'Univers</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa dell'universo</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_VENUS</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Venus</English>
		<French>Voyager vers Vénus</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa di Venere</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GO_TO_MAP_VIRGO_SUPERCLUSTER</Tag>
		<English>Travel to Virgo Superscluster</English>
		<French>Voyager vers le superamas de la Vierge</French>
		<Italian>Vai alla mappa del superammasso della Vergine</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GREAT_COMMANDER</Tag>
		<English>Field Commander</English>
		<French>Commandant de Terrain</French>
		<German>Feldkommandeur</German>
		<Italian>Comandante da campo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Comandante de tierra</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dow&#243;dca Polowy</Polish>
		<Russian>Полевой командир</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GREAT_COMMODORE</Tag>
		<English>Sea commodore</English>
		<French>Amiral de terrain</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GREAT_COMMODORE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Sea Commodore, will lose its ability to join cities make Wonders, but will get the ability to earn Experience, gain Promotions and lead naval units into battle.</English>
		<French>L'Amiral de terrain perdra sa capacité à rejoindre les villes et construire des Merveilles, mais gagnera la capacité d'accumuler de l'expérience, d'obtenir des promotions et de diriger les unités navales au combat.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_GREAT_COMMANDER_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Turns the Great General into a Field Commander: it loses its abilities to join cities, units, or construct Wonders, but acquires the ability to earn Experience, gain Promotions, and lead units in the field.</English>
		<French>Converti le Général Illustre en Commandant de Terrain, qui perd la possibilité de s'associer aux Villes et Unités, mais peut acquérir de l'expérience et des promotions, et mener les Unités sur le terrain.</French>
		<German>Verwandelt den Großen General in einen Feldkommandeur, wodurch er seine normalen Fertigkeiten verliert. Dafür kann er nun Erfahrungspunkte und Beförderungen aus Schlachten erhalten, an denen er teilnimmt, und damit die Einheiten in seinem näheren Umfeld unterstützen.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Trasforma il gran generale in un comandante da campo: perderà l'abilità di unirsi a città ed unità e di costruire le Meraviglie, ma guadagnerà esperienza, promozioni e potrà condurre altre unità sul campo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Convierte al Gran general en un Comandante de tierra, que pierde sus habilidades para unirse a las ciudades y unidades, o construir maravillas, pero le otorga la capacidad de adquirir experiencia y ascensos, y liderar a las unidades en el campo de batalla.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Zmie&#241; Wielkiego Genera&#179;a w Dow&#243;dce Polowego, traci w&#243;wczas mo&#191;liwo&#156;&#230; by do&#179;&#185;czy&#230; do miast, jednostek czy budowa&#230; cuda, ale daje mo&#191;liwo&#156;&#230; zdobywania do&#156;wiadczenia, promocji oraz prowadzi&#230; jednostki na polu bitwy.</Polish>
		<Russian>Превращает Великого Генерала в Полевого командира, который теряет возможность присоединяются к городам, отрядам или чудесам, но дает ему способность заработать опыт, повышения и лидерство в поле.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HEAL</Tag>
		<English>Fortify Until Healed</English>
		<French>Se retrancher jusqu'à guérison</French>
		<German>Bis zur vollständigen Heilung verschanzen</German>
		<Italian>Fortificazione (fino alla guarigione)</Italian>
		<Spanish>Fortificar hasta curarse</Spanish>
		<Russian>Укрепиться до исцеления</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HEAL_BUILDUP</Tag>
		<English>Automate Build Up Selections for Healing</English>
		<French>Retranchement avec Spécialisation de Soin.</French>
		<German>Training (automatisiert) - Heilung</German>
		<Italian>Automatizza selezione degli allenamenti per la guarigione</Italian>
		<Russian>Автоматизировать лечение</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HEAL_BUILDUP_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Automate build up selections (with emphasis on healing) for all units selected until fully healed. Turns to heal is maximum - with this mission, units may take less time to heal (but may also be weaker while doing so.)</English>
		<French>Automatise la sélection du retranchement (spécialisation soins) pour toutes les unités sélectionnées, jusqu'à qu'elles soient complètement guéries. Le nombre de tours indiqué est un maximum - Car le bonus de soin est incrémental - l'unité met moins de temps pour se soigner, mais est plus vulnérable.</French>
		<German>Automatische Steigerung der Regeneration der ausgewählten Einheiten bis zur kompletten Wiederherstellung. Einheiten sind auf diesem Weg schneller wieder einsatzbereit, dafür sind sie in der Rekonvaleszenzzeit aber schwächer und ungeschützter.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Automatizza le selezioni degli allenamenti (con enfasi sulla guarigione) per tutte le unità selezionate finché non sono completamente guarite.</Italian>
		<Russian>Автоматизировать действия (с упором на исцеление) всех выбранных единиц до их полного восстановления. У подразделений с этим указанием может уйти меньше времени - а также может снизиться эффективность - до окончания лечения.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HEAL_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit remains inactive until it reaches full strength.</English>
		<French>L'unité reste inactive tant que son niveau de santé n'est pas au maximum.</French>
		<German>Einheit ruhen und heilen lassen, bis diese wieder volle Stärke besitzt.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità rimane inattiva finché non ritorna al massimo delle forze.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad permanecerá inactiva hasta que recobre el total de su fuerza.</Spanish>
		<Russian>Единица останется неактивной, пока полностью не восстановит силы.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HERITAGE</Tag>
		<English>Add Heritage</English>
		<French>Ajouter au patrimoine</French>
		<Russian>Добавить культурное наследние</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HERITAGE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Consumes the unit.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]utilise et détruit l'unité.</French>
		<Russian>[ICON_BULLET]Подразделение исчезнет в процессе.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HURRY_FOOD</Tag>
		<English>Hurry Food</English>
		<French>Surplus de Nourriture</French>
		<German>Nahrungsproduktion beschleunigen</German>
		<Italian>Accelera cibo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Envío alimentario</Spanish>
		<Polish>Przy&#156;piesz &#191;ywno&#156;&#230;</Polish>
		<Russian>Добавить пищу</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HURRY_FOOD_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order will increase the cities Food supply. It consumes the unit.</English>
		<French>Cet Ordre va accroitre la réserve de nourriture des Villes. L'unité est détruite.</French>
		<German>Dieser Befehl wird die Nahrungsmittelvorräte in der Stadt erhöhen. Die Einheit wird dabei verbraucht.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Incrementa le riserve di cibo della città. Consuma l'unità nel processo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta orden incrementará la comida almacenada en las ciudades. Consumirá a la unidad.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Ten rozkaz zwi&#234;kszy zaopatrzenie miasta w &#191;ywno&#156;&#230;. Jest to zu&#191;ywane przez jednostki.</Polish>
		<Russian>Подразделение исчезнет, увеличив поставки продовольствия в городе.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HURRY_PRODUCTION</Tag>
		<English>Hurry Production</English>
		<French>Accélérer la production</French>
		<German>Produktion beschleunigen</German>
		<Italian>Accelera produzione</Italian>
		<Spanish>Acelerar la producción</Spanish>
		<Russian>Ускорить производство</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_HURRY_PRODUCTION_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order will hurry production on the city's current effort. It consumes the unit.</English>
		<French>Accélérer la production en cours de la ville, ce qui détruit le personnage illustre.</French>
		<German>Opfern Sie die Große Persönlichkeit, um die aktuelle Produktion der Stadt zu beschleunigen.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]La produzione attuale della città viene accelerata. L'unità viene sacrificata nel processo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El gran personaje acelera la producción que la ciudad esté llevando a cabo, consumiéndose en el proceso.</Spanish>
		<Russian>Подразделение исчезнет, ускорив текущее производство города.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_INFILTRATE</Tag>
		<English>Infiltrate Player's City</English>
		<French>Infiltrer la ville d'un joueur</French>
		<German>Spielerstadt infiltrieren</German>
		<Italian>Infiltrazione città</Italian>
		<Spanish>Infiltrar en ciudad de jugador</Spanish>
		<Russian>Внедрение в чужой город</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_INFILTRATE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order will have the Spy or Criminal infiltrate a foreign city to bring home useful information (Espionage Points) about the rival. Spies use Espionage Points and are consumed. Criminals must pass an investigation check to be successful. If they are, they are sent back to the capital. Otherwise, they become wanted and lose the rest of their movement for that turn.</English>
		<French>Cet ordre demande à l'espion ou au criminel d'infiltrer une ville étrangère pour rapporter des informations utiles (points d'espionnage) sur le rival. Les espions utilisent des points d'espionnage et sont consommés. Les criminels doivent réussir un contrôle d'enquête pour réussir. S'ils réussissent, ils sont renvoyés à la capitale. Sinon, ils deviennent recherchés et perdent le reste de leur mouvement pour ce tour.</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]La spia o il criminale si infiltra in una città straniera per portare a casa informazioni utili (punti spionaggio) riguardo il rivale. Le spie usano i punti spionaggio e sono consumate nel processo. I criminali devono superare un controllo investigativo per avere successo. In caso positivo, vengono rispediti alla capitale. Altrimenti, diventano ricercati e perdono il resto del loro movimento per quel turno.</Italian>
		<Russian>Прикажет шпиону или преступнику проникнуть в чужой город, чтобы раздобыть в нем ценную информацию (очки шпионажа) о сопернике. Шпионы используют и тратят очки шпионажа. Преступники должны пройти проверку от местных правоохранителей, чтобы добиться успеха. В случае успеха миссии, их возвращают обратно в столицу. В противном случае их объявляют в розыск и они потеряют оставшиеся очки движения за этот ход..</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_INQUISITION</Tag>
		<English>Perform Inquisition</English>
		<French>Réaliser une Inquisition</French>
		<German>Inquisition durchführen</German>
		<Italian>Inquisizione</Italian>
		<Spanish>Convocar un Tribunal de la Fé</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dokonaj Inkwizycji</Polish>
		<Russian>Провести инквизиционный процесс</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_INQUISITION_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Allows the unit to remove all Non-State Religions.</English>
		<French>Permet à l'unité de purger la ville de toutes les religions non officielles.</French>
		<German>Ermöglicht der Einheit alle nichtstaatlichen Religionen zu entfernen.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Permette all'unità di rimuovere tutte le religioni non di stato.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Permite a la unidad eliminar todas las religiones no oficiales.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pozwala jednostce, usun&#185;&#230; wszystkie niepa&#241;stwowe religie.</Polish>
		<Russian>Позволяет подразделению удалить все негосударственные религии из города</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_INTERCEPT</Tag>
		<English>Intercept</English>
		<French>Intercepter</French>
		<German>Abfangen</German>
		<Italian>Intercetta</Italian>
		<Spanish>Interceptar</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_INTERCEPT_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This air unit order will tell the craft to attempt interception with any incoming air attacks.</English>
		<French>Ordonner à l'unité de tenter d'intercepter toutes les raids aériens ennemis.</French>
		<German>Befehlen Sie einer Lufteinheit, alle Luftangriffe abzufangen.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Il velivolo cercherà di intercettare qualsiasi tentativo di attacco aereo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta orden es para unidades aéreas y les dice que intenten interceptar todos los ataques aéreos que lleguen.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_JOIN_CITY</Tag>
		<English>Join City</English>
		<French>Rejoindre la ville</French>
		<German>Sich einer Stadt anschließen</German>
		<Italian>Risiedi in città</Italian>
		<Spanish>Unirse a ciudad</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_JOIN_CITY_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order will make the Great Person join the city as a Super Specialist. It will consume the Great Person.</English>
		<French>Ordonner à ce personnage illustre de rejoindre la ville en tant que super-spécialiste. Il est alors détruit.</French>
		<German>Opfern Sie eine Große Persönlichkeit und befehlen Sie ihr, sich als Super-Spezialist in der Stadt anzusiedeln.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Il gran personaggio può unirsi alla città in veste di super specialista, venendo sacrificato nel processo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta orden hace que el gran personaje se quede en la ciudad como un superespecialista, consumiéndose en el proceso.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_KILL_SPY</Tag>
		<English>Kill Nearby Spy</English>
		<French>Tuer espion proche</French>
		<German>Spion in der Nähe töten</German>
		<Italian>Uccidi spia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Matar al espía cercano</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_KILL_SPY_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Kill adjacent Spy</English>
		<French>Tuer espion adjacent</French>
		<German>Spion in der Nähe eliminieren</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Uccidi una spia su una casella adiacente</Italian>
		<Spanish>Matar al espía adyacente.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_LAWYER_REMOVE_CORPORATIONS</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Litigate[COLOR_REVERT][NEWLINE]Take legal action and drive all Corporations from the city.</English>
		<French>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]mettre en litige[COLOR_REVERT][NEWLINE]Prendre des mesures juridiques et conduire toutes les entreprises de la ville au procès.</French>
		<Italian>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Querela[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Spanish>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Denunciar[COLOR_REVERT][NEWLINE]Tomar acciones legales para expulsar a todas las corporaciones de la ciudad.</Spanish>
		<Polish>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Zaskar&#191;[COLOR_REVERT][NEWLINE]Legalnym sposobem wyp&#234;d&#159; wszystkie korporacje ze swojego miasta.</Polish>
		<Russian>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Судебный процесс[COLOR_REVERT][NEWLINE]Предъявите судебный иск от имени государства и изгоните все корпорации из города.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_LAWYER_REMOVE_CORPORATIONS_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Litigate[COLOR_REVERT][NEWLINE]Take legal action and drive all Corporations from the city.</English>
		<French>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]mettre en litige[COLOR_REVERT][NEWLINE]Prendre des mesures juridiques et conduire toutes les entreprises de la ville au procès.</French>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Tramite azioni legali rimuovi tutte le corporazioni dalla città.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]Puede tomar acciones legales</Spanish>
		<Polish>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Zaskar&#191;[COLOR_REVERT][NEWLINE]Legalnym sposobem wyp&#234;d&#159; wszystkie korporacje ze swojego miasta.</Polish>
		<Russian>[COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Судебный процесс[COLOR_REVERT][NEWLINE]Предъявите судебный иск от имени государства и изгоните все корпорации из города.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_MOVE_TO</Tag>
		<English>Move To</English>
		<French>Aller vers</French>
		<German>Fortbewegen nach</German>
		<Italian>Muovi</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mover a</Spanish>
		<Russian>Двигаться к</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_MOVE_TO_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Set your unit to move to a specific plot</English>
		<French>Ordonner à l'unité de rejoindre une position sur la carte.</French>
		<German>Schicken Sie Ihre Einheit auf ein bestimmtes Geländefeld.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE] Muovi l'unità su una specifica casella.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Para decirle a la unidad que vaya a una casilla concreta.</Spanish>
		<Russian>Приказать подразделению переместиться на опредленную клетку</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_MOVE_TO_SENTRY</Tag>
		<English>Move and Sentry</English>
		<French>Déplacement et Surveillance</French>
		<German>Wache bei Fortbewegung</German>
		<Italian>Movimento e sentinella</Italian>
		<Spanish>Moverse y vigilar</Spanish>
		<Polish>Ruch i Warta</Polish>
		<Russian>Перемещаться, наблюдая</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_MOVE_TO_SENTRY_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit moves until an enemy unit of the same type enters its visibility range.</English>
		<French>L'unité se déplace automatiquement tant qu'une unité ennemie ne pénètre pas dans son champ de vision.</French>
		<German>Lässt eine sich bewegende Einheit aktiv werden, bis sie sich einer feindlichen Einheit desselben Einheitentyps nähert</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità si muove finché un'unità nemica dello stesso tipo non entra nel suo raggio di visibilità.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad se mueve hasta que una unidad enemiga del mismo tipo se sitúe en su campo de visión.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jednostka b&#234;dzie porusza&#230; si&#234; tak d&#179;ugo a&#191; nie spotka wrogiej jednostki</Polish>
		<Russian>Единица будет двигаться до тех пор, пока в ее зоне видимости не окажутся вражеские подразделения того же типа.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_MOVE_TO_UNIT</Tag>
		<English>Move To Unit</English>
		<French>Aller vers l'unité</French>
		<German>Einheit fortbewegen nach</German>
		<Italian>Muovi verso unità</Italian>
		<Spanish>Llevar hasta la unidad</Spanish>
		<Russian>Переместиться к подразделению</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_MOVE_TO_UNIT_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Set your unit to move to a unit</English>
		<French>Ordonner à l'unité de rejoindre une autre unité.</French>
		<German>Schicken Sie Ihre Einheit zu einer anderen Einheit.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità si muove verso un'altra unità.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Para decirle a la unidad que vaya hasta otra unidad.</Spanish>
		<Russian>Приказать единице двигаться к указанному подразделению.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_NUKE</Tag>
		<English>Plant Nuclear Device</English>
		<French>Placer une arme nucléaire</French>
		<German>Nuklearen Sprengkörper einschleusen</German>
		<Italian>Lancia bomba atomica</Italian>
		<Spanish>Colocar una bomba nuclear</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pod&#179;&#243;&#191; &#163;adunek Nuklearny</Polish>
		<Russian>Ядерный удар</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_NUKE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Drops a nuclear device onto the selected space.</English>
		<French>Larguer une arme nucléaire sur la case sélectionnée.</French>
		<German>Werfen Sie im Zielgebiet eine Atombombe ab.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Lancia una bomba atomica nella casella selezionata.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Deja caer una bomba nuclear en la casilla seleccionada.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_PARADROP</Tag>
		<English>Paradrop</English>
		<French>Parachuter</French>
		<German>Fallschirmsprung</German>
		<Italian>Lancio col paracadute</Italian>
		<Spanish>Desembarco aéreo</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_PARADROP_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Paradrops to a specified location. The mission is subject to interception.</English>
		<French>Parachuter des troupes à un endroit précis. La mission peut être interceptée.</French>
		<German>Fallschirmsprung an eine ausgewählte Stelle. Die Mission kann abgefangen werden.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Paracaduta le truppe nella casella specificata. La missione può essere intercettata.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Se lanza en paracaídas en el lugar especificado. La misión es susceptible de ser interceptada.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_PERFORM_ESPIONAGE</Tag>
		<English>Perform Espionage Mission</English>
		<French>Exécuter mission d'espionnage</French>
		<German>Spionagemission ausführen</German>
		<Italian>Missione di spionaggio</Italian>
		<Spanish>Realizar misión de espionaje</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_PILLAGE</Tag>
		<English>Pillage</English>
		<French>Pillage</French>
		<German>Plünderung</German>
		<Italian>Saccheggio</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saquear</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_PILLAGE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit destroys an Improvement in the tile it occupies.</English>
		<French>L'unité détruit un aménagement de terrain dans la case qu'elle occupe.</French>
		<German>Die Einheit plündert und zerstört Landschaftsverbesserungen auf ihrem Geländefeld.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità distrugge un miglioramento sulla casella che occupa.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad destruye una mejora en la casilla en que se encuentra.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jednostka zniszczy&#179;a udoskonalenie na okupowanym polu.</Polish>
		<Russian>Отряд уничтожает улучшения клетки, на которой находится.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_PLUNDER</Tag>
		<English>Blockade</English>
		<French>Blocus</French>
		<German>Blockade</German>
		<Italian>Blocco commerciale</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bloqueo</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_PLUNDER_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit disrupts the Trade Route so that no intercontinental trade can pass through the blockaded tile</English>
		<French>L'unité effectue le blocus de la case pour empêcher tout commerce intercontinental par cette route commerciale.</French>
		<German>Die Einheit unterbricht den Handelsweg, daher kann kein interkontinentaler Handel auf dem blockierten Geländefeld stattfinden</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità interrompe la rotta commerciale in modo che non possa passare dalla casella bloccata.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad corta la ruta comercial para que ninguna operación de comercio intercontinental pueda atravesar la casilla bloqueada.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_POWER</Tag>
		<English>Disable Power Grid</English>
		<French>Désactiver la production d'électricité</French>
		<German>Energieversorgung lahmlegen</German>
		<Italian>Disabilita rete elettrica</Italian>
		<Spanish>Desactivar producción eléctrica</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wy&#179;&#185;cz Pr&#185;d</Polish>
		<Russian>Повредите энергосистему</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_RANGE_ATTACK</Tag>
		<English>Range Attack</English>
		<French>Attaque à Distance</French>
		<Russian>Дальняя атака</Russian>
		<Italian>Attacco dalla distanza</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_RBOMBARD</Tag>
		<English>Ranged Assault</English>
		<French>Assaut à distance</French>
		<Polish>Atak dystansowy</Polish>
		<Russian>Дальняя атака</Russian>
		<Italian>Assalto dalla distanza</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_RBOMBARD_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Select a ranged unit, select the bombard mission, then click on the plot to bombard.</English>
		<French>Sélectionnez une unité d'artillerie puis une mission de bombardement. Cliquez ensuite sur la case à bombarder.</French>
		<German>Wählen Sie eine Artillerieeinheit, aktivieren Sie die Mission "Bombardierung" und klicken Sie dann auf das Geländefeld, das bombardiert werden soll.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Seleziona attacco dalla distanza, quindi seleziona sulla casella da bombardare.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Selecciona una unidad de ataque a distancia, selecciona la misión "Cañoneo de alcance" y haz clic en la casilla a bombardear.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wybierz jednostk&#234; artyleryjsk&#185;, wybierz misj&#234; ataku dystansowego a nast&#234;pnie kliknij na polu, kt&#243;re chcesz zbombardowa&#230;.</Polish>
		<Russian>Выбрав артиллерийский юнит, нажмите кнопку бомбардировки, а затем щелкните клетку для обстрела.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_RECON</Tag>
		<English>Recon</English>
		<French>Reconnaissance</French>
		<German>Aufklärung</German>
		<Italian>Ricognizione</Italian>
		<Spanish>Reconocer</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_RECON_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Clears the fog of war from around the selected space for one turn.</English>
		<French>Lever le brouillard de guerre autour de la case sélectionnée pendant un tour.</French>
		<German>Der Nebel des Krieges lichtet sich im Zielgebiet eine Runde lang.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Elimina la nebbia di guerra attorno allo spazio selezionato per un turno.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Despeja durante un turno la niebla de la guerra que haya alrededor de la casilla seleccionada.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_REVOLT</Tag>
		<English>Aid Rebel Factions</English>
		<French>Aider les Factions Rebelles</French>
		<German>Rebellengruppierungen unterstützen</German>
		<Italian>Aiuta le fazioni ribelli</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ayudar a organizaciones rebeldes</Spanish>
		<Polish>Zaoferuj Pomoc Rebelii</Polish>
		<Russian>Помочь повстанцам</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_ROUTE_TO</Tag>
		<English>Route To</English>
		<French>Route vers</French>
		<German>Straße nach</German>
		<Italian>Costruisci percorso fino a</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ir en ruta a</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_ROUTE_TO_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order causes the Worker to build a road Improvement (or railroad) to the location selected. The Worker will follow the shortest path to the location. The Worker wakes when it has completed the assignment.</English>
		<French>Ordonner à l'ouvrier de construire une route (ou une voie ferrée) vers l'endroit indiqué. Il suivra le chemin le plus court et sera à nouveau disponible lorsqu'il aura terminé sa mission.</French>
		<German>Befehlen Sie einem Bautrupp, eine Straße (oder Eisenbahnstrecke) zur gewählten Position zu bauen. Ihr Bautrupp wählt nun den kürzesten Weg und wartet nach dem Bau der Straße/Eisenbahnstrecke auf weitere Befehle.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Il lavoratore costruisce un percorso fino alla casella selezionata. Seguirà il percorso più breve per raggiungere la casella e interromperà l'automazione quando avrà completato il proprio incarico.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Con esta orden hacéis que un trabajador construya una carretera (o ferrocarril) al lugar seleccionado. El trabajador seguirá el camino más corto hasta dicho lugar. Se despertará cuando haya cumplido su cometido.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SABOTAGE</Tag>
		<English>Sabotage</English>
		<French>Sabotage</French>
		<German>Sabotage</German>
		<Italian>Sabotaggio</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sabotear</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SABOTAGE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Spy[COLOR_REVERT] will attempt to sabotage the tile's Improvement.</English>
		<French>L'[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]espion[COLOR_REVERT] tente de saboter un aménagement sur cette case.</French>
		<German>Der [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Spion[COLOR_REVERT] versucht, alle Modernisierungen eines Geländefelds zu sabotieren.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]La [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]spia[COLOR_REVERT] tenterà di sabotare il miglioramento della casella.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Espía[COLOR_REVERT] intentará sabotear la mejora que haya en la casilla.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SEAPATROL</Tag>
		<English>Sea Patrol</English>
		<French>Patrouille des mers</French>
		<German>Seepatrouille</German>
		<Italian>Pattuglia marittima</Italian>
		<Spanish>Patrulla marítima</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SEAPATROL_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order will tell the unit to attack enemy ships attempting to pillage adjacent tiles</English>
		<French>Ordonner à l'unité d'attaquer les navires ennemis se livrant au pillage de cases adjacentes</French>
		<German>Die Einheit wird feindliche Schiffe angreifen, um angrenzende Geländefelder zu plündern</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità attaccherà le navi nemiche che cercano di saccheggiare le caselle adiacenti</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta orden le dirá a la unidad que ataque a los barcos enemigos que intenten saquear las casillas adyacentes.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SENTRY</Tag>
		<English>Sentry</English>
		<French>Sentinelle</French>
		<German>Wache</German>
		<Italian>Sentinella</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vigilar</Spanish>
		<Russian>Наблюдать</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SENTRY_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit remains inactive until an enemy unit enters any adjacent square.</English>
		<French>L'unité reste inactive tant qu'une autre unité ne pénètre pas dans une case adjacente.</French>
		<German>Einheit in den Wachmodus versetzen. Die Einheit wird erst wieder aktiv, wenn eine feindliche Einheit ein Nachbarfeld betritt.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Unità inattiva finché un'unità nemica non entra in una delle caselle adiacenti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad permanecerá inactiva hasta que una unidad enemiga entre en cualquier casilla adyacente.</Spanish>
		<Russian>Единица останется неактивной до тех пор, пока в любую соседнюю к ней клетку не войдет враг.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SENTRY_LAND_UNITS</Tag>
		<English>Sentry (Land Units)</English>
		<French>Surveillance (Unités terrestres)</French>
		<German>Wache (Landeinheiten)</German>
		<Italian>Sentinella (unità terrestri)</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vigilar (unidades terrestres)</Spanish>
		<Polish>Warta (Jednostki l&#185;dowe)</Polish>
		<Russian>Наблюдать за сушей</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SENTRY_LAND_UNITS_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit remains inactive until an enemy land unit enters its vision range.</English>
		<French>L'unité reste inactive tant qu'aucune unité terrestre ennemie ne pénètre pas dans son champ de vision.</French>
		<German>Einheit in den Wachmodus versetzen. Die Einheit wird erst wieder aktiv, wenn eine feindliche Landeinheit ihr Sichtfeld betritt.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Unità inattiva finché un'unità terrestre nemica non entra nel suo raggio di visibilità.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad permanecerá inactiva hasta que una unidad terrestre enemiga se sitúe en su campo de visión.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jednostka pozostaje bezczynna, dop&#243;ki wroga jednostka l&#185;dowa nie zbli&#191;y si&#234; do zasi&#234;gu.</Polish>
		<Russian>Единица будет неактивна до тех пор, пока в ее зоне видимости не появятся вражеские наземные подразделения.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SENTRY_NAVAL_UNITS</Tag>
		<English>Sentry (Naval Units)</English>
		<French>Surveillance (Unités Navales)</French>
		<German>Wache (Marineeinheiten)</German>
		<Italian>Sentinella (unità navali)</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vigilar (unidades navales)</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wartownik (Jednostki morskie)</Polish>
		<Russian>Наблюдать за водой</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SENTRY_NAVAL_UNITS_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit remains inactive until an enemy naval unit enters its vision range.</English>
		<French>L'unité reste inactive tant qu'aucune unité navale ennemie ne pénètre pas dans son champ de vision.</French>
		<German>Einheit in den Wachmodus versetzen. Die Einheit wird erst wieder aktiv, wenn eine feindliche Marineeinheit ihr Sichtfeld betritt.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Unità inattiva finché un'unità navale nemica non entra nel suo raggio di visibilità.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad permanecerá inactiva hasta que una unidad naval enemiga se sitúe en su campo de visión.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jednostka pozostaje bezczynna, dop&#243;ki wroga jednostka morska nie zbli&#191;y si&#234; do zasi&#234;gu.</Polish>
		<Russian>Единица будет неактивна до тех пор, пока в ее зоне видимости не появятся вражеские плавсредства.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SENTRY_WHILE_HEAL</Tag>
		<English>Sentry Until Healed</English>
		<French>Surveillance pendant la Guérison</French>
		<German>Wache bis geheilt</German>
		<Italian>Sentinella (fino alla guarigione)</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vigilar hasta curarse</Spanish>
		<Polish>Ulecz</Polish>
		<Russian>Наблюдать до исцеления</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SENTRY_WHILE_HEAL_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The unit remains inactive until it reaches full strength or an enemy unit enters its vision range.</English>
		<French>L'unité reste inactive jusqu'à ce qu'elle soit guérie, et tant qu'aucune unité ennemie ne pénètre pas dans son champ de vision.</French>
		<German>Lässt eine Einheit inaktiv bleiben, bis sie vollständig geheilt ist oder sich eine feindliche Einheit nähert</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità rimane inattiva finché non ritorna a piena forza o un'unità nemica non entra nel suo raggio di visibilità.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad permanecerá inactiva hasta que recobre el total de su fuerza o una unidad enemiga se sitúe en su campo de visión.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jednostka pozostaje bezczynna, dop&#243;ki nie osi&#185;ga pe&#179;nej si&#179;y lub jednostka wroga nie zbli&#191;y si&#234; do zasi&#234;gu.</Polish>
		<Russian>Единица будет неактивна до тех пор, пока полностью не восстановит силы или в ее зоне видимости не появится вражеское подразделение.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SKIP</Tag>
		<English>Skip Turn</English>
		<French>Passer le tour</French>
		<German>Runde überspringen</German>
		<Italian>Salta turno</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saltar turno</Spanish>
		<Russian>Пропустить ход</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SKIP_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Do nothing. The unit will awake and ask again for orders the next turn.</English>
		<French>Ne rien faire. L'unité attend le tour suivant pour demander de nouveaux ordres.</French>
		<German>Tun Sie gar nichts, wartet die Einheit in der nächsten Runde auf weitere Befehle.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Nessun ordine. L'unità attenderà altri ordini al turno successivo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La unidad no hará nada, despertará y volverá a solicitar órdenes al turno siguiente.</Spanish>
		<Russian>Ничего не делать. На следующий ход подраздлеение снова обратится за поручением.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SLEEP</Tag>
		<English>Sleep</English>
		<French>Dormir</French>
		<German>Ausruhen</German>
		<Italian>Dormi</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dormir</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SLEEP_HELP</Tag>
		<English>Order the unit to sleep until activated by the player</English>
		<French>Ordonner à l'unité de se mettre en sommeil tant qu'elle n'est pas réactivée par le joueur.</French>
		<German>Versetzen Sie die Einheit in den Ausruhmodus, bis Sie sie wieder aktivieren.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]L'unità diventa inattiva finché non viene riattivata dal giocatore</Italian>
		<Spanish>Para ordenarle a la unidad que duerma hasta que la activéis.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SPREAD</Tag>
		<English>Spread Religion</English>
		<French>Propager la religion</French>
		<German>Religion verbreiten</German>
		<Italian>Diffondi religione</Italian>
		<Spanish>Propagar religión</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SPREAD_CORPORATION</Tag>
		<English>Expand Corporation</English>
		<French>Développer une société commerciale</French>
		<German>Kapitalgesellschaft expandieren</German>
		<Italian>Espandi corporazione</Italian>
		<Spanish>Expandir corporación</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SPREAD_CORPORATION_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order will consume the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Executive[COLOR_REVERT] unit but expand their Corporation into the city.</English>
		<French>Cet ordre détruira le [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Directeur[COLOR_REVERT] mais développera sa société commerciale dans la ville.</French>
		<German>Der [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Vorstand[COLOR_REVERT] wird geopfert, damit die Kapitalgesellschaft in die Stadt expandieren kann.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Il [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]funzionario[COLOR_REVERT] viene consumato nel processo, ma la corporazione si espande nella città.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta orden consumirá a la unidad de [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Ejecutivo[COLOR_REVERT] pero expandirá su corporación en la ciudad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_SPREAD_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order will consume the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Missionary[COLOR_REVERT] unit but spread their Religion to the city.</English>
		<French>Cet ordre détruit le [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]missionnaire[COLOR_REVERT], mais sa religion sera propagée à la ville.</French>
		<German>Opfern Sie einen [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Missionar[COLOR_REVERT], damit dieser seine Religion in der Welt verbreitet.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Il [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]missionario[COLOR_REVERT] viene consumato nel processo, ma la religione si diffonde nella città.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta orden hará que se consuma la unidad de [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Misionero[COLOR_REVERT], pero propagará la religión por la ciudad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_START_GOLDENAGE</Tag>
		<English>Start a Golden Age</English>
		<French>Déclencher un âge d'or</French>
		<German>Goldenes Zeitalter beginnen</German>
		<Italian>Inizia età dell'oro</Italian>
		<Spanish>Iniciar una edad de oro</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_START_GOLDENAGE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>This order consumes one or more Great People to start a Golden Age. If multiple are needed, they must be of different types (e.g., not two Great Prophets). Great Generals and Admirals do not count. Bonus to: [ICON_PRODUCTION], [ICON_COMMERCE], [ICON_GREATPEOPLE], no Anarchy.</English>
		<French>Cet ordre consomme une ou plusieurs Personnages illustres pour déclencher un Âge d'Or. Si plusieurs sont nécessaires, elles doivent être de types différents (par exemple, pas deux Grands Prophètes). Les Grands Généraux et Amiral ne comptent pas. Bonus à : [ICON_PRODUCTION], [ICON_COMMERCE], [ICON_GREATPEOPLE], pas d'Anarchie.</French>
		<German>Opfern Sie eine oder mehrere Große Persönlichkeiten (unterschiedlicher Klassen), um ein Goldenes Zeitalter (zusätzliche [ICON_PRODUCTION], [ICON_COMMERCE], [ICON_GREATPEOPLE], keine Anarchie) zu begründen.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]Consumando nel processo uno o più gran personaggi (di tipi differenti), si avvia un'età dell'oro (extra [ICON_PRODUCTION], [ICON_COMMERCE], [ICON_GREATPEOPLE], nessuna anarchia per i cambi di forma di governo).</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta orden consume uno o más grandes personajes (de diferentes tipos) e inicia una edad de oro (extra [ICON_PRODUCTION], [ICON_COMMERCE], [ICON_GREATPEOPLE], sin Anarquía).</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_STEAL_PLANS</Tag>
		<English>Steal Plans</English>
		<French>Voler des plans</French>
		<German>Pläne stehlen</German>
		<Italian>Furto di documenti</Italian>
		<Spanish>Robar planos</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISSION_STEAL_PLANS_HELP</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Spy[COLOR_REVERT] will attempt to steal plans, which will reveal all of the target civilization's units.</English>
		<French>L'[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]espion[COLOR_REVERT] tentera de voler des plans, qui révèlent toutes les unités de la civilisation visée.</French>
		<German>Der [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Spion[COLOR_REVERT] versucht, Pläne zu stehlen, die alle Einheiten der gewünschten Zivilisation enthüllen.</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]La [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]spia[COLOR_REVERT] tenterà di rubare dei documenti per rivelare tutte le unità della civiltà bersaglio.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Espía[COLOR_REVERT] intentará robar los planos, que revelarán todas las unidades de la civilización objetivo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_CISLUNAR</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Cislunar Space</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers l'espace cislunaire</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa dello spazio cislunare</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_DISTANT_COSMOS</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Distant Cosmos</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers le cosmos lointain</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa dello spazio distante</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_EARTH</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Earth</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers la Terre</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa della Terra</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_INNER_SOLAR_SYSTEM</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Inner Solar System</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers le système solaire intérieur</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa dello sistema solare interno</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_LOCAL_GROUP</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Local Group</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers le Groupe local</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa del gruppo locale di galassie</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_MARS</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Mars</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers Mars</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa di Marte</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_MILKY_WAY</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Milky Way</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers la Voie lactée</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa della via lattea</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_MOON</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Moon</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers la Lune</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa della luna</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_NEARBY_STARS</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Nearby Stars</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers des étoiles proches</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa delle stelle vicine</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_ORION_ARM</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Orion Arm</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers le Bras d'Orion</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa del braccio di Orione</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_OUTER_SOLAR_SYSTEM</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Outer Solar System</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers le système solaire extérieur</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa del sistema solare esterno</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_SUBTERRAIN</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Earth Underground</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité sous la surface de la Terre</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa del sottosuolo terrestre</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_TITAN</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Titan</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers Titan</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa di Titano</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_TRANSNEPTUNIAN</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Kuiper Belt</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers la ceinture de Kuiper</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa della fascia di Kuiper</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_UNIVERSE</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Universe</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers l'Univers</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa dell'universo</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_VENUS</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Venus</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers Vénus</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa di Venere</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_OUTCOME_GO_TO_MAP_VIRGO_SUPERCLUSTER</Tag>
		<English>Transfer unit to Virgo Superscluster</English>
		<French>Transférer l'unité vers le superamas de la Vierge</French>
		<Italian>Trasferimento unità alla mappa del superammasso della Vergine</Italian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
