<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ANIMAL_TOTEM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The tradition of having a mascot or flag/standard that identifies the people in a military unit.</English>
		<Italian>La tradizione di avere una mascotte o una bandiera che identifica le persone che fanno parte di un'unità militare.</Italian>
		<Polish>Tradycja posiadania maskotki lub sztandaru, który identyfikuje ludzi w jednostce wojskowej.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BISON_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Represent the Bison of North America, Water Buffalo of South East Asia and all herbivore herds of Africa.</English>
		<Italian>Rappresenta il bisonte del Nordamerica, il bufalo d'acqua dell'Asia sudorientale e tutti i branchi di erbivori dell'Africa.</Italian>
		<Polish>Żubry zamieszkują środowiska leśne, te nie są jednak optymalne, ponieważ zimą nie dostarczają wystarczającej ilości pożywienia dla tak dużego roślinożercy, większość populacji jest w czasie cięższych zim dokarmianych przez człowieka, ponieważ brak lub niedostateczne dokarmianie powoduje, że zwierzęta te migrują na tereny otwarte, powodując szkody w uprawach rolniczych. W ramach polsko-niemieckich badań składu izotopowego kości (zawartości stabilnych izotopów węgla i azotu) najstarszych w Europie zachowanych kości żubra Bison bonasus potwierdzono, że w czasach prehistorycznych żubry preferowały tereny otwarte, a ich dieta miała mieszany charakter i zawierała porosty, trawy i pędy drzew oraz krzewów.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BOXING_KANGAROO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BUFFALO_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Only domesticated buffalos can build the Herd - Buffalo; provides a resource of buffalos.</English>
		<Italian>Solo i bufali addomesticati possono costruire il Branco - Bufali; fornisce una risorsa di bufali.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BUFFALO_TRAINER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Buffalo Trainer is required to build Buffalo Worker.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAMEL_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Only domesticated camels can build the Herd - Camels; provides a resource of camels.</English>
		<Italian>Solo i cammelli addomesticati possono costruire il Branco - Cammelli; fornisce una risorsa di cammelli.</Italian>
		<Polish>Wielbłąd (Camelus) rodzaj dużych ssaków z rodziny wielbłądowatych. Fizjologicznie przystosowane do życia w warunkach suchego i gorącego klimatu, są w wielu krajach wykorzystywane jako zwierzęta użytkowe.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CARNIVAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Carnival is a decent provider of culture and happiness for the city in which it is built. If you bring captured wolves, lions, or tigers to the city and add them to the Carnival, it can generate more culture and happiness than most wonders. The Subdue Animal promotion, available only to recon units after Animal Husbandry is researched, will allow you to capture these beasts if you beat them in combat.</English>
		<French>Le Carnaval est un fournisseur décent de culture et de bonheur pour la ville dans laquelle il est construit. Si vous amené des loups, panthères, lions et tigres dans la ville et que vous les ajoutez au Carnaval, il générera plus de culture et de bonheur que bien des merveilles. La promotion Assujettir Animal, accessible seulement aux unités de reconnaissances après que la technologie Elevage est découverte, vous permettra de capturer ces bêtes si vous les battez en combat.</French>
		<German>Der Jahrmarkt ist ein guter Versorger für Kultur und Zufriedenheit für die Stadt, in der er gebaut wird. Wenn man gefangene Wölfe, Panther, Löwen oder Tiger in die Stadt und zum Jahrmarkt bringt, kann dieser mehr Kultur und Zufriedenheit produzieren als die meisten Wunder. Die Beförderung "Tierbändigung", welche nur für Aufklärungseinheiten und erst ab der Technologie "Viehhaltung" verfügbar ist, erlaubt, diese Tiere einzufangen, wenn man sie im Kampf besiegt.</German>
		<Italian>Il carnevale fornisce una buona dose di cultura e felicità nella città in cui è costruito. Portando i lupi, i leoni o le tigri che hai addomesticato nelle città in cui hai costruito il carnevale, puoi potenziarlo in modo che generi più cultura e felicità di gran parte delle meraviglie. La linea di promozioni "Cacciatore" ti permetterà di catturare più facilmente le bestie in combattimento.</Italian>
		<Polish>Karnawał, zapusty okres zimowych balów, maskarad, pochodów i zabaw. Rozpoczyna się najczęściej w dniu Trzech Króli, a kończy we wtorek przed Zrodą Popielcową, która oznacza początek wielkiego postu i oczekiwania na Wielkanoc.</Polish>
		<Russian>Êàðíàâàë ÿâëÿåòñÿ äîñòîéíûì èñòî÷íèêîì êóëüòóðû è ñ÷àñòüÿ äëÿ ãîðîäà, â êîòîðîì îí ïîñòðîåí. Åñëè âû ïðèâåçåòå â ãîðîä çàõâà÷åííûõ âîëêîâ, ëüâîâ èëè òèãðîâ è äîáàâèòå èõ â êàðíàâàë, ýòî ìîæåò ïðèíåñòè áîëüøå êóëüòóðû è ñ÷àñòüÿ, ÷åì áîëüøèíñòâî ÷óäåñ. Äåéñòâèå «Ïðèðó÷èòü æèâîòíîå», äîñòóïíîå òîëüêî ðàçâåäûâàòåëüíûì ïîäðàçäåëåíèÿì ïîñëå èññëåäîâàíèÿ æèâîòíîâîäñòâà, ïîçâîëèò âàì ïîéìàòü ýòèõ çâåðåé, åñëè âû ïîáåäèòå èõ â áîþ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CEPHALOPOD_INSTITUTE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A center specialized in the study of cephalopods. The cephalopods (Cephalopoda, from the Greek kephale, head and pous, podos, foot) are exclusively marine molluscs, among the most evolved, with a shell reduced internally or completely absent, purely nectonic (like cuttlefish and squid) or benthic (like the octopus and baby octopus). They developed in a great multitude of forms during the Mesozoic, colonizing practically all marine environments with the nautiloid, ammonoid and belemnoid groups, the last two totally extinct. Recent hypotheses consider cephalopods derived directly from monoplacophores with a more pronounced spiraling shell; it is supposed that the apical region of the viscera sac of these molluscs withdrew from time to time and the mantle that covered them formed a successive series of internal calcareous septa, delimiting cavities filled with gas. This produced an ever greater lightness, a characteristic that allowed them to acquire a neutral buoyancy in order to move in the liquid with less effort. During these early evolutionary stages, the cephalopods acquired speed and predation ability, developing a head with prehensile lobes, derived from simple tentacles of ancestral monoplacophores. The dimensions are very variable, from a few millimeters to several meters in the case of the giant squid, which is the second largest mollusk, as well as being the second largest animal among all current invertebrates. In size it is surpassed only by the colossal squid, Mesonychoteuthis hamiltoni, which can have a coat almost twice as long as its own. Some extinct cephalopods, such as the Cretaceous vampiromorph Tusoteuthis and the Ordovician nautiloid Cameroceras, could reach even larger sizes. </English>
		<Italian>Un centro specializzato nello studio dei cefalopodi. I cefalopodi (Cephalopoda, dal greco kephale, testa e pous, podos, piede) sono molluschi esclusivamente marini, tra i più evoluti, con conchiglia ridotta internamente o del tutto assente, prettamente nectonici (come le seppie e i calamari) o bentonici (come il polpo e il moscardino). Si svilupparono in una grande moltitudine di forme durante il Mesozoico, colonizzando praticamente tutti gli ambienti marini con i gruppi dei nautiloidi, ammonoidea e belemnoidi, gli ultimi due totalmente estinti. Ipotesi recenti considerano i cefalopodi derivati direttamente da monoplacofori con conchiglia a spiralizzazione più accentuata; si suppone che la regione apicale del sacco dei visceri di questi molluschi si ritirasse di tanto in tanto e il mantello che li ricopriva formasse una serie successiva di setti calcarei interni, delimitando cavità ripiene di gas. Ciò produsse una sempre maggiore leggerezza, caratteristica questa che permise loro di acquisire un galleggiamento neutro per potersi spostare nel liquido con minor sforzo. Durante questi primi stadi evolutivi, i cefalopodi acquisirono velocità e capacità di predazione, sviluppando un capo dotato di lobi prensili, derivati da tentacoli semplici di monoplacofori ancestrali. Le dimensioni sono molto variabili, da pochi millimetri a vari metri nel caso del calamaro gigante, che è il secondo mollusco più grande, oltre ad essere anche il secondo animale più grande tra tutti gli invertebrati attuali. Nelle dimensioni è superato solamente dal calamaro colossale, Mesonychoteuthis hamiltoni, che può avere un mantello lungo quasi il doppio del suo. Alcuni cefalopodi estinti, come il vampiromorfo cretaceo Tusoteuthis ed il nautiloide ordoviciano Cameroceras potevano raggiungere dimensioni perfino più grandi.</Italian>
		<Polish>Sieci na ryby były konstruowane przez bogatych by dostarczać im ciągle świeżych i egzotycznych gatunków ryb na ich wykwintne uczty.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CETAEA_INSTITUTE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A center specialized in the study of cetaceans. Cetaceans are an order of euplacentate mammals, fully adapted to aquatic life. The cetacean name derives from the Greek and means whale or sea monster; it was introduced by Aristotle to designate aquatic animals with lung respiration. They have a fusiform body, similar to that of fish, which ensures them greater hydrodynamics. The forelimbs are modified into fins; the hind limbs as such are absent; only a few small vestigial bones remain, hidden inside the body, and not connected to the spine due to the absence of the pelvis. The caudal fin is arranged horizontally and divided into two lobes. They are generally hairless and are thermally insulated by a thick layer of fat. The order Cetacea includes about 85 species, almost all of which are marine except for 5 species of freshwater dolphins. The species are divided into two suborders: Mysticeti and Odontoceti. There is a third suborder, Archaeoceti, to which only extinct species belong. Among the mysticetes there are animals commonly called whales, the largest known in the world: in particular, the blue whale is the largest animal existing on Earth today. Among the odontoceti, however, there are dolphins and killer whales, often reared and trained in dolphinaria. </English>
		<Italian>Un centro specializzato nello studio dei cetacei. I Cetacei sono un ordine di mammiferi euplacentati, completamente adattatisi alla vita acquatica. Il nome cetaceo deriva dal greco e significa balena o mostro marino; fu introdotto da Aristotele per designare gli animali acquatici dotati di respirazione polmonare. Presentano un corpo fusiforme, simile a quello dei pesci, che assicura loro una maggiore idrodinamicità. Gli arti anteriori sono modificati in pinne; gli arti posteriori come tali sono assenti; rimangono solo alcune piccole ossa vestigiali, nascoste dentro al corpo, e non collegate alla spina dorsale per l'assenza del bacino. La pinna caudale è disposta orizzontalmente e divisa in due lobi. Sono generalmente privi di peli e sono isolati termicamente da uno spesso strato di grasso. L'ordine Cetacea comprende circa 85 specie, quasi tutte marine tranne 5 specie di delfini di acqua dolce. Le specie sono suddivise in due sottordini: Mysticeti ed Odontoceti. Esiste un terzo sottordine, Archaeoceti, cui appartengono solo specie estinte. Tra i misticeti si trovano gli animali comunemente chiamati balene, i più grandi conosciuti al mondo: in particolare la balenottera azzurra è il più grande animale oggi esistente sulla Terra. Tra gli odontoceti, invece, si trovano delfini e orche, spesso allevati e addestrati nei delfinari.</Italian>
		<Polish>Instytut Morski jednostka naukowo-badawcza. Placówka wykonuje prace naukowe, badawcze i wdrożeniowe: m.in. zajmuje się modernizacją i eksploatacją portów, oceanografią operacyjną, czy problematyką zagospodarowania regionu nadmorskiego. Misją Instytutu jest dbałość o zachowanie wartości morza i zrównoważony rozwój polskiej gospodarki morskiej. Instytut opracowuje studia wykonalności i eksperyzy oraz udziela konsultacji w zakresie: hydrotechniki morskiej, geotechniki, oceanografii operacyjnej, ochrony środowiska (badania chemiczne i biologiczne), transportu, logistyki, zagospodarowania przestrzennego regionu nadmorskiego, modernizacji i eksploatacji portów, żeglugi śródlądowej, turystyki, bezpieczeństwa przeciwpowodziowego, elektroniki morskiej, a także tworzenia baz danych i monitoringu zjawisk ciągłych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_COASTAL_FISH_FARM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Fish Pens were constructed by the rich to provide them with a ready source of some exotic or rare sea fish for their feasts.</English>
		<Italian>Le pinne di pesce venivano fornite alle persone ricche per fornire loro una fonte di pesce raro ed esotico per le loro feste.</Italian>
		<Polish>Sieci na ryby były konstruowane przez bogatych by dostarczać im ciągle świeżych i egzotycznych gatunków ryb na ich wykwintne uczty.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_COW_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Only domesticated cattle can build the Herd - Bovines; provides a resource of cattle.</English>
		<Italian>Solo i bovini addomesticati possono costruire il Branco - Bovini; fornisce una risorsa di bovini.</Italian>
		<Polish>Bydło domowe (Bos taurus) gatunek zwierząt z rodziny wołowatych, rzędu parzystokopytnych. Gatunek ten pochodzi od tura wielkiego i tura krótkorogiego.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CRAB_NETS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Crabs (Brachyura, from the Greek short abdomen / tail) a group [a] of short-legged crustaceans from the order Decapoda. Crabs are the most numerous (10,500 species have been described) group of tenths, in which the first pair of crotch legs developed into claws. The size of the body is very varied, with a leg span from a few millimeters (Pinnotheres pisum) to almost 4 m (Japanese Pacific crab). </English>
		<Polish>Kraby (Brachyura, z języka greckiego krótki odwłok/ogon) grupa[a] krótkoodwłokowych skorupiaków z rzędu dziesięcionogów (Decapoda). Kraby są najliczniejszą (opisano 10 500 gatunków) grupą dziesięcionogów, u której pierwsza para odnóży krocznych przekształciła się w szczypce. Wielkość ciała bardzo zróżnicowana, o rozpiętości odnóży od kilku milimetrów (Pinnotheres pisum) do prawie 4 m (japoński krab pacyficzny).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DANCING_BEAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Dancing Bear is a popular source of amusement for the people of Erebus, be they Veil Ritualists or Order Acolytes. Dancing Bears can't be built, a wild Bear must be captured, taken to a city, and turned into a Dancing Bear. A Carnival is not needed to build the dancing bear, and in fact they dislike the competition.</English>
		<French>L'Ours Dansant est une source d'amusement populaire pour les gens d'Erebus, aussi bien les vils ritualistes du Voile que les austères acolytes de l'Ordre. Les Ours Dansants ne peuvent être construit, un Ours sauvage doit être capturé, amené dans une ville et transformé en Ours Dansant. Un Carnaval n'est pas nécessaire pour construire un Ours Dansant, et en réalité ils n'aiment pas la compétition.</French>
		<German>Der Tanzende Bär ist eine beliebte Unterhaltungsquelle für die Menschen von Erebus, böse Ritualisten des Schleiers oder Akolyten der Weisung. Tanzende Bären können nicht gebaut werden. Ein wilder Bär muss eingefangen und in eine Stadt transportiert, und in einen Tanzenden Bären verwandelt werden. Ein Jahrmarkt wird für einen Tanzenden Bären nicht benütigt. Genau genommen mögen die Bären den Jahrmarkt nicht besonders.</German>
		<Italian>L'Orso ballerino è una fonte popolare di divertimento per il popolo di Erebus, siano essi i Ritualisti di Veil o gli Accoliti dell'Ordine. Gli orsi danzanti non possono essere costruiti, un orso selvatico deve essere catturato, portato in una città, e trasformato in un orso ballerino. Un carnevale non è necessario per costruire l'orso ballerino, infatti a loro non piace la concorrenza.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El Oso Pisador es una fuente popular de entretenimiento para la gente de Erebus, ya sean ritualistal del Velo malvados o acólitos del Orden. El Oso Pisador no puede ser construido; hay que capturar un Oso Salvaje, llevarlo a una ciudad y convertirlo en un Oso Pisador. No es necesario tener un Carnaval para construir el Oso Pisador, y de hecho no les gusta la competencia.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Tańczący Niedźwiedź to popularnia rozrywka na miejskich targach lub karnawałach.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DEER_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The history of deer breeding goes back millennia. Though the precise date is in dispute, humans could have domesticated the deer as far back as approximately 4500 BCE. However, evidence of planned breeding has a more blurry history.[PARAGRAPH:2]One of the earliest people known to document the breedings of their deers were the Bedouin of the Middle East, the breeders of the Arabian deer. While it is difficult to determine how far back the Bedouin passed on pedigree information via an oral tradition, there were written pedigrees of Arabian deers by A.D. 1330. The Akhal-Teke of West-Central Asia is another breed with roots in ancient times that was also bred specifically for war and racing. The nomads of the Mongolian steppes bred deers for several thousand years as well.[PARAGRAPH:2]The types of deers bred varied with culture and with the times. The uses to which a deer was put also determined its qualities, including smooth amblers for riding, fast deers for carrying messengers, heavy deers for plowing and pulling heavy wagons, ponies for hauling cars of ore from mines, packdeers, carriage deers and many others.</English>
		<Italian>La storia dell'allevamento dei cervi risale a migliaia di anni fa. Anche se la data precisa è in discussione, gli esseri umani potrebbero avere addomesticato il cervo nel lontano 4500 a.C.; tuttavia, le prove di un allevamento più intensivo sono molto rare.[PARAGRAPH:2]Uno dei primi popoli noti per aver documentato l'allevamento dei loro cervi sono stati i beduini del Medio Oriente, gli allevatori dell cervo arabo. Anche se è difficile determinare per quanto tempo i beduini abbiano tramandato informazioni sull'allevamento attraverso una tradizione orale, ci sono state documentazioni scritte riguardo cervi arabi sin dal 1330 d.C.. Gli Akhal-Teke dell'Asia centro-occidentale sono un'altra razza con radici antiche che è stata allevata appositamente per la guerra e la corsa. I nomadi delle steppe mongole allevarono i cervi per diverse migliaia di anni.[PARAGRAPH:2]I tipi di cervi addomesticati variarono con la cultura e con i tempi. Gli usi a cui un elefante era destinato determinavano anche le sue qualità, tra cui cervi a pelle liscia per l'equitazione, cervi veloci per trasportare messaggeri, cervi pesanti per l'aratura e per tirare carri pesanti, pony per trasportare carichi di minerali dalle miniere, cervi carrozza e molti altri.</Italian>
		<Polish>Jelenie żyją w stadach, w gwarze myśliwskiej nazywanych chmarami. Stadu przewodzi łania licówka, która musi prowadzić tegoroczne młode cielę. Przepisy wykonawcze polskiego prawa łowieckiego zakazują strzelania do licówki podczas polowania.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DOG_KENNEL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Kennels is a building or a collection of building in which dogs are housed, maintained, and bred. Historically, these structures were primarily used for breeding and improving the strength, velocity and other quality of a breed. Starting with the 20th century, they were turned into formal, heavily regulated establishments for the propagation of animals.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DONKEY_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Asses were first domesticated around 3000 BC, or 4000 BC, probably in Egypt or Mesopotamia, and have spread around the world. They continue to fill important roles in many places today. While domesticated species are increasing in numbers, the African wild ass and another relative, the Onager, are endangered. As "beasts of burden" and companions, asses and donkeys have worked together with humans for millennia.</English>
		<Italian>Gli asini vennero addomesticati intorno al 3000 a.C. o al 4000 a.C., probabilmente in Egitto o Mesopotamia, e vennero diffusi in tutto il mondo; al giorno d'oggi, continuano a ricoprire importanti ruoli in molti posti. Mentre le specie addomesticate sono in aumento in termini numerici, l'asino selvatico africano e un altro parente, l'onagro, sono in pericolo di estinzione. Come "bestie da soma" e compagni, gli asini hanno lavorato insieme con gli esseri umani per millenni.</Italian>
		<Polish>Osioł został udomowiony przez człowieka wcześniej niż koń. Pierwsze informacje dotyczące udomowienia pochodzą z Doliny Nilu z ok. 4000 p.n.e. czyli 6 tys. lat temu. Na tych terenach występowały obydwa żyjące do dzisiaj podgatunki osła afrykańskiego. Przypuszcza się, że z ich krzyżówek powstał osioł domowy (Equus africanus f.asinus).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ELEPHANT_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The history of elephant breeding goes back millennia. Though the precise date is in dispute, humans could have domesticated the elephant as far back as approximately 4500 BCE. However, evidence of planned breeding has a more blurry history.[PARAGRAPH:2]One of the earliest people known to document the breedings of their elephants were the Bedouin of the Middle East, the breeders of the Arabian elephant. While it is difficult to determine how far back the Bedouin passed on pedigree information via an oral tradition, there were written pedigrees of Arabian elephants by A.D. 1330. The Akhal-Teke of West-Central Asia is another breed with roots in ancient times that was also bred specifically for war and racing. The nomads of the Mongolian steppes bred elephants for several thousand years as well.[PARAGRAPH:2]The types of elephants bred varied with culture and with the times. The uses to which a elephant was put also determined its qualities, including smooth amblers for riding, fast elephants for carrying messengers, heavy elephants for plowing and pulling heavy wagons, ponies for hauling cars of ore from mines, pack elephants, carriage elephants and many others.</English>
		<Italian>La storia dell'allevamento degli elefanti risale a migliaia di anni fa. Anche se la data precisa è in discussione, gli esseri umani potrebbero avere addomesticato l'elefante nel lontano 4500 a.C.; tuttavia, le prove di un allevamento più intensivo sono molto rare.[PARAGRAPH:2]Uno dei primi popoli noti per aver documentato l'allevamento dei loro elefanti sono stati i beduini del Medio Oriente, gli allevatori dell'elefante arabo. Anche se è difficile determinare per quanto tempo i beduini abbiano tramandato informazioni sull'allevamento attraverso una tradizione orale, ci sono state tramandazioni scritte di elefanti arabi sin dal 1330 d.C.. Gli Akhal-Teke dell'Asia centro-occidentale sono un'altra razza con radici antiche che è stata allevata appositamente per la guerra e la corsa. I nomadi delle steppe mongole allevarono gli elefanti per diverse migliaia di anni.[PARAGRAPH:2]I tipi di elefanti addomesticati variarono con la cultura e con i tempi. Gli usi a cui un elefante era destinato determinavano anche le sue qualità, tra cui elefanti a pelle liscia per l'equitazione, elefanti veloci per trasportare messaggeri, elefanti pesanti per l'aratura e per tirare carri pesanti, pony per trasportare carichi di minerali dalle miniere, elefanti carrozza e molti altri.</Italian>
		<Polish>Oswajanie słoni (lecz nie udomowienie wciąż łapano dziko żyjące osobniki) rozpoczęło się około 4000 lat temu w dolinie Indusu. Pierwszym oswojonym gatunkiem słonia był słoń indyjski (Elephas maximus), którego używano do prac w polu. Pierwsze użycie tych zwierząt do celów militarnych, wspomniane w zapisanych w języku wedyjskim hymnach, datuje się na rok 1100 p.n.e., a miało miejsce w północnych Indiach.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_EXOTIC_HERBAVOURS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A cage used for wild subdued animals.</English>
		<Italian>Una gabbia in cui vengono rinchiusi gli erbivori selvaggi addomesticati.</Italian>
		<Polish>Klatka używana do przetrzymywania dzikich, poskromionych zwierząt.</Polish>
		<Russian>Êëåòêà äëÿ óêðîùåííûõ äèêèõ æèâîòíûõ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FEATHER_WORKER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Feathers have a number of utilitarian, cultural and religious uses.[NEWLINE]Utilitarian functions Feathers are both soft and excellent at trapping heat; thus, they are sometimes used in high-class bedding, especially pillows, blankets, and mattresses. They are also used as filling for winter clothing, such as quilted coats and sleeping bags; goose and eider down have great loft, the ability to expand from a compressed, stored state to trap large amounts of compartmentalized, insulating air.[PARAGRAPH:2]Bird feathers have long been used for fletching arrows. Colorful feathers such as those belonging to pheasants have been used to decorate fishing lures.[PARAGRAPH:2]Feathers of large birds (most often geese) have been and are used to make quill pens. The word pen itself is derived from the Latin penna for feather. In French, plume can mean either feather or pen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Feathers are also valuable in aiding the identification of species in forensic studies, particularly in bird strikes to aircraft. The ratios of hydrogen isotopes in feathers help in determining the geographic origins of birds. Feathers may also be useful in the non-destructive sampling of pollutants.[PARAGRAPH:2]The poultry industry produces a large amount of feathers as waste, and like other forms of keratin, these are slow in their decomposition. Feather waste has been used in a number of industrial applications as a medium for culturing microbes, biodegradable polymers, and production of enzymes. Feather proteins have been tried as an adhesive for wood board.[NEWLINE]In religion and cultureEagle feathers have great cultural and spiritual value to American Indians in the USA and First Nations peoples in Canada as religious objects. In the United States the religious use of eagle and hawk feathers are governed by the eagle feather law, a federal law limiting the possession of eagle feathers to certified and enrolled members of federally recognized Native American tribes.[PARAGRAPH:2]Various birds and their plumages serve as cultural icons throughout the world, from the hawk in ancient Egypt to the bald eagle and the turkey (bird) in the United States. In Greek mythology, Daedelus the inventor and Icarus tried to escape his prison by attaching feathered wings to his shoulders with wax, which was melted by the Sun.[PARAGRAPH:2]In South America, brews made from the feathers of Condors are used in traditional medications. In India, feathers of the Indian Peacock have been used in traditional medicine for snakebite, infertility and coughs.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the 18th, 19th, and even 20th Centuries a booming international trade in plumes, to satisfy market demand in North America and Europe for extravagant head-dresses as adornment for fashionable women, caused so much destruction (for example, to egret breeding colonies) that a major campaign against it by conservationists led to the Lacey Act and caused the fashion to change and the market to finally collapse. Frank Chapman noted in 1886 that as many as 40 species of birds were used in about three-fourths of the 700 ladies' hats that he observed in New York City.[PARAGRAPH:2]More recently, rooster plumage has become a popular trend as a hairstyle accessory, with feathers formerly used solely as fishing lures being now used to provide color and style to hair. Modern feather usage in fashion and also adorning military regimental headdresses and cloths are derived as a waste product of farming of poultry birds, this includes chicken, geese, turkey, pheasant and ostrich. Feathers used for these purposes are deliberately modified through dyeing and manipulation to enhance the appearance of these poultry feathers, as they are naturally often dull in appearance compared to wild species which they are attempting to mimic. The number of feather products manufacturers in Europe has decreased enormously in the last 60 years mainly due to competition from Asia. One surviving company Jaffe et fils founded in 1946, formerly of London now based in Axminster, Devon is one of the last in Europe to dye and manufacture feather products for fashion, theatre and military regalia. Feathers have adorn hats at many prestigious events such as Weddings and Ladies day at Race courses(Royal Ascot). One milliner, Philip Treacy, has specialised in the use of feathers. He has created highly regarded hats notably for the Royal Family. One such as the hat was worn by the Camilla now the Duchess of Cornwall on her marriage to Prince Charles.</English>
		<Italian>Le piume hanno vari utilizzi utilitari, culturali e religiosi.[H1]Funzioni utilitaristiche [\H1]Le piume sono sia morbide, sia ottime per intrappolare il calore; per questo vengono a volte utilizzate nell'arredo da letto di alta classe, soprattutto cuscini, coperte e materassi. Vengono anche utilizzate anche come imbottitura per l'abbigliamento invernale, come cappotti trapuntati e sacchi a pelo; la piuma d'oca ha la possibilità di espandersi da una dimensione compressa in cui viene immagazzinata, ad una dimensione più grande per intrappolare grandi quantità di aria isolante.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le piume di uccelli sono state a lungo utilizzate per impennare le frecce. Piume colorate come quelle appartenenti ai fagiani sono state utilizzate per decorare le esche da pesca.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le piume degli uccelli di grandi dimensioni (più spesso oche) sono state e sono tuttora usate per fare le penne d'oca. La parola penna stessa deriva dal latino penna, ovvero piuma. In francese, plume può significare sia piuma che penna.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le piume sono utili anche nel favorire l'identificazione delle specie nelle indagini forensiche, in particolare nelle collisioni di aerei con uccelli. I rapporti degli isotopi di idrogeno nelle piume aiutano a determinare le origini geografiche degli uccelli. Le piume possono anche essere utili nel campionamento non distruttivo di sostanze inquinanti.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'industria del pollame produce una grande quantità di piume come rifiuti, che come altre sostanze a base di cheratina hanno una decomposizione molto lenta. Le piume di scarto sono state utilizzate in un certo numero di applicazioni industriali come mezzo per la coltura di microbi, polimeri biodegradabili e produzione di enzimi. Le proteine delle piume vengono usate come collante per le tavole di legno. [H1]Nella religione e cultura[\H1]Le piume d'aquila hanno un grande valore culturale e spirituale per gli indiani americani negli Stati Uniti e in Canada come oggetti religiosi. Negli Stati Uniti l'uso religioso di piume di aquila e falco viene regolata da una legge federale che limita il possesso di piume d'aquila a membri iscritti a tribù di nativi americani riconosciute a livello federale.[PARAGRAPH:2]Vari uccelli, con i relativi piumaggi, servono come icone culturali in tutto il mondo, dal falco in Egitto all'aquila reale e al tacchino negli Stati Uniti. Nella mitologia greca, Dedalo e suo figlio Icaro cercarono di sfuggire dalla prigione attaccando delle ali piumate sulle spalle per mezzo di cera, che fu poi sciolta dal sole.[PARAGRAPH:2]In Sud America, infusi a base di piume di condor vengono utilizzati come farmaci tradizionali. In India, le piume del pavone indiano sono state usate nella medicina tradizionale per i morsi di serpente, infertilità e tosse.[PARAGRAPH:2]Durante il 18°, 19° e 20° secolo il commercio internazionale delle piume, in forte espansione per soddisfare la domanda di mercato in Nord America e in Europa per stravaganti copricapi come ornamento per le donne alla moda, causò così tanta distruzione che una grande campagna contro di essa effettuata dagli ambientalisti portò al Lacey Act, che portò il mercato al collasso. Frank Chapman osservò nel 1886 che ben 40 specie di uccelli venivano utilizzate in circa tre quarti dei cappelli delle 700 signore che aveva osservato a New York.[PARAGRAPH:2]Più di recente, le piume di gallo sono diventate una tendenza popolare come un accessorio di taglio di capelli; piume che precedentemente venivano utilizzate esclusivamente come esche da pesca vengono ora utilizzate per fornire colore e stile di capelli. Le piume utilizzate attualmente negli accessori di moda e militari derivano da prodotti di scarto dell'allevamento di uccelli da pollame, tra cui polli, oche, tacchini, fagiani e struzzi; le piume utilizzate per questi scopi vengono deliberatamente modificate con tintura e manipolazione per migliorarne l'aspetto, in quanto sono spesso più brutte rispetto alle piume delle specie selvatiche che stanno cercando di imitare. Il numero dei produttori di piume in Europa è diminuito enormemente negli ultimi 60 anni soprattutto a causa della concorrenza asiatica. La società inglese Jaffe et Fils, fondata nel 1946 a Londra e attualmente con sede ad Axminster, nel Devon, è una delle ultime società in Europa che tinge e fabbrica prodotti utilizzando le pium. Le piume adornano i cappelli in molti eventi prestigiosi, come matrimoni e Giorni delle donne alle corse (Royal Ascot). Una modista, Philip Treacy, si è specializzata nell'uso di piume; ha creato cappelli apprezzati particolarmente dalla Famiglia Reale inglese. Uno di questi cappelli è stato indossato da Camilla Parker Bowles nel giorno del suo matrimonio con il principe Carlo.</Italian>
		<Polish>Pierzarz to pracownik przemysłu pierzarskiego (działu przemysłu obejmującego pozyskiwanie i późniejszą obróbkę pierza, a niekiedy także ich wykorzystanie podczas produkcji poduszek, pierzyn i galanterii)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FISH_PENS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Fish Pens were constructed by the rich to provide them with a ready source of some exotic or rare sea fish for their feasts.</English>
		<Italian>Le pinne di pesce venivano fornite alle persone ricche per fornire loro una fonte di pesce raro ed esotico per le loro feste.</Italian>
		<Polish>Sieci na ryby były konstruowane przez bogatych by dostarczać im ciągle świeżych i egzotycznych gatunków ryb na ich wykwintne uczty.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FUR_FARM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Fur farming is the practice of breeding or raising certain types of animals for their fur. This became possible in the 1860's.</English>
		<Italian>L'allevamento di animali da pelliccia è la pratica di incrociare e allevare certi tipi di animali principalmente per ottenere la loro pelliccia; quest'attività divenne possibile negli anni '60 dell'Ottocento.</Italian>
		<Polish>Można spotkać się z poglądem, że hodowla norek i innych stworzeń na futro wiąże się z niehumanitarnym traktowaniem zwierząt. Szczególnie dobrze jest to udokumentowane w krajach Trzeciego Zwiata. Jednak raport dotyczący sytuacji wielkopolskich ferm futrzarskich autorstwa Najwyższej Izby Kontroli z 2011 roku, wskazuje że "w 87% tych ferm nie przestrzegano wymagań ochrony środowiska, w 48% działalność hodowlana prowadzona była w obiektach nielegalnie wybudowanych lub użytkowanych, a w 35% niezgodnie z przepisami weterynaryjnymi." Aktywiści pro-zwierzęcy twierdzą iż fermy hodowlane są przyczyną skażenia środowiska licznymi związkami takimi jak siarkowodór, amoniak, mocznik, fosfor czy azot, które nie są odpowiednio utylizowane.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GOAT_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The domestic goat (Capra aegagrus hircus) is a subspecies of goat domesticated from the wild goat of southwest Asia and Eastern Europe. The goat is a member of the Bovidae family and is closely related to the sheep as both are in the goat-antelope subfamily Caprinae. There are over three hundred distinct breeds of goat.[PARAGRAPH:2]Goats are one of the oldest domesticated species. Goats have been used for their milk, meat, hair, and skins over much of the world. In the twentieth century they also gained in popularity as pets.[PARAGRAPH:2]Female goats are referred to as does or nannies, intact males as bucks or billies; their offspring are kids. Note that many goat breeders prefer the terms "buck" and "doe" to "billy" and "nanny". Castrated males are wethers. Goat meat from younger animals is called kid or cabrito, and from older animals is sometimes called chevon, or in some areas "mutton".</English>
		<Italian>La capra domestica (Capra aegagrus hircus) è una sottospecie di capra addomesticata dalla capra selvatica dall'Asia sud-occidentale e dell'Europa orientale. La capra è un membro della famiglia dei bovidi ed è strettamente correlata alle pecore in quanto entrambi appartengono alla sottofamiglia Caprinae. Ci sono oltre trecento razze distinte di capra.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le capre sono una delle più antiche specie domestiche. Le capre sono state utilizzate per il loro latte, carne, capelli e pelle su gran parte del mondo. Nel XX secolo, hanno anche guadagnato in popolarità come animali da compagnia.</Italian>
		<Polish>Badania genetyczne współczesnych kóz ujawniają, że chociaż zostały one oswojone równolegle w kilku częściach świata to geny tych pionierów zmieszały się w całej populacji. Pewnie wynika to z tego, że kozy są doskonałymi towarzyszami podróży nie przeszkadzają im ciężkie warunki środowiskowe i nie mają wygórowanych wymagań pokarmowych. Dużym plusem owych zwierząt były ich małe wymiary ułatwiające sprzedaż kóz pomiędzy sąsiadującymi nawet w dużych odległościach osadami. W starożytności podawano całkiem słuszny przykład popierający tę tezę "posiadanie czterech kóz daje ci większy zasięg w handlu i mniejsze ryzyko niż posiadanie jednej krowy". Bez tych zwierząt migracje plemion ludzkich mogłyby wyglądać zupełnie inaczej, gdyż przybycie koczowniczych pasterzy zapewne mobilizowało miejscową ludność do udomowiania także innych ras zwierząt.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GOVENORS_MENAGERIE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>If one wild animal is a status symbol what better than many to boost your standing among your fellows and foreigners alike.</English>
		<Italian>Se un animale selvatico è uno status symbol, cosa c'è di meglio di molti per aumentare la tua posizione tra i tuoi sudditi e gli stranieri?</Italian>
		<Polish>Jeśli jedno zwierzę to za mało to dlaczego nie stworzyć całej menażerii?.</Polish>
		<Russian>Åñëè îäíî äèêîå æèâîòíîå ÿâëÿåòñÿ ñèìâîëîì ñòàòóñà, ÷òî ëó÷øå, ÷åì ìíîãèå, ïîâûñèòü âàøó ðåïóòàöèþ ñðåäè âàøèõ ñîïëåìåííèêîâ è èíîñòðàíöåâ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GOVENORS_PETS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>As a status symbol a live wild, dangerous, large or exotic animal is a boon for any leader.</English>
		<Italian>Come status symbol, un animale selvatico pericoloso, grande o esotico è una manna per qualsiasi leader.</Italian>
		<Polish>Jako symbol statusu, dziko żyjące zwierzęta, wielkie lub egzotyczne zwierzęta są ozdobą każdej kolekcji nowoczesnego przywódcy.</Polish>
		<Russian>Â êà÷åñòâå ñèìâîëà èëè ñòàòóñà äèêîå, îïàñíîå, êðóïíîå èëè ýêçîòè÷åñêîå æèâîòíîå ÿâëÿåòñÿ áëàãîì äëÿ ëþáîãî ëèäåðà.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HAWKING_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Hawking is the practice of hunting with a trained falconry bird. Falconry is "the taking of wild quarry in its natural state and habitat by means of a trained raptor". There are two traditional terms used to describe a person involved in falconry: a falconer flies a falcon; an austringer (German origin) flies a hawk (Accipiter and some buteos and similar) or an eagle (Aquila or similar). In modern falconry the Red-tailed Hawk (Buteo jamaicensis) and the Harris hawk are often used. The words "hawking" and "hawker" have become used so much to mean petty traveling traders, that the terms "falconer" and "falconry" now apply to all use of trained birds of prey to catch game. In early English falconry literature, the word "falcon" referred to a female falcon only, while the word "hawk" or "hawke" referred to a female hawk. A male hawk or falcon was referred to as a "tiercel" (sometimes spelled "tercel") as it was roughly one third less than the female in size. Many contemporary practitioners still use these words in their original meaning.</English>
		<Italian>La falconeria è la pratica della caccia con un falco addestrato. La falconeria è "la cattura di prede selvatiche nel suo stato naturale e habitat per mezzo di un rapace addestrato". Ci sono due termini tradizionali usati per descrivere una persona coinvolta nella falconeria: un falconiere fa volare un falco, un austringer (di origine tedesca) fa volare un falco (Accipiter e alcune poiane e simili) o un'aquila. Nella falconeria moderna vengono spesso utilizzati il falco dalla coda rossa (Buteo jamaicensis) e il falco Harris. Le parole "Falconiere" e "Venditore ambulante" sono diventate usate così tanto da definire meschini i commercianti che viaggiano, tanto che i termini "falconiere" e "falconeria" ora si applicano a tutti gli usi di uccelli rapaci addestrati a catturare selvaggina. Nell'antica letteratura inglese riguardante la falconeria, la parola "falcon" si riferiva solo a un falcone femmina, mentre le parole "hawk" o "hawke" indicavano un falco femmina. Un falco o falcone maschio veniva chiamato "tiercel" (a volte scritto "tercel") dato che aveva una taglia circa un terzo in meno rispetto alla femmina. Molti praticanti contemporanei utilizzano ancora queste parole nel loro significato originale.</Italian>
		<Polish>Początki sokolnictwa sięgają początków ludzkiej cywilizacji i zamierzchłych czasów, kiedy to nawet u prymitywnych ludów, a zwłaszcza nomadów wiodących koczowniczy tryb życia, stało ono na bardzo wysokim poziomie. Było podstawą ich egzystencji obok zbieractwa i myślistwa. Zwiadczą o tym m.in. motywy na starożytnych malowidłach. Myśliwego z ptakiem na pięści, przedstawiają też datowane na 1500 lat p.n.e rzeźby, znalezione w Turcji.Płaskorzeźba z czasów Sargona II (722-705 p.n.e) myśliwy z orłem, potwierdza, że ten sposób polowania znali Asyryjczycy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HORSE_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The history of horse breeding goes back millennia. Though the precise date is in dispute, humans could have domesticated the horse as far back as approximately 4500 BCE. However, evidence of planned breeding has a more blurry history.[PARAGRAPH:2]One of the earliest people known to document the breedings of their horses were the Bedouin of the Middle East, the breeders of the Arabian horse. While it is difficult to determine how far back the Bedouin passed on pedigree information via an oral tradition, there were written pedigrees of Arabian horses by A.D. 1330. The Akhal-Teke of West-Central Asia is another breed with roots in ancient times that was also bred specifically for war and racing. The nomads of the Mongolian steppes bred horses for several thousand years as well.[PARAGRAPH:2]The types of horses bred varied with culture and with the times. The uses to which a horse was put also determined its qualities, including smooth amblers for riding, fast horses for carrying messengers, heavy horses for plowing and pulling heavy wagons, ponies for hauling cars of ore from mines, packhorses, carriage horses and many others.</English>
		<Italian>La storia dell'allevamento dei cavalli risale a migliaia di anni fa. Anche se la data precisa è in discussione, gli esseri umani potrebbero avere addomesticato i cavalli nel lontano 4500 a.C.; tuttavia, le prove di un allevamento più intensivo sono molto rare.[PARAGRAPH:2]Uno dei primi popoli noti per aver documentato l'allevamento dei loro cavalli sono stati i beduini del Medio Oriente, gli allevatori del cavallo arabo. Anche se è difficile determinare per quanto tempo i beduini abbiano tramandato informazioni sull'allevamento attraverso una tradizione orale, ci sono state documentazioni scritte riguardo cavalli arabi sin dal 1330 d.C.. Gli Akhal-Teke dell'Asia centro-occidentale sono un'altra razza con radici antiche che è stata allevata appositamente per la guerra e la corsa. I nomadi delle steppe mongole allevarono i cavalli per diverse migliaia di anni.[PARAGRAPH:2]I tipi di cavalli addomesticati variarono con la cultura e con i tempi. Gli usi a cui un elefante era destinato determinavano anche le sue qualità, tra cui cavalli a pelle liscia per l'equitazione, cavalli veloci per trasportare messaggeri, cavalli pesanti per l'aratura e per tirare carri pesanti, pony per trasportare carichi di minerali dalle miniere, cavalli per carrozze e molti altri.</Italian>
		<Polish>Zwinia domowa pochodzi od dzika, którego udomowienie nastąpiło przed ok. 7 tys. lat w Azji, a następnie w Europie. Według innych badaczy domestykacja tego gatunku nastąpiła znacznie wcześniej - już 12 700 - 13 000 lat p.n.e., a miało to miejsce w dorzeczu Eufratu i Tygrysu (późniejsza Mezopotamia).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_LLAMA_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The domestication of the lama took place around 4,000,000 BC. in the Andean basin, probably near Lake Titicaca. In pre-Inca times, representatives of the Mochica culture placed the remains of llamas in their graves, and also presented them on their pottery. Llamas and alpacas were the staple animal in the Inca State as food, fuel, fiber for clothing, as pack animals. They were also used in religious ceremonies as sacrificial animals. After the Inca conquest by the conquistadors, the importance of the llamas declined significantly, as the conquistadors brought their own pack animals. Despite this, llamas and alpacas remained important animals in South America, mainly in highland areas. South American countries at the beginning of the 20th century introduced a ban on the export of these animals. This ban was finally lifted for llamas and alpacas in the 1980s. </English>
		<Polish>Udomowienie lamy miało miejsce około 4000 5000 lat p.n.e. na terenach andyjskiej puny, prawdopodobnie w okolicach jeziora Titicaca. W czasach przedinkaskich, przedstawiciele kultury Mochica umieszczali szczątki lam w grobach, przedstawiali je także na swojej ceramice. Lamy i alpaki były podstawowym zwierzęciem w Państwie Inków, jako żywność, źródło paliwa, włókien na ubrania, jako zwierzęta juczne. Były także wykorzystywane w ceremoniach religijnych, jako zwierzęta ofiarne. Po podboju Państwa Inków przez konkwistadorów znaczenie lam znacznie spadło, gdyż konkwistadorzy sprowadzili własne zwierzęta juczne. Mimo tego lamy i alpaki pozostały ważnymi zwierzętami w Ameryce Południowej, głównie na terenach wysokogórskich. Państwa południowoamerykańskie na początku XX wieku wprowadziły zakaz eksportu tych zwierząt. Zakaz ten został ostatecznie zniesiony dla lam i alpak w latach 80. XX wieku.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MARINE_INSTITUTE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MASTER_HUNTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>«I fletch arrows, as hunters feast on game. I sharpen blades as the rangers trades the secrets of the wilds, of topography and the enemies movements. I brew poison as the assassins discuss their cleanest kills with grim smiles. Why do I toil away, you ask, serving the brave brothers and deadly sisters of the lodge, not to mention their pets? Because one day, one day soon, I will be one of them.» --Locke Thorne, Scout</English>
		<French>«Je tire des flèches, alors que les chasseurs se régalent de gibier. J'affûte les lames pendant que les rangers troquent les secrets de la nature, de la topographie et des mouvements des ennemis. Je prépare du poison pendant que les assassins discutent de leurs meurtres les plus purs avec des sourires sinistres. Pourquoi est-ce que je travaille dur, demandez-vous, au service des braves frères et sœurs mortelles de la loge, sans parler de leurs animaux de compagnie? Parce qu'un jour, un jour bientôt, je serai l'un d'entre eux.» -- Locke Thorne, Scout</French>
		<German>«Ich bewege Pfeile, während Jäger sich am Wild erfreuen. Ich schärfe die Klingen, während die Waldläufer die Geheimnisse der Wildnis, der Topographie und der Bewegungen des Feindes tauschen. Ich braue Gift, während die Attentäter ihre grimmigsten Tötungen mit grimmigem Lächeln besprechen. Warum arbeite ich mich ab, fragst du und diene den tapferen Brüdern und tödlichen Schwestern der Lodge, ganz zu schweigen von ihren Haustieren? Denn eines Tages, eines Tages werde ich einer von ihnen sein.» -- Locke Thorne, Pfadfinder</German>
		<Italian>«Io costruisco le frecce, mentre i cacciatori banchettano con la selvaggina. Io affilo le spade, mentre i ranger commerciano i segreti della natura, della topografia e dei movimenti dei nemici. Io fermento il veleno mentre gli assassini discutono le loro uccisioni più pulite con sorrisi torvi. Perché lavoro duramente, chiedete, servendo i fratelli coraggiosi e le sorelle mortali, per non accennare ai loro animali domestici? Poiché un giorno, presto, io sarò uno di loro.» -- Locke Thorne, esploratore</Italian>
		<Spanish>«Hago flechas, mientras los cazadores se deleitan con la caza. Afilo las espadas, mientras los guardabosques intercambian los secretos de la naturaleza, la topografía y los movimientos de los enemigos. Revuelvo el veneno mientras los asesinos discuten sus asesinatos más limpios con sonrisas sombrías. ¿Por qué trabajo duro, preguntas, sirviendo a hermanos valientes y hermanas mortales, sin mencionar a sus mascotas? Porque algún día pronto seré uno de ellos.» -- Locke Thorne, explorador</Spanish>
		<Polish>Łowy polowanie było jedną z najważniejszych czynności pierwotnych ludzi przez wiele tysiącleci. Nie było wówczas pojęcia "własności" i zwierzyna była niczyja. Polowania były głównym źródłem utrzymania i przeżycia ludzi oprócz pożywienia pozyskiwano w ten sposób skóry na okrycia, a kości i rogi na proste narzędzia. Na przestrzeni wieków, w wyniku zachodzących zmian cywilizacyjnych jak i społecznych, z powodu trzebienia puszcz, rozwoju rolnictwa, polowania przestały być głównym zajęciem człowieka, a stały się okazją do wykazania swojej siły, zręczności i męstwa w bezpośrednich spotkaniach z dzikim zwierzem. Poczynając od ok. X w. łowy zaczęły być w coraz większym stopniu przywilejem ludzi "dobrze urodzonych", cesarzy, królów, duchowieństwa i rycerstwa. Łowy stały się również głównym źródłem zaopatrzenia wojsk podczas wypraw wojennych.</Polish>
		<Russian>«ß ìåòàþ ñòðåëû, êàê îõîòíèêè íàñëàæäàþòñÿ ïîéìàííîé äè÷üþ. ß òî÷ó ëåçâèÿ, ïîêà ñëåäîïûòû îáìåíèâàþòñÿ òàéíàìè äèêîé ïðèðîäû, òîïîãðàôèè è ïåðåìåùåíèé âðàãîâ. ß çàâàðèâàþ ÿä, êîãäà àññàñèíû îáñóæäàþò ñâîè ÷èñòåéøèå óáèéñòâà ñ ìðà÷íûìè óëûáêàìè. Âû áóäåòå ñïðàøèâàòü, ñëóæèòå ëè âû õðàáðûì ñîáðàòüÿì è ñìåðòåëüíûì ñåñòðàì ïî ëîæå, íå ãîâîðÿ óæå î èõ äîìàøíèõ æèâîòíûõ? Èáî îäíàæäû ñêîðî ÿ áóäó îäíèì èç íèõ.» - Ëîêê Òîðí, ðàçâåä÷èê</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MASTER_SEA_HUNTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Hunting is the practice of killing or trapping any animal, or pursuing it with the intent of doing so. Hunting wildlife or feral animals is most commonly done by humans for food, recreation, or trade. In present-day use, lawful hunting is distinguished from poaching, which is the illegal killing, trapping or capture of the hunted species. The species that are hunted are referred to as game and are usually mammals and birds.</English>
		<Italian>Un mastro pescatore rappresenta le conoscenze che la tua gente ha riguardo ai pesci.</Italian>
		<Polish>Rybak osoba trudniąca się rybołówstwem, utrzymująca się z połowu ryb i innych owoców morza (frutti di mare) krewetek, małży itp. Słowem tym współcześnie określa się zarówno osoby wykonujące ten zawód w pojedynkę (na morzu rzadko) lub w niewielkich, kilkuosobowych zespołach, pływających na kilkutonowych kutrach (rybactwo), jak również marynarzy wielkich jednostek oceanicznych (rybołówstwo przemysłowe). Na potrzeby rybactwa śródlądowego, na rzekach i jeziorach rybacy na ogół posługują się niewielkimi łodziami, kutry morskie są zazwyczaj większe i dysponują mocniejszymi silnikami.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MULE_TRAINER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Mule Trainer is required to build Mule units.</English>
		<Italian>L'addestratore di muli è necessario per addestrare le unità di muli.</Italian>
		<Polish>Muł mieszaniec międzygatunkowy klaczy konia domowego z ogierem osła, najbardziej znana hybryda. Najczęściej bezpłodny, tylko ok. 5% mulic jest płodnych. Zewnętrznie jest bardziej podobny do konia. Charakteryzuje się dużą głową, długimi uszami oraz krótką szyją ze stojącą grzywą i typowo końskim ogonem z długimi włosami. W kłębie osiąga wysokość do 180 cm.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MUSKOX_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FOLKLORE_ANIMAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Folklore pseudobuildings represent myths, legends, stories, fables and commoner knowledge about animals and landscape.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NAVAL_TOTEM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The mascot of a ship.</English>
		<Italian>La mascotte di una nave.</Italian>
		<Polish>Maskotka statku.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PIG_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Pigs were originally wild boars in Europe and Asia that were first tamed to be domestic animals about 10000 years ago. There are many different kinds of pig. Some pigs have a pink skin but there are brown, white and black skinned pigs too. Some pigs have patterns or spots. Something in skin called pigment makes the colour and it's different for different pig breeds. There are about 73 different breeds of pig.</English>
		<Italian>I maiali erano originariamente cinghiali selvatici in Europa e in Asia, addomesticati circa 10000 anni fa. Ci sono molti tipi diversi di maiali: alcuni maiali hanno una pelle di colore rosa, ma ci sono anche maiali con pelle marrone, bianca e nera. Alcuni maiali hanno strisce o macchie. Qualcosa nella pelle chiamato pigmento è responsabile del colore, ed è diverso nelle diverse razze suine. Ci sono circa 73 diverse razze di maiali.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_POULTRY_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RATITE_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A ratite is any of a diverse group of large, flightless birds of Gondwanan origin, most of them now extinct. There is still some controversy regarding the systematics involved. Some sources state that Ratites are synonymous with Struthioiniformes, while other sources state that Ratites are the same group, only that the order Struthioniformes contains only the Ostrich and possibly the Elephant Bird. Unlike other flightless birds, the ratites have no keel on their sternum hence the name from the Latin ratis (for raft). Without this to anchor their wing muscles, they could not fly even if they were to develop suitable wings.[PARAGRAPH:2]Most parts of the former Gondwana have ratites, or did have until the fairly recent past. Their closest living relatives are the tinamous of South America.[PARAGRAPH:2]Some taxonomical systems consider the various families of ratites to be orders, but the system used here uses the order "Struthioniformes" to refer to all ratites. The African Ostrich is the largest living ratite. A large member of this species can be nearly 2.8 metres (9.2 ft) tall, weigh as much as 156 kilograms (340 lb), and can outrun a horse.[PARAGRAPH:2]Of the living species, the Australian emu is next in height, reaching up to 1.9 metres (6.2 ft) tall and about 50 kilograms (110 lb). Like the ostrich, it is a fast-running, powerful bird of the open plains and woodlands.[PARAGRAPH:2]Also native to Australia and the islands to the north are the three species of cassowary. Shorter than an emu, but heavier and solidly built, cassowaries prefer thickly vegetated tropical forest. They can be very dangerous when surprised or cornered because of their razor sharp talons. In New Guinea, cassowary eggs are brought back to villages and the chicks raised for eating as a much-prized delicacy, despite (or perhaps because of) the risk they pose to life and limb. They reach up to 1.7 metres (5.6 ft) tall and weigh as much as 59 kilograms (130 lb)[PARAGRAPH:2]South America has two species of rhea, large fast-running birds of the Pampas. The larger American rhea grows to about 1.4 metres (4.6 ft) tall and usually weighs 15 to 40 kilograms (3388 lb).[PARAGRAPH:2]The smallest ratites are the five species of kiwi from New Zealand. Kiwi are chicken-sized, shy, and nocturnal. They nest in deep burrows and use a highly developed sense of smell to find small insects and grubs in the soil. Kiwi are notable for laying eggs that are very large in relation to their body size. A kiwi egg may equal 15 to 20 percent of the body mass of a female kiwi. The smallest species of kiwi is the Little Spotted Kiwi, at 0.9 to 1.9 kilograms (2.04.2 lb) and 35 to 45 centimetres (1418 in).</English>
		<Italian>I ratiti sono una famiglia di uccelli, che comprende i Paleognati, che non volano. Il termine "Ratiti" viene dal latino "ratis" ("zattera"), poiché questi uccelli hanno lo sterno piatto invece che carenato. La loro distribuzione è australe di origine gondwaniana. Tranne il kiwi sono tutti di taglia grande e sono onnivori. Hanno prole precoce e le femmine covano nella stessa buca a turno; la cova è effettuata anche dal maschio. I ratiti più importanti sono gli struzzi africani, i nandù, i casuari, i kiwi e i moa (attualmente estinti).</Italian>
		<Polish>Struś syryjski od dawna zajmuje znaczące miejsce w kulturze regionu. Dorosły struś z jedenastoma młodymi został przedstawiony na słynnym prehistorycznym "Graffiti Rock I" (rysunki wyryte na skale datowane na 20001000 p.n.e. odkryte w pobliżu Rijad). W Mezopotamii, był wykorzystywany jako zwierzę ofiarne i przedstawiany na dziełach sztuki, malowany na kubkach i innych przedmiotach wykonanych ze strusich jaj, sprzedawanych aż po Etrurię w okresie nowoasyryjskim. W epoce ekspansji islamu struś syryjski reprezentował bogactwo i elegancję. Polowanie na strusie stało się popularną rozrywką dla bogaczy i szlachty (jeśli zabito strusia w odpowiedni sposób, jego mięso uznawane było przez muzułmanów za halaal). Jaja, pióra i skóry były szeroko wykorzystywane w rękodziele. Zarówno produkty otrzymane ze strusi jak i żywe ptaki były eksportowane aż do Chin.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ROO_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SALACHIMORPHA_INSTITUTE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Until recently only a few benthic species of shark, such as hornsharks, leopard sharks, catsharks, and zebra sharks had survived in aquarium conditions for up to a year or more. This gave rise to the belief that sharks, as well as being difficult to capture and transport, were difficult to care for. A better knowledge of sharks has led to more species (including the large pelagic sharks) being able to be kept for far longer. At the same time, transportation techniques have improved and long distance movement of sharks is becoming easier. One shark that never had been successfully held in captivity for long was the great white. But in September 2004 the Monterey Bay Aquarium successfully kept a young female great white shark for 198 days before releasing her back into the wild.</English>
		<Italian>Fino ad oggi poche specie di squali sono in grado di sopravvivere più di un anno in cattività. Questo ha portato a credere che gli squali, oltre a essere difficili da catturare e da trasportare, fossero anche difficili da mantenere. Recenti studi sugli squali hanno però permesso di mantenere in buone condizioni un maggior numero di specie di squali. Allo stesso tempo, le tecniche di trasporto sono migliorate e il movimento a lunga distanza di squali sta diventando più facile. Uno squalo che non era mai stato tenuto con successo in cattività per lungo tempo è stato il grande squalo bianco. Ma nel settembre 2004 il Monterey Bay Aquarium ha tenuto con successo una giovane femmina di squalo bianco per 198 giorni prima di rilasciarla di nuovo in libertà.</Italian>
		<Polish>Instytut Morski jednostka naukowo-badawcza. Placówka wykonuje prace naukowe, badawcze i wdrożeniowe: m.in. zajmuje się modernizacją i eksploatacją portów, oceanografią operacyjną, czy problematyką zagospodarowania regionu nadmorskiego. Misją Instytutu jest dbałość o zachowanie wartości morza i zrównoważony rozwój polskiej gospodarki morskiej. Instytut opracowuje studia wykonalności i eksperyzy oraz udziela konsultacji w zakresie: hydrotechniki morskiej, geotechniki, oceanografii operacyjnej, ochrony środowiska (badania chemiczne i biologiczne), transportu, logistyki, zagospodarowania przestrzennego regionu nadmorskiego, modernizacji i eksploatacji portów, żeglugi śródlądowej, turystyki, bezpieczeństwa przeciwpowodziowego, elektroniki morskiej, a także tworzenia baz danych i monitoringu zjawisk ciągłych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SHEEP_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SNAKE_CHARMER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The earliest evidence for snake charming comes from Ancient Egyptian sources. Charmers there mainly acted as magicians and healers. As literate and high-status men, part of their studies involved learning the various types of snake, the gods to whom they were sacred, and how to treat those who were bitten by the reptiles. Entertainment was also part of their repertoire, and they knew how to handle the animals and charm them for their patrons.[PARAGRAPH:2]One of the earliest records of snake charming appears in the Bible in Psalm (58:3-5): "The wicked turn aside from birth; liars go astray as soon as they are born. Their venom is like that of a snake, like a deaf serpent that does not hear, that does not respond to the magicians, or to a skilled snake-charmer." Snakes have long been popular subjects of Hindu art.[PARAGRAPH:2]Snake charming as it exists today probably originated in India. Hinduism has long held serpents to be sacred; the animals are related to the Nagas, and many gods are pictured under the protection of the cobra. Indians thus considered snake charmers to be holy men who were influenced by the gods.</English>
		<Italian>Le prime prove dell'esistenza degli incantatori di serpenti provengono da fonti egiziane antiche; qui gli incantatori agivano principalmente come maghi e guaritori. Come uomini colti e di alto rango, una parte dei loro studi consisteva nell'imparare i vari tipi di serpenti, gli dei a cui erano sacri e come trattare coloro che erano stati morsi dai rettili. Anche l'intrattenimento era parte del loro repertorio, e sapevano come gestire ed incantare gli animali.[PARAGRAPH:2]Uno dei più antichi documenti di serpenti incantati appare nella Bibbia nel Salmo (58:3-5): "i malvagi si allontanano dalla nascita; i bugiardi vanno fuori strada, non appena nascono. Il loro veleno è come quello di un serpente, come un serpente sordo che non sente, che non risponde ai maghi o ad un esperto incantatore di serpenti". I serpenti sono stati a lungo soggetti popolari nell'arte indù.[PARAGRAPH:2]Gli incantatori di serpenti attuali probabilmente ebbero origine in India. L'induismo ha da sempre ritenuto i serpenti sacri; gli animali sono legati ai Naga, e molti dei sono raffigurati sotto la protezione del cobra. Gli indiani quindi consideravano gli incantatori di serpenti essere uomini santi che venivano influenzati dagli dei.</Italian>
		<Polish>Zaklinanie węży to jedna z najstarszych rozrywek towarzyszących człowiekowi.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SNAKE_PIT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Snake Pits[COLOR_REVERT] are places of horror, torture and even death in European legends and fairy tales. The Viking warlord Ragnar Lodbrok is said to have been thrown into a snake pit and died there, after his army had been defeated in battle by King Aelle II of Northumbria. An older legend recorded in Atlakvioa and Oddrunargratr tells that Attila the Hun murdered Gunnarr, the King of Burgundy, in a snake pit. In a medieval German poem, Dietrich von Bern is thrown into a snake pit by the giant Sigenot - he is protected by a magical jewel that had been given to him earlier by a dwarf.[PARAGRAPH:2]Nothing however supports the assumption, that snake pits were ever actually maintained or used for torture or execution. The necessary effort and the risks would have been far too big for something the effect of which could hardly been foreseen or controlled with sufficient precision.</English>
		<Italian>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Fosse dei serpenti[COLOR_REVERT] sono descritti nelle leggende europee come posti di orrore, tortura e perfino morte. Si dice che il guerriero vichingo Ragnar Lodbrok sia stato gettato in una fossa piena di serpenti e sia morto lì, dopo che il suo esercito era stato sconfitto in battaglia da Re Aelle II di Northumbria. Un'antica leggenda tramandata a Atlakviða e Oddrúnargrátr narra che Attila uccise Gunnarr, Re di Burgundia, gettandolo in una fossa piena di serpenti velenosi. In un poema medievale tedesco, Dietrich von Bern viene gettato in una fossa piena di serpenti dal gigante Sigenot - anche se è protetto da un gioiello magico che gli era appena stato donato da un nano.[PARAGRAPH:2]Nulla invece sostiene l'ipotesi che le fosse di serpenti siano state effettivamente mantenute o utilizzate per torture o esecuzioni. Lo sforzo necessario e il rischio sarebbero stati troppo grandi per qualcosa il cui effetto sarebbe stato difficilmente previsto o controllato con sufficiente precisione.</Italian>
		<Polish>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Dół z wężami[COLOR_REVERT] to miejsce do którego wrzuca się skazańców na tortury i śmierć przez pokąsanie przez węże i żmije.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TORTOISE_SHELL_WORKER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Tortoiseshell or tortoise shell is a material produced mainly from the shell of the hawksbill turtle, an endangered species. It was widely used in the 1960s and 1970s in the manufacture of items such as combs, sunglasses, guitar picks and knitting needles. In 1973, the trade of tortoiseshell worldwide was banned under CITES (the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species).[PARAGRAPH:2]Tortoiseshell was attractive to manufacturers and consumers because of its beautiful appearance and its durability, and its organic warmth against the skin. It was used in guitar picks because it can be easily shaped, has excellent bending properties, and is very durable. Tortoiseshell picks could sometimes be used for years. Piqué-work, jewelry made from tortoiseshell inlaid with precious metals in patterns or pictures, was made during the Victorian Era and was highly prized.[PARAGRAPH:2]There have been a number of faux tortoiseshell materials developed since the 1970s, most of which mimic the appearance of tortoiseshell. Tortex is a material that was created to replace tortoiseshell guitar picks and has been widely accepted as a suitable substitute.</English>
		<Italian>Un guscio di testuggine è un materiale prodotto principalmente dal guscio della tartaruga embricata, una specie in via di estinzione. È stato ampiamente utilizzato negli anni 60 e 70 per la fabbricazione di articoli come pettini, occhiali da sole, plettri e aghi per lavoro a maglia. Nel 1973, il commercio di tartaruga in tutto il mondo è stato vietato dalla CITES (Convenzione sul commercio internazionale delle specie minacciate di estinzione).[PARAGRAPH:2]Il guscio di testuggine era attraente per i produttori ed i consumatori a causa della sua bella apparenza e la sua durata, e il suo calore organica contro la pelle. Veniva utilizzata nei plettri perché poteva essere facilmente modellata, ha eccellenti proprietà di curvatura, ed è molto resistente. I gusci di tartaruga potrebbero talvolta essere utilizzati per anni. Durante l'era vittoriana venivano realizzati gioielli di tartaruga intarsiati con metalli preziosi nei modelli, ed erano molto apprezzati.[PARAGRAPH:2]Ci sono stati un certo numero di materiali eco-tartaruga sviluppato dal 1970, la maggior parte dei quali imitavano l'aspetto della tartaruga. Il Tortex è un materiale creato per sostituire i plettri di tartaruga ed è stato ampiamente accettato come un sostituto adatto.</Italian>
		<Polish>Skorupy żółwi od dawien dawna były wykorzystywane do produkcji ozdób i prostych narzędzi na całym świecie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TRAINED_SEAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WILD_ANIMAL_CAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A cage used for wild subdued animals.</English>
		<Italian>Una gabbia in cui vengono rinchiusi gli animali selvaggi addomesticati.</Italian>
		<Polish>Klatka używana do przetrzymywania dzikich, poskromionych zwierząt.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WONDERS_OF_THE_DEEP_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Wonders of the deep represent the knowledge of your people about sea animals.</English>
		<Italian>Le meraviglie degli abissi rappresentano la conoscenza che la tua gente ha degli animali marini.</Italian>
		<Polish>Cuda Głębin reprezentują wiedzę jaką Twoi ludzi posiadają o zwierzętach morskich.</Polish>
		<Russian>×óäåñà Ãëóáèí ïðåäñòàâëÿþò çíàíèÿ âàøåìó íàðîäó î ìîðñêèõ îáèòàòåëÿõ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ZEBRA_HERD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_MYTHS_LEGENDS_STORIES</Tag>
		<English>Folklore</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_MYTHS_LEGENDS_STORIES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Folklore buildings represent oral traditions and have the main aim of simulating the neolithic burst in "scientific" discovery by providing science. Folklore give themselves to simulate their spread. Folklore provides education to represent the written tradition such as stories, fables, and commoner knowledge about environment or animal groups. There are Folklores about individual animals (e.g. Moon Bear), animal groups (e.g. Bears), natural elements (Earth, Sky, Sea, etc.), landscapes (a C2C extension to Platyping's Natural Wonders component) and mythical beasts.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_SUBDUED_ANIMALS</Tag>
		<English>Subdued animals</English>
		<French>Animaux apprivoisés</French>
		<German>Gefangene Tiere</German>
		<Italian>Animali addomesticati</Italian>
		<Polish>Poskromione zwierzęta</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïðèðó÷åííûå æèâîòíûå</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_SUBDUED_ANIMALS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Subdued animals[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Subdued animals are wild (barbarian) animals captured in combat. They make exotic pets and some become indispensable additions to the human condition.[PARAGRAPH:2]Subdued animals can be used to[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]create buildings[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]fight in "games" in your arena for money and happiness[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]be studied for science and culture.[NEWLINE]All these bonuses are small.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Sea Creatures[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2]Captured Sea Creatures come in two types "Tales of..." which are adventurer and fisherman stories told about the creature; and "Subdued..." which is the actual creature. Which version you get depends on the animal and the tech you have.[PARAGRAPH:2]Sea critters are different to land animals because your capital may not be on the coast. Which means that if it was not on the coast you would not have any sea critter myths. To fix that I made it so that you can choose where you want the myths to go by making a "Myth of the Sea" which is the same restriction as Palace for the other myth buildings. The "Myth Effect - Sea" stops you being able to build any myth buildings in other cities.[PARAGRAPH:2]At the start of the game you only get "Tales of...". When you capture a sea creature you get, and "Tales of..." back at the nearest city. The "Tales of..." can then be used for a Myth building or +1 and +1. You can't butcher them because you already have.[PARAGRAPH:2]As time goes by you start to be able to capture sea animals, the smaller fish first. Depending on your latitude and what Admin buildings you have subdued fish can build "Fish Pens" and later "Coastal Fisheries".[PARAGRAPH:2]At "Marine Biology" you can start to capture the larger sea animals. "Marine Biology" opens up a number of sea creature related buildings.[PARAGRAPH:2]"Tales of Narwal" and "Tales of Dugong" can build myth buildings in any city.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Options[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2]There are ways you can modify how Subdued Animals work in Caveman2Cosmos. You can adjust the rate that animals spawn and what happens to the unit when you subdue it. These are set in the XML file [BOLD]A_New_Dawn_GlobalDefines.XML[\BOLD] found in the Assets/XML folder. The variables dealing with spawn rate are[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]ANIMAL_SPAWN_MODIFIER for the rate land animals spawn at a value between 100 and 200 seems to work best. Set this value to zero (0) if you want to play without land animals.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]SEA_ANIMAL_SPAWN_MODIFIER for the rate sea animals. Note that sea animals start spawning later than land animals do.[PARAGRAPH:2]The following variables affect the rate at which you can explore in a naturalistic way if set to 0. This also increases the micro management a bit. Setting the value to 1 reduces the micromanagement but leads to unrealistic exploration rates.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]DONT_ESCORT_SUBDUED_SEA_ANIMAL for sea creatures rather than land animals.</English>
		<Italian>[H1]Animali addomesticati[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Gli animali addomesticati sono animali selvaggi catturati; vengono usati come animali da compagnia esotici, ed alcuni di loro diventano indispensabili per gli uomini.[PARAGRAPH:2]Gli animali addomesticati possono essere usati per:[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Costruire edifici[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Essere macellati in cambio di cibo, produzione o oro; ottieni migliori risultati macellando i tuoi animali in città invece che in territorio selvaggio, e risultati intermedi macellandoli nei tuoi territori.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Combattere nei giochi organizzati nelle tue arene in cambio di oro e felicità[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Essere studiati in cambio di ricerca e cultura[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Creature marine[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2]Le creature marine addomesticate sono di due tipi: "Storie di..." che sono storie narrate da avventurieri e pescatori riguardanti la creatura, e "... addomesticato" che è realmente la creatura addomesticata. La versione che puoi ottenere dipende dall'animale che catturi e dalle tecnologie che hai ricercato.[PARAGRAPH:2]Una differenza delle creature marine rispetto agli animali terrestri è che la tua capitale potrebbe non essere sulla costa; in questo caso sarebbe impossibile costruire i miti legati alle creature marine. Per ovviare a questo problema puoi decidere dove costruire i tuoi miti, costruendo un Mito del mare, che sostituisce il palazzo come prerequisito per i miti. Il "Canto del mare" è un edificio costruito gratuitamente nelle altre città che ti impedisce di costruire ovunque i miti.[PARAGRAPH:2]All'inizio della partita puoi ottenere solo "Storie di...", che vengono trasportate direttamente alla tua città più vicina. Le "Storie di..." possono essere usate per costruire miti, ma non possono essere macellate.[PARAGRAPH:2]Con il progredire del tempo potrai iniziare a catturare gli animali marini, partendo da quelli più piccoli. A seconda della latitudine e dell'amministrazione della tua città potresti essere in grado di costruire le pinne di pesce, e in seguito gli allevamenti costieri.[PARAGRAPH:2]Ricercando la "Biologia marina" potrai catturare anche gli animali più grandi; inoltre questa tecnologia sblocca molti edifici costruibili solo da creature marine.[PARAGRAPH:2]"Storie di narvali" e "Storie di dugonghi" possono costruire miti in qualsiasi città.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Opzioni[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2]Ci sono vari modi per modificare il funzionamento degli animali addomesticati in Caveman2Cosmos. Puoi modificare il tasso a cui gli animali compaiono e cosa succede ad un'unità quando la addomestichi. Le opzioni sono codificate nel file [BOLD]A_New_Dawn_GlobalDefines.XML[\BOLD] che si trova nella cartella Assets/XML. Le variabili sono:[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]ANIMAL_SPAWN_MODIFIER per il tasso a cui gli animali terrestri compaiono; si consiglia un valore compreso tra 100 e 200. Imposta questo valore a zero (0) se vuoi giocare senza animali terrestri.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]SEA_ANIMAL_SPAWN_MODIFIER per il tasso a cui compaiono gli animali marini. Nota che iniziano a comparire più tardi degli animali terrestri.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]DONT_ESCORT_SUBDUED_SEA_ANIMAL come sopra, ma per le creature marine.</Italian>
		<Russian>[H1]Ïðèðó÷åííûå æèâîòíûå[\H1][PARAGRAPH]Ïðèðó÷åííûå æèâîòíûå - ýòî äèêèå (âàðâàðñêèå) æèâîòíûå, çàõâà÷åííûå â áîþ. Îíè ìîãóò âûñòóïàòü â êà÷åñòâå ýêçîòè÷åñêèõ äîìàøíèõ æèâîòíûõ, à íåêîòîðûå èç íèõ ñòàíîâÿòñÿ íåîòúåìëåìîé ÷àñòüþ äîìàøíåãî áûòà.[PARAGRAPH:2]Óñìèðåííûõ æèâîòíûõ ìîæíî èñïîëüçîâàòü äëÿ:[NEWLINE][TAB][ICON_BULLET]Ñòðîèòåëüñòâà îñîáûõ çäàíèé;[NEWLINE][TAB][ICON_BULLET]Ó÷àñòèÿ â ñðàæåíèÿõ è «èãðàõ» íà âàøåé àðåíå ðàäè äîõîäîâ è ñ÷àñòëèâûõ ëèö;[NEWLINE] [TAB] [ICON_BULLET]Óñêîðåíèÿ èññëåäîâàíèé èëè êóëüòóðíîãî ðîñòà.[NEWLINE]Âñå ýòè áîíóñû íåâåëèêè.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Îáèòàòåëè ìîðÿ[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2]Çàõâà÷åííûå ìîðñêèå æèâîòíûå èëè ðûáû áûâàþò äâóõ òèïîâ «Ñêàç îá...», êîòîðûå ïðåäñòàâëÿþò ñîáîé èñòîðèè ïðèêëþ÷åíèé è ðûáàêîâ î âñòðå÷å ñ ñóùåñòâîì; è "Ðó÷íîé...", êîòîðûé ÿâëÿåòñÿ ôàêòè÷åñêèì óñìèðåííûì æèâîòíûì. Òî, êàêóþ âåðñèþ âû ïîëó÷èòå, çàâèñèò îò æèâîòíîãî è òåõíîëîãèÿìè, êîòîðûìè âû ðàñïîëàãàåòå.[PARAGRAPH]Ìîðñêèå æèâîòíûå âûäåëÿþòñÿ íà ôîíå íàçåìíûõ åùå òåì, ÷òî âàøà ñòîëèöà ìîæåò îêàçàòüñÿ íå íà ïîáåðåæüå. Ýòî îçíà÷àåò, ÷òî åñëè áû îíà íå áûëà íà ïîáåðåæüå, ó âàñ íå áûëî áû íèêàêèõ ìèôîâ î ìîðñêèõ ñóùåñòâàõ. ×òîáû èñïðàâèòü ýòî, ìû ñäåëàëè òàê, ÷òîáû âû ìîãëè âûáèðàòü, êóäà âû õîòèòå îòïðàâëÿòü ìèôû, ñîçäàâ «Ìèô î ìîðå», êîòîðûé ÿâëÿåòñÿ òåì æå îãðàíè÷åíèåì, ÷òî è Äâîðåö äëÿ äðóãèõ ìèôîëîãè÷åñêèõ çäàíèé. «Ýôôåêò ìèôà - ìîðå» ëèøàåò âàñ âîçìîæíîñòè ñòðîèòü ëþáûå ìèôè÷åñêèå çäàíèÿ â äðóãèõ ãîðîäàõ.[PARAGRAPH]Â íà÷àëå èãðû âû ïîëó÷àåòå òîëüêî «Ñêàçû...». Êîãäà âû çàõâàòûâàåòå ìîðñêîå ñóùåñòâî, âû ïîëó÷àåòå èõ, è «Ñêàçêè...» âîçâðàùàþòñÿ â áëèæàéøèé ãîðîä. «Ñêàçêè...» ìîãóò áûòü èñïîëüçîâàíû äëÿ ñîçäàíèÿ Ìèôà èëè +1 è +1. Âû íå ìîæåòå ðàñïóñèòü èõ, ïîòîìó ÷òî ó âàñ óæå åñòü.[PARAGRAPH:2]Ñî âðåìåíåì âû íà÷èíàåòå ëîâèòü ìîðñêèõ æèâîòíûõ, â ïåðâóþ î÷åðåäü íåáîëüøóþ ðûáó. Â çàâèñèìîñòè îò âàøåé øèðîòû è òîãî, êàêèå àäìèíèñòðàòèâíûå çäàíèÿ âû óñïåëè ïîñòðîèòü, ñ ïîìîùüþ ðûáû ìîæíî ïîñòðîèòü «Ðûáíûå çàâîäè», à çàòåì «Ïðèáðåæíîå ðûáîëîâñòâî».[PARAGRAPH:2]Ñ òåõíîëîãèåé «Ìîðñêàÿ áèîëîãèÿ» âû ìîæåòå íà÷àòü ëîâèòü êðóïíûõ ìîðñêèõ æèâîòíûõ. «Ìîðñêàÿ áèîëîãèÿ» îòêðûâàåò ðÿä çäàíèé, ñâÿçàííûõ ñ ìîðñêèìè ñóùåñòâàìè.[PARAGRAPH: 2]«Ñêàçêè î Íàðâàëå» è «Ñêàçêè î äþãîíè» ïîçâîëÿþò ñòðîèòü ìèôè÷åñêèå çäàíèÿ â ëþáîì ãîðîäå.[PARAGRAPH][BOLD]Íàñòðîéêè[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2]Ñóùåñòâóþò ñïîñîáû èçìåíèòü ðàáîòó ïðèðó÷åííûõ æèâîòíûõ â ìîäå Caveman2Cosmos. Âû ìîæåòå íàñòðîèòü ñêîðîñòü ïîÿâëåíèÿ æèâîòíûõ è òî, ÷òî ïðîèñõîäèò ñ îòðÿäîì, êîãäà âû åãî óñìèðÿåòå. Îíè óñòàíîâëåíû â XML-ôàéëå [BOLD]A_New_Dawn_GlobalDefines.xml[\BOLD], êîòîðûé íàõîäèòñÿ â ïàïêå Assets/XML. Ïåðåìåííûå, îòíîñÿùèåñÿ ê ñêîðîñòè ïîÿâëåíèÿ, ñëåäóþùèå:[NEWLINE][TAB][ICON_BULLET]ANIMAL_SPAWN_MODIFIER äëÿ ñêîðîñòè ïîÿâëåíèÿ íàçåìíûõ æèâîòíûõ ïðè çíà÷åíèè ìåæäó 100 è 200, êàæåòñÿ, ðàáîòàþò ëó÷øå âñåãî. Óñòàíîâèòå ýòî çíà÷åíèå íà íîëü (0), åñëè âû õîòèòå èãðàòü áåç íàçåìíûõ æèâîòíûõ.[NEWLINE][TAB][ICON_BULLET]SEA_ANIMAL_SPAWN_MODIFIER äëÿ ÷àñòîòû ïîÿâëåíèÿ ìîðñêèõ æèâîòíûõ. Îáðàòèòå âíèìàíèå, ÷òî ìîðñêèå æèâîòíûå íà÷èíàþò ïîÿâëÿòüñÿ ïîçæå, ÷åì íàçåìíûå æèâîòíûå. [PARAGRAPH]Ñëåäóþùèå ïåðåìåííûå âëèÿþò íà ñêîðîñòü, ñ êîòîðîé âû ìîæåòå èññëåäîâàòü åñòåñòâåííûì îáðàçîì, åñëè óñòàíîâëåíî çíà÷åíèå 0. Ýòî òàêæå íåìíîãî óïðîùàåò ìèêðîêîíòðîëü. Óñòàíîâêà çíà÷åíèÿ 1 óìåíüøàåò ìèêðîêîíòðîëü, íî ïðèâîäèò ê íåðåàëèñòè÷íûì ïîêàçàòåëÿì èññëåäîâàíèÿ. [NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] DONT_ESCORT_SUBDUED_LAND_ANIMAL, åñëè óñòàíîâëåíî 1 ïðèðó÷åííîå æèâîòíîå, òåëåïîðòèðóìîå â áëèæàéøèé íàçåìíûé ãîðîä. Ïî óìîë÷àíèþ èñïîëüçóåòñÿ òåëåïîðò. [NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] DONT_ESCORT_SUBDUED_SEA_ANIMAL äëÿ ìîðñêèõ ñóùåñòâ, à íå íàçåìíûõ æèâîòíûõ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_SUBDUED_SEA_ANIMALS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Subdued sea animals are wild (barbarian) sea animals defeated in combat.</English>
		<French>Les animaux marins apprivoisés sont des animaux marins sauvages (barbares) vaincus au combat.</French>
		<Italian>Gli animali marini addomesticati sono animali marini che vengono sconfitti in battaglia (vedi Animali addomesticati per maggiori dettagli sui loro utilizzi).</Italian>
		<Polish>Poskromione zwierzęta morskie są dzikimi (barbarzyńskimi) zwierzętami wodnymi pokonanymi w walce.</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïðèðó÷åííûå ìîðñêèå æèâîòíûå - ýòî äèêèå (âàðâàðñêèå) ìîðñêèå æèâîòíûå, ïîáåæäåííûå â áîþ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_TALESOF_SEA_ANIMALS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Tales of sea animals are stories about sea animals defeated in combat.</English>
		<French>Les histoires d'animaux marins sont des histoires d'animaux marins vaincus au combat.</French>
		<Italian>Le storie di animali marini sono storie riguardanti creature marine sconfitte in combattimento.</Italian>
		<Polish>Opowieści o morskich zwierzętach są opowieściami o zwierzętach pokonanych w walce.</Polish>
		<Russian>Ðàññêàçû î ìîðñêèõ æèâîòíûõ - ýòî ðàññêàçû î ïîáåæäåííûõ â áîþ ìîðñêèõ ñóùåñòâàõ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HUNTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Years of living in the wilderness on their own terms have taught these men a thing or two about the importance of stealth, speed and senses. They specialise in the hunting and subduing of animal units.</English>
		<French>Des années de vie dans la nature selon leurs propres termes ont enseigné à ces hommes une ou deux choses sur l'importance de la furtivité, de la vitesse et des sens. Ils se spécialisent dans la chasse et la maîtrise des unités animales.</French>
		<Italian>Anni di vita nella natura e in solitudine hanno insegnato a questi uomini una cosa o due sull'importanza della silenziosità, della velocità e della percezione sensoriale. Sono specializzati nella caccia e nell'addomesticamento di animali selvaggi.</Italian>
		<Polish>Łowy polowanie było jedną z najważniejszych czynności pierwotnych ludzi przez wiele tysiącleci. Nie było wówczas pojęcia "własności" i zwierzyna była niczyja. Polowania były głównym źródłem utrzymania i przeżycia ludzi oprócz pożywienia pozyskiwano w ten sposób skóry na okrycia, a kości i rogi na proste narzędzia. Na przestrzeni wieków, w wyniku zachodzących zmian cywilizacyjnych jak i społecznych, z powodu trzebienia puszcz, rozwoju rolnictwa, polowania przestały być głównym zajęciem człowieka, a stały się okazją do wykazania swojej siły, zręczności i męstwa w bezpośrednich spotkaniach z dzikim zwierzem. Poczynając od ok. X w. łowy zaczęły być w coraz większym stopniu przywilejem ludzi "dobrze urodzonych", cesarzy, królów, duchowieństwa i rycerstwa. Łowy stały się również głównym źródłem zaopatrzenia wojsk podczas wypraw wojennych.</Polish>
		<Russian>Ãîäû æèçíè â ïóñòûíå íà èõ ñîáñòâåííûõ óñëîâèÿõ íàó÷èëè ýòèõ ëþäåé îäíîé èëè äâóì âåùàì î âàæíîñòè ñêðûòíîñòè, ñêîðîñòè è ÷óâñòâ. Îíè ñïåöèàëèçèðóþòñÿ íà îõîòå è îäîìàøíèâàíèè çâåðåé.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
