<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DE_WITT_1</Tag>
		<English>I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Know that I shall be a fair and forthright adversary, if not a... calculating... one.</English>
		<Polish>Jestem [OUR_NAME] z [OUR_EMPIRE]. Wiedz, źe będę wymagającym, ale uczciwym przeciwnikiem.</Polish>
		<Russian>Я - [OUR_NAME] из [OUR_EMPIRE]. Знай, что я буду честным и решительным, если не... расчетливым... противником.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DE_WITT</Tag>
		<English>Johan de Witt</English>
		<Russian>ßí äå Âèòò</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DE_WITT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Johan de Witt[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Grand Pensionary of Holland[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1625 - 1672[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Johan de Witt was a key figure in Dutch politics at a time when the Republic of the United Provinces was one of the Great Powers in Europe, dominating trade routes and thus one of the wealthiest and mightiest nations in the world. He was born as the son of Jacob de Witt, an influential burgher from the patrician class in the city of Dordrecht which, in the seventeenth century, was one of the most important cities of the dominating province of Holland. Johan and his older brother Cornelis de Witt grew up in a privileged environment in terms of education.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1650 he was appointed leader of the deputation of Dordrecht to the States of Holland, the year that stadtholder William II of Orange died. In 1653 his uncle Cornelis de Graeff have made him to a 'raadpensionaris', a sort of chairman, of the States of Holland. Holland being the most powerful province, he was effectively the political leader of the United Provinces as a whole.[PARAGRAPH:1]De Witt's power base was the wealthy merchant class of which he was born. This class broadly coincided politically with the "States faction", stressing Protestant religious moderation and pragmatic foreign policy defending commercial interests. The "Orange faction", consisting of the middle class, preferred a strong leader from the House of Orange as a counterweight against the rich upperclasses, in economic and religious matters alike, although leaders that did emerge from the House of Orange rarely were strict Calvinists themselves. In the period following the Treaty of Westminster the Republic grew in wealth and influence under De Witt's leadership. De Witt created a strong navy, appointing one of his political cronies, Lieutenant-Admiral Jacob van Wassenaer Obdam, as supreme commander of the confederate fleet. Later De Witt became a personal friend of Lieutenant-Admiral Michiel de Ruyter. The Second Anglo-Dutch War began in 1665, lasting until 1667 when it ended with the Treaty of Breda, in which De Witt negotiated very favorable agreements for the Republic after the partial destruction of the British fleet in the Raid on the Medway, initiated by De Witt himself and executed in 1666 by De Ruyter.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the Dutch rampjaar (disaster year) of 1672, when France and England during the Franco-Dutch War (Third Anglo-Dutch War) attacked the Republic, the Orangists took power by force and expelled him. Recovering from an earlier attempt on his life in June, he was assassinated by a carefully organized lynch "mob" after visiting his brother Cornelis de Witt in prison.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Johan de Witt[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Wielki Pensjonariusz Holandii.[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 1625 - 1672[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Był synem Jakuba de Witta (1589-1674), jednego z głównych opozycjonistów z czasów rządów Wilhelma II Orańskiego, zwolennika partii republikańskiej. Był wszechstronnie wykształconym prawnikiem i matematykiem. Specjalizował się w dziedzinie ubezpieczeń. Był równieź poetą. Dzięki licznym koligacjom rodzinnym (jego wuj, Cornelis de Graeff był jednym z regentów Holandii), zrobił szybką karierę urzędniczą i juź w wieku 28 lat został Wielkim Pensjonariuszem Holandii. Po śmierci Wilhelma II, w tzw. "okresie bez namiestnika" dzięki silnej pozycji prowincji Holandii i miasta Amsterdam Jan de Witt przejął de facto ster władzy w aparacie administracyjnym Niderlandów. Jan stał na czele mieszczańskiego stronnictwa republikańskiego, przeciwnego powrotowi domu Orańskiego do władzy i zwalczającego wszelkie wpływy o zabarwieniu monarchistycznym.</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Ян де Витт[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Великий пенсионарий Голландии[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни: [\BOLD] 1625 - 1672[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Ян де Витт был ключевой фигурой в голландской политике в то время, когда Республика Соединенных провинций была одной из великих держав в Европе, доминирующей на торговых путях и, следовательно, одной из самых богатых и могущественных стран в мире. Он родился как сын Якоба де Витта, влиятельного бюргера из класса патрициев в городе Дордрехт, который в семнадцатом веке был одним из самых важных городов доминирующей провинции Голландии. Ян и его старший брат Корнелис де Витт выросли в привилегированной среде с точки зрения полученного ими образования.[PARAGRAPH:1]В 1650 году он был назначен главой делегации Дордрехта в государствах Голландии, в год смерти штатгальтера Вильгельма II Оранского. В 1653 году его дядя Корнелис де Грефф сделал его «raadpensionaris», своего рода председателем, в государствах Голландии. Голландия, будучи самой могущественной провинцией, он был фактически политическим лидером Соединенных провинций в целом.[PARAGRAPH:1]Основой власти Де Витта был класс богатого купечества, из которого он был выходцем. Этот класс в целом политически совпадал с «фракцией государств», подчеркивая протестантскую религиозную умеренность и прагматичную внешнюю политику, защищающую коммерческие интересы. «Оранжевая фракция», состоящая из среднего класса, предпочитала сильного лидера из Оранской династии в качестве противовеса богатым высшим классам, как в экономических, так и в религиозных вопросах, хотя лидеры, вышедшие из Оранской династии, редко являлись строгими кальвинистами. В период после Вестминстерского договора Республика под руководством Де Витта выросла в богатстве и влиянии. Де Витт создал сильный флот, назначив одного из своих политических соратников, лейтенант-адмирала Якоба ван Вассенаера Обдама, верховным главнокомандующим конфедеративным флотом. Позже Де Витт стал личным другом лейтенант-адмирала Михеля де Рюйтера. Вторая англо-голландская война началась в 1665 году и продолжалась до 1667 года, когда она закончилась Бредским договором, в котором Де Витт заключил очень выгодные для республики соглашения после частичного уничтожения британского флота в рейде на Медуэй, инициированном Сам Де Витт и казнен Де Рюйтером в 1666 году.[PARAGRAPH:1]С началом голландского rampjaar (года бедствия) в 1672 году, когда Франция и Англия во время франко-голландской войны (Третья англо-голландская война) напали на республику, оранжисты взяли власть силой и изгнали его. Оправляясь от предыдущего покушения на его жизнь в июне, он был убит вместе с его братом, Корнелисом де Виттом, спровоцированной и разогретой «толпой» линчевателей после посещения его в тюремном заключении.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>