<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HELLSMOUTH_SANCTUARY</Tag>
		<English>Hellsmouth Sanctuary</English>
		<French>Sanctuaire d'Hellsmouth</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Santuario della Bocca dell'Inferno</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Sanktuarium Bram Piekieł</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïðèþò äåìîíîâ</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HELLSMOUTH_SANCTUARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Where the voodoo wizards come in deals with the averns.</English>
		<Italian>Questo è il luogo dove i maghi voodoo entrano in contatto con gli spiriti infernali.</Italian>
		<Polish>Sanktuarium Bram Piekieł</Polish>
		<Russian>Ìåñòî, ãäå êîëäóíû âóäó çàêëþ÷àåò ñäåëêè ñ äóõàìè çàãðîáíîãî ìèðà.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VOODOO_CATHEDRAL</Tag>
		<English>Voodoo Market</English>
		<French>Marché Vaudou</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Mercato voodoo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Targ Voodoo</Polish>
		<Russian>Ëàâêà âóäó</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VOODOO_CATHEDRAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In Civilization IV, a cathedral is defined as an especially large and ornate religious building where the faithful worship. Only the most prosperous cities can afford to create cathedrals, as they require huge amounts of raw material and years of dedicated labor by skilled craftsmen. For example, the Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris, France, took over two centuries to complete.</English>
		<French>Dans Civilization IV, un grand lieu de culte est défini comme un édifice religieux particulièrement grand et richement orné dans lequel les fidèles pratiquent leur religion: "cathédrales" pour les chrétiens, "mosquées" pour les musulmans et "synagogues" pour les juifs. Seules les villes les plus prospères ont les moyens de construire de tels édifices. En effet, ils nécessitent d'énormes quantités de matériaux bruts et des artisans spécialisés doivent y consacrer des années de travail. Ainsi, il a fallu plus de deux siècles pour terminer la cathédrale Notre-Dame à Paris.</French>
		<German>In Civilization IV sind Kathedralen große und prächtige Gotteshäuser, in denen Gläubige beten. Nur die reichsten aller Städte können sich den Bau einer Kathedrale leisten, da hierfür große Mengen an Baumaterial und die jahrelange Arbeit erfahrener Handwerker erforderlich sind. Die Kathedrale von Notre Dame in Paris wurde beispielsweise erst nach 200-jähriger Bauzeit fertig gestellt.</German>
		<Italian>In Civilization IV, viene definito cattedrale un edificio religioso particolarmente grande e sfarzoso adibito a luogo di culto per i fedeli. Solamente le città più prosperose possono permettersi l'edificazione di cattedrali poiché sono necessari un'enorme quantità di materiali e operai esperti. Per esempio, per completare la cattedrale di Notre-Dame de Paris, in Francia, ci sono voluti più di due secoli.</Italian>
		<Spanish>En Civilization IV, una catedral se define como un edificio religioso especialmente grande y ornamentado en el que se reúnen los fieles para celebrar sus ritos. Solo las ciudades más grandes pueden permitirse el lujo de crear catedrales, puesto que requieren enormes cantidades de materias primas y años de dedicación por parte de trabajadores especializados. Por ejemplo, la catedral de Notre Dame, Francia, tardó dos siglos en completarse.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Katedra, kościół katedralny, kościół biskupi (łac. ecclesia cathedralis, z gr. kathedra - krzesło, siedziba) - główny kościół biskupa diecezjalnego, arcybiskupa (archikatedra) lub patriarchy (kościół patriarchalny), w którym głosi on doktrynę katolicką. Termin stosuje się także do konkatedr i prokatedr. Niekiedy swobodnie jako określenie głównego kościoła miejskiego - nie zawsze jednak największy i najpiękniejszy kościół danej diecezji jest zarazem jej kościołem katedralnym, choćby w przypadku diecezji rzymskiej Bazylika św. Piotra znacznie przewyższa rozmiarami Bazylikę Laterańską. W historii sztuki i kultury utarło się, by ogólnie nazywać katedrami wielkie kościoły romańskie i gotyckie, niekoniecznie stanowiące katedry we właściwym sensie.</Polish>
		<Russian>Â Öèâèëèçàöèè IV, ïîä ñîáîðîì ïîíèìàåòñÿ îñîáî êðóïíîå è áîãàòî óêðàøåííîå êóëüòîâîå ñîîðóæåíèå, ãäå âåðóþùèå ïîêëîíÿþòñÿ âåðõîâíîìó áîæåñòâó èëè äóõó. Òîëüêî ñàìûå áîãàòûå è ïðîöâåòàþùèå ãîðîäà ìîãóò ïîçâîëèòü ñåáå ñîçäàòü ñîáîðû, òàê êàê îíè òðåáóþò îãðîìíîãî êîëè÷åñòâà ñûðüÿ è ìíîãîëåòíåãî öåëåíàïðàâëåííîãî òðóäà êâàëèôèöèðîâàííûõ ðåìåñëåííèêîâ. Íàïðèìåð, äëÿ Ñîáîðà Íîòð-Äàì â Ïàðèæå, âî Ôðàíöèè, ïîòðåáîâàëîñü áîëåå äâóõ ñòîëåòèé íà çàâåðøåíèå ñòðîèòåëüòâà.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VOODOO_MONASTERY</Tag>
		<English>Hounfor</English>
		<Russian>Äîì âóäó</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VOODOO_MONASTERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A monastery is a building where monks can retreat from the world and concentrate upon the divine. Usually a monastery will have strict rules of conduct to protect its unworldly members from temptation. In some monasteries, the monks are totally silent; in others no visitors are allowed inside. Monasteries usually have many daily rituals and religious services.[PARAGRAPH:1]Throughout the ages monasteries have often been centers of learning. In remote areas the monks may be the only literate people for miles around. Monks have often been employed as scribes, copying out the words of their religion's sacred scripture. Monasteries frequently have extensive libraries, holding religious, scientific, medical and philosophical texts.</English>
		<French>Un monastère est un édifice dans lequel les moines peuvent se retirer du monde et se concentrer sur le divin. Généralement, les règles de conduite y sont strictes afin de protéger ses membres, détachés du monde, de la tentation. Dans certains monastères, les moines sont totalement silencieux ; dans d'autres, les visiteurs ne sont pas autorisés à pénétrer dans leur enceinte. Les monastères ont généralement de nombreux rituels et services religieux quotidiens.[PARAGRAPH:1]A travers les siècles, les monastères ont souvent été des centres d'érudition. Dans les zones retirées, les moines étaient parfois les seules personnes sachant lire et écrire à des kilomètres à la ronde. Ils ont souvent servi de scribes, recopiant les textes sacrés de leur religion. Les monastères ont généralement de grandes bibliothèques possédant des textes religieux, scientifiques, médicaux et philosophiques.</French>
		<German>Klöster sind Gebäude, in die sich Mönche zurückziehen, um sich auf Gott zu konzentrieren. In Klöstern gelten strenge Verhaltensregeln, die die Mönche vor Versuchungen bewahren sollen. In einigen Klöstern herrscht ein strenges Redeverbot, in anderen sind keine Besucher gestattet. Die Mönche selbst gehen täglich ihren religiösen Pflichten nach.[PARAGRAPH:1]In der Vergangenheit waren Klöster stets auch Zentren des Wissens. In abgelegenen Gegenden waren die Mönche oft die einzigen gebildeten Menschen, die als Schreiber ihre religiösen Schriften kopierten. Klöster haben nicht selten Bibliotheken, in denen unzählige religiöse, wissenschaftliche, medizinische und philosophische Texte aufbewahrt werden.</German>
		<Italian>Il monastero è un edificio nel quale i monaci possono ritirarsi dal mondo e concentrarsi sul Divino. In genere, nel monastero vige un regolamento ferreo per proteggere i membri della comunità dalle tentazioni. In alcuni monasteri, i monaci erano completamente silenziosi e non erano permesse visite dall'esterno per non interrompere i rituali quotidiani e le cerimonie religiose.[PARAGRAPH:1]Nel corso dei secoli, i monasteri sono stati spesso centro di insegnamento: in alcune zone, i monaci erano sovente gli unici in grado di leggere e scrivere nel giro di diversi chilometri. Da sempre, i monaci sono stati utilizzati come scribi per copiare le parole sacre della propria religione; i monasteri ospitavano spesso delle biblioteche che contenevano testi religiosi, scientifici, medici e filosofici.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Un monasterio es un edificio en el que los monjes pueden retirarse del mundo para concentrarse en los asuntos de la divinidad. Normalmente tienen estrictas reglas de comportamiento para proteger a sus miembros de la tentación. En algunos monasterios, los monjes guardan un silencio total, mientras que en otros no se permite el acceso a los visitantes. Lo habitual es que sus miembros tengan que celebrar a diario muchos rituales y servicios religiosos.[PARAGRAPH:1]A lo largo de la historia, los monasterios han sido muchas veces centros de estudio. En las regiones remotas, los monjes podían ser las únicas personas letradas en muchos kilómetros a la redonda. A menudo han sido empleados como escribas, y se han dedicado a copiar los textos sagrados de su religión. Normalmente cuentan con grandes bibliotecas, que contienen textos religiosos, científicos, médicos y filosóficos.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Klasztor - budynek lub zespół budynków, w którym mieszkają wspólnoty religijne zakonników albo zakonnic. Klasztory są znane przede wszystkim z chrześcijaństwa i buddyzmu, choć występują lub występowały także w hinduizmie, dżinizmie, islamie i judaizmie. Nazwą tą określa się często sam zakon czy zgromadzenie zakonne.</Polish>
		<Russian>Ìîíàñòûðü - ýòî çäàíèå, ãäå ìîíàõè ìîãóò óäàëèòüñÿ îò ìèðà è ñêîíöåíòðèðîâàòüñÿ íà ïîñòèæåíèè Âûñøåé Èñòèíû. Êàê ïðàâèëî ëþáîé ìîíàñòûðü èìååò ñîáñòâåííûå ñòðîãèå óñòàâû, ÷òîáû çàùèòèòü ñâîþ îáùèíó îò ñîáëàçíîâ ìèðà ñåãî. Â íåêîòîðûõ ìîíàñòûðÿõ ìîíàõè ïðîæèâàþò â ïîëíîé èçîëÿöèè, à â äðóãèõ îáèòåëÿõ ðàäû ïîÿâëåíèþ ïîñåòèòåëåé è ïàëîìíèêîâ. Ó ìîíàñòûðåé îáû÷íî èìåþòñÿ ìíîæåñòâà åæåäíåâíûõ ðèòóàëîâ è áîãîñëóæåíèé. [PARAGRAPH:1] Íà ïðîòÿæåíèè âåêîâ ìîíàñòûðè íåðåäêî áûëè öåíòðàìè îáó÷åíèÿ. Â îòäàëåííûõ ðàéîíàõ ëèøü ñðåäè ìîíàõîâ ìîãóò áûòü ãðàìîòíûå ëþäè íà ìíîæåñòâî âåðñò âîêðóã. Ìîíàõè çà÷àñòóþ èñïîëüçóþòñÿ êàê ïåðåïèñ÷èêè, ïðè ñîñòàâëåíèè ñïèñêîâ òåêñòîâ èç Ñâÿùåííîãî Ïèñàíèÿ. Ìîíàñòûðè ÷àñòî èìåþò îáøèðíûå áèáëèîòåêè, ñîñòîÿùèõ èç ðåëèãèîçíûõ, íàó÷íûõ, ìåäèöèíñêèõ è ôèëîñîôñêèõ òåêñòîâ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VOODOO_SHRINE</Tag>
		<English>The Tomb of Ansyen Bon</English>
		<French>Tombe de Ansyen Bon</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Tomba di Ansyen Bon</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Krypta Ansyen Bon</Polish>
		<Russian>Äðåâíÿÿ ãðîáíèöà</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VOODOO_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Crypt of Ansyen Bon</English>
		<Polish>Krypta Ansyen Bon</Polish>
		<Russian>Ìîãèëüíèê - â âóäó - ÿâëÿåòñÿ êîìïëåêñ ïîãðåáåíèé äëÿ ò.í. ''çàëîæíûõ ïîêîéíèêîâ'', áûâøèõ ïðè æèçíè ÷åðíûìè ìàãàìè-ìàëåôèêàðàìè. Ñ÷èòàëîñü, ÷òî äóøà ''çàëîæíîãî'' ïîêîéíèêà íå ìîæåò ïåðåéòè â çàãðîáíûé ìèð, è ïîýòîìó ''áëóäèò'' ïî çåìëå. Îäíàêî, åñëè ó áîëüøèíñòâà íàðîäîâ ñêëåïû ñ ïîõîðîíåííûìè ÷åðíûìè êîëäóíàìè, ñ÷èòàëèñü ïðîêëÿòûìè ìåñòàìè, òî â ðåëèãèè Âóäó ýòî áûëè íàèáîëåå âûãîäíûå ìåñòà äëÿ òåìíûõ îáðÿäîâ, öåëü êîòîðûõ - íàâåäåíèå ïîð÷è è ñãëàçà íà íåäðóãà.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VOODOO_TEMPLE</Tag>
		<English>Loa-Hwe</English>
		<Russian>Õèæèíà êîëäóíà</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VOODOO_TEMPLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In Civilization IV, a temple is defined as a building where the faithful come to worship. Christians call their temples "churches," while Muslims call theirs "mosques," and Jews call theirs, simply, "temples." Temples are far more common than cathedrals, but much less large and ornate. Even the smallest village can possess a temple.</English>
		<French>Dans Civilization IV, un petit lieu de culte est défini comme un édifice dans lequel les fidèles viennent pratiquer leur religion: "églises" pour les chrétiens, "petites mosquées" pour les musulmans et "petites synagogues" pour les juifs. Ces petits lieux de culte sont bien plus courants que les grands lieux de culte mais sont de taille plus réduite et sont bien moins richement ornés. Même le village le plus petit peut posséder un petit lieu de culte.</French>
		<German>In Civilization IV sind Tempel Gebäude, in denen Gläubige beten. Christen nennen ihre Tempel "Kirchen", Moslems "Moscheen". Es gibt deutlich mehr Tempel als Kathedralen. Allerdings sind sie wesentlich kleiner und schlichter. Selbst das kleinste Dorf kann einen Tempel besitzen.</German>
		<Italian>In Civilization IV, il tempio è un edificio all'interno del quale i fedeli si recano a pregare. I Cristiani chiamano i loro templi "chiese", i Musulmani "moschee", gli Ebrei semplicemente "templi". I templi sono più comuni delle cattedrali, ma sono più piccoli e poco fastosi. Anche il villaggio più piccolo ospita un tempio.</Italian>
		<Spanish>En Civilization IV, un templo se define como un lugar al que los fieles acuden a venerar. Los cristianos llaman a sus templos "iglesias", mientras que para los musulmanes son "mezquitas" y para los judíos, sencillamente, "templos". Son mucho más comunes que las catedrales, pero también mucho más pequeños y humildes. Hasta la más pequeña aldea puede poseer uno.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Swiątynia - miejsce kultu religijnego. W sensie szerszym, jest to każda budowla wzniesiona w celu sprawowania w niej wszelkiego rodzaju obrzędów religijnych. W sensie węższym, świątynią może być tylko taka budowla, która spełnia przynajmniej niektóre wyższe funkcje kultowe (np. składanie ofiar), sprawowane jedynie przez kapłanów.</Polish>
		<Russian>Â Öèâèëèçàöèè IV, ïîä õðàìîì ïîäðàçóìåâàåòñÿ çäàíèå, êóäà âåðóþùèå ïðèõîäÿò ñîâåðøàòü áîãîñëóæåíèå. Õðèñòèàíå íàçûâàþò ñâîè õðàìû ''öåðêâÿìè'', òîãäà êàê ìóñóëüìàíå íàçûâàþò èõ ''ìå÷åòÿìè'', à åâðåè íàçûâàþò èõ, ïðîñòî, ''õðàìàìè.'' Õðàìû íàìíîãî áîëüøå ðàñïðîñòðàíåíû, ÷åì ñîáîðû, íî îñòàþòñÿ ãîðàçäî ìåíåå êðóïíûìè è ñêðîìíûìè óáðàíñòâîì. Õðàì ìîæåò ðàñïîëàãàòüñÿ äàæå â ñàìîé çàõóäàëîé äåðåâóøêå.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_VOODOO</Tag>
		<English>Voodoo</English>
		<French>Vaudou</French>
		<Russian>Âóäó</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_VOODOO_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Voodoo</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Vaudou</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Voodoo</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter:Neuter:Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Voodoo:Voodoo:Voodoo:Voodoo</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Voodoo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian>Âóäó</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_VOODOO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>RELIGION HELP: Voodoo doesn't work as usual religions does, it has a particularity. The only way to spread it is using shamans, as Voodoo doesn't spread by itself Vodun is a traditional Polytheistic organised religion of coastal West Africa, from Nigeria to Ghana. It is distinct from the unorganised traditional animistic religions in the interiors of these same countries, as well as from various religions with often similar names of the African Diaspora in the New World, such as Haitian Vodou, the similar Vudu of the Dominican Republic, Candomblé Jejé in Brazil (which uses the term Vodum), Louisiana Voodoo, and Santería in Cuba, which are syncretized with Christianity and the traditional religions of the Kongo people of Congo and Angola. The word vodún is the Gbe (Fon-Ewe) word for spirit. When the word is capitalized, Vodun, it denotes the religion. When it is not, vodun, it denotes the spirits that are central to the religion. "Voodoo" is the most common pronunciation amongst English speakers. Vodun is practised by the Ewe, Kabye, Mina, Fon, and (under a different name) the Yoruba peoples of southeastern Ghana, southern and central Togo, southern and central Benin, and southwestern Nigeria.</English>
		<Italian>ATTENZIONE: Il voodoo non funziona come le altre religioni, ha una particolarità. L'unico modo per diffonderla è usando gli sciamani, dato che il Voodoo non si diffonde da solo. Vodun è una religione tradizionale e organizzata Politeista della costa occidentale dell'Africa, dalla Nigeria al Ghana. Si distingue dalle altre religioni tradizionali animiste presenti in questi stessi paesi, così come da altre religioni con nomi simili derivate dalla diaspora africana nel Nuovo Mondo, come il vudù haitiano, l'analogo Vudu della Repubblica Dominicana, Candomblé jeje in Brasile (che utilizza il termine Vodum), Voodoo in Louisiana e Santeria a Cuba, che sono sincretizzate con il cristianesimo e le religioni tradizionali del popolo congolese in Congo e Angola. La parola Vodun è la parola Gbe (Fon-Ewe) che indica lo spirito. Quando la parola è maiuscola, Vodun, denota la religione. Quando non lo è, Vodun, denota gli spiriti che sono al centro della religione. "Voodoo" è la pronuncia più comune tra gli anglofoni. Vodun è praticato dai Ewe, Kabyé, Mina, Fon e (con un nome diverso) dal popolo Yoruba del sud-est del Ghana, del Togo meridionale e centrale, del Benin meridionale e centrale, del sud-ovest della Nigeria.</Italian>
		<Polish>Voodoo a. wudu (inne formy Vodun (Benin); również Vodoun (kreolski), Sevi Lwa) jest synkretyczną religią afroamerykańską wyznawaną głównie w Haiti i na południu USA. Podstawę voodoo stanowią rdzenne wierzenia ludów zachodnioafrykańskich (szczególnie Joruba, Kongo, Fulanie) wraz z elementami religii katolickiej i spirytyzmu. Wykrystalizowała się ona na Haiti wraz ze sprowadzeniem w XVII/XVIII w. niewolników z Afryki, którym próbowano narzucać katolicyzm. Niewolnicy nie odrzucili swoich rdzennych wierzeń łącząc je z nową religią. W voodoo istnieje wprawdzie wiara w Bon Dieu (jednego Boga), nie oddaje mu się jednak czci (koncepcja deus otiosus). Istotny jest za to kult wielu miejscowych i afrykańskich loa (duchów/bogów), uważanych za tożsame z katolickimi świętymi. Te, które pochodzą z Afryki, nazywane są Rada Loa (z Dahomeju) lub Wangol Loa (z Angoli); te zaś, które objawiły się na Haiti, nazywane są Petro Loa. Słowo "voodoo" wywodzi się z języka plemienia Fulanów i oznacza duch. Wyznawcy voodoo uprawiają także kult przodków oraz czynnie włączają do swego panteonu ludzi zasłużonych dla narodu lub lokalnej społeczności.</Polish>
		<Russian>Вуду (англ. Voodoo) - традиционная африканская религия, имеющая статус государственной на территории некоторых стран, расположенных в Западной Африке. Например, вуду практикуется населением эва живущим на юге и востоке Ганы и в южной и центральной части Того, кабье, мина и фон южного и центрального Того, Бенина и (под другим наименованием) йоруба в юго-западной части Нигерии. Вуду представляет собой конгломерат из всевозможных анимистических культов, который включает в себя традиционные верования африканской (негритянской) диаспоры в Новом свете, как, например, гаитянская вуду (англ. Voodoo, Vodun, Vodoun, кандомбле в Бразилии, винти в Суринаме, луизианская (новоорлеанская) вуду и сантерия на Кубе и в Доминиканской республике. Все эти направления имеют синкретическую природу, соединяя с христианством африканские традиционные религии, зародившиеся в среде народа конго на территории современных Республики Конго, Демократической республики Конго и Анголы.[NEWLINE]Религиозные практики, присущие вуду:[PARAGRAPH:2]От зла спасают очистительные жертвоприношения и талисманы. Наиболее известной разновидностью вудуистских талисманов являются мешочки с различными предметами, называемые гри-гри;[PARAGRAPH:1]Музыка и танцы - ключевая часть ритуалов вуду;[PARAGRAPH:1]В качестве святилища вудуисты выбирают обычное жилище (хунфор - святилище). Основные атрибуты: митан (столб - дорога богов) и черные свечи. Пятеро барабанщиков, выстукивая четкий ритм, причем каждый свой, возвещают об открытии церемонии. После чего поется песня-прошение, обращенная к лоа (искаженное французское «loi») Легбе: «Папа Легба, отвори ворота. Папа Легба, отвори ворота и дай мне пройти. Отвори ворота, чтобы я смог возблагодарить лоа»;[PARAGRAPH:1]Танцуя вокруг столба-шеста, мамбо (колдунья), вместе со своей помощницей унси и помощником ла пласом, струйкой воды из кувшина создают вокруг шеста магический круг в честь Папы Легба и охранителя дома Огу Фера (Ogou Fer), дабы отогнать от себя и присутствующих злых духов. Хунган или мамбо посыпает пол мукой и чертит веве (символы лоа). Затем обязательна экстатическая пляска под звук барабанов - женщины в белых платьях и мужчины в костюмах. Когда публика достаточно разогрелась, бокор пускает петуха, которому отрубают голову. После этого участники сантерии (церемонии) впадают в транс и на них нисходит благодать духов (лоа);[PARAGRAPH:1]Непристойные танцы и выходки с сексуальным подтекстом во время праздника Fete de Gede сообщают лоа о том, что люди готовы с ними встретиться.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_VOODOO_QUOTE</Tag>
		<English>"Asaka, build me a garden[NEWLINE]Please Agwe, don't flood my garden.[NEWLINE]Erzulie, who will my love be.[NEWLINE]Papa Ge, don't come around me."[NEWLINE]- from the musical, "Once on This Island", lyrics by Lynn Ahrens</English>
		<Spanish>"Asaka, constrúyeme un jardín[NEWLINE]Por favor Agwe, no inundes mi jardín.[NEWLINE]Erzulie, quién será mi amor.[NEWLINE]Papa Ge, no vengas a mi alrededor."[NEWLINE]- del musical "Once on This Island", letra por Lynn Ahrens</Spanish>
		<Polish>"Asaka, zbuduj mi ogród, Agwe proszę, nie sprowadzaj powodzi na mój ogród, Erzulie, kto będzie moją miłością, Papa Ge, nie zbliżaj się do mnie." - Lynn Ahrens, z musicalu "Once on This Island"</Polish>
		<Russian>«Асака, устрой мне сад[NEWLINE]Молю тебя, Агве, не затопляй мой сад.[NEWLINE]Эрзули, моя грядущая любовь.[NEWLINE]Папаша Ге, не подходи ко мне».[NEWLINE] - от мюзикл "Однажды на этом острове", слова Линн Аренс</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HELLSMOUTH_DOG</Tag>
		<English>Hell's Mouth Dog</English>
		<French>Chien Gueule de l'enfer</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cane dell'Inferno</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pies z Bram Piekieł</Polish>
		<Russian>Àäñêàÿ ïàñòü</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HELLSMOUTH_DOG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Mad dogs coming directly from the hell's mouth. At least, according to skeptics, that is what their owners would have you believe.</English>
		<Italian>Un cane impazzito che proviene direttamente dalla bocca dell'inferno; o secondo gli scettici, questo è ciò che i loro possessori vogliono far credere.</Italian>
		<Polish>Wściekłe psy hodowane przez świątynie Voodoo.</Polish>
		<Russian>ßðîñòíûå áåñòèè, ïðèõîäÿùèå íåïîñðåäñòâåííî èç ãëóáèí àäà. Ïî êðàéíåé ìåðå, ïî ñëîâàì ñêåïòèêîâ, èõ õîçÿåâà õîòåëè áû çàñòàâèòü âàñ ïîâåðèòü â ðåàëüíîñòü ïîäîáíûõ ìîíñòðîâ.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_UNDEAD_WORKER</Tag>
		<English>Entranced Worker</English>
		<French>Ouvrier en trance</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Lavoratore in trance</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Robotnik-Zombie</Polish>
		<Russian>Çîìáè</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_VOODOO_MISSIONARY</Tag>
		<English>Houngan</English>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Houngan</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Russian>Âóä. æðåö</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_VOODOO_MISSIONARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Houngan is the term for a male priest in Haitian Vodou (a female priest is known as a mambo). The term is derived from the Fon word "hùn gan". There are two ranks of houngan: houngan asogwe (high priest) and houngan sur pwen (junior priest). A houngan asogwe is the highest member of clergy in voodoo and the only one with authority to ordain other priests. It is the houngan's role to preserve the rituals and songs and maintain the relationship between the spirits and the community as a whole (though some of this is the responsibility of the whole community as well). They are entrusted with leading the service of all of the spirits of their lineage. Sometimes they may also be bokor (sorcerers).</English>
		<Polish>Houngan to wielki kapłan w religii voodoo na Haiti (jego żeńskim odpowiednikiem jest mambo). Hounganie są kapłanami najwyższej rangi, prowadzą rytuały wywoływania duchów (loa) lub duchów własnych zmarłych przodków. Ich obowiązkiem jest podtrzymywanie stałej więzi między zmarłymi i żyjącymi wyznawcami voodoo. Czuwają nad zachowaniem tradycji i czystości kultu.</Polish>
		<Russian>Õóíãàí (ñâÿùåííèê) è ìàìáî (æåíùèíà-ñâÿùåííèê) - ñîáñòâåííî æðåöû ãàèòÿíñêîé ðàçíîâèäíîñòè âóäó, äåÿòåëüíîñòü êîòîðûõ îðèåíòèðîâàíà íà ïîëó÷åíèå ïðåäñêàçàíèé îò äóõîâ âî âðåìÿ îäåðæèìîñòè. Îíè ïðèíöèïèàëüíî îòëè÷àþòñÿ îò áîêîðîâ - êîëäóíîâ, ïðîôåññèîíàëüíî çàíèìàþùèõñÿ ìàãè÷åñêîé äåÿòåëüíîñòüþ. Áîêîðû ÷àñòî ïîíèìàþòñÿ êàê ëþäè, ïðàêòèêóþùèå ''÷åðíóþ ìàãèþ'' è íå âñåãäà ïðèçíàþòñÿ õóíãàíàìè è ìàìáî â êà÷åñòâå àäåïòîâ âóäó.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>