<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NEFERTITI_1</Tag>
		<English>I am [OUR_NAME] of the great and glorious [OUR_EMPIRE]! Let us sit in peace with one another.</English>
		<French>Je suis [OUR_NAME] du grand et glorieux [OUR_EMPIRE]! Asseyons-nous en paix les uns avec les autres.</French>
		<Polish>Jestem [OUR_NAME], z wielkiego i wspaniałego [OUR_EMPIRE]! Usiądźmy w pokoju i porozmawiajmy.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_NEFERTITI</Tag>
		<English>Nefertiti</English>
		<French>Néfertiti</French>
		<Polish>Nefretete</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_NEFERTITI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Nefertiti[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Great Royal Wife of Akhenatent[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates: [\BOLD]  BC c. 1370 - c. 1330[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Nefertiti was the Great Royal Wife (chief consort) of the Egyptian Pharaoh Akhenaten. Nefertiti and her husband were known for changing Egypt's religion from a polytheistic religion to a henotheistic religion. They revered only one god, Aten, the sun disc. This was not strictly monotheism, as they did not deny the existence of other gods. She had many titles; for example, at Karnak there are inscriptions that read Heiress, Great of Favours, Possessed of Charm, Exuding Happiness, Mistress of Sweetness, beloved one, soothing the king's heart in his house, soft-spoken in all, Mistress of Upper and Lower Egypt, Great King's Wife, whom he loves, Lady of the Two Lands, Nefertiti'.[PARAGRAPH:1]She was made famous by her bust, now in Berlin's Altes Museum, shown to the right. The bust is one of the most copied works of ancient Egypt. It was attributed to the sculptor Thutmose, and it was thought to have been found in his workshop. The bust itself is notable for exemplifying the understanding Ancient Egyptians had regarding realistic facial proportions. Recently, it has been suggested by Swiss art historian Henri Stierlin that the bust is a copy dating from 1912.[PARAGRAPH:1]Some scholars believe that Nefertiti ruled briefly after her husband's death and before the accession of Tutankhamun as Smenkhkare, although this identification is a matter of ongoing debate. During Akhenaten's reign (and perhaps after) Nefertiti enjoyed unprecedented power, and by the twelfth year of his reign, there is evidence that she may have been elevated to the status of co-regent: equal in status to the pharaoh himself. She was often depicted on temple walls the same size as the king, signifying her importance, and shown worshiping the Aten alone. Perhaps most impressively, Nefertiti is shown on a relief from the temple at Amarna which is now in the MFA in Boston, smiting a foreign enemy with a mace before the Aten. Such depictions had traditionally been reserved for the pharaoh alone, and yet Nefertiti was depicted as such.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Coregency Stela may show her as a co-regent with her husband, who possibly ruled after his death. It is thought by some scholars that Nefertiti changed her name, first to Ankhkheperure Neferneferuaten and later to Ankhkheperure Smenkhkare and that she enjoyed a brief sole rule under the latter name. it is also believed that, as her husband's co-regent and successor she might have attempted to reconcile the Atenist and Traditional religions Nefertiti would have prepared for her death and for the succession of her daughter, now named Ankhsenamun, and her stepson, Tutankhamun. They would have been educated in the traditional way, worshiping the old gods. This theory has Neferneferuaten dying after two years of kingship and was then succeeded by Tutankhamun, thought to have been a son of Akhenaten. He married Nefertiti's daughter Ankhesenpaaten. The royal couple were young and inexperienced, by any estimation of their age, and Ankhesenpaaten bore two stillborn (and premature) daughters whose mummies were found by Howard Carter in Tutankhamen's tomb. Some theories believe that Nefertiti was still alive and held influence on the younger royals.[PARAGRAPH:1]Nefertiti's place as an icon in popular culture is secure as she has become somewhat of a celebrity. After Cleopatra she is the second most famous "Queen" of Egypt in the Western imagination and influenced through photographs that changed standards of feminine beauty of the 20th century, and is often referred to as "the most beautiful woman in the world".</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Nefretete[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Wielka Żona Króla Akhenatent[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Daty: [\BOLD]  ok. 1370 - ok. 1330 p.n.e [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Żona faraona Echnatona z XVIII dynastii ( Amenhotep IV/Amenhatpa IV). Prawdopodobnie imię jej wymawiało się jako Nafteta. Pochodzenie Nefertiti nie jest do końca jasne. Przedstawia się teorię jakoby była księżniczką mitannijską - co tłumaczyłoby jej imię, utożsamia się ją też z Taduhepą. Często przyjmuje się także, iż była córką doradcy dworu Aj, który wstąpił na tron po śmierci Tutanchamona. Była ukochaną żoną Echnatona, z którym miała 6 córek: Meritaton, Maketaton, Anchesenpaaton, Neferneferuaton-Taszerit, Neferneferure i Setepenre. Prawdopodobnie została wyniesiona na tron jako współregent i przybrała imię Neferneferuaton ("Nadzwyczajna piękność Atona"). Jako jedyna królowa w historii Egiptu jest przedstawiana na nielicznych zachowanych płaskorzeźbach w pozach zarezerwowanych dla faraonów, np. zwyciężania lub upokarzania wrogów Egiptu. Była także macochą Tutanchamona, syna ze związku Echnatona i jego drugorzędnej żony Kiji. Stawiane są także hipotezy, że po śmierci swego męża objęła tron jako Anchcheperure Semenchkare.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
