<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KAMEHAMEHA_1</Tag>
		<English>Hello! Ask me what is the greatest thing in the world, I will reply: It is people, it is people, it is people!</English>
		<French>Hello! Me demande quelle est la plus grande chose dans le monde, je répondrai: C'est gens, les gens, les gens!</French>
		<German>Hallo! Frag mich bitte, was ist die größte Sache in der Welt, werde ich antworten: Es sind die Menschen, sind es die Menschen, sind es die Menschen!</German>
		<Italian>Saluti! Chiedimi qual è la cosa più grande del mondo, io risponderò: è la gente, è la gente, è la gente!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Hola! Me pregunta qué es lo más grande en el mundo, voy a responder: Es la gente, es la gente, es la gente</Spanish>
		<Polish>Witam! Spytaj się mnie co jest najważniejszą rzeczą na świecie, a ja odpowiem: To ludzie!, To ludzie!, To ludzie!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KAMEHAMEHA</Tag>
		<English>Kamehameha</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KAMEHAMEHA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Kamehameha the Great[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Hawaii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1758 - 1819[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Kamehameha's birth is surrounded by legend, and it is said that the Hawaiians claimed that a great king would one day unite the islands, and a comet would be the sign of his birth. When Kamehameha was born, Halley's Comet was visible in Hawaii. Kamehameha's birth name was Pai'ea, and he was born to Keku'iapoiwa, chief of the Kohala on the island of Hawai'i, and to Keoua. Keoua, his father, was the son of Keaweikekahiali'iokamoku, who was the chief of a large portion of Hawai'i. However, after his reign a war over succession broke, and Alapa'i emerged victorious over his brothers and their sons, including Keoua. When Kamehameha was born, Alapa'i ordered that he be killed, and was nervous at the thought that the child might eventually rule over Hawai'i. So, Kamehameha was given to another noble, Nae'ole, and thus disappeared from sight. Alapa'i, in remorse for his actions, invited the child to live in the royal court. [PARAGRAPH: 1] When Alapa'i died, he was succeeded by his son Keawea'opala who was challenged by Kalani'opu'u, Alapa'i's great nephew, and was backed by Kamehameha. At a battle at Kealakekua Bay, Keawea'opala was victorious and made Kamehameha his aid. In 1779, on a trip with Kalani'opu'u to Kealakekua Bay, Kamehameha met Captain Cook. Cook was mistaken to be the Hawaiian god of fertility, Lono, and Kamehameha may have been onboard his ship for some time. After Kalani'opu'u's death, kingship was inherited by his son Kiwala'o. Kamehameha was still given a prominent position, but there was a conflict between the two cousins. When a group of chiefs offered Kamehameha the kingship instead of Kiwala'o, he accepted and later defeated Kiwala'o at the Battle of Moku'ohai. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In 1790, Kamehameha deposed the chief of the district of Puna, Keawema'uhili. At the same time Keoua, exiled to his home, led an uprising. However, a third of his warriors were killed when he fled from the returning Kamehameha past a volcano. Kamehameha built a temple to sacrifice Keoua later, so that Kamehameha became the chief of all of Hawai'i. Kamehameha had other ambitions, and sought the help from British and American traders, who sold guns and ammunition to Kamehameha. When Kamehameha invaded the weakened islands of Maui and O'ahu, he did not think that his rival, Kalanikupule, also possessed firearms. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In 1795, Kamehameha set sail with an astonishing 1,200 war canoes and 10,000 soldiers. He quickly captured the islands of Maui and Moloka'i, and then moved on to O'ahu. However, one of Kamehameha's best commanders defected to Kalanikupule. In a series of skirmishes, Kamehameha and his army pushed back Kalanukupule until he was trapped. After Kamehameha's troops faced heavy cannon fire advancing to Kalanikupule, he sent his best warriors to attack the cannons from behind, which proved to be successful. Thus, Kalanikupule's troops fell into disarray and were defeated, with Kalanikupule being sacrificed later. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha was now the complete ruler of all of Hawai'i east of O'ahu, but the islands of Kaua'i and Ni'ihau were continuously escaping him. Kamehameha's first invasion was unsuccessful, and his second resulted in disease. After being intimidated by Kamehameha's new strong army, Kaumali'i, chief of Kaua'i, agreed to become a vassal of Kamehameha. As the first king of Hawai’i, Kamehameha made several steps to make certain that the islands remained united after his death. He unified the legal system and didn't allow non-Hawaiians to own land. This proclamation guaranteed the islands' independence while other islands in the Pacific gave in to colonial authority. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha also instituted the Mamalohoe Kanawi, the Law of the Splintered Paddle. This law had origins in Kamehameha's early battles. The Law provided the safety of noncombatants during wartime, and remains in Hawaii's state constitution today, being its first law. When Kamehameha died in 1819, his body was trusted to his friend, Haopili. To this day, his resting place remains unknown.</English>
		<French>[H1]Kamehameha le Grand[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi de Hawaii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates: [\BOLD]1758 - 1819[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Kamehameha la naissance est entourée de légende, et il est dit que les Hawaïens affirmé qu'un grand roi serait un jour unir les îles, et une comète serait le signe de sa naissance. Quand Kamehameha est né, la comète de Halley était visible à Hawaii. Kamehameha le nom de naissance était Pai'ea, et il est né à Keku'iapoiwa, chef de la Kohala sur l'île de Hawaii, et à Keoua. Keoua, son père, était le fils de Keaweikekahiali'iokamoku, qui était le chef d'une grande partie de Hawai'i. Cependant, après son règne sur une guerre de succession a éclaté, et Alapa'i sorti vainqueur de ses frères et leurs fils, dont Keoua. Quand naquit Kamehameha, Alapa'i ordonné qu'il soit tué, mais était nerveux à l'idée que l'enfant pourrait finalement régner sur Hawai'i. Donc, Kamehameha a été donnée à un autre nobles, Nae'ole, et donc perdue de vue. Alapa'i, dans le remords de ses actes, a invité les enfants à vivre dans la cour royale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Quand Alapa'i est mort, il a été remplacé par son fils Keawea'opala qui a été contestée par Kalani'opu'u, Alapa'i grand neveu, et a été appuyée par le Kamehameha. Lors d'une bataille à Kealakekua Bay, Keawea'opala a été victorieuse et fait Kamehameha son aide. En 1779, lors d'un voyage avec Kalani'opu'u à Kealakekua Bay, Kamehameha rencontré Captain Cook. Cook s'est trompé à l'hawaiien dieu de la fertilité, Lono, et Kamehameha peut avoir été à bord de son navire pendant un certain temps. Après Kalani'opu'u la mort, la royauté a été hérité par son fils Kiwala'o. Kamehameha était toujours donné une place importante, mais il y avait un conflit entre les deux cousins. Quand un groupe de chefs offert Kamehameha la royauté au lieu de Kiwala'o, il a accepté, puis battu Kiwala'o lors de la bataille de Moku'ohai. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En 1790, Kamehameha destitué le chef du district de Puna, Keawema'uhili. Dans le même temps Keoua, exilé à son domicile, a conduit un soulèvement. Cependant, un tiers de ses guerriers ont été tués quand il a fui le revenant Kamehameha passé d'un volcan. Kamehameha construit un temple à sacrifier Keoua plus tard, afin que Kamehameha est devenu le chef de l'ensemble de Hawai'i. Kamehameha avait d'autres ambitions, et a sollicité l'aide de la part des commerçants britanniques et américains, qui a vendu des fusils et des munitions à Kamehameha. Quand Kamehameha envahi les îles de Maui affaibli et O'ahu, il ne pensait pas que son rival, Kalanikupule, possédaient aussi des armes à feu. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En 1795, Kamehameha embarqua avec une étonnante 1200 guerre canots et 10000 soldats. Il a rapidement capturé les îles de Maui et Moloka'i, ensuite dirigé vers O'ahu. Toutefois, l'un des meilleurs commandants Kamehameha défection à Kalanikupule. Dans une série d'escarmouches, Kamehameha et son armée repoussé Kalanukupule jusqu'à ce qu'il ait été pris au piège. Ainsi, Kalanikupule troupes tombé dans le désarroi et l'ont battu, avec Kalanikupule sacrifié plus tard. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha était désormais la règle complète de l'ensemble des Hawai'i est du O'ahu, mais les îles de Kaua'i et Ni'ihau étaient continuellement lui échapper. Kamehameha la première invasion a échoué, et sa seconde conduit à la maladie. Après avoir été intimidés par Kamehameha la nouvelle armée forte, Kaumali'i, chef de Kaua'i, a accepté de devenir un vassal de Kamehameha. Comme le premier roi d'Hawai'i, Kamehameha fait plusieurs mesures pour s'assurer que les îles restent unies après sa mort. Il a unifié le système juridique et ne permet pas non Hawaïens de posséder des terres. Cette annonce garantit les îles' indépendance, alors que d'autres îles dans le Pacifique a donné à l'autorité coloniale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha également institué des Mamalohoe Kanawi, le droit de la Splintered Paddle. Cette loi a Kamehameha origines dans le début des combats. La loi prévoit la sécurité des non-combattants en temps de guerre, et reste à Hawaii's Constitution de l'Etat aujourd'hui, étant sa première loi. Quand Kamehameha est mort en 1819, son corps a été digne de confiance à son ami, Haopili. à ce jour, son lieu de repos ne reste inconnu.</French>
		<German>[H1]Kamehameha der Große[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]König von Hawaii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte: [\BOLD]1758 - 18190[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Kamehameha Geburt ist umgeben von Legenden, und es wird gesagt, dass die Hawaiianer behauptet, dass ein großer König eines Tages vereinen die Inseln, und einem Kometen wäre das Zeichen seiner Geburt. Wenn Kamehameha wurde geboren, Halley's Comet wurde in Hawaii. Kamehameha Geburt war Pai'ea, und er war geboren zu Keku'iapoiwa, Chef der Kohala auf der Insel Hawaii, und Keoua. Keoua, sein Vater, der Sohn des Keaweikekahiali'iokamoku, der als Chef eines großen Teils von Hawaii. Aber nach seiner Herrschaft ein Krieg über Nachfolge brach, und Alapa'i den Sieg über seinen Brüdern und ihren Söhnen, einschließlich Keoua. Wenn Kamehameha wurde geboren, Alapa'i ordneten an, dass er getötet werden, wurde aber nervös bei dem Gedanken, dass das Kind vielleicht auch Herrschaft über Hawaii. Also, Kamehameha wurde auf einen anderen edlen, Nae'ole, und so verschwand aus dem Blick. Alapa'i, in der Reue für seine Taten, forderte das Kind auf ein Leben in der königlichen Gericht. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Wenn Alapa'i starb, wurde er Nachfolger seines Sohnes Keawea'opala, wurde von Kalani'opu'u, Alapa'i große Neffe, und wurde von Kamehameha. Bei der Schlacht bei Kealakekua Bay, Keawea'opala war siegreich und machte Kamehameha seine Hilfe. In 1779, auf einer Reise mit Kalani'opu'u zu Kealakekua Bay, Kamehameha traf Captain Cook. Cook war irre zu werden, die hawaiianische Gott der Fruchtbarkeit, Lono und Kamehameha Mai wurden an Bord seines Schiffes für einige Zeit. Nach Kalani'opu'u Tod, Königtum wurde geerbt von seinem Sohn Kiwala'o. Kamehameha war immer noch eine herausragende Stellung, aber es war ein Konflikt zwischen den beiden Vettern. Wenn eine Gruppe von Chefs angeboten Kamehameha das Königtum statt Kiwala'o, er akzeptiert, und später besiegt Kiwala'o in der Schlacht von Moku'ohai. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In 1790, Kamehameha abgesetzt, der Chef des Bezirks Puna, Keawema'uhili. Gleichzeitig Keoua, ins Exil zu seinem Haus, führte ein Aufstand. Aber ein Drittel seiner Krieger getötet wurden, wenn er floh aus der Vergangenheit zurückkehren Kamehameha ein Vulkan. Kamehameha ein Tempel zu opfern Keoua später, so dass Kamehameha wurde der Chef der von Hawaii. Kamehameha hatte andere Ambitionen, und suchte die Hilfe von britischen und amerikanischen Händlern, die verkauft Waffen und Munition zu Kamehameha. Wenn Kamehameha Invasion der Schwächung der Inseln Maui und O'ahu er nicht der Meinung, dass seine Rivalen, Kalanikupule, auch Schusswaffen besaß. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In 1795, Kamehameha die Segel mit einem erstaunlichen 1200 Krieg Kanus und 10000 Soldaten. Er eroberte schnell die Inseln Maui und Moloka'i, und wechselte dann auf O'ahu. Aber, einer der besten Kommandeure Kamehameha abtrünnig zu Kalanikupule. In einer Reihe von Scharmützeln, Kamehameha und seine Armee nach hinten Kalanukupule, bis er gefangen war. Nach Kamehameha's Truppen vor schweren Kanone Feuer voran zu Kalanikupule, schickte er seine besten Krieger zum Angriff gegen die Kanonen von hinten, die sich als erfolgreich. So Kalanikupule Truppen fiel in Unordnung und wurden besiegt, mit Kalanikupule geopfert später. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha wurde nun die vollständige Herrscher aller Hawaii östlich von O'ahu, aber die Inseln Kaua'i und Ni'ihau wurden kontinuierlich ihm zu entkommen. Kamehameha der ersten Invasion war nicht erfolgreich, und seine zweite führte in der Krankheit. Nach der eingeschüchtert von Kamehameha's neues starken Armee, Kaumali'i, Chef von Kaua'i, stimmte zu einem Vasallenstaat von Kamehameha. Da der erste König von Hawaii, Kamehameha mehrere Schritte, um sicherzustellen, dass die Inseln blieb vereint nach seinem Tod. Er vereinheitlichte das Rechtssystem und nicht erlauben nicht zu Hawaiianer eigenen Land. Diese Proklamation garantiert den Inseln die Unabhängigkeit, während die anderen Inseln im Pazifik hat in der Kolonialzeit Behörde. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha Darüber hinaus wurde die Mamalohoe Kanawi, das Recht der Splintered Rudern. Dieses Gesetz hatte Kamehameha Ursprung in der frühen Schlachten. Das Gesetz, die die Sicherheit der noncombatants in Kriegszeiten, und bleibt auf Hawaii die staatliche Verfassung heute, die ihre erste Gesetz. Wenn Kamehameha starb 1819, sein Körper war vertrauter zu seinem Freund, Haopili. Zu diesem Tag, seine Ruhestätte bleibt unbekannt.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Kamehameha il Grande[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Hawaii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita: [\BOLD]1758 - 1819[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Kamehameha la nascita è circondato da leggenda, e si dice che il hawaiani sosteneva che un grande re sarebbe un giorno unire le isole, e una cometa sarebbe il segno della sua nascita. Kamehameha quando è nato, la cometa di Halley era visibile nelle Hawaii. Kamehameha la nascita nome era Pai'ea, ed egli è nato per Keku'iapoiwa, capo della Kohala sull'isola di Hawaii, e di Keoua. Keoua, suo padre, è stato il figlio di Keaweikekahiali'iokamoku, che era il capo di una grossa porzione di Hawai'i. Tuttavia, dopo il suo regno su una guerra di successione rotto, e Alapa'i uscito vittorioso oltre i suoi fratelli e dei loro figli, tra cui Keoua. Quando è nato Kamehameha, Alapa'i ordinato che egli essere ucciso, ma è stato nervoso al pensiero che il bambino potrebbe eventualmente dominerà Hawai'i. Così, Kamehameha è stato assegnato a un altro nobile, Nae'ole e, quindi, è scomparso dalla vista. Alapa'i, nel rimorso per le sue azioni, ha invitato il bambino a vivere in corte reale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Quando Alapa'i morto, è stato succeduto da suo figlio Keawea'opala che è stato contestato da Kalani'opu'u, Alapa'i grande nipote, ed è stato sostenuto da Kamehameha. Nel corso di una battaglia a Kealakekua Bay, Keawea'opala è stato vittorioso e reso Kamehameha suo aiuto. Nel 1779, su un viaggio con Kalani'opu'u a Kealakekua Bay, Kamehameha incontrato il capitano Cook. Cook, è stato scambiato per il dio della fertilità hawaiano, Lono, Kamehameha e può essere stato per la sua nave a bordo di un po 'di tempo. Dopo Kalani'opu'u la morte, regalità è stata ereditata dal figlio Kiwala'o. Kamehameha è stato ancora dato un posto di rilievo, ma non vi è stato un conflitto tra i due cugini. Quando un gruppo di capi offerti Kamehameha la regalità invece di Kiwala'o, ha accettato e poi sconfitto Kiwala'o nella battaglia di Moku'ohai. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nel 1790, Kamehameha deposto il capo del distretto di Puna, Keawema'uhili. Allo stesso tempo Keoua, in esilio a casa sua, ha condotto una rivolta. Tuttavia, un terzo dei suoi guerrieri sono stati uccisi quando fuggì dal ritorno Kamehameha passato un vulcano. Kamehameha costruito un tempio a sacrificare Keoua più tardi, in modo che Kamehameha divenne il capo di tutte le Hawaii. Kamehameha aveva altre ambizioni, e ha chiesto l'aiuto dei commercianti britannici e americani, che hanno venduto armi e munizioni a Kamehameha. Quando Kamehameha invaso il indebolito isole di Maui e O'ahu, egli non pensa che il suo rivale, Kalanikupule, possedeva armi da fuoco. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nel 1795, Kamehameha salpare con un sorprendente 1200 guerra canoe e 10000 soldati. Egli ha rapidamente catturato le isole di Maui e Moloka'i, e poi passati alla O'ahu. Tuttavia, uno dei migliori comandanti Kamehameha disertavano a Kalanikupule. In una serie di scaramucce, e il suo esercito Kamehameha spinto indietro Kalanukupule fino a che non è stata intrappolata. Dopo Kamehameha le truppe di fronte pesante cannone fuoco avanzando a Kalanikupule, che ha inviato le sue migliori guerrieri di attaccare i cannoni da dietro, che si è rivelato efficace. Così, Kalanikupule truppe cadde in caos e sono stati respinti, con Kalanikupule essere sacrificati dopo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha era ormai completo principe di tutti Hawai'i est di O'ahu, ma le isole di Kaua'i e Ni'ihau sono stati continuamente in fuga lui. Kamehameha la prima invasione è stata infruttuosa, e il suo secondo risultato malattia. Dopo essere stato intimidito da Kamehameha c'è di nuovo forte esercito, Kaumali'i, capo della Kaua'i, ha accettato di diventare un vassallo di Kamehameha. Come il primo re di Hawai'i, Kamehameha compiuti diversi passi per rendere certo che le isole sono rimasti uniti dopo la sua morte. Egli ha unificato il sistema giuridico e non ha consentito non hawaiani al possesso della terra. Questo annuncio garantite le isole 'indipendenza, mentre le altre isole del Pacifico ha dato al potere coloniale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha anche istituito il Mamalohoe Kanawi, il diritto del Splintered Paddle. Questa legge ha avuto origine nel Kamehameha's prime battaglie. La legge prevedeva la sicurezza dei noncombatants durante il tempo di guerra, e resta in Hawaii costituzione dello stato di oggi, essendo la sua prima legge. Quando Kamehameha morì nel 1819, il suo corpo è stato confidato al suo amico, Haopili. Per questo giorno, il suo luogo di riposo rimane sconosciuto.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Kamehameha El Grande[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Hawái[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivió: [\BOLD]1758 - 1819[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Kamehameha del nacimiento está rodeado de leyenda, y se dice que los hawaianos afirmó que un gran rey un día unir a las islas, y un cometa sería el signo de su nacimiento. Cuando nació Kamehameha, Cometa Halley fue visible en Hawaii. Kamehameha de nacimiento del nombre fue Pai'ea, y que nació a Keku'iapoiwa, jefe de la Kohala en la isla de Hawai, y para Keoua. Keoua, su padre, era hijo de Keaweikekahiali'iokamoku, que era el jefe de una gran parte de Hawai'i. Sin embargo, después de su reinado una guerra por la sucesión se rompió, y Alapa'i salido victorioso más de sus hermanos y sus hijos, incluyendo Keoua. Cuando nació Kamehameha, Alapa'i ordenó que se le mató, pero fue nervioso al pensar que el niño pueda llegar a la regla más de Hawai'i. Así, Kamehameha fue entregado a otra nobles, Nae'ole, y por lo tanto desapareció de la vista. Alapa'i, en el remordimiento por sus acciones, invitó a los niños a vivir en la corte real. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Cuando Alapa'i murió, fue sucedido por su hijo Keawea'opala que fue impugnado por Kalani'opu'u, Alapa'i del gran sobrino, y fue respaldado por Kamehameha. En una batalla en la bahía de Kealakekua, Keawea'opala fue victorioso e hizo Kamehameha su ayuda. En 1779, en un viaje con Kalani'opu'u a Kealakekua Bay, Kamehameha se reunió el capitán Cook. Cook se equivocaba al ser el Hawaiian dios de la fertilidad, Lono, y Kamehameha puede haber sido a bordo de su barco durante algún tiempo. Después de Kalani'opu'u de la muerte, la monarquía fue heredado por su hijo Kiwala'o. Kamehameha fue dado todavía una posición destacada, pero hay un conflicto entre los dos primos. Cuando un grupo de jefes ofrecido Kamehameha la monarquía en lugar de Kiwala'o, aceptó y más tarde derrotó Kiwala'o en la Batalla de Moku'ohai. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En 1790, Kamehameha depuesto el jefe del distrito de Puna, Keawema'uhili. Al mismo tiempo Keoua, exiliado a su casa, llevó un levantamiento. Sin embargo, un tercio de sus guerreros fueron muertos cuando huían de la repatriación de Kamehameha pasado de un volcán. Kamehameha construido un templo a sacrificar Keoua más tarde, de manera que Kamehameha se convirtió en el jefe de todos los de Hawai'i. Kamehameha tenía otras ambiciones, y solicitó la ayuda de los comerciantes británicos y americanos, que vendieron armas y municiones a Kamehameha. Cuando Kamehameha invadido el debilitamiento de las islas de Maui y O'ahu, no cree que su rival, Kalanikupule, también poseen armas de fuego. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En 1795, Kamehameha zarpó con un asombroso 1200 la guerra canoas y 10000 soldados. Rápidamente capturados en las islas de Maui y Moloka'i, y luego se trasladó a O'ahu. Sin embargo, uno de los mejores comandantes de Kamehameha desertado a Kalanikupule. En una serie de escaramuzas, y su ejército Kamehameha aplazado Kalanukupule hasta que fue atrapado. Después de las tropas de Kamehameha enfrentan pesados cañones fuego avanza a Kalanikupule, envió sus mejores guerreros para atacar por detrás de los cañones, lo que resultó ser un éxito. Así, Kalanikupule las tropas cayó en desorden y fueron derrotados, con Kalanikupule ser sacrificado más tarde. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha se completa ahora el gobernante de la totalidad de Hawai'i este de O'ahu, pero las islas de Kaua'i y Ni'ihau fueron continuamente escapar de él. Kamehameha la primera invasión no fue exitosa, y su segundo resultado en la enfermedad. Después de haber sido intimidado por Kamehameha del nuevo ejército fuerte, Kaumali'i, jefe de Kaua'i, de acuerdo a convertirse en vasallo de Kamehameha. Como el primer rey de Hawai, Kamehameha hecho varias medidas para asegurarse de que las islas permanecieron unidas después de su muerte. He unificado el sistema jurídico y no permitir que los hawaianos no a la posesión de tierras. Esta proclamación garantiza las islas' independencia mientras que en otras islas en el Pacífico dio a la autoridad colonial. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kamehameha también instituyó la Mamalohoe Kanawi, la Ley de la Splintered Paddle. Esta ley tuvo origen en las primeras batallas Kamehameha. La Ley siempre que la seguridad de los no combatientes en tiempos de guerra, y sigue siendo en Hawai la constitución del Estado de hoy, siendo su primera ley. Cuando Kamehameha murió en 1819, su cuerpo fue a su amigo de confianza, Haopili. Hasta el día de hoy, su tumba sigue siendo desconocido.</Spanish>
		<Polish>[H1]Kamehameha Wielki[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Król Hawajów[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył: [\BOLD]1758 - 1819[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Przywódca jednego z wielu królestw hawajskich, doprowadził do ich zjednoczenia w 1810 i został pierwszym królem Królestwa obejmującego cały archipelag. Założył dynastię panującą do 1874 roku (ostatnim władcą z tejże dynastii był Kamehameha V). Zakończył wojny domowe i wprowadził jednakowe prawo. Był inicjatorem handlu z Europą i USA. W uznaniu jego zasług, jeden z jego następców, Kamehameha V, ustanowił dzień króla Kamehameha I. Swięto to Hawajczycy obchodzą 11 czerwca każdego roku. Relację z ostatnich chwil życia i pogrzebu Kamehamehy I przytoczył Mark Twain w autobiograficznej powieści "Pod gołym niebem".</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
