<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_WILHELMINA_1</Tag>
		<English>I am honored to meet you, [CT_NAME]. I hope that our two nations will be able to live in peace and friendship.</English>
		<French>Je suis honoré de vous rencontrer, [CT_NAME]. J'espère que nos deux nations seront capables de vivre dans la paix et l'amitié.</French>
		<German>Es ist mir eine Ehre, [CT_NAME]. Ich hoffe, es wird Friede und Freundschaft zwischen unseren Völkern herrschen.</German>
		<Italian>È un onore incontrarti, [CT_NAME]. Spero che le nostre due nazioni riusciranno a vivere in pace e amicizia.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es un honor conoceros, [CT_NAME]. Espero que nuestras dos naciones sean capaces de vivir en paz y armonía.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jestem zaszczycona, że Cie spotkałam, [CT_NAME]. Mam nadzieję, że nasze kraje będą mogły współistnieć razem w pokoju i przyjąźni.</Polish>
		<Russian>Для меня большая честь познакомиться с вами, [CT_NAME]. Я надеюсь, что наши два народа смогут жить в мире и дружбе.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_WILHELMINA</Tag>
		<English>Wilhelmina</English>
		<Russian>Вильгельмина</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_WILHELMINA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Wilhelmina[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Queen of the Netherlands[NEWLINE]Lived:[\BOLD] August 31, 1890 - 30 April, 1962[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]She was the only child of King William III and his second wife, Emma of Waldeck and Pyrmont. Her childhood was characterised by a close relationship with her parents, especially with her father, who was already 63 years of age when she was born.[PARAGRAPH:1]Since King William already had three sons with his first wife, Queen Sophie, when Wilhelmina was born, there was little chance she would ascend the throne. However, William outlived all of his sons, the last of whom died when Wilhelmina was four.[PARAGRAPH:1]King William III died on November 23, 1890 and, although Princess Wilhelmina became Queen of the Netherlands instantly, her mother, Emma, was named Regent until her 18th birthday.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1901 she married Hendrik, Duke of Mecklenburg-Schwerin. Although the marriage was said to be essentially without love, initially Wilhelmina truly cared for Hendrik, and it is likely that those feelings were mutual. Hendrik however, suffered from his role as prince-consort, stating that it was boring to be nothing more than decoration, forced always to walk one step behind his wife. He had no power in the Netherlands, and Wilhelmina made sure this remained so.[PARAGRAPH:1]Although the Netherlands remained neutral during World War I, sizeable German investments in the Dutch economy combined with a large trading partnership in goods forced the United Kingdom to blockade the Dutch ports in an attempt to weaken the German Empire. The Dutch government traded with Germany in response. German soldiers were given Edam cheese for their rations before an assault. Wilhemina was a "soldier's queen"; being a woman, she could not be Supreme Commander, but she nevertheless used every opportunity she had to inspect her forces. On many occasions she appeared without prior notice, wishing to see the reality, not a prepared show. She loved her soldiers, but was very unhappy with most of her governments, which used the military as a constant source for budget-cutting. Wilhelmina wanted a small but well trained and equipped army. However, this was far from the reality. In the war, she felt she was a "Queen-On-Guard". She was always wary of a German attack, especially in the beginning. However, violation of Dutch territorial sovereignty came from both Britain and the United States, who, with the blockade, captured many Dutch trade and cargo ships in an attempt to disrupt the German war effort. This led to increased tensions between the Netherlands and the Allied forces.[PARAGRAPH:1]Civil unrest, spurred on by the Bolshevik revolt in Imperial Russia in 1917, gripped the Netherlands after the war. A socialist leader named Troelstra tried to overthrow the government and the Queen. Instead of a violent revolution, he wanted to control the Tweede Kamer, the legislative body of Parliament, and hoped to achieve this by means of elections, convinced that the working class would support him. However, the popularity of the young Queen helped restore confidence in the government. Wilhelmina brought about a mass show of support by riding with her daughter through the mobs in an open carriage. It was very clear that the revolution would not succeed.[PARAGRAPH:1]On 10 May 1940, Nazi Germany invaded the Netherlands, and Queen Wilhelmina and her family fled to the United Kingdom three days later. Queen Wilhelmina had wanted to stay in the Netherlands: she had planned to go to the southern province of Zeeland with her troops in order to coordinate further resistance from the town of Breskens and remain there until help arrived, much as King Albert I of Belgium had done during World War I. She went aboard a British cruiser at The Hague, which was to take her there. However, when she was on board the captain stated that he was forbidden to make contact with the Dutch shore, as Zeeland was under heavy attack from the Luftwaffe and it was too dangerous to return. Wilhelmina then took the decision to go to Britain, planning to return as soon as possible. Wilhelmina also spent time in Canada during the war, staying at the Governor General's residence, Rideau Hall. It was said that while she was there she made a great impact on the household, notably for living relatively simply. The Queen insisted on doing her shopping personally, walking the streets of Ottawa unassisted (though simply raising her hand to stop traffic whenever she wished to cross the road), and travelling to the United States on a regular civilian train.[PARAGRAPH:1]During the war her photograph was a sign of resistance against the Germans. Like Winston Churchill, Queen Wilhelmina broadcast messages to the Dutch people over Radio Oranje. As always, the Queen pulled no punches, calling Adolf Hitler "the arch-enemy of mankind". Her late-night broadcasts were eagerly awaited by her people, who had to hide in order to listen to them illegally. During the war, the Queen was almost killed by a bomb that took the lives of several of her guards and severely damaged her country home near South Mimms in England. In 1944 Queen Wilhelmina became only the second woman to be inducted into the Order of the Garter. Churchill described her as the only real man among the governments-in-exile in London.[PARAGRAPH:1]In England she developed ideas about a new political and social life for the Dutch after the liberation. She wanted a strong cabinet formed by people active in the resistance. She dismissed De Geer during the war and installed a prime minister with the approval of other Dutch politicians. The Queen "hated" politicians, instead stating a love for the people. When the Netherlands was liberated in 1945 she was disappointed to see the same political factions taking power as before the war.[PARAGRAPH:1]Following the end of World War II, Queen Wilhelmina made the decision not to return to her palace but move into a mansion in The Hague, where she lived for eight months, and she travelled through the countryside to motivate people, sometimes using a bicycle instead of a car. However, in 1947, while the country was still recovering from World War II, the revolt in the oil-rich Dutch East Indies saw sharp criticism of the Queen by the Dutch economic elite. Her loss of popularity and the forced departure from the East Indies under international pressure led to her abdication soon after.[PARAGRAPH:1]On September 4, 1948, after a reign of 58 years and 50 days, Wilhelmina abdicated in favour of her daughter Juliana. She was thenceforward styled "Her Royal Highness Princess Wilhelmina of the Netherlands". After her reign, the influence of the Dutch monarchy began to decline but the country's love for its royal family continued. No longer queen, Wilhelmina retreated to Het Loo Palace, making few public appearances until the country was devastated by the North Sea flood of 1953. Once again she travelled around the country to encourage and motivate the Dutch people.[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Wilhelmina died at the age of 82 on November 28, 1962 and was buried in the Dutch Royal Family crypt in the Nieuwe Kerk in Delft, on 8 December 1962. The funeral was, at her request and contrary to protocol, completely in white to give expression to her belief that earthly death was the beginning of eternal life.
		</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Wilhelmina[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Królowa Holandii[NEWLINE]Żyła:[\BOLD] 31 Sierpnia 1890 - 30 Kwietnia 1962[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Córka Wilhelma III i jego drugiej żony - Emmy Waldeck-Pyrmont. Kiedy się urodziła, żył jeszcze jej przyrodni brat Aleksander, z małżeństwa jej ojca z Zofią Wirtemberską, i Wilhelmina nie była brana pod uwagę jako przyszła królowa. Jednak jej ojciec przeżył swego syna i zmarł, kiedy dziewczynka miała 10 lat. Na skutek zmian w prawie mogła objąć tron, jednak do uzyskania przez nią pełnoletności władzę sprawowała jej matka - jako regentka. Wilhelmina tak opisywała swoje trudne dzieciństwo w zamknięciu: "Zawsze otaczały mnie mury nie do przebicia [...] rzadko mogłam choćby zobaczyć społeczeństwo. Od czasu do czasu dalekie echa życia na zewnątrz przedzierały się przez otaczającą mnie pustkę, ale nic ponadto". W 1901 poślubiła Henryka, księcia Mecklenburg-Schwerin, o którym mówiono, iż był playboyem i alkoholikiem. Podobno ją zdradzał i miał kilkoro nieślubnych dzieci. Ich jedyne dziecko - Juliana - przyszło na świat 30 kwietnia 1909. Dzień ten był uroczyście świętowany w Holandii, a narodziny Juliany zostały - jak się uważa - odebrane jako cud. 10 maja 1940 wojska hitlerowskich Niemiec uderzyły na Holandię. Królowa Wilhelmina chciała zostać w kraju - planowała przeniesienie się na południe, do Zelandii, gdzie mogłaby koordynować działania własnych wojsk w oparciu o bazę w miejscowości Breskens, w oczekiwaniu na nadejście alianckiej odsieczy tak, jak król Belgii, Albert I zrobił w czasie I wojny światowej. Opuściła więc Hagę na pokładzie brytyjskiego niszczyciela, który miał ją zawieżć na południe, jednakże gdy była w morzu, Zelandia znalazła się pod silnymi nalotami Luftwaffe i uznano, że jej powrót będzie zbyt niebezpieczny. Wilhelminie nie pozostało nic innego niż skorzystać z oferty Jerzego VI i przyjąć azyl w Wielkiej Brytanii. Udała się więc do Zjednoczonego Królestwa gotowa wrócić do kraju tak szybko, jak się tylko da. Holenderskie siły zbrojne skapitulowały 15 maja. Królowa Wilhelmina stanęła na czele holenderskiego rządu na uchodźstwie, ustalając zakresy obowiązków i natychmiast powiadamiając o tym naród. Stosunki między rządem a królową były napięte, a wzajemna niechęć narastała w miarę trwania wojny. Tymczasem Wilhelmina była bardzo popularna i szanowana przez światowych przywódców. Rząd nie miał parlamentu, który mógłby go wspierać, a urzędników raczej niewielu. Premier Dirk Jan de Geer uważał, że alianci przegrają wojnę i zamierzał wynegocjować z Niemcami separatystyczny układ pokojowy. W tej sytuacji Wilhelmina nie widziała innego wyjścia, jak zdymisjonować premiera.
		</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Вильгельмина[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Королева Нидерландов[NEWLINE]Годы жизни:[\BOLD] 31 августа 1890 - 30 апреля 1962[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Она была единственным ребенком короля Вильгельма III и его второй жены, Эммы Вальдек и Пирмонт. Ее детство характеризовалось теплыми отношениями с ее родителями, особенно с ее отцом, которому было уже 63 года, когда она родилась.[PARAGRAPH:1]Поскольку у короля Вильгельма уже было три сына с его первой женой, королевой Софией, когда родилась Вильгельмина, было мало шансов, что она вступит на престол. Однако Вильгельм пережил всех своих сыновей, последние из которых умерли, когда Вильгельмине было четыре года.[PARAGRAPH:1]Король Вильгельм III умер 23 ноября 1890 года, и хотя принцесса Вильгельмина мгновенно стала королевой Нидерландов, ее мать, Эмма, была назначена регентом до ее 18-летия.[PARAGRAPH:1]В 1901 году она вышла замуж за Хендрика, герцога Мекленбург-Шверинского. Хотя брак, как говорили, по сути был без любви, изначально Вильгельмина действительно заботилась о Хендрике, и вполне вероятно, что эти чувства были взаимными. Хендрик, однако, очень тяготился своей церемониальной ролью принца-консорта, заявив, что скучно быть не более, чем украшением и тенью своей жены. У него не было власти в Нидерландах, и Вильгельмина позаботилась о том, чтобы это продолжалось.[PARAGRAPH:1]Хотя Нидерланды оставались нейтральными во время Первой мировой войны, значительные немецкие инвестиции в голландскую экономику в сочетании с большим торговым партнерством в товарах вынудили Великобританию блокировать порты Нидерландов в попытке ослабить Германскую империю. Голландское правительство торговало с Германией в ответ. Перед штурмом немецким солдатам давали эдамский сыр для пайков. Вильгемина была «королевой солдат»; будучи женщиной, она не могла быть Верховным главнокомандующим, но, тем не менее, она использовала любую возможность, чтобы осмотреть свои силы. Во многих случаях она появлялась без предварительного уведомления, желая увидеть реальность, а не готовое шоу. Она любила своих солдат, но была очень недовольна большинством правительств, которые использовали вооруженные силы в качестве постоянного источника сокращения бюджета. Вильгельмина хотела маленькую, но хорошо обученную и экипированную армию. Однако это было далеко от реальности. На войне она чувствовала себя королевой на страже. Она всегда опасалась нападения немцев, особенно в начале. Тем не менее, нарушение территориального суверенитета Нидерландов произошло со стороны Великобритании и Соединенных Штатов, которые с помощью блокады захватили много голландских торговых и грузовых судов в попытке сорвать военные действия Германии. Это привело к усилению напряженности в отношениях между Нидерландами и союзными войсками.[PARAGRAPH:1]Волнения и анархия, вызванные революцией в царской России в феврале 1917 года, охватили и Нидерланды после войны. Лидер социалистов по имени Троэльстра пытался свергнуть правительство и королеву. Вместо насильственной революции он хотел контролировать законодательный орган парламента, и рассчитывал добиться этого путем выборов, убежденный, что рабочий класс поддержит его. Однако популярность молодой королевы помогла восстановить доверие к правительству. Вильгельмина вызвала массовую демонстрацию поддержки, катаясь со своей дочерью через толпы в открытой коляске. Было совершенно ясно, что революция не удастся.[PARAGRAPH:1]10 мая 1940 года нацистская Германия вторглась в Нидерланды, а королева Вильгельмина и ее семья через три дня бежали в Великобританию. Королева Вильгельмина хотела остаться в Нидерландах: она планировала отправиться со своими войсками в южную провинцию Зеландии, чтобы координировать дальнейшее сопротивление со стороны города Брескенс и оставаться там до прибытия помощи, так же как и король Бельгии Альберт I сделано во время Первой мировой войны. Она отправилась на борт британского крейсера в Гааге, который должен был отвезти ее туда. Однако, когда она была на борту, капитан заявил, что ему запрещено вступать в контакт с голландским берегом, поскольку Зеландия подверглась сильной атаке со стороны люфтваффе, и возвращаться было слишком опасно. Затем Вильгельмина приняла решение отправиться в Великобританию, планируя вернуться как можно скорее. Вильгельмина также провела время в Канаде во время войны, оставаясь в резиденции генерал-губернатора, Ридо Холл. Было сказано, что, находясь там, она оказала большое влияние на домохозяйство, в частности, на то, чтобы жить относительно просто. Королева настояла на том, чтобы лично делать покупки, ходить по улицам Оттавы без посторонней помощи (хотя просто поднимать руку, чтобы остановить движение, когда она захочет перейти дорогу) и путешествовать в Соединенные Штаты на обычном гражданском поезде.[PARAGRAPH:1]Во время войны ее фотография была признаком сопротивления немцам. Как и Уинстон Черчилль, королева Вильгельмина транслировала сообщения голландцам по радио Оранье. Как всегда, королева не наносила ударов, называя Адольфа Гитлера «заклятым врагом человечества». Ее ночные трансляции с нетерпением ждали ее люди, которые должны были скрываться, чтобы слушать их незаконно. Во время войны королева была почти убита бомбой, которая унесла жизни нескольких ее охранников и нанесла серьезный ущерб ее загородному дому недалеко от Южного Ми.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>