<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_THEODORA_1</Tag>
		<English>I agree you on before of the [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Pray that I do not grow to curse your progeny.</English>
		<French>Je vous salue au nom de [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Priez pour que je n'ai jamais à maudir votre progéniture.</French>
		<German>Du stehst vor dem großen [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Bete, dass ich mich nicht dazu entscheide, Deine Nachkommen zu verfluchen.</German>
		<Polish>Zgodziłam się z tobą w przeszłości, [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Módl się abym nie zemściła się na Twoich następcach.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_THEODORA</Tag>
		<English>Theodora</English>
		<French>Théodora</French>
		<Polish>Teodora</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_THEODORA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Theodora[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Empress of the Byzantine Empire[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.500 to June 28, 548 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Theodora was born to Acacius, a bear keeper, and her mother who was a dancer.  She was born to the lowest class of society.  She emerged as a comic actress in burlesque theatre.  She made use of every opportunity to move up Byzantine society.  She was a prostitute and a courtesan.  For a time she served as the mistress of Hecebolus, the governor of Pentapolis.  She bore a child from him, a son.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 523, Theodora married Justinian, the nephew of Emperor Justin I.  On his accession to the throne in 527, he made Theodora a join ruler of the empire.  This decision was a wise on, because she was a strong-willed woman and had a talent for power.  She saved the empire during the Nika riots of 523 after she called for a strong military response to the riots.[PARAGRAPH:1]Some scholars believe that Theodora was a noted promoter and practitioner of abortion.  She convinced Justinian to change the law that forbade noblemen to marry lower class women.  Theodora was also against the act of killing women who commited adultery.  She was also an advocate of women’s rights.  She also helped lessen the break in Christian sects, and played large parts in many of Justinian’s decisions.  Theodora also participated in less charitable acts.  Rumors arose about private dungeons in her room where people whom she disliked would disappear.  More pleasant was the story of how she sheltered an overthrown patriarch for twelve years in secrecy.[PARAGRAPH:1]Theodora died of cancer before the age of fifty, twenty-some years before Justinian’s death.  Some scholars suggest she died of breast cancer, though there is no documentation.  She was buried in the Church of the Holy Apostles, one of the churches the emperor and empress had built in Constantinople.  Both Theodora and Justinian are represented in numerous mosaics.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Teodora[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Cesarzowa Imperium Bizantyjskiego[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żyła:[\BOLD] ok. 500 do 28 Lipca 548 n.e.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Miejsce jej urodzenia jest przedmiotem sporów historyków - mogła urodzić się w Konstantynopolu, jednak część badaczy przypuszcza, iż jej rodzina mogła przybyć do tego miasta z Paflagonii, Cypru lub pogranicza bizantyńsko-perskiego. Jej ojcem był Akakios, treser niedźwiedzi stronnictwa "zielonych" w hipodromie w Konstantynopolu - Teodora była drugą z jego trzech córek. Ojciec zmarł ok. 503 roku, matka zaś wkrótce ponownie wyszła za mąż. Ojczym, dzięki opisanemu w źródłach aktowi publicznego błagania matki Teodory na arenie (w wyniku odrzucenia przez "zielonych") został zatrudniony na podobnym stanowisku w stronnictwie "błękitnych", z którymi odtąd Teodora była związana. W młodości Teodora trafiła na scenę teatralną, zapewne wprowadzona tam przez swą starszą siostrę Komito. Prokopiusz z Cezarei w pełnej jadu i nienawiści wobec Teodory Historii sekretnej szeroko opisał jej rozwiązłość wskazując, iż oprócz aktorstwa uprawiała również nierząd i oskarżając o najgorsze bezeceństwa ("często szła w gościnę z dziesięcioma lub więcej młodzieńcami..."). Ok. 515-516 roku urodziła córkę. Po zdobyciu pewnego uznania w grupie mimów stała się najpewniej utrzymanką bogatych obywateli Konstantynopola. Według Prokopiusza w tym okresie powiła syna Jana, którego ojciec zabrał ze sobą do Arabii. W 521 roku wyjechała do Cyrenajki za Hekebulosem z Tyru, który został zarządcą prowincji Pentapolis. Ten jednak po jakimś czasie oddalił ją. Teodora udała się wówczas w drogę powrotną do Konstantynopola, trafiając w drodze do Aleksandrii. Tam zapewne nawiązała bliskie kontakty z duchownymi monofizyckimi, być może wówczas właśnie przechodząc przełom i zrywając z dotychczasowym trybem życia. Kolejnym przystankiem w drodze do stolicy była Antiochia, gdzie na powrót nawiązała kontakty z "błękitnymi". Wróciła do stolicy w 521 lub 522 roku i wkrótce potem poznała Petrusa Sabbatiusa, wówczas około czterdziestoletniego siostrzeńca i bardzo bliskiego współpracownika cesarza Justyna I.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
