<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AFRICA</Tag>
		<English>Africa</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AFRICA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Africa</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AFRICA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Africa</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AFRICA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Africa region. [PARAGRAPH:2]The.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AFRICA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Africa</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ASIA</Tag>
		<English>Asia</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ASIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Asia</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ASIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Asia</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ASIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Asia region. [PARAGRAPH:2]The.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ASIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Asia</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_EUROPE</Tag>
		<English>Europe</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_EUROPE_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Europe</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_EUROPE_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Europe</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_EUROPE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Europe region. [PARAGRAPH:2]The.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_EUROPE_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Europe</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MIDDLEEAST</Tag>
		<English>Middle East</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MIDDLEEAST_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Middle East</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MIDDLEEAST_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Middle East</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MIDDLEEAST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Middle East region. [PARAGRAPH:2]The.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MIDDLEEAST_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Middle East</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NORTH_AMERICA</Tag>
		<English>North America</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NORTH_AMERICA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>North America</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NORTH_AMERICA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>North America</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NORTH_AMERICA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The North America is one of the largest expanses of grassland in the world, extending from Alberta, Saskatchewan and Manitoba in Canada all the way south to western Texas. The North America includes parts of North Dakota, South Dakota, Montana, Wyoming, Colorado, Nebraska, Kansas, Oklahoma, New Mexico and Texas.
[PARAGRAPH:2]Evidence suggests that the first human occupation of the Plains occurred at the end of the last ice age (around 10000 b.c., when the Clovis and then Folsom peoples inhabited the region). Between 5000 and 2000 b.c., a long drought made the region uninhabitable. Around 1000 a.d. the drought receded and the Eastern Woodland culture entered the central Plains to farm stream bottoms. The climate shifted again and many of its inhabitants withdrew, as others took their place.
[PARAGRAPH:3]The first documented European visit to the Plains was made in 1540 by the Spanish explorer Francisco Vasquez de Coronado. One hundred and fifty years later, the French investigated trading opportunities with Plains tribes in the region. American interest in the Plains was cemented with its purchase from France in 1803. In the twenty years after the Louisiana Purchase, three government expeditions led to the common perception of this region as the Great American Desert. Trails were blazed through the Plains from the 1830s, taking settlers to California and Oregon, and, by the late 1870s, the military had forced many Indian nations such as the Arapahos, Cheyennes, and Apaches onto reservations.
[PARAGRAPH:4]Plains Indians are usually divided into two broad classifications, with some degree of overlap. The first group were fully nomadic, following the vast herds of buffalo. Some tribes occasionally engaged in agriculture; growing tobacco and corn primarily. These included the Blackfoot, Arapaho, Assiniboine, Cheyenne, Comanche, Crow, Gros Ventre, Kiowa, Lakota, Lipan, Plains Apache (or Kiowa Apache), Plains Cree, Plains Ojibwe, Sarsi, Shoshone, Stoney, and Tonkawa. The second group of Plains Indians (sometimes referred to as Prairie Indians) were the semi-sedentary tribes who, in addition to hunting buffalo, lived in villages and raised crops. These included the Arikara, Hidatsa, Iowa, Kaw (or Kansa), Kitsai, Mandan, Missouria, Nez Perce, Omaha, Osage, Otoe, Pawnee, Ponca, Quapaw, Santee, Wichita, and Yankton. The nomadic tribes of the North America survived on hunting, some of their major hunts centered around deer and buffalo. Some tribes are described as part of the 'Buffalo Culture' (sometimes called, for the American Bison). Though the Plains Indians hunted other animals, such as elk or antelope, bison was their primary game food source. Bison flesh, hide and bones provided the chief source of raw materials for items that Plains Indians made, including food, cups, decorations, crafting tools, knives, and clothing.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NORTH_AMERICA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>North America</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_OCEANIA</Tag>
		<English>Oceania</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_OCEANIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Oceania</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_OCEANIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Oceania</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_OCEANIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Oceania region. [PARAGRAPH:2]The.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_OCEANIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Oceania</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SOUTH_AMERICA</Tag>
		<English>South America</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SOUTH_AMERICA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>South America</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SOUTH_AMERICA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>South America</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SOUTH_AMERICA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The South America region. [PARAGRAPH:2]The.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SOUTH_AMERICA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>South America</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
