<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 Beyond the Sword -->
<!-- Modified by the Civ Gold Team -->
<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ZIMBABWE</Tag>
		<English>Zimbabwean Empire</English>
		<French>Zimbabwean Empire</French>
		<German>Zimbabwean Empire</German>
		<Italian>Zimbabwean Empire</Italian>
		<Spanish>Zimbabwean Empire</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SHORT_ZIMBABWE</Tag>
		<English>Zimbabwe</English>
		<French>Zimbabwe</French>
		<German>Zimbabwe</German>
		<Italian>Zimbabwe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Zimbabwe</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ADJECTIVE_ZIMBABWE</Tag>
		<English>Zimbabwean</English>
		<French>Zimbabwean</French>
		<German>Zimbabwean</German>
		<Italian>Zimbabwean</Italian>
		<Spanish>Zimbabwean</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ZIMBABWE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD]Strategy:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]The Zimbabwean Empire is truly a unique and innovative civilization suitable for any map or terrain. With a total of three leaders to choose from, almost any strategy is possible. Per example, if you combine Joshua Nkomo and his "Aggressive" and " Protective" traits with the Zimbabwean [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Rozwi Warrior[COLOR_REVERT] UU, a unit that heals while moving and has a slight withdrawal chance, and you have the perfect agressive player. If you rather prefer prefer peaceful empire-building, Matope with his "Expansive" and "Industrous" traits will be quite the match. Then Include the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Zimba[COLOR_REVERT] UB, a Castle that increases the cultural output in the city, and your empire builder-style is complete. Or fif you rather would like to go for economy, then Khama is your guy. He's combination of the "Financial" and "Organized" traits will easily rival the economical potential of even the Netherlands. And that's just a small taste of the greatness that's within the Zimbabwean Empire...[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]The region of Southern Africa, usually including Zimbabwe, Mozambique, Botswana, Namibia, Zambia and the country of South-Africa, although in civ-terms South-Africa is represented by the Zulu. This mod aims mainly to represent the other nations north of South-Africa and allows all you Africa fans out there to play as another African state; the Zimbabwean Empire.[PARAGRAPH:1]The region encompassing Zimbabwe, Botswana, Mozambique, Zambia and Namibia have seen rise to many empires through the ages, all of them centred in the Zimbabwean area and its immediate surroundings (Botswana, Zambia and Mozambique). While these regions were previously inhabited by other people, the real history of Southern Africa starts with the huge Bantu expansion between 1000 BC and 500 AD. When they reached South-Africa in 300 AD they had established a firm foothold in a region they would later dominate.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Kingdom of Mapungubwe was the first state in Southern Africa, with its capital at Mapungubwe. The state arose in the 12th century CE. Its wealth came from controlling the trade in ivory from the Limpopo Valley, copper from the mountains of northern Transvaal, and gold from the Zimbabwe Plateau between the Limpopo and Zambezi rivers, with the Swahili merchants at Chibuene. By the mid 13th century, Mapungubwe was abandoned.[PARAGRAPH:1]After the decline of Mapungubwe, Great Zimbabwe rose on the Zimbabwe Plateau. Zimbabwe means stone building. Great Zimbabwe was the first city in Southern Africa and was the center of an empire, consolidating lesser Shona polities. Stone building was inherited from Mapungubwe. These building techniques were enhanced and came into maturity at Great Zimbabwe, represented by the wall of the Great Enclosure. The dry-stack stone masonry technology was also used to build smaller compounds in the area. Great Zimbabwe flourished by trading with Swahili Kilwa and Sofala. The rise of Great Zimbabwe parallels the rise of Kilwa. Great Zimbabwe was a major source of gold. Its royal court lived in luxury, wore Indian cotton, surrounded themselves with copper and gold ornaments, and ate on plates from as far away as Persia and China. Around the 1420s and 1430s, Great Zimbabwe was on the decline. The city was abandoned by 1450. Some have attributed the decline to the rise of the trading town Ingombe Ilede.[PARAGRAPH:1]A new chapter of Southern African history ensued. Mutota, a northern Shona king of the Karanga,, engaged in conquest. He and his son Mutope conquered the Zimbabwe Plateau, going through Mozambique to the east coast, linking the empire to the coastal trade. They called their empire Wilayatu 'l Mu'anamutapah or mwanamutapa (Lord of the Plundered Lands), or the Kingdom of Mutapa. Monomotapa was the Portuguese corruption. They did not build stone structures; the northern Shonas had no traditions of building in stone. After the death of Matope in 1480, the empire split into two small empires: Torwa in the south and Mutapa in the north. The split occurred over rivalry from two Shona lords, Changa and Togwa, with the mwanamutapa line. Changa was able to acquire the south, forming the Kingdom of Butua with its capital at Khami.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Mutapa Empire continued in the north under the mwanamutapa line. During the 16th century the Portuguese were able to establish permanent markets up the Zambezi River in an attempt to gain political and military control of Mutapa. They were partially successful. In 1628, a decisive battle allowed them to put a puppet mwanamutapa named Mavura, who signed treaties that gave favorable mineral export rights to the Portuguese. The Portuguese were successful in destroying the mwanamutapa system of government and undermining trade. By 1667, Mutapa was in decay. Chiefs would not allow digging for gold because of fear of Portuguese theft, and the population declined.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Kingdom of Butua was ruled by a changamire, a title derived from the founder, Changa. Later it became the Rozwi Empire. The Portuguese tried to gain a foothold but were thrown out of the region in 1693, by Changamire Dombo. The 17th century was a period of peace and prosperity. The Rozwi Empire fell into ruins in the 1830s from invading Nguni from Natal.[PARAGRAPH:1]After this followed a long period of European colonization and Zulu conquest. This period were characterized by the European greed to pump as many resources out of the colonies as possible, and the only state that managed some kind of independence was Botswana, who's chieftain had agreed a mutual protection pact with the British, becoming more of a vassal than a true colony. Under the British, Botswana emerged as a Kingdom under protection.[PARAGRAPH:1]Botswana was also the country to emerge the most successful during the decolonization of Africa. With Zimbabwe and Namibia being led by white minority governments, and although black-African leaders such as Joshua Nkomo, Andimba Toivo and Robert Mugabe managed through diplomacy and successful guerilla wars to liberate the black Majority, the regions are still suffering from the after-effects of Colonization. Mozambique was for a while savaged by Civil War and massive emigration, but the country have managed to get rid of these problems and switched to a capitalist system, with peace returning in the 1990s. Botswana, today is considered one of the best countries to live in in all of Sub-Saharan Africa. It has a growing economy and can almost be considered an Industrial country, something the very able leader Seretse Khama accomplished through his rule as president. His son Ian Khama was in 2008 elected president of Botswana and the country has since showed that one can, through able rule, emerge as a better nation also in the troubled Africa, a path Zambia have chosen to follow them on. Now only the future can tell if this path is the path that the rest of Southern Africa will join, or if they will continue their political turmoil into the 21st century.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
		<French>INSERT</French>
		<German>INSERT</German>
		<Italian>INSERT</Italian>
		<Spanish>INSERT</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MATOPE</Tag>
		<English>Matope</English>
		<French>Matope</French>
		<German>Matope</German>
		<Italian>Matope</Italian>
		<Spanish>Matope</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MATOPE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Matope[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Mutapa[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]15th Century AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][NEWLINE][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Matope was the second king of the Mutapa Empire, reigning from the death of his father (c. 1450) to probably early 16th century. During his reign, the kingdom drasticcaly extended its borders into an empire encompassing most of the lands between Tavara and the Indian Ocean. This again led to control of new areas where more resources could be exploited. Matope and his sucsessors soon grew rich on trade with copper from Chidzurgwe and ivory from the middle Zambezi.[PARAGRAPH:1]Matope also severly weakened the Torwa kingdom, the southern Shona state from which his dynasty originated. Matope's armies overran the kingdom of the Manyika as well as the coastal kingdoms of Kiteve and Madanda. By the time the Portuguese arrived on the coast of Mozambique, the Mutapa Kingdom was the premier Shona state in the region.[PARAGRAPH:1] </English>
		<French>INSERT</French>
		<German>INSERT</German>
		<Italian>INSERT</Italian>
		<Spanish>INSERT</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_GREAT_ZIMBABWE</Tag>
		<English>Great Zimbabwe</English>
		<French>Great Zimbabwe</French>
		<German>Great Zimbabwe</German>
		<Italian>Great Zimbabwe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Great Zimbabwe</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_KHAMI</Tag>
		<English>Khami</English>
		<French>Khami</French>
		<German>Khami</German>
		<Italian>Khami</Italian>
		<Spanish>Khami</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MAPUNGUBWE</Tag>
		<English>Mapungubwe</English>
		<French>Mapungubwe</French>
		<German>Mapungubwe</German>
		<Italian>Mapungubwe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mapungubwe</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ZWONGOMBE</Tag>
		<English>Zwongombe</English>
		<French>Zwongombe</French>
		<German>Zwongombe</German>
		<Italian>Zwongombe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Zwongombe</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SOFALA</Tag>
		<English>Sofala</English>
		<French>Sofala</French>
		<German>Sofala</German>
		<Italian>Sofala</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sofala</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_BAMBANDYANALO</Tag>
		<English>Bambandyanalo</English>
		<French>Bambandyanalo</French>
		<German>Bambandyanalo</German>
		<Italian>Bambandyanalo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bambandyanalo</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_DANAMOMBE</Tag>
		<English>Danamombe</English>
		<French>Danamombe</French>
		<German>Danamombe</German>
		<Italian>Danamombe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Danamombe</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ZIWA</Tag>
		<English>Ziwa</English>
		<French>Ziwa</French>
		<German>Ziwa</German>
		<Italian>Ziwa</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ziwa</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_INHAMBANE</Tag>
		<English>Inhambane</English>
		<French>Inhambane</French>
		<German>Inhambane</German>
		<Italian>Inhambane</Italian>
		<Spanish>Inhambane</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_BUMBUSI</Tag>
		<English>Bumbusi</English>
		<French>Bumbusi</French>
		<German>Bumbusi</German>
		<Italian>Bumbusi</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bumbusi</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_NALETALE</Tag>
		<English>Naletale</English>
		<French>Naletale</French>
		<German>Naletale</German>
		<Italian>Naletale</Italian>
		<Spanish>Naletale</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_KARANGA</Tag>
		<English>Karanga</English>
		<French>Karanga</French>
		<German>Karanga</German>
		<Italian>Karanga</Italian>
		<Spanish>Karanga</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_GWANDA</Tag>
		<English>Gwanda</English>
		<French>Gwanda</French>
		<German>Gwanda</German>
		<Italian>Gwanda</Italian>
		<Spanish>Gwanda</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_KOREKORE</Tag>
		<English>Korekore</English>
		<French>Korekore</French>
		<German>Korekore</German>
		<Italian>Korekore</Italian>
		<Spanish>Korekore</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_NDAU</Tag>
		<English>Ndau</English>
		<French>Ndau</French>
		<German>Ndau</German>
		<Italian>Ndau</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ndau</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_KITEVE</Tag>
		<English>Kiteve</English>
		<French>Kiteve</French>
		<German>Kiteve</German>
		<Italian>Kiteve</Italian>
		<Spanish>Kiteve</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MAXIXE</Tag>
		<English>Maxixe</English>
		<French>Maxixe</French>
		<German>Maxixe</German>
		<Italian>Maxixe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Maxixe</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MANYIKA</Tag>
		<English>Manyika</English>
		<French>Manyika</French>
		<German>Manyika</German>
		<Italian>Manyika</Italian>
		<Spanish>Manyika</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ZEZURU</Tag>
		<English>Zezuru</English>
		<French>Zezuru</French>
		<German>Zezuru</German>
		<Italian>Zezuru</Italian>
		<Spanish>Zezuru</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CHIMOIO</Tag>
		<English>Chimoio</English>
		<French>Chimoio</French>
		<German>Chimoio</German>
		<Italian>Chimoio</Italian>
		<Spanish>Chimoio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MADANDA</Tag>
		<English>Madanda</English>
		<French>Madanda</French>
		<German>Madanda</German>
		<Italian>Madanda</Italian>
		<Spanish>Madanda</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MOLEPOLOLE</Tag>
		<English>Molepolole</English>
		<French>Molepolole</French>
		<German>Molepolole</German>
		<Italian>Molepolole</Italian>
		<Spanish>Molepolole</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_TAVARA</Tag>
		<English>Tavara</English>
		<French>Tavara</French>
		<German>Tavara</German>
		<Italian>Tavara</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tavara</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CHIDZURGWE</Tag>
		<English>Chidzurgwe</English>
		<French>Chidzurgwe</French>
		<German>Chidzurgwe</German>
		<Italian>Chidzurgwe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Chidzurgwe</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_TORWA</Tag>
		<English>Torwa</English>
		<French>Torwa</French>
		<German>Torwa</German>
		<Italian>Torwa</Italian>
		<Spanish>Torwa</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_TETE</Tag>
		<English>Tete</English>
		<French>Tete</French>
		<German>Tete</German>
		<Italian>Tete</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tete</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SENA</Tag>
		<English>Sena</English>
		<French>Sena</French>
		<German>Sena</German>
		<Italian>Sena</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sena</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_KUMAKOMOYO</Tag>
		<English>Kumakomoyo</English>
		<French>Kumakomoyo</French>
		<German>Kumakomoyo</German>
		<Italian>Kumakomoyo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Kumakomoyo</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_HARARE</Tag>
		<English>Harare</English>
		<French>Harare</French>
		<German>Harare</German>
		<Italian>Harare</Italian>
		<Spanish>Harare</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_GABORONE</Tag>
		<English>Gaborone</English>
		<French>Gaborone</French>
		<German>Gaborone</German>
		<Italian>Gaborone</Italian>
		<Spanish>Gaborone</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_KADOMA</Tag>
		<English>Kadoma</English>
		<French>Kadoma</French>
		<German>Kadoma</German>
		<Italian>Kadoma</Italian>
		<Spanish>Kadoma</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_NYANGABGWE</Tag>
		<English>Nyangabgwe</English>
		<French>Nyangabgwe</French>
		<German>Nyangabgwe</German>
		<Italian>Nyangabgwe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nyangabgwe</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_NYANGA</Tag>
		<English>Nyanga</English>
		<French>Nyanga</French>
		<German>Nyanga</German>
		<Italian>Nyanga</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nyanga</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MATOBO</Tag>
		<English>Matobo</English>
		<French>Matobo</French>
		<German>Matobo</German>
		<Italian>Matobo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Matobo</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_NTSWENG</Tag>
		<English>Ntsweng</English>
		<French>Ntsweng</French>
		<German>Ntsweng</German>
		<Italian>Ntsweng</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ntsweng</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_KANYE</Tag>
		<English>Kanye</English>
		<French>Kanye</French>
		<German>Kanye</German>
		<Italian>Kanye</Italian>
		<Spanish>Kanye</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SEROWE</Tag>
		<English>Serowe</English>
		<French>Serowe</French>
		<German>Serowe</German>
		<Italian>Serowe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Serowe</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ZEERUST</Tag>
		<English>Zeerust</English>
		<French>Zeerust</French>
		<German>Zeerust</German>
		<Italian>Zeerust</Italian>
		<Spanish>Zeerust</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
<!--MATOPE-->	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MATOPE</Tag>
		<English>It is good that you visit me, [CT_NAME]. The [OUR_EMPIRE] are always open to trade with other great nations. Perhaps you have something good to offer us?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_MATOPE</Tag>
		<English>Lies! Lies! No more! Begone!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_MATOPE</Tag>
		<English>I must first avenge [OUR_CIV_SHORT]'s fallen sons before I have peace with the likes of you!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_MATOPE</Tag>
		<English>It is a good thing to see you again, [CT_NAME]! Let us speak of trade and mutual cooperation between our two great lands.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_MATOPE</Tag>
		<English>You come again, you fool. What curses do you bring to me today?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_MATOPE</Tag>
		<English>Be kind, [CT_NAME]. We ask with much desperation, and perhaps you can comply.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_MATOPE</Tag>
		<English>I see that [CT_CIV_SHORT] has many things that might be of use to [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Perhaps you can share them with us, [CT_NAME]?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_MATOPE</Tag>
		<English>I'll make my demands clear, [CT_NAME]. Give us want we want, or else [CT_CIV_SHORT] shall have no peace for the rest of its short existence.</English>
	</TEXT>
<!--JOSHUA NKOMO-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JOSHUA_NKOMO</Tag>
		<English>The people of [OUR_CIV_SHORT] are strong. Be careful around us, [CT_NAME], and we shall take care around you as well.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_JOSHUA_NKOMO</Tag>
		<English>People will believe anything, won't they? But do you think I will ever believe you?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_JOSHUA_NKOMO</Tag>
		<English>People will believe anything, won't they? And you believed that you could have peace! No! We shall free our lands of your domination!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_JOSHUA_NKOMO</Tag>
		<English>Good, [CT_NAME], good. Let us discuss politics, or perhaps something more relaxing, for the time being.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_JOSHUA_NKOMO</Tag>
		<English>Your tyrannical leadership tests my patience, [CT_NAME].</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_JOSHUA_NKOMO</Tag>
		<English>Come, [CT_NAME], it would be heartless and inhumane to ignore our plight. Please help us!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_JOSHUA_NKOMO</Tag>
		<English>You should acknowledge your friends, [CT_NAME], and physical displays of friendship are the easiest to accomplish.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_JOSHUA_NKOMO</Tag>
		<English>I laugh in the face of nations led ignorant, inept tyrants such as yourself, [CT_NAME]. Come, show me the best things you have, and I'll take them!</English>
	</TEXT>
<!--KHAMA-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KHAMA</Tag>
		<English>The world is my church. To do good my religion. Let us be good friends, [CT_NAME]!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_KHAMA</Tag>
		<English>I think that the trouble we now face in the world is caused mainly by the refusal to try and see another mans point of view. And you, [CT_NAME], have shown little of that open-mindedness.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_KHAMA</Tag>
		<English>Peace? No! I will fight against your oppressive rule until the very end!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_KHAMA</Tag>
		<English>Friend, friend, it is good to see you again. I am always happy to welcome you.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_KHAMA</Tag>
		<English>I detest the sight of your face, [CT_NAME], but I must be calm and patient in the meanwhile.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_KHAMA</Tag>
		<English>[OUR_CIV_SHORT] is a poor country and at present is unable to stand on its own feet and develop its recourses without assistance from its friends.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_KHAMA</Tag>
		<English>We [OUR_CIV_ADJ] are not desperate beggars, but we do kindly ask for some help at the moment.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_KHAMA</Tag>
		<English>A nation without a past is a lost nation, and a people without a past is a people without a soul. The might of the [OUR_EMPIRE] can easily, easily remove your past and your people from the face of the planet if you refuse to comply with our demands!</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
