<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOCALYPSE_URBAN_CROSSBOWMAN</Tag>
		<English>Urban Crossbowman</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Arbalétrier Urbain</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Balestriere urbano</Italian>
		<Polish>Miejski Kusznik</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOCALYPSE_URBAN_CROSSBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In the years following the Great War, the United States devolved into a post-apocalyptic environment commonly dubbed "the Wasteland". The War and subsequent nuclear Armageddon has severely depopulated the country, leaving large expanses of property decaying from neglect. In addition, virtually all food and water is irradiated and radiation exposure, combined with a mutagenic bioweapon that was accidentally released into the atmosphere during the War, have caused mutation in nearly all forms of life. With a large portion of the country's infrastructure in ruins, basic necessities are scarce. Barter is the common method of exchange, with bottlecaps providing a more conventional form of currency. Most cities and towns are empty, having been looted and deserted in favor of smaller, makeshift communities scattered around the Wasteland.</English>
		<Italian>Unità post-apocalisse</Italian>
		<Polish>Fantastyka postapokaliptyczna - wizja, konwencja traktująca o wydarzeniach bezpośrednio po kataklizmie, apokalipsie. W książkach lub filmach fabuła rozgrywa się zazwyczaj po wojnie jądrowej, pandemii lub katastrofie ekologicznej. Ziemia staje się wówczas areną dla ludzi czerpiących z resztek zniszczonej cywilizacji, starających się przetrwać i przystosować do niesprzyjających warunków.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOCALYPSE_URBAN_CROSSBOWMAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Urban Crossbowman is an alt-timeline Post-Apocalypse Unit. It should not be build unless you have been nuked and you can build nothing else.</English>
		<Italian>Il balestriere urbano è un'unità post-apocalisse. Non dovrebbe essere costruito, a meno che tu non sia stato bombardato con l'atomica e non possa costruire nient'altro.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CROWBAR_GUARD</Tag>
		<English>Crowbar Guard</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Combattant au Pied-de-biche</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Guardia con piede di porco</Italian>
		<Polish>Strażnik z łomem</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CROWBAR_GUARD_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Crowbar Guard is an alt-timeline Post-Apocalypse Unit. It should not be build unless you have been nuked and you can build nothing else.</English>
		<Italian>La guardia con piede di porco è un'unità post-apocalisse. Non dovrebbe essere costruito, a meno che tu non sia stato bombardato con l'atomica e non possa costruire nient'altro.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HATCHET_MAN</Tag>
		<English>Hatchet Warrior</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Combattant avec Hachette</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Guerriero con accetta</Italian>
		<Polish>Wojownik z siekierą</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HATCHET_MAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Hatchet Warrior is an alt-timeline Post-Apocalypse Unit. It should not be build unless you have been nuked and you can build nothing else.</English>
		<Italian>Il guerriero con accetta è un'unità post-apocalisse. Non dovrebbe essere costruito, a meno che tu non sia stato bombardato con l'atomica e non possa costruire nient'altro.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MACHETE_WARRIOR</Tag>
		<English>Machete Warrior</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Combattant avec Machette</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Guerriero con machete</Italian>
		<Polish>Wojownik z maczetą</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MACHETE_WARRIOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Machete Warrior is an alt-timeline Post-Apocalypse Unit. It should not be build unless you have been nuked and you can build nothing else.</English>
		<Italian>Il guerriero con machete è un'unità post-apocalisse. Non dovrebbe essere costruito, a meno che tu non sia stato bombardato con l'atomica e non possa costruire nient'altro.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_POST_APOCALYPTIC_GRENADIER</Tag>
		<English>Molotov Cocktail Thrower</English>
		<French>Lanceur de Coktail Molotov</French>
		<Polish>Miotacz Koktaili Mołotowa</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_POST_APOCALYPTIC_GRENADIER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Molotov Cocktail Thrower can easily take the wreckage of buildings and cities from enemy forces by burning them out. Be careful though with the flammables, you only have so many resources.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WRENCH_WARRIOR</Tag>
		<English>Wrench Warrior</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Combattant avec Clé à Molette</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Guerriero con chiave inglese</Italian>
		<Polish>Wojownik z kluczem fr.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WRENCH_WARRIOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Wrench Warrior is an alt-timeline Post-Apocalypse Unit. It should not be build unless you have been nuked and you can build nothing else.</English>
		<Italian>Il guerriero con chiave inglese è un'unità post-apocalisse. Non dovrebbe essere costruito, a meno che tu non sia stato bombardato con l'atomica e non possa costruire nient'altro.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
