<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_CLOCKPUNK</Tag>
		<English>Clockpunk</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_CLOCKPUNK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Clockpunk is a subgenre of speculative fiction which is similar to steampunk, in that it portrays advanced technology based on pre-modern designs, but the technology used is based on springs and clockwork, and is usually set during the Renaissance.</English>
		<Polish>Clockpunk - odmiana science-fiction, która wyewoluowała z steampunku. Akcja utworów przeważnie w erze preindustrialnej, chociaż rozmach z jakim jest stosowana technologia sugeruje co innego. Technika opiera się przede wszystkim na sprężynach, podstawowej mechanice (clockwork - stąd nazwa gatunku) i wynalazkach podobnych do urządzeń Leonarda da Vinci.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_AUTOMATION_CLOCK</Tag>
		<English>Automation Clock</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Horloges Automatiques</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Orologio automatico</Italian>
		<Polish>Automat Zegarowy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_AUTOMATION_CLOCK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>An automaton clock or automata clock is a type of striking clock featuring automatons. Clocks like these were built from the Middle Ages through to Victorian times in Europe. Our tradition of inventive genius makes them far more common in our country than in others. The automatons usually perform on the hour, half-hour or quarter-hour, usually to strike bells.</English>
		<Italian>Un orologio automatizzato è un tipo di orologio che presenta alcuni automi. Orologi come questi venivano costruiti in Europa dal Medioevo, fino all'era Vittoriana. La nostra tradizione di inventori geniali li ha resi molto più comuni nel nostro paese rispetton agli altri. Gli automi si attivano all'ora piena, mezz'ora o quarto d'ora, solitamente per suonare le campane.</Italian>
		<Polish>Automat zegarowy to specjalny mechanizm zegarowy napędzający konstrukty i maszyny z epoki Clocpunkowej.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_AUTOMATION_CLOCK_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build an Automation Clock to increase your city's production.</English>
		<French>La construction d'Horloges Automatiques augmente la production de votre ville.</French>
		<Italian>Costruisci un orologio automatico per incrementare la produzione della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOCKPUNK_AIRPORT</Tag>
		<English>Ornithopter Aerie</English>
		<French>Aire d'Ornithoptères</French>
		<Italian>Area per ornitotteri</Italian>
		<Polish>Baza Ornitopterów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOCKPUNK_AIRPORT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>An Ornithopter Aerie is an early airport for flying Ornithopters.</English>
		<French>Une Aire d'Ornithoptères est un petit aérodrome d'où peuvent décoller les Ornithoptères.</French>
		<Italian>Un'area per ornitotteri è un primitivo aeroporto, ideato per gli ornitotteri.</Italian>
		<Polish>Baza Ornitopterów to wczesna wersja lotniska.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOCKPUNK_AIRPORT_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build an Ornithopter Aerie to increase your city's wealth.</English>
		<French>Construisez une [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Aire d'Ornithoptères[COLOR_REVERT] pour augmenter la richesse la ville</French>
		<Italian>Costruisci un'area per ornitotteri per incrementare la ricchezza della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOCKPUNK_EMBASSY</Tag>
		<English>Culture (Clockpunk)</English>
		<Italian>Cultura (Clockpunk)</Italian>
		<Polish>Kultura (Clockpunk)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOCKPUNK_EMBASSY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Clockpunk is a subgenre of speculative fiction which is similar to steampunk, in that it portrays advanced technology based on pre-modern designs, but the technology used is based on springs and clockwork, and is usually set during the Renaissance.</English>
		<French>Le Clockpunk est un sous-genre de la fiction spéculative, similaire au Steampunk, cyberpunk. Il est basé des technologies des mécanismes et engrenages, et est en général situé à l'ère de la Renaissance.</French>
		<Italian>Clockpunk è un sottogenere di finzione speculativa simile allo steampunk, nel fatto che descrive tecnologia avanzata basandosi su un design pre-moderno, ma la tecnologia utilizzata si basa su molle e orologi, e viene solitamente ambientata durante il Rinascimento.</Italian>
		<Polish>Clockpunk - odmiana science-fiction, która wyewoluowała z steampunku. Akcja utworów przeważnie w erze preindustrialnej, chociaż rozmach z jakim jest stosowana technologia sugeruje co innego. Technika opiera się przede wszystkim na sprężynach, podstawowej mechanice (clockwork - stąd nazwa gatunku) i wynalazkach podobnych do urządzeń Leonarda da Vinci.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOCKPUNK_EMBASSY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build Culture (Clockpunk) to gain access to unique buildings and units.</English>
		<French>Construire la culture (Clockpunk) permet d'accéder à des bâtiments et unités uniques.</French>
		<Italian>Costruisci Cultura (Clockpunk) per ottenere l'accesso a edifici e unità uniche.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOCKWORK_WORKSHOP</Tag>
		<English>Clockwork Workshop</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Atelier d'horlogerie</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Atelier di orologeria</Italian>
		<Polish>Warsztat Zegarmistrzowski</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOCKWORK_WORKSHOP_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A clockwork is the inner workings of either a mechanical clock or a device that operates in a similar fashion. Specifically, the term refers to a mechanical device utilizing a complex series of gears.</English>
		<Italian>Un ingranaggio è la parte più interna di un orologio meccanico, o di un meccanismo che opera in modo simile. Nello specifico, il termine si riferisce a un meccanismo che utilizza una complessa serie di ruote dentate.</Italian>
		<Polish>Zegarmistrzostwo - wytwarzanie czasomierzy, prace związane z utrzymaniem lub przywróceniem ich sprawności technicznej, dziedzina sztuki użytkowej i rzemiosła, także artystycznego. Związane z doskonaleniem pomiarów i praktycznym wskazywaniem czasu oraz rozwojem wzornictwa, również przemysłowego.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOCKWORK_WORKSHOP_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a Clockwork Workshop to increase your city's production.</English>
		<French>Construire un [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Atelier d'horlogerie[COLOR_REVERT] vous permettra d'améliorer la production de votre ville.</French>
		<Italian>Costruisci un atelier di orologeria per incrementare la produzione della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ORCHESTRION_THEATER</Tag>
		<English>Orchestrion Theater</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Théatre d'Orchestrion</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Teatro Orchestrion</Italian>
		<Polish>Orchestrion</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ORCHESTRION_THEATER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>An orchestrion is a generic name for a machine that plays music and is designed to sound like an orchestra or band. Orchestrions may be operated by means of a large pinned cylinder or by a music roll and less commonly book music. The sound is usually produced by pipes, though they will be voiced differently to those found in a pipe organ, as well as percussion instruments. Many orchestrions contain a piano as well. In our age of clockwork, orchestrion theaters comprise enormous wall sized machines, usually complete with mechanical dolls moving in time to the music, and seats from which citizens can appreciate the works of our music roll composers.</English>
		<Italian>Orchestrione è un nome genrico per una macchina che suona musica, ed è progettata per funzionare come un'orchestra o una banda. Gli Orchestrion  possono essere azionati da un grande cilindro con dei rilievi, oppure da un rotolo musicale. Solitamente il suono è prodotto da canne, anche se è diverso da quallo prodtto dalle canne di un organo, così come da uno strumento a percussione. Molti orchestrion contengono anche un piano. Nella nostra era piena di ingranaggi. gli orchestrion comprendono enormi macchine, di solito complete di bambole meccaniche che si muovono a tempo con la musica, e posti dai quali i cittadini possono apprezzare i lavoratori dei nostri compositori.</Italian>
		<Polish>Orchestrion (orkiestron) - rodzaj szafy grającej zaliczanej do instrumentów mechanicznych, popularny szczególnie w XIX wieku. Zbudowany z oszklonej szafki, wewnątrz której umieszczony był mechanizm wagowy, który po wrzuceniu monety włączał urządzenie poruszające kolczasty walec. Za pomocą kolców umieszczonych na walcu uruchamiane były specjalne młoteczki uderzające następnie o struny, dzwonki czy też bębenki. Całość uzyskanej melodyjki odbywała się według specjalnie zaprojektowanego wzorca melodycznego. Z biegiem lat urządzenie to zostało zastąpione przez automaty płytowe.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ORCHESTRION_THEATER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build an Orchestrion Theater to increase your city's culture.</English>
		<French>Construire un [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Théatre d'Orchestrion[COLOR_REVERT] vous permettra d'améliorer la culture de votre ville.</French>
		<Italian>Costruisci un Teatro Orchestrion per incrementare la cultura della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STEPRECKONER_MANUFACTORY</Tag>
		<English>Step Reckoner Manufactory</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Usine de Calculateurs mécaniques</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>Costruttore di calcolatori meccanici</Italian>
		<Polish>Fabryka Maszyn Liczących</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STEPRECKONER_MANUFACTORY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Step Reckoners are portable cranked mechanical calculators that can add, subtract, multiply and divide. They're a real step up from the abacus when it comes to calculating arithmetic. Other less inventive countries claim that the fiddly bits are impossible to make reliably but we managed just fine.</English>
		<Italian>I calcolatori meccanici sono strumenti portatili in grado di aggiungere, sottrarre, moltiplicare e dividere. Sono un grande passo avanti rispetto all'abaco, per quanto riguarda i calcoli aritmetici. Altri paesi meno ingegnosi sostengono che sia difficile rendere affidabili questi macchinari, ma noi ci siamo riusciti benissimo.</Italian>
		<Polish>Maszyna licząca - urządzenie mechaniczne, elektryczne lub elektroniczne wspomagające proces obliczeń. Pojęcie "elektroniczna maszyna licząca" było używane w języku polskim, w drugiej połowie XX wieku, na określenie komputera.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STEPRECKONER_MANUFACTORY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build a Step Reckoner Manufactory to increase your city's production.</English>
		<French>Construire une [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Usine de Calculateurs mécaniques[COLOR_REVERT] vous permettra d'améliorer la production de votre ville.</French>
		<Italian>Costruisci un Costruttore di calcolatori meccanico per incrementare la produzione della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_CLOCKPUNK</Tag>
		<English>Clockpunk</English>
		<French>Clock-punk</French>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Clockpunk</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_CLOCKPUNK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD]Clockpunk[\BOLD], is a subgenre of speculative fiction which is similar to steampunk, but deviates in its technology. As with steampunk, it portrays advanced technology based on pre-modern designs, but rather than the steam power of the Industrial Age, the technology used is based on springs, clockwork and similar. Clockpunk is based very intensively on the works of Leonardo da Vinci and as such, it is typically set during the Renaissance. The idea is fairly new and very few works have been created in this genre. Clockpunk works include Pasquale's Angel by Paul J. McAuley, and Jack Faust by Michael Swanwick, as well as the upcoming novel Mainspring by Jay Lake. There are also clockpunk elements in the Marvel 1602 comic series and its sequels, and in the Discworld novels of Terry Pratchett, most notably a da Vinci space shuttle in The Last Hero. Benot Sokal's Syberia adventure game could also be considered clockpunk, as it features spring-based machines and clockwork automata.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_CLOCKPUNK_QUOTE</Tag>
		<English>"A clockwork heart can't replace the real thing." - Dru Pagliassotti, Clockwork Heart</English>
		<French>"Un coeur d'horlogerie ne peut pas remplacer la chose réelle." - Dru Pagliassotti, Le Coeur d'Horlogerie</French>
		<Polish>"Mechaniczne serce może zastąpić rzeczywiste." - Dru Pagliassotti, Clockwork Heart</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_CLOCKPUNK_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CLOCKWORK_GOLEM</Tag>
		<English>Clockwork Golem</English>
		<French>Golem Mécanique</French>
		<Italian>Golem meccanico</Italian>
		<Polish>Mechaniczny Golem</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CLOCKWORK_GOLEM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Bipedal Armored combat unit</English>
		<Italian>Unità corazzata bipede da combattimento</Italian>
		<Polish>Dwunorzna opancerzona maszyna bojowa.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CLOCKWORK_GOLEM_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Clockwork golem is an alt-timeline Da Vinci/Clockpunk unit. It has good all-around combat skills.</English>
		<Italian>Il Golem meccanico è un'unità Clockpunk. Ha ottime caratteristicche di combattimento, contro ogni nemico</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DAVINCI_TANK</Tag>
		<English>Da Vinci Tank</English>
		<French>Char 'Da Vinci'</French>
		<Italian>Carro di Leonardo</Italian>
		<Polish>Czołg Da Vinci</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DAVINCI_TANK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Wheeled Armored combat unit</English>
		<Italian>Unità corazzata su ruote in stile Clockpunk</Italian>
		<Polish>Czołg wynaleziony przez Leonarda DaVinci</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DAVINCI_TANK_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Da Vinci Tank is an alt-timeline Da Vinci/Clockpunk unit. It has good all-around combat skills.</English>
		<Italian>Il carro di Leonardo è un'unità in stile Clockpunk. Ha ottime capacità in combattimento.</Italian>
		<Polish>Czołg wynaleziony przez Leonarda DaVinci.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ORNITHOPTER</Tag>
		<English>Ornithopter</English>
		<French>Ornithoptère</French>
		<Italian>Ornitottero</Italian>
		<Polish>Ornitopter</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ORNITHOPTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>An ornithopter (from Greek ornithos "bird" and pteron "wing") is an aircraft that flies by flapping its wings. Designers seek to imitate the flapping-wing flight of birds, bats, and insects. Though machines may differ in form, they are usually built on the same scale as these flying creatures. Manned ornithopters have also been built, and some have been successful. The machines are of two general types: those with engines, and those powered by the muscles of the pilot.</English>
		<Italian>Unità da combattimetno aereo stile Clockpunk</Italian>
		<Polish>Ornitopter - aerodyna napędzana ruchem powierzchni nośnych pracujących tak, jak skrzydła u ptaków. Poza modelami, jedna z nielicznych praktycznych realizacji została dokonana przez profesora Jamesa DeLauriera z Uniwersytetu Toronto Institute for Aerospace Studies w 2006. Pierwszy polski skrzydłowiec, Ornitopter Boratiniego, powstał w 1648.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ORNITHOPTER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Ornithopter[COLOR_REVERT] is an alt-timeline Da Vinci/Clockpunk unit. It is the earliest available air unit for anyone, so getting this is a good advantage.</English>
		<Italian>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]L'ornitottero[COLOR_REVERT] è un'unità in stile Clockpunk. E' la più antica unità aerea del gioco, per cui ottenrela rappresenta un grande vantaggio.</Italian>
		<Polish>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Ornitopter[COLOR_REVERT] to prymitywny samolot wynaleziony przez Leonardo Da Vinci</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_REPEATING_CROSSBOWMAN</Tag>
		<English>Repeating Crossbowman</English>
		<French>Guerrier avec arbalète à répétition</French>
		<Italian>Balestriere a ripetizione</Italian>
		<Polish>Kusza Samopowtarzlna</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_REPEATING_CROSSBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The repeating crossbow is a crossbow where the separate actions of stringing the bow, placing the bolt and shooting it can be accomplished with a simple one-handed movement while keeping the crossbow stationary. This allows a higher rate of fire than a normal crossbow: there is a magazine containing a number of bolts on top of the bow, and the mechanism is worked by moving a rectangular lever forward and backward.</English>
		<Italian>Unità di arcieri stile Clockpunk</Italian>
		<Polish>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Kusza Samopowtarzlna[COLOR_REVERT] to automatyczna broń miotjąca wynaleziona przez Leonarda Da Vinci.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_REPEATING_CROSSBOWMAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Repeating Crossbowman[COLOR_REVERT] is an alt-timeline Da Vinci/Clockpunk unit. It has an incredibly good ranged attack, but is crap on defense.</English>
		<Italian>Il balestriere a ripetizione è un'unità in stile Clockpunk. Ha un ottimo attacco a distanza, ma soffre in fase difensiva.</Italian>
		<Polish>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Kusza Samopowtarzlna[COLOR_REVERT] to automatyczna broń miotjąca wynaleziona przez Leonarda Da Vinci.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ZEPHYR</Tag>
		<English>Zephyr</English>
		<Italian>Zefiro</Italian>
		<Polish>Zefir</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ZEPHYR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Airships are popular forms of transport in clockpunk stories. Varieties of airships vary widely. One of the main types of airship is known as non-rigid, but such airships are commonly called Zephyrs. They are uncommon in steampunk stories, wherein the preference is for a more industrial and mechanical aesthetic. Semi-rigid airships are slightly more common and are slightly larger than non-rigid types. They also contain an internal support structure known as a keel.</English>
		<Italian>Unità da combattimento aereo Clockpunk</Italian>
		<Polish>W 1851 roku Henri Jules Giffard zgłosił patent na zastosowanie maszyny parowej do napędu statków powietrznych. Opracował pierwowzór sterowca - balon wyposażony w śmigło napędzane maszyną parową o mocy 2,2 kW. 24 września 1852 wzniósł się z hipodromu w Paryżu na wysokość 1800 m i pokonał 27-kilometrową trasę do Elancourt koło Trappes z prędkością około 8 km/h. 9 sierpnia 1884 r. w Chalais-Meudon kpt. Charles Renard (1847-1905) i kpt. Arthur Krebs (1850-1935) pokonali 7,6-kilometrową trasę sterowcem La France z prędkością niemal 20 km/h (5,5 m/s). Sterowiec o wydłużonym kształcie miał podwieszoną gondolę, na końcu której był zamocowany silnik elektryczny o mocy 6,6 kW ze śmigłem. Statkiem kierowano za pomocą steru.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ZEPHYR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Zephyr[COLOR_REVERT] is an alt-timeline Da Vinci/Clockpunk unit. It was sort of concieved as a wooden sailing ship held up by a balloon.</English>
		<Italian>Lo zefiro è un'unità in stile Clockpunk. Era ideato come una nave di legno sospesa in aria da una mongolfiera.</Italian>
		<Polish>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Zefir[COLOR_REVERT] to renesansowy sterowiec z czasów Leonarda Da Vinci.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
