<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_JAMES_1</Tag>
		<English>I come in peace to ask for assistance. What do you say?</English>
		<French>Je suis venu en paix vous demander de l'aide. Qu'avez-vous à répondre?</French>
		<German>Ich komme in Frieden und bitte um Unterstützung. Wie lautet Eure Antwort?</German>
		<Italian>Vengo in pace alla ricerca di aiuto. Cosa mi rispondi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vengo en son de paz a pedir ayuda. ¿Qué me decís?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Przybywam w pokoju. Czy pomożesz mi?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_JAMES_1</Tag>
		<English>I hold the fate of the [CT_EMPIRE] in my hand. Give me what I demand.</English>
		<French>Je tiens le destin de l'[CT_EMPIRE] dans ma main. Donnez-moi ce que j'exige.</French>
		<German>Ich halte das Schicksal vom [CT_EMPIRE:3] in meinen Händen. Gebt mir, was ich verlange.</German>
		<Italian>Ho nelle mani il destino di [CT_EMPIRE]. Dammi ciò che chiedo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tengo el destino del [CT_EMPIRE] en mis manos. Dadme lo que os exijo.</Spanish>
		<Polish>W moich rękach leży los [CT_EMPIRE]. Daj mi czego się domagam.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_JAMES_1</Tag>
		<English>My town folks are in need, can the [CT_EMPIRE] help?</English>
		<French>Ma personnes est dans le besoin, l'[CT_EMPIRE] peut-il nous aider?</French>
		<German>Mein Stamm ist in Not, kann uns das [CT_EMPIRE:2] helfen?</German>
		<Italian>La mia tribù ha bisogno di aiuto, potete aiutarci?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mi puebla está necesitada. ¿Podrá ayudarnos el [CT_EMPIRE]?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Mieszkańcy mojego imperium potrzebują Twojej pomocy. Pomożesz?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JAMES_1</Tag>
		<English>Hello. I am [OUR_NAME], an outlaw of [OUR_CIV_ADJ] township. I consider you a friend. It is in your best interest that I never change that opinion.</English>
		<Polish>Witam. Jestem [OUR_NAME], Bandyta z [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Traktuję Cię jak przyjaciela. W Twoim interesie leży nie zmieniać tego statusu.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_JAMES_1</Tag>
		<English>It is good to hear from the [CT_EMPIRE]. To what do I owe this honor?</English>
		<French>Quel plaisir d'avoir de vos nouvelles! Que me vaut cet honneur? </French>
		<German>Es ist gut, etwas vom [CT_EMPIRE:3] zu hören. Womit haben wir diese Ehre verdient?</German>
		<Italian>È bello avere notizie da [CT_EMPIRE]. A cosa debbo quest'onore?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es un placer oír al [CT_EMPIRE]. ¿A qué debo este honor?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dobrze usłyszeć znajomy głos z CT_EMPIRE]. Czym mogę służyć?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_JAMES_1</Tag>
		<English>You have started down a path that will lead to your destruction. Feel free to try to explain yourself.</English>
		<French>Vous vous êtes engagé sur la voie qui menera à votre destruction. J'attends vos explications.  </French>
		<German>Ihr habt begonnen, einen Pfad zu beschreiten, der zu Eurer Vernichtung führen wird. Wollt Ihr Euch möglicherweise rechtfertigen?</German>
		<Italian>Ti sei avviato lungo un cammino che porterà alla tua distruzione. Prova pure a cercare di spiegarti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Habéis hollado una senda que os llevará a la destrucción. Intentad explicaros como queráis.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wstąpiłeś na ściężkę, która doprowadzi Cię do zguby. Masz coś na usprawiedliwienie?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_JAMES_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace? Never!</English>
		<French>La paix? Jamais!</French>
		<German>Frieden? Niemals!</German>
		<Italian>Pace? Mai!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Paz? ¡Jamás!</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pokój? Nigdy!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_JAMES_1</Tag>
		<English>You want to talk? It is a little too late for that.</English>
		<French>Vous voulez parler? C'est un peu tard pour ça.</French>
		<German>Ihr wollt reden? Dafür ist es etwas zu spät.</German>
		<Italian>Vuoi parlare? È un po' troppo tardi per farlo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Ahora queréis hablar? Es un poco tarde para eso.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Chcesz rozmawiać? Niestety jest już na to zbyt późno.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JAMES</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Jesse James</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>James</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>James</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>James</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>James</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JAMES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Jesse Woodson James[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]American outlaw[NEWLINE]Lived: [\BOLD]c.September 5, 1847 – April 3, 1882[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]was an American outlaw, gang leader, bank robber, train robber, and murderer from the state of Missouri and the most famous member of the James-Younger Gang. Already a celebrity when he was alive, he became a legendary figure of the Wild West after his death. Some recent scholars place him in the context of regional insurgencies of ex-Confederates following the American Civil War rather than a manifestation of frontier lawlessness or alleged economic justice. [PARAGRAPH:1]Jesse and his brother Frank James were Confederate guerrillas during the Civil War. They were accused of participating in atrocities committed against Union soldiers. After the war, as members of one gang or another, they robbed banks, stagecoaches and trains. Despite popular portrayals of James as a kind of Robin Hood, robbing from the rich and giving to the poor, there is no evidence that he and his gang used their robbery gains for anyone but themselves. [PARAGRAPH:1]The James brothers were most active with their gang from about 1866 until 1876, when their attempted robbery of a bank in Northfield, Minnesota, resulted in the capture or deaths of several members. They continued in crime for several years, recruiting new members, but were under increasing pressure from law enforcement. On April 3, 1882, Jesse James was killed by Robert Ford, who was a member of the gang living in the James house and who was hoping to collect a state reward on James' head.Jesse Woodson James was born in Clay County, Missouri, near the site of present day Kearney, on September 5, 1847. Jesse James had two full siblings: his older brother, Alexander Franklin "Frank", and a younger sister, Susan Lavenia James. Across a creek and up a hill from the house on the right was the home of Daniel Askew, where Askew was killed on April 12, 1875. Askew was suspected of cooperating with the Pinkertons in the January 1875 arson of the house (in a room on the left). James's original grave was on the property but he was later moved to a cemetery in Kearney. The original footstone is still outside, although the family has replaced the headstone.His father, Robert S. James, was a commercial hemp farmer and Baptist minister in Kentucky, who migrated to Bradford, Missouri, after marriage and helped found William Jewell College in Liberty, Missouri. He was prosperous, acquiring six slaves and more than 100 acres (0.40 km2) of farmland. Robert James traveled to California during the Gold Rush to minister to those searching for gold and died there when Jesse was three years old.After Robert James' death, his widow Zerelda remarried twice, first to Benjamin Simms and then in 1855 to Dr. Reuben Samuel, who moved into the James home. Jesse's mother and Reuben Samuel had four children together: Sarah Louisa, John Thomas, Fannie Quantrell, and Archie Peyton Samuel. Zerelda and Reuben Samuel acquired a total of seven slaves, who served mainly as farmhands in tobacco cultivation in Missouri.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Jesse Woodson James[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Amerykańki Bandyta[NEWLINE]Żył: [\BOLD]5 Września 1847 -– 3 Kwietnia 1882[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]was an American outlaw, gang leader, bank robber, train robber, and murderer from the state of Missouri and the most famous member of the James-Younger Gang. Already a celebrity when he was alive, he became a legendary figure of the Wild West after his death. Some recent scholars place him in the context of regional insurgencies of ex-Confederates following the American Civil War rather than a manifestation of frontier lawlessness or alleged economic justice. [PARAGRAPH:1]Jesse and his brother Frank James were Confederate guerrillas during the Civil War. They were accused of participating in atrocities committed against Union soldiers. After the war, as members of one gang or another, they robbed banks, stagecoaches and trains. Despite popular portrayals of James as a kind of Robin Hood, robbing from the rich and giving to the poor, there is no evidence that he and his gang used their robbery gains for anyone but themselves. [PARAGRAPH:1]The James brothers were most active with their gang from about 1866 until 1876, when their attempted robbery of a bank in Northfield, Minnesota, resulted in the capture or deaths of several members. They continued in crime for several years, recruiting new members, but were under increasing pressure from law enforcement. On April 3, 1882, Jesse James was killed by Robert Ford, who was a member of the gang living in the James house and who was hoping to collect a state reward on James' head.Jesse Woodson James was born in Clay County, Missouri, near the site of present day Kearney, on September 5, 1847. Jesse James had two full siblings: his older brother, Alexander Franklin "Frank", and a younger sister, Susan Lavenia James. Across a creek and up a hill from the house on the right was the home of Daniel Askew, where Askew was killed on April 12, 1875. Askew was suspected of cooperating with the Pinkertons in the January 1875 arson of the house (in a room on the left). James's original grave was on the property but he was later moved to a cemetery in Kearney. The original footstone is still outside, although the family has replaced the headstone.His father, Robert S. James, was a commercial hemp farmer and Baptist minister in Kentucky, who migrated to Bradford, Missouri, after marriage and helped found William Jewell College in Liberty, Missouri. He was prosperous, acquiring six slaves and more than 100 acres (0.40 km2) of farmland. Robert James traveled to California during the Gold Rush to minister to those searching for gold and died there when Jesse was three years old.After Robert James' death, his widow Zerelda remarried twice, first to Benjamin Simms and then in 1855 to Dr. Reuben Samuel, who moved into the James home. Jesse's mother and Reuben Samuel had four children together: Sarah Louisa, John Thomas, Fannie Quantrell, and Archie Peyton Samuel. Zerelda and Reuben Samuel acquired a total of seven slaves, who served mainly as farmhands in tobacco cultivation in Missouri.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
