<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOCALYPSE_URBAN_CROSSBOWMAN</Tag>
		<English>Post-apocalyptic Urban Crossbowman</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Arbalétrier urbain</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Balestriere urbano:Balestrieri urbani</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Miejski Kusznik</Polish>
		<Russian>Áîåö ñ ñàìîñòðåëîì</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOCALYPSE_URBAN_CROSSBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In the years following the Great War, the United States devolved into a post-apocalyptic environment commonly dubbed "the Wasteland". The War and subsequent nuclear Armageddon has severely depopulated the country, leaving large expanses of property decaying from neglect. In addition, virtually all food and water is irradiated and radiation exposure, combined with a mutagenic bioweapon that was accidentally released into the atmosphere during the War, have caused mutation in nearly all forms of life. With a large portion of the country's infrastructure in ruins, basic necessities are scarce. Barter is the common method of exchange, with bottlecaps providing a more conventional form of currency. Most cities and towns are empty, having been looted and deserted in favor of smaller, makeshift communities scattered around the Wasteland.</English>
		<Italian>Il [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]balestriere urbano[COLOR_REVERT] è un'unità post-apocalittica.</Italian>
		<Polish>Fantastyka postapokaliptyczna - wizja, konwencja traktująca o wydarzeniach bezpośrednio po kataklizmie, apokalipsie. W książkach lub filmach fabuła rozgrywa się zazwyczaj po wojnie jądrowej, pandemii lub katastrofie ekologicznej. Ziemia staje się wówczas areną dla ludzi czerpiących z resztek zniszczonej cywilizacji, starających się przetrwać i przystosować do niesprzyjających warunków.</Polish>
		<Russian>Â ãîäû ïîñëå Âåëèêîé âîéíû Ñîåäèíåííûå Øòàòû ïðåâðàòèëèñü â ïîñòàïîêàëèïòè÷åñêóþ òåððèòîðèþ, íàçâàííóþ "ïóñòîøüþ". Âîéíû è ïîñëåäîâàâøèé çà íèìè ÿäåðíûé Àðìàãåääîí, ñèëüíî ñîêðàòèëè íàñåëåíèå, îñòàâèâ ãîðîäñêóþ èíôðàñòðóêòóðó ðàçðóøàòüñÿ â çàïóñòåíèè. Êðîìå òîãî, ïðàêòè÷åñêè âñå ïðîäîâîëüñòâèå è âîäà ïîäâåðãëèñü ðàäèàöèîííîìó îáëó÷åíèþ. Â ñî÷åòàíèè ñ ìóòàãåííûì äåéñòâèåì áèîëîãè÷åñêîãî îðóæèÿ, ñëó÷àéíî ïîïàâøåãî â àòìîñôåðó âî âðåìÿ âîéíû, ýòî âûçâàëî ìóòàöèè ïðàêòè÷åñêè âñåõ ôîðì æèçíè. Áîëüøàÿ ÷àñòü ñòðàíû ïðåâðàùåíà â ðóèíû, â äåôèöèòå âñå ñàìîå íåîáõîäèìîå. Ðàñïðîñòðàíåí ñïîñîá îáìåíà ñ ïðîáêàìè âìåñòî îáû÷íûõ äåíåã. Áîëüøèíñòâî ãîðîäîâ áåçëþäíû è ðàçãðàáëåíû. Èõ çàìåíèëè íåáîëüøèå, èìïðîâèçèðîâàííûå îáùèíû, ðàçáðîñàííûå ïî ïóñòîøè.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CROWBAR_GUARD</Tag>
		<English>Post-apocalyptic Crowbar Guard</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Combattant au pied-de-biche</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guardia con piede di porco:Guardie con piede di porco</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Strażnik z łomem</Polish>
		<Russian>Áîåö ñ ãâîçäîäåðîì</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HATCHET_MAN</Tag>
		<English>Post-apocalyptic Hatchet Warrior</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Combattant avec hachette</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guerriero con accetta:Guerrieri con accetta</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Wojownik z siekierą</Polish>
		<Russian>Áîåö ñ òåñàêîì</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MACHETE_WARRIOR</Tag>
		<English>Post-apocalyptic Machete Warrior</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Combattant avec machette</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guerriero con machete:Guerrieri con machete</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Wojownik z maczetą</Polish>
		<Russian>Áîåö ñ ìà÷åòå</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_POST_APOCALYPTIC_GRENADIER</Tag>
		<English>Post-apocalyptic Molotov Cocktail Thrower</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Lanceur de cocktail molotov</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Lanciatore di cocktail molotov:Lanciatori di cocktail molotov</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Miotacz koktajli Mołotowa</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïèðîìàí</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_URBAN_HORSEMAN</Tag>
		<English>Post-apocalyptic Urban Horseman</English>
		<French>Cavalier Urbain</French>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Jinete urbano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Nowoczesna Konnica</Polish>
		<Russian>Ãîðîäñêîé âñàäíèê</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_URBAN_HORSEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Urban horsemen have resorted to using horses instead of mechanized vehicles, because computerized vehicles are vulnerable to cyber attacks and are more easily located by tracking devices and scanning equipment. The horse is a low tech solution to a problem created by advanced technology. These mounted urban soldiers are propelled by their desparation and their hope that any change will be for the better.</English>
		<Polish>Nowoczesna Konnica to jednostka, którą możesz zwerbowac jeśli z jakiś powodów nie masz dostępu do nowoczesnych pojazdów.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WRENCH_WARRIOR</Tag>
		<English>Post-apocalyptic Wrench Warrior</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Combattant avec clé à molette</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guerriero con chiave inglese:Guerrieri con chiave inglese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Wojownik z kluczem fr.</Polish>
		<Russian>Ñëåñàðü</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
