<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_JIVARO_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Jivaro</English>
		<Polish>Jiwaro</Polish>
		<Russian>õèâàðî</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_JIVARO_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Jivaro Empire</English>
		<French>Empire jivaro</French>
		<Italian>Impero Jivaro</Italian>
		<Polish>Imperium Jiwaro</Polish>
		<Russian>Ïëåìÿ õèâàðî</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_JIVARO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Although there were many headhunting cultures throughout the world, only one group was known for ancient practice of shrinking human heads (tsantsa). They were called the Jivaro clan who lived deep in the Ecuadorian, and neighboring Peruvian Amazon. The Jivaros are one of the most primitive societies that have caught the attention of the Western world because of their unusual customs.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Jivaroan tribes are comprised of four sub-tribes or dialect groups known to inhabit the tropical forest of the Ecuadorian and Peruvian Amazon. The AShuar, Aguaruna, Huambisa, and the Shuar. Of these, the Shuar, are most commonly referred to when speaking of the Jivaro Indians. The Shuar have achieved their notoriety through their customary practice of head-shrinking. The Jivaros are the only tribe known to have successfully revolted against the Spanish Empire and to have been able to thwart all subsequent attempts by the Spaniards to conquer them. They have withstood armies of gold-seeking Incas and defied the brovado of the early conquistadors. The Jivaro Indians are known to be an intensely warlike group, tremendously protective of their freedom and unwilling to subordinate themselves to other authorities. The Jivaro Indians have a reputation for their fierceness which distinguishes them from their counterparts based on the savageness directed toward their enemies. Early Spanish chronicles relate that in the year 1599, the Jivaros banded together and killed 25,000 white people in raids on two settlements. In particular, the massacre of the Logrono stands out as particularly ruthless. The attack was instigated over the natives being taxed in their gold-trade. After uncovering the unscrupulous practices of the visiting governor, molten gold was later poured down his throat until his bowels burst. Following his execution, the remaining Spaniards were killed along with the older women and children. The younger useful women were taken as prisoners to join the clan. The settlement itself was raided and burned to the ground. From this point onward, the Jivaro Indians remained unconquered despite the fact that they inhabited one of the richest regions in South America for gold deposits. The Jivaro's fierce fighting reputation and head-shrinking practice continued to discourage outsiders from entering their territories.[PARAGRAPH:2]Within the vast region of the Amazon a perpetual animosity existed between the neighboring tribes of the Jivaro. Once again, due to the fervent belief in witch craft and sorcery this was the primary cause of warfare between the tribes. A fundamental difference between wars enacted within the same tribe and against neighboring tribes is such that " wars between different tribes are in principle wars of extermination" A significant goal of these wars was geared toward the annihilation of the enemy tribe, including women and children. This was done in order to prevent them from seeking revenge against the victors in the future. There were however, many instances where the women and children were taken as prisoners and forced to become a part of the victors families. It is solely in these wars that trophies/tsantsa were taken. The Jivaros consistently engaged in this practice toward their mortal enemies.[PARAGRAPH:2]As wars between tribal cultures were not instigated with the hope of acquiring additional territory, as soon as fighting was over, the victorious tribesmen made a hasty retreat. Superstitious fear and contempt of the enemy compelled the Jivaros to abandon the area quickly where they believed that secret supernatural dangers would threaten them after they had conquered their natural enemies. Should blood revenge have continued at the extreme rate of the early 1900's, extermination was evident. Through the work of missionaries, the killing slowly subsided. Today, in a relatively calm existence, superstitions are still very strong, but the harm done to past ancestors is not forgotten.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Jivaro by nature are a highly superstitious and impulsive people, thereby giving rise to frequent disputes and wars between each other, as well as between neighboring tribes. Because witchcraft and sorcery can account for the majority of murders and natural deaths within a tribe, it is not surprising that the medicine men, or shamans, are most susceptible to attack as they are frequently accused of using their powers against others. Each tribe is thereby compelled to kill the opposing medicine man to free themselves of his evil magic. On the whole, the Jivaro Indians do subscribe to the notion of a natural death, but rather attributed each death to supernatural causes. Following each death a vicious cycle of retaliation ensues in which someone is always held accountable for the murder of another. As the Jivaro Indian is consumed with the notion of retaliation, his " desire for revenge is an expression of his sense of justice." This cycle of blood-revenge is perpetuated by religious reasons by which the soul of the victim requires that his relatives should avenge his death. If the surviving members do not retaliate against the slayer, the anger of the vengeful spirit may in fact turn against themselves. If blood-revenge cannot be directed to the actual slayer, it may be directed toward one of his relations. Once a murder has been avenged, blood-guilt or tumashi akerkama is atoned for and the offended family is satisfied Male children were taught at an early age about the concept of blood revenge. The father instructs the younger men, often as young as six years of age, to listen to the various crimes that had been committed against his people. A strong sense of family justice is instilled in the minds of the young, who are later expected to avenge previous injustices committed against their family members. Further incentive is encouraged by the notion of reward, including blessings, good luck, long life and many opportunities to kill one's enemy. It must be noted that trophies/ tsantsa were not taken during the disputes between blood-relatives.</English>
		<Polish>Jiwaro - grupa plemion indiańskich żyjących w Ekwadorze (wschodnie skłony Andów - tzw. region Montańa) oraz północno-wschodnim Peru (na północ od rzeki Marańón). Zajmują się uprawą batatów i ryżu, zbieractwem, rybołówstwem i myślistwem. Bitni wojownicy - słynni łowcy głów, znani z techniki preparowania ich do rozmiarów owocu pomarańczy (tzw. tsantsa, których posiadanie daje zgodnie z wierzeniami Jiwaro nadnaturalną siłę). Preparowanie polega na wygotowaniu zdjętej uprzednio skóry, którą następnie wypełnia się gorącymi kamykami i piaskiem - po wychłodzeniu ulega ona silnemu skurczeniu. Populację Jiwaro szacuje się obecnie na około 20 tys.</Polish>
		<Russian>[NEWLINE][TAB]Хотя во всем мире существовало много культур охоты за головами, только одна группа была известна древней практикой уменьшения человеческих голов (цанца). Их называли племенем хиваро, жившим в глубине Эквадора и соседней перуанской Амазонки. Хиваро - одно из самых примитивных обществ, которое привлекло внимание западного мира из-за своих необычных обычаев.[PARAGRAPH:2]Племена хиваро состоят из четырех подплемен или диалектных групп, населяющих тропические леса эквадорской и перуанской Амазонии: Ашуар, Агуаруна, Хуамбиса и Шуар. Из них чаще всего упоминаются шуары, когда говорят об индейцах дживаро. Шуар добились своей известности благодаря своей обычной практике уменьшения головы. Хиваро - единственное известное племя, которое успешно восстало против Испанской империи и сумело помешать всем последующим попыткам испанцев покорить их. Они противостояли армиям инков, ищущих золото, и бросили вызов броваду ранних конкистадоров. Индейцы хиваро известны как крайне воинственная группа, чрезвычайно защищающая свою свободу и не желающая подчиняться другим властям. Индейцы хиваро имеют репутацию свирепости, которая отличает их от своих собратьев, основанная на жестокости по отношению к своим врагам. Ранние испанские хроники рассказывают, что в 1599 году хиваро объединились и убили 25 000 белых людей в набегах на два поселения. В частности, резня в Логроньо выделяется как особо безжалостная. Нападение было спровоцировано тем, что туземцев облагали налогами при торговле золотом. После того, как он раскрыл недобросовестные действия посетившего его губернатора, расплавленное золото было позже вылито ему в горло, пока его кишечник не лопнул. После его казни оставшиеся испанцы были убиты вместе со старшими женщинами и детьми. Более молодые полезные женщины были взяты в плен и присоединились к клану. Само поселение подверглось нападению и сожжено дотла. С этого момента индейцы хиваро остались непокоренными, несмотря на то, что они населяли один из самых богатых месторождений золота в Южной Америке. Ожесточенная боевая репутация хиваро и его умопомрачительная практика продолжали удерживать посторонних от проникновения на их территории. [PARAGRAPH:2]В обширном регионе Амазонии между соседними племенами хиваро существовала вечная вражда. Еще раз, из-за горячей веры в колдовство и колдовство, это было основной причиной войны между племенами. Фундаментальное различие между войнами, разыгрываемыми внутри одного и того же племени, и войнами против соседних племен состоит в том, что «войны между различными племенами в принципе являются войнами на истребление». Важная цель этих войн была направлена ??на уничтожение вражеского племени, включая женщин и детей. Это было сделано для того, чтобы в будущем они не отомстили победителям. Однако было много случаев, когда женщин и детей брали в плен и заставляли становиться частью семей победителей. Только в этих войнах брали трофеи/цанца. Хиваро постоянно применяли эту практику по отношению к своим смертельным врагам.[PARAGRAPH:2]Поскольку войны между племенными культурами не разжигались с надеждой на захват дополнительных территорий, как только боевые действия заканчивались, победившие соплеменники поспешно отступали. Суеверный страх и презрение к врагу вынудили хиваро быстро покинуть местность, где, по их мнению, им угрожали тайные сверхъестественные опасности после того, как они победили своих естественных врагов. Если кровавая месть продолжалась с чрезвычайной скоростью начала 1900-х годов, истребление было очевидным. Благодаря работе миссионеров убийства постепенно утихли. Сегодня при относительно спокойном существовании суеверия все еще очень сильны, но не забыт вред, нанесенный прошлым предкам.[PARAGRAPH:2]Хиваро по своей природе очень суеверные и импульсивные люди, из-за чего часто возникают споры и войны между собой, а также между соседними племенами. Поскольку колдовство и колдовство могут быть причиной большинства убийств и естественных смертей в племени, неудивительно, что знахари или шаманы наиболее подвержены нападениям, поскольку их часто обвиняют в использовании своих сил против других. Таким образом, каждое племя вынуждено убить вражеского знахаря, чтобы освободиться от его злой магии. В целом индейцы хиваро придерживаются концепции естественной смерти, а скорее приписывают каждую смерть сверхъестественным причинам. После каждой смерти следует замкнутый круг возмездия, в котором кто-то всегда несет ответственность за убийство другого. Поскольку индеец хиваро поглощен идеей возмездия, его «желание мести является выражением его чувства справедливости». Этот цикл кровной мести увековечивается религиозными причинами, по которым душа жертвы требует, чтобы его родственники отомстили за его смерть. Если выжившие члены не предпримут ответных действий против убийцы, гнев мстительного духа может фактически обратиться против них самих. Если кровная месть не может быть направлена ??на настоящего убийцы, она может быть направлена ??на одного из его родственников. После отмщения за убийство искупается кровная вина или тумаси акеркама, и обиженная семья получает полное удовлетворение. Детей мужского пола с раннего возраста учили концепции кровной мести. Отец наставляет молодых людей, зачастую даже шестилетнего возраста, выслушать различные преступления, совершенные против его народа. В сознании молодых людей прививается сильное чувство семейной справедливости, от которых позже ожидается, что они отомстят за предыдущую несправедливость, совершенную в отношении членов их семей. Дополнительный стимул поощряется понятием награды, включающей благословения, удачу, долгую жизнь и множество возможностей убить врага. Следует отметить, что трофеи/цанцы не брались во время споров между кровными родственниками.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_JIVARO_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Head Hunters</English>
		<French>Jivaros</French>
		<Italian>Cacciatori di teste</Italian>
		<Polish>Jiwaro</Polish>
		<Russian>Õèâàðî</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>