<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CLEOPATRA_1</Tag>
		<English>Do not underestimate our resolve, [CT_NAME]. All strange and terrible events are welcome by the [OUR_EMPIRE], but comforts we despise.</English>
		<French>Ne sous-estimez pas ma détermination, [CT_NAME]. Tous les événements étranges et terribles sont les bienvenus par le [OUR_EMPIRE], mais nous méprisons confort.</French>
		<German>Unterschätze unsere Entschlossenhait nicht, [CT_NAME]. Alle seltsamen und schrecklichen Ereignisse sind willkommen im [OUR_EMPIRE], aber wir verabscheuen die Bequemlichkeit.</German>
		<Spanish>No subestimes nuestra determinación, [CT_NAME]. Todos los sucesos extraños y terribles son bienvenidos por el [OUR_EMPIRE], solamente despreciamos las comodidades.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Nie przeceniaj naszych rozwiązań, [CT_NAME]. Wszystkie dziwne i straszne wydarzenia są mile widziane w granicach naszego imperium, ale spokój cenimy najbardziej.</Polish>
		<Russian>Не стоит недооценивать нашу решимость, [CT_NAME]. [OUR_EMPIRE] готов встретить все странные и ужасные события, а негу и праздность мы порицаем.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CLEOPATRA</Tag>
		<English>Cleopatra</English>
		<French>Clèopatre</French>
		<Polish>Kleopatra</Polish>
		<Russian>Êëåîïàòðà</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CLEOPATRA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Cleopatra VII[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Pharaoh of Egypt[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates:[\BOLD] 69-30 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Cleopatra VII Thea Philopator was a Hellenistic ruler of Egypt, originally sharing power with her father Ptolemy XII and later with her brothers/husbands Ptolemy XIII and Ptolemy XIV; eventually gaining sole rule of Egypt.[PARAGRAPH:1]Cleopatra's mother was Cleopatra V of Egypt who co-ruled Egypt with another daughter, Berenice IV, for a year before her death yet Cleopatra, borne of the union with Ptolemy XII Auletes, was a direct descendant of Alexander the Great's general, Ptolemy I Soter, son of Arsinoe and Lacus, both of Macedon. Ptolemy XII died in March 51 BC, making the 17-year-old Cleopatra and her brother, the 12-year-old Ptolemy XIII joint monarchs. The first three years of their reign were difficult, due to economic difficulties, famine, deficient floods of the Nile, and political conflicts. Although Cleopatra was married to her young brother, she quickly showed indications that she had no intentions of sharing power with him.[PARAGRAPH:1]As Pharaoh, she consummated a liaison with Gaius Julius Caesar that solidified her grip on the throne, and, after Caesar's assassination, aligned with Mark Antony, with whom she produced twins. Eager to take advantage of Julius Caesar's anger with Ptolemy, Queen Cleopatra returned to the palace rolled into a Persian carpet and had it presented to Caesar by her servants: when it was unrolled, Cleopatra tumbled out. It is believed that Caesar was charmed by the gesture, and she became his mistress. Despite the almost thirty year age difference, Cleopatra and Caesar became lovers during his stay in Egypt between 48 BC and 47 BC. They met when they were 21 (Cleopatra) and 50 (Caesar). On 23 June 47 BC Cleopatra gave birth to a child, Ptolemy Caesar (nicknamed "Caesarion" which means "little Caesar").[PARAGRAPH:1]In 42 BC, Mark Antony, one of the triumvirs who ruled Rome in the power vacuum following Caesar's death, summoned Cleopatra to meet him in Tarsus to answer questions about her loyalty. Cleopatra arrived in great state, and so charmed Antony that he chose to spend the winter of 41 BC–40 BC with her in Alexandria. On 25 December 40 BC she gave birth to two children Alexander Helios and Cleopatra Selene II. In all, Cleopatra had four children, one by Caesar (Caesarion) and three by Antony (Cleopatra Selene II, Alexander Helios, and Ptolemy Philadelphus). Her unions with her brothers produced no children. It is possible that they were never consummated; in any case, they were not close. Her reign marks the end of the Hellenistic Era and the beginning of the Roman Era in the eastern Mediterranean. She was the last Pharaoh of Ancient Egypt (her son by Julius Caesar, Caesarion, ruled in name only before Augustus had him executed).[PARAGRAPH:1]Though she bore the ancient Egyptian title Pharaoh, her primary language was Greek; for several centuries preceding her rule, Egyptian kings had been of Greek (i.e. Hellenistic) origin rather than Egyptian origin. The establishment of a Greek-speaking aristocracy in Egypt had come with Alexander the Great nearly 300 years before. Cleopatra is reputed to have been the first member of her family in their 300-year reign in Egypt to have learned the Egyptian language. The Ptolemaic dynasty had maintained their Greek heritage at the expense of Egyptian religion, and while the populace of Egypt used the Demotic script to write, the ancient system of writing with hieroglyphics, which had primarily been used by priests, was falling into disuse. Cleopatra adopted common Egyptian beliefs and deities. Her patron goddess was Isis, and thus during her reign, it was believed that she was the re-incarnation and embodiment of the goddess of wisdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]After Antony and Cleopatra were defeated at Actium by their rival and Caesar's legal heir, Gaius Julius Caesar Octavian (who later became the first Roman Emperor, Augustus), Cleopatra committed suicide, the traditional date being 12 August 30 BC, allegedly by means of an asp bite. Cleopatra's son by Caesar, Caesarion, was proclaimed pharaoh by the Egyptians, but Octavian had already won. Caesarion was captured and executed, his fate reportedly sealed by Octavian's famous phrase: "Two Caesars are one too many." This ended not just the Hellenistic line of Egyptian pharaohs, but the line of all Egyptian pharaohs. The three children of Cleopatra and Antony were spared and taken back to Rome where they were taken care of by Antony's wife, Octavia Minor.[PARAGRAPH:1]To this day she remains popular in Western culture. Her legacy survives in numerous works of art and the many dramatizations of her story in literature.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Kleopatra VII[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Faraon Egiptu[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Daty:[\BOLD] 69-30 p.n.e.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Ostatnia królowa hellenistycznego Egiptu, panująca w latach 51-30 p.n.e. Nosiła tytuły Królowa, Nowa Bogini, Bogini Miłująca Ojca, Bogini Miłująca Ojczyznę. Była córką Ptolemeusza XII Auletesa. Po wstąpieniu na tron poślubiła swego brata Ptolemeusza XIII. Na skutek intryg dworskich opuściła Egipt i udała się do Palestyny, gdzie zdobyła poparcie Cezara, z którym miała syna, Ptolemeusza XV Cezariona. Dzięki interwencji wojskowej Cezara powróciła na tron egipski. Po śmierci Ptolemeusza XIII, który zginął na skutek zamieszek antyrzymskich w Aleksandrii, Kleopatra poślubiła drugiego brata, Ptolemeusza XIV. Z drugim małźonkiem odbyła podróź do Rzymu w celu wzmocnienia więzi politycznych pomiędzy obydwoma państwami. Po śmierci Cezara, powróciła do Egiptu i rozkazała zamordować małźonka, po czym w imieniu małoletniego Cezariona objęła rządy.</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Клеопатра VII[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Фараон Египта[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни:[\BOLD] 69-30 гг. до н.э.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Клеопатра VII Теа Филопатор была эллинистическим правителем Египта, первоначально разделявшая власть со своим отцом Птолемеем XII, а затем со своими братьями/мужьями Птолемеем XIII и Птолемеем XIV; в конце концов обретает единоличную власть в Египте.[PARAGRAPH:1]Мать Клеопатры была Клеопатрой V из Египта, которая управляла Египтом вместе с другой дочерью, Береникой (Вероникой) IV, за год до ее смерти, но Клеопатра, рожденная в союзе с Птолемеем XII Авлетом, была прямым потомком Птолемея I Сотера - одного из полководцев Александра Македонского, сына Арсинои и Лага, оба из Македонии. Птолемей XII умер в марте 51 г. до н.э., сделав 17-летнюю Клеопатру и ее брата 12-летним Птолемеем XIII совместными монархами. Первые три года их правления были неоднозначными из-за экономических трудностей, голода, недостаточного разлива Нила и политических конфликтов. Хотя Клеопатра была замужем за своим младшим братом, она быстро показала признаки того, что она не собиралась делиться с ним властью.[PARAGRAPH:1]Будучи фараоном, она вступила в связь с Гаем Юлием Цезарем, который укрепил ее власть на троне, и, после убийства Цезаря она сближается уже с Марком Антонием, которому она родила близнецов. Воспользовавшись некогда гневом Юлия Цезаря на Птолемея, царица Клеопатра вернулась во дворец, завернутой согласно преданию в персидский ковер с помощью преданной служанки. Когда римский военачальник велел развернуть ковер, то его взору предстала юная царица Египта. Считается, что Цезарь был очарован этим жестом, и с той поры она стала его любовницей. Несмотря на почти тридцатилетнюю разницу в возрасте, Клеопатра и Цезарь стали любовниками во время своего пребывания в Египте между 48 г. до н.э. и 47 г. до н.э. Они встретились, когда им было 21 (Клеопатра) и 50 (Цезарь). 23 июня 47 г. до н.э. Клеопатра родила ребенка, Птолемея Цезаря (прозванного сплетниками «Цезарион», что означает «Цезареныш»).[PARAGRAPH:1]В 42 г. до н.э. Марк Антоний, один из триумвиров, правивших Римом после вакуума власти, возникшего после убийства Юлия Цезаря, обратился с письмом к Клеопатре с просьбой о встрече в Тарсе, чтобы получить заверения о ее преданности. Клеопатра прибыла к месту встречи в самых изысканных одениях и настолько очаровала Антония, что он решил провести зиму 41 г. до н.э. - 40 г. до н.э. с ней в Александрии. 25 декабря 40 г. до н.э. у нее родились двое детей: Александр Гелиос и Клеопатра Селена II. Всего у Клеопатры было четверо детей, один от Цезаря (Цезарион) и трое от Антония (Клеопатра Селена II, Александр Гелиос и Птолемей Филадельф). От ее союзов с братьями, напротив, не было детей. Ее правление знаменует конец эллинистической эры и начало римской эры в восточной части Средиземного моря. Она была последним фараоном Древнего Египта (ее сын Юлия Цезаря, Цезарион, правил по имени только до того, как Август казнил его).[PARAGRAPH:1]Хотя она носила древнеегипетский титул фараона, ее родным языком был греческий; в течение нескольких веков, предшествовавших ее правлению, египетские цари имели греческое (то есть эллинистическое), а не египетское происхождение. Появление грекоязычной аристократии связано с завоеваниями Александра Великого за 300 лет до указанных событий. Клеопатра считается первым членом династии за 300 лет правления в Египте, изучившим египетский язык. Династия Птолемеев сохранила свое греческое наследие за счет египетской религии, и в то время как население Египта пользовалось демотическим письмом, древняя система написания иероглифами, которая в основном использовалась жрецами, вышла из употребления. Клеопатра приняла общие египетские верования и божества. Ее богиней-покровительницей была Исида, и поэтому во время ее правления считалось, что она была реинкарнацией и воплощением богини мудрости.[PARAGRAPH:1]После того, как Антоний и Клеопатра были побеждены в Акциуме их соперником и законным наследником Цезаря Гай Юлий Цезарь Октавиан (впоследствии ставший первым римским императором Августом), Клеопатра покончила жизнь самоубийством, традиционная дата - 12 августа 30 г. до н.э., предположительно с помощью укуса аспида. Сын Клеопатры от Цезаря, Цезарион, был провозглашен фараоном египтянами, но Октавиан к тому времени уже разбил остатки войск Антония и Клеопратры. Цезарион был схвачен и казнен, его судьба, по сообщениям, решена знаменитой фразой Октавиана: «Два Цезаря - это слишком много». На этом закончилась не только эллинистическая линия египетских фараонов, но и линия всех египетских фараонов. Трое детей Клеопатры и Антония были избавлены и возвращены в Рим, где за ними ухаживала жена Антония, Октавия Младшая.[PARAGRAPH:1]По сей день она остается популярной в мировой культуре. Ее наследие сохранилось в многочисленных произведениях искусства и во многих новеллизациях ее в истории и литературе.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>