<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD1_1</Tag>
		<English>We must welcome opportunities to integrate our communities. Pay them what they ask.</English>
		<French>Nous devons favoriser ces échanges. Payez ce qu'ils demandent.</French>
		<Italian>Dobbiamo sfruttare le opportunità di integrare le comunità. Date loro ciò che vogliono</Italian>
		<Polish>Musimy takie okazje wykorzystywać dla dobra społeczności. Zapłaćcie im.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD1_1HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Gain a random resource near a city.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Obtient une ressource aléatoire près de la ville.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ottieni una risorsa casuale vicino ad una città.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Losowy surowiec pojawia się niedaleko miasta.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD1_2</Tag>
		<English>Welcome them, but decline; we cannot afford the project at this time.</English>
		<French>Accueillez-les, mais refusez leur offre. Nous ne pouvons pas nous permettre une telle dépense.</French>
		<Italian>Accoglieteli, ma rifiutate la loro offerta; non possiamo permetterci una simile spesa.</Italian>
		<Polish>Powitajcie ich, ale im nie zapłaćcie. Nie stać nas teraz na dodatowe wydatki.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD2_1</Tag>
		<English>Although some may accuse us of exploiting them, we appreciate their help and loyalty. Find them gear.</English>
		<French>Même si certains nous accuserons de profiter d'eux, nous apprécions leur aide et leur loyauté. Trouvez-leur de l'équipement.</French>
		<Italian>Anche se alcuni potrebbero accusarci di sfruttarli, noi apprezziamo il loro aiuto e la loro lealtà. Trovate loro dell'equipaggiamento.</Italian>
		<Polish>Niektórzy mogą uważać to za wykorzystywanie, ale znajdźcie im jakąś broń. Będziemy im wdzięczni.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD2_1HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Suffer 40 point increase in native anger and gain units in your capital city.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Pénalité de 40 en mécontentement. Procure des unités dans votre capitale.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Soffri una penalità di 40 punti alla rabbia dei nativi e ottieni unità nella tua capitale.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Traci 40 punktów i wzrasta niezadowolenie lokalnej ludności, ale w stolicy uzyskujesz jednostki wojowników.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD2_2</Tag>
		<English>We don't need them enough to jump into the controversy. Send them home.</English>
		<French>Nous n'avons pas besoin de troupes à ce point. Renvoyez-les à la maison.</French>
		<Italian>Non abbiamo bisogno di loro. Mandateli a casa.</Italian>
		<Polish>Nie potrzebujemy ich i kontrowersji z tym związanych. Odeślijcie ich do domu.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD3_1</Tag>
		<English>Excellent.</English>
		<Italian>Eccellente.</Italian>
		<Polish>Zwietnie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD3_1HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Gain gold from your indigenous community.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Obtient de l'or de la communauté indigène.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ottieni oro dalla comunità indigena.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Otrzymujesz złoto od społeczności tubylców.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD4</Tag>
		<English>Magnificent! I always suspected they were hiding something!</English>
		<French>Magnifique! J'ai toujours supposé qu'ils cachaient quelquechose!</French>
		<Italian>Magnifico! Sapevo che stavano nascondendo qualcosa!</Italian>
		<Polish>Niesmowiet! Zawsze podejrzewałem, że czegoś nam nie mówili!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD4_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Gain gold from your indigenous community.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Obtient de l'or de la communauté indigène.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ottieni oro dalla comunità indigena.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Otrzymujesz złoto od społeczności tubylców.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD_1</Tag>
		<English>An indigenous community has approached the %s1_civ_adjective civilization with an offer to help locate resources!</English>
		<French>Une communauté indigène est entrée en contact avec la civilisation %s1_civ_adjective, et lui a proposé de l'aider à trouver de nouvelles ressources!</French>
		<Italian>Una comunità indigena ha contattato la civiltà %s1:2_civ_adjective, con l'offerta di aiutare a localizzare risorse!</Italian>
		<Polish>Tubylcy przybyli do cywilizacji %s1_civ_adjective z ofertą pomocy zlokalizowania cennych surowców!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD_1A</Tag>
		<English>An indigenous community has approached us with an opportunity. They believe that with a little financing, they can convince their people to expose and develop a hidden resource for the use of the general public.</English>
		<French>Une communauté indigène est entrée en contact avec nous. Ils envisagent de vous indiquer l'emplacement de ressources cachées, en échange d'une petite contribution financière.</French>
		<Italian>Una comunità indigena ci ha contattati con un'opportunità. Credono che con un piccolo finanziamento possono convincere i loro simili a indicare e sviluppare una risorsa attualmente sconosciuta.</Italian>
		<Polish>Tubylcy przybyli z ciekawą ofertą. Z małą finansową pomocą zgodzili się przekazać wiedzę o położeniu i pozyskaniu cennych surowców.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD_2</Tag>
		<English>An indigenous community has approached the %s1_civ_adjective civilization with an offer to help fortify cities with native soldiers!</English>
		<French>Une communauté indigène est entrée en contact avec la civilisation %s1_civ_adjective, et lui a proposé de l'aider à défendre ses villes grâce à leurs soldats!</French>
		<Italian>Una comunità indigena ha contattato la civiltà %s1:2_civ_adjective con l'offerta di fortificare le città utilizzando soldati dei nativi!</Italian>
		<Polish>Tubylcy przybyli do cywilizacji %s1_civ_adjective z ofertą wysłania swoich wojowników do obrony miast!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD_2A</Tag>
		<English>An indigenous community has approached us with young men and women who wish to help us defend our country!</English>
		<French>Une communauté indigène est entrée en contact avec nous. Ils ont des hommes et femmes prêts à défendre notre territoire!</French>
		<Italian>Una comunità indigena ci ha contattato con uomini e donne che desiderano difendere la nostra nazione!</Italian>
		<Polish>Tubylcy przybyli z ciekawą ofertą. Pragną wysłać swoich wojowników do obrony naszego państwa!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD_3</Tag>
		<English>An indigenous community has donated money to the %s1_civ_adjective civilization!</English>
		<French>Une communauté indigène a fait un don d'or à la civilisation %s1_civ_adjective!</French>
		<Italian>Una comunità indigena ha donato dell'oro alla civiltà %s1:2_civ_adjective!</Italian>
		<Polish>Tubylcy przekazali sumę pieniędzy cywilizacji %s1_civ_adjective!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD_3A</Tag>
		<English>An indigenous community would like to strengthen its bonds with our civilization, and donate money to our treasury!</English>
		<French>Une communauté indigène souhaite renforcer les liens avec notre civilisation, et nous apporte de l'or pour notre trésor!</French>
		<Italian>Una comunità indigena vorrebbe rinforzare i propri legami con la nostra civiltà, donandoci dell'oro!</Italian>
		<Polish>Tubylcy chcą wzmocnić więzy z naszą cywilizacją i przekazują pieniądze do naszego skarbca.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD_4</Tag>
		<English>An indigenous community has been meeting in secret with leaders in the %s1_civ_adjective civilization!</English>
		<French>Une communauté indigène a rencontré en sevret les leaders de la civilisation %s1_civ_adjective!</French>
		<Italian>Una comunità indigena si è segretamente incontrata con i leader della civiltà %s1:2_civ_adjective!</Italian>
		<Polish>Liderzy tubylców w sekrecie spotykają się w sekrecie z przywódcą %s1_civ_adjective!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EVENT_NATIVEGOOD_4A</Tag>
		<English>Elders in our indigenous community have approached us with ancient technology! They claim that they have been guarding the secret for centuries, and would now like to share it with us!</English>
		<French>Des aînés de notre communauté indigène nous ont contacté pour nous montré une ancienne technologie! Ils en sont les gardiens depuis des siècles, et veulent à présent nous en faire profiter!</French>
		<Italian>Gli anziani della comunità indigena ci hanno contattati offrendo antiche tecnologie! Dicono di aver sorvegliato questi segreti per secoli, e ora vorrebbero condividerli con noi!</Italian>
		<Polish>Starszyzna naszych tubylców przybyła do naszej stolicy z starożytną technologią. Twierdzą, że strzegli jej przez wieki i chcą się nią z nami podzielić.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
