<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KIM_1</Tag>
		<English>I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. National defense is the sacred duty of the young and all other people. We stand ready to defend against our aggressors, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Je suis [OUR_NAME] du [OUR_EMPIRE]. La défense nationale est un devoir sacré pour les jeunes et tous les autres peuples. Nous sommes prêts à nous défendre contre nos agresseurs, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<Polish>Jestem [OUR_NAME] z [OUR_EMPIRE]. Obrona narodu jest świętym obowiązkiem młodych i reszty obywateli. Jesteśmy gotowi bronić się przed agresorami, [CT_NAME].</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KIM</Tag>
		<English>Kim Jong Il</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KIM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Kim Jong Il[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] February 16, 1942 - December 17, 2011[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Kim Jong-il is the leader of the Democratic People's Republic of Korea. He is the Chairman of the National Defense Commission, Supreme Commander of the Korean People's Army, and General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea (the ruling party since 1948). He succeeded his father Kim Il-sung, founder of North Korea, who died in 1994, and commands the fifth largest standing army in the world. North Korea officially refers to him as the "Dear Leader".[PARAGRAPH:1]Kim Jong-il's official biography states that he was born in a secret military camp on Baekdu Mountain in northern Korea on February 16, 1942. Official biographers claim that his birth at Baekdu Mountain was foretold by a swallow, and heralded by the appearance of a double rainbow over the mountain and a new star in the heavens. However, Soviet records show he was born in the village of Vyatskoye, near Khabarovsk, in 1941 where his father, Kim Il-sung, commanded the 1st Battalion of the Soviet 88th Brigade, made up of Chinese and Korean exiles.[PARAGRAPH:1]President Kim Il-sung died July 8, 1994, at age 82 of a heart attack. He was not replaced as President, and received the designation of "Eternal President", resting in the Kumsusan Memorial Palace in central Pyongyang. The active position has been abolished in deference to the memory of Kim Il-sung. Kim Jong-il officially took the titles of General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea and chairman of the National Defense Commission on October 8, 1997. In 1998, his Defense Commission position was declared to be "the highest post of the state", so Kim may be regarded as North Korea's head of state from that date. Since Kim is not the president, he is not constitutionally required to hold elections to confirm his legitimacy and has not done so.[PARAGRAPH:1]Critics maintain Kim Jong-il is the centre of an elaborate personality cult inherited from his father and founder of the DPRK, Kim Il-sung. Defectors have been quoted as saying that North Korean schools deify both father and son, teaching that they do not urinate or defecate like mortal humans. He is often the centre of attention throughout ordinary life in the DPRK. His birthday is one of the most important public holidays in the country. On his 60th birthday (based on his official date of birth), mass celebrations occurred throughout the country.[PARAGRAPH:1]One point of view is that Kim Jong Il's cult of personality is solely out of respect for Kim Il-sung or out of fear of punishment for failure to pay homage. Media and government sources from outside of North Korea generally tout this view,while North Korean government sources claim that it is genuine hero worship.[PARAGRAPH:1]Kim reportedly also enjoys basketball. Former United States Secretary of State Madeleine Albright ended her summit with Kim by presenting him with a basketball signed by NBA legend Michael Jordan. Also an apparent golfer, North Korean state media reports that Kim routinely shoots three or four holes-in-one per round. His official biography also claims Kim has composed six operas and enjoys staging elaborate musicals. Kim also refers to himself as an Internet expert. Defectors claim that Kim has 17 different palaces and residences, including a private resort near Paektu Mountain, a seaside lodge in the city of Wonsan, and a palace complex northeast of Pyongyang surrounded with multiple fence lines, bunkers, and anti-aircraft batteries.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Kim Jong Il[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Sekretarz Generalny Partii Robotniczej Korei [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 1942-2011[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Przywódca Korei Północnej w latach 1994-2011. Był następcą swego ojca i założyciela KRLD, Kim Ir Sena po jego śmierci w 1994 roku. Był również sekretarzem generalnym Partii Pracy Korei, przewodniczącym Narodowej Komisji Obrony, a także marszałkiem i dowódcą Koreańskiej Armii Ludowej. W lipcu 1994 Kim Ir Sen zmarł na atak serca - Kim Dzong Il został faktycznym przywódcą Korei Północnej. Jednak fakt, że w kolejnych latach nie przyjął oficjalnych tytułów swojego ojca (który w 1998 został ogłoszony Wiecznym Prezydentem), może świadczyć o tym, że miał trudności w umocnieniu swojej władzy. Kim Dzong Il objął jeszcze w 1993 funkcję Przewodniczącego Narodowej Komisji Obrony stanowiącej (według Konstytucji z 1998 r.) "najwyższe stanowisko w państwie". Szefem partii komunistycznej został dopiero w październiku 1997 r.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>