<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_LOGAN_1</Tag>
		<English>I come in peace to ask for assistance. What do you say?</English>
		<French>Je suis venu en paix vous demander de l'aide. Qu'avez-vous à répondre?</French>
		<German>Ich komme in Frieden und bitte um Unterstützung. Wie lautet Eure Antwort?</German>
		<Italian>Vengo in pace alla ricerca di aiuto. Cosa mi rispondi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vengo en son de paz a pedir ayuda. ¿Qué me decís?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Przybywam w pokoju. Czy pomożesz mi?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_LOGAN_1</Tag>
		<English>I hold the fate of the [CT_EMPIRE] in my hand. Give me what I demand.</English>
		<French>Je tiens le destin de l'[CT_EMPIRE] dans ma main. Donnez-moi ce que j'exige.</French>
		<German>Ich halte das Schicksal vom [CT_EMPIRE:3] in meinen Händen. Gebt mir, was ich verlange.</German>
		<Italian>Ho nelle mani il destino di [CT_EMPIRE]. Dammi ciò che chiedo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tengo el destino del [CT_EMPIRE] en mis manos. Dadme lo que os exijo.</Spanish>
		<Polish>W moich rękach leży los [CT_EMPIRE]. Daj mi czego się domagam.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_LOGAN_1</Tag>
		<English>My people are in need, can the [CT_EMPIRE] help?</English>
		<French>Ma personnes est dans le besoin, l'[CT_EMPIRE] peut-il nous aider?</French>
		<German>Mein Stamm ist in Not, kann uns das [CT_EMPIRE:2] helfen?</German>
		<Italian>La mia tribù ha bisogno di aiuto, potete aiutarci?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mi puebla está necesitada. ¿Podrá ayudarnos el [CT_EMPIRE]?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Mieszkańcy mojego imperium potrzebują Twojej pomocy. Pomożesz?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LOGAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Hello. I am [OUR_NAME], chief and protector of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people. I consider you a friend. It is in your best interest that I never change that opinion.</English>
		<French>Bonjour. Je suis [OUR_NAME], chef et protecteur des [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3]. Je vous considère comme mon ami. Il va de votre intérêt que je ne change jamais d'opinion.</French>
		<German>Hallo. Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Oberhaupt und Beschützer des [OUR_CIV_ADJ:2] Volkes. Ich betrachte Euch als Freund. Ich hoffe für Euch, dass ich diese Meinung nie ändere.</German>
		<Italian>Salve. Mi chiamo [OUR_NAME], capo e protettore del popolo [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Ti considero un amico. È nel tuo migliore interesse che io non cambi mai idea.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hola. Soy [OUR_NAME], jefe y protector del pueblo [OUR_CIV_ADJ:1]. Os considero mis amigos. Y más os vale que nunca cambie de opinión.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Witam, jestem [OUR_NAME], wódz i obrońca ludu [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Traktuję Cię jak przyjaciela. W Twoim interesie leży nie zmieniać tego statusu.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_LOGAN_1</Tag>
		<English>It is good to hear from the [CT_EMPIRE]. To what do I owe this honor?</English>
		<French>Quel plaisir d'avoir de vos nouvelles! Que me vaut cet honneur?</French>
		<German>Es ist gut, etwas vom [CT_EMPIRE:3] zu hören. Womit haben wir diese Ehre verdient?</German>
		<Italian>È bello avere notizie da [CT_EMPIRE]. A cosa debbo quest'onore?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es un placer oír al [CT_EMPIRE]. ¿A qué debo este honor?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dobrze usłyszeć znajomy głos z CT_EMPIRE]. Czym mogę służyć?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_LOGAN_1</Tag>
		<English>You have started down a path that will lead to your destruction. Feel free to try to explain yourself.</English>
		<French>Vous vous êtes engagé sur la voie qui menera à votre destruction. J'attends vos explications.</French>
		<German>Ihr habt begonnen, einen Pfad zu beschreiten, der zu Eurer Vernichtung führen wird. Wollt Ihr Euch möglicherweise rechtfertigen?</German>
		<Italian>Ti sei avviato lungo un cammino che porterà alla tua distruzione. Prova pure a cercare di spiegarti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Habéis hollado una senda que os llevará a la destrucción. Intentad explicaros como queráis.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wstąpiłeś na ściężkę, która doprowadzi Cię do zguby. Masz coś na usprawiedliwienie?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_LOGAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace? Never!</English>
		<French>La paix? Jamais!</French>
		<German>Frieden? Niemals!</German>
		<Italian>Pace? Mai!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Paz? ¡Jamás!</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pokój? Nigdy!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_LOGAN_1</Tag>
		<English>You want to talk? It is a little too late for that.</English>
		<French>Vous voulez parler? C'est un peu tard pour ça.</French>
		<German>Ihr wollt reden? Dafür ist es etwas zu spät.</German>
		<Italian>Vuoi parlare? È un po' troppo tardi per farlo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Ahora queréis hablar? Es un poco tarde para eso.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Chcesz rozmawiać? Niestety jest już na to zbyt późno.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LOGAN</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Logan</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LOGAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Logan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Chief of the Mingo[NEWLINE]Lived:[\BOLD] c. 1725 - 1780[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Logan was chief of the Mingo tribe, a branch of the powerful Iroquois Confederacy, living in the frontier land of Virginia in the 18th century. Little is known about his early life before the actions of one misguided English colonist brought the Iroquois leader painfully to English attention.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1774, a man named Daniel Greathouse, responding to the summons of a nervous innkeeper, lead a small militia in what became known as the Yellow Creek Massacre. Roughly a dozen Iroquois were killed by Greathouse and his men, many of them direct blood relatives of Logan - including Logan's sister and daughter.[PARAGRAPH:1]In response, Logan organized a party of his fellow Iroquois and led them on a series of brutal raids across the frontier settlements of Virginia. So successful were the attacks of Logan and his small group that the governor of Virginia, one Lord Dunmore, declared war on the whole of the Mingo nation. The Mingo and the English forces met on the field of Point Pleasant, where the superior numbers of the Virginians secured victory.[PARAGRAPH:1]Logan, however, was not present for the battle. Instead, he conveyed a message that he saw no further need to battle the whites. This message, which became known as "Logan's Lament" would become a sort of manifesto for the natives and their white proponents, demonstrating that those who were so often called "savages" were actually rational beings just like the English. In his message, Logan said, "During the course of the last long and bloody war [the French and Indian War], Logan remained idle in his cabin, an advocate for peace. Such was my love for the whites - I had even thought to have lived with you but for the injuries of one man... This has called on me for revenge. I have sought it; I have killed many; I have glutted my vengeance; for my country I rejoice at the beams of peace."</English>
		<French>[H1]Logan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Chef des Mingos[NEWLINE]Dates:[\BOLD] vers 1725 - 1780[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Logan fut le chef de la tribu des Mingos, branche de la puissante Confédération iroquoise vivant sur les territoires frontaliers de la Virginie au 18ème siècle. On sait peu de choses sur sa jeunesse avant que les atrocités commises par un colon n'attirent l'attention des Anglais sur le chef iroquois.[PARAGRAPH:1]En 1774, un homme nommé Daniel Greathouse, répondant à l'appel d'un aubergiste inquiet, mena une petite milice lors du tristement célèbre Massacre de Yellow Creek. Environ une douzaine d'Iroquois furent tués par Greathouse et ses hommes, dont un bon nombre étaient des parents de Logan, y compris sa soeur et sa fille.[PARAGRAPH:1]En représailles, Logan rassembla certains membres de sa tribu et mena une série de raids sanglants dans les colonies frontalières de Virginie. Les attaques de Logan furent si efficaces que le gouverneur de Virginie, un certain Lord Dunmore, déclara la guerre contre l'ensemble de la nation mingo. Les Mingos et les troupes anglaises s'affrontèrent sur le champ de bataille de Point Pleasant, où la supériorité numérique des Virginiens leur assura la victoire.[PARAGRAPH:1]Logan, cependant, n'était pas présent à la bataille. Au lieu de cela, il envoya un message déclarant qu'il ne voyait plus d'intérêt à combattre les blancs. Ce message, qui devint connu sous le nom de Complainte de Logan allait devenir une sorte de manifeste pour les indigènes et leurs partisans blancs, démontrant que ceux que l'on appelait si souvent "sauvages" étaient en fait des êtres rationnels, tout comme les Anglais. Dans son message, Logan disait: "lors de la dernière grande guerre [celle des Français contre les Indiens], Logan resta immobile dans sa cabane, prônant la paix. Car j'aimais vraiment les blancs ; je pensais même pouvoir vivre avec vous si un homme ne m'avait pas porté outrage... Cet acte exigeait une vengeance. Je l'ai cherchée. J'ai tué de nombreux hommes. Je suis rassasié. Désormais, je me réjouis de l'apparition des rayons de la paix."</French>
		<German>[H1]Logan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Häuptling der Mingo[NEWLINE]Lebte:[\BOLD] ca. 1725 - 1780[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Logan war der Häuptling der Mingo, eine Gruppierung des mächtigen Irokesenbunds, und lebte im 18. Jahrhundert im Grenzland von Virginia. Von seinen jungen Jahren ist wenig bekannt, bis die Taten eines fehlgeleiteten englischen Kolonisten die englische Aufmerksamkeit aufs Schmerzlichste auf den Irokesenführer lenkte.[PARAGRAPH:1]1774 führte ein Mann namens Daniel Greathouse auf Bitten eines nervösen Schankwirts eine kleine Miliz in einen Kampf, der später als das Yellow-Creek-Massaker bekannt werden sollte. Etwa ein Dutzend Irokesen wurden von Greathouse und seinen Männern getötet, darunter auch viele direkte Blutsverwandte von Logan - einschließlich seiner Schwester und seiner Tochter.[PARAGRAPH:1]Als Reaktion darauf stellte Logan eine Gruppe Irokesen zusammen und führte sie in eine Serie brutaler Überfälle quer durch die Siedlungen an der Grenze Virginias. Die Angriffe von Logan und seiner kleinen Gruppe waren derart erfolgreich, dass der Gouverneur von Virginia, ein gewisser Lord Dunmore, der gesamten Nation der Mingo den Krieg erklärte. Die Mingo und die Engländer trafen auf dem Feld von Point Pleasant aufeinander, wo die zahlenmäßige Überlegenheit der Engländer Virginia den Sieg sicherte.[PARAGRAPH:1]Logan jedoch war bei der Schlacht nicht dabei. Stattdessen schickte er eine Nachricht, die besagte, dass er keine weitere Notwendigkeit darin sähe, weiter gegen die Weißen zu kämpfen. Diese Nachricht, die als "Logans Klage" bekannt wurde, sollte eine Art Manifest für die Ureinwohner und ihre weißen Fürsprecher werden, das demonstrierte, dass die so oft als "Wilde" bezeichneten Ureinwohner tatsächlich rationale Wesen waren - ebenso wie die Engländer. Logans Nachricht lautete: "Im Verlauf des letzten langen und blutigen Krieges [der Krieg zwischen Indianern und Franzosen] ist Logan untätig in seiner Behausung geblieben, als Verfechter des Friedens. So groß war meine Liebe für die Weißen - ich dachte sogar, wir könnten gemeinsam leben, bis zu den Untaten eines Mannes... die meine Rache forderten. Ich habe sie vollstreckt. Ich habe viele getötet, ich habe ausreichend Vergeltung geübt. Für mein Land freue ich mich über die Strahlen des Friedens."</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Logan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Capo dei mingo[NEWLINE]Vita:[\BOLD] c. 1725 - 1780[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Logan era il capo della tribù mingo, una fazione della potente Confederazione irochese, che viveva sulle terre di frontiera della Virginia nel XVIII secolo. Si sa poco della sua vita prima che le azioni di uno sprovveduto colono inglese richiamassero dolorosamente su di lui l'attenzione inglese.[PARAGRAPH:1]Nel 1774 un uomo di nome Daniel Greathouse, rispondendo alla chiamata di un negoziante nervoso, guidò un gruppo di miliziani in quello che venne conosciuto come il Massacro di Yellow Creek. Morirono circa una dozzina di irochesi, molti dei quali parenti di Logan, e tra i quali c'erano sua sorella e sua figlia.[PARAGRAPH:1]Come risposta Logan organizzò un gruppo di irochesi e li guidò in una serie di brutali incursioni contro gli insediamenti di frontiera della Virginia. Gli attacchi di Logan e della sua banda ebbero così tanto successo che il governatore della Virginia, tale Lord Dunmore, dichiarò guerra all'intera nazione mingo. Le forze inglesi e quelle dei mingo si scontrarono sul campo a Point Pleasant, dove la superiorità numerica diede la vittoria ai virginiani.[PARAGRAPH:1]Logan non era però presente alla battaglia. Invece inviò un messaggio in cui diceva che non vedeva ulteriore necessità di combattere i bianchi. Questo messaggio, conosciuto come il "Lamento di Logan", sarebbe diventato una sorta di manifesto per i nativi e per i loro sostenitori bianchi, dimostrando che coloro che così spesso venivano chiamati "selvaggi" erano in realtà esseri razionali, proprio come gli inglesi. Nel suo messaggio, Logan diceva: "Nel corso dell'ultima lunga e sanguinosa guerra [la guerra franco-indiana], Logan è rimasto inattivo nella sua capanna, sostenendo la pace. Tale era il mio amore per i bianchi che avevo anche pensato di vivere con voi, se non fosse stato per l'offesa di un uomo... Questo ha causato la mia vendetta. L'ho cercata; ho ucciso molte persone; ho soddisfatto la mia sete di vendetta; per la mia terra gioisco all'apparire dei raggi della pace."</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Logan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Jefe de los mingo[NEWLINE]Vivió:[\BOLD] alrededor de 1725 - 1780[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biografía:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Logan era el jefe de la tribu de los mingo, una rama de la poderosa Confederación Iroquesa que vivía en la tierra fronteriza de Virginia en el s. XVIII. Poco se sabe de su vida antes que los actos de un imprudente colono inglés hicieran que el líder iroqués llamara dolorosamente la atención de los ingleses.[PARAGRAPH:1]En 1774, un hombre llamado Daniel Greathouse, en respuesta a la llamada de un posadero nervioso, condujo a una pequeña milicia en lo que posteriormente se conoció como "la matanza de Yellow Creek". Greathouse y sus hombres mataron a una veintena de iroqueses aproximadamente, muchos de ellos parientes de Logan, incluyendo a su hermana y a su hija.[PARAGRAPH:1]Como respuesta, Logan montó una partida de sus fieles iroqueses y los lideró en una serie de incursiones brutales por los asentamientos fronterizos de Virginia. Tanto daño hicieron los ataques de Logan y su pequeño grupo que el gobernador de Virginia, un lord Dunmore, declaró la guerra contra toda la nación mingo. Las fuerzas mingo e inglesas se encontraron en el campo de Point Pleasant, donde la superioridad numérica de los virginianos les valió la victoria.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sin embargo, Logan no estuvo presente en la batalla. En vez de eso, hizo llegar un mensaje en el que decía que ya no veía la necesidad de combatir a los blancos. Este mensaje, que pasó a conocerse como "El lamento de Logan" se convertiría en una especie de manifiesto para los indígenas y sus defensores blancos, pues en él demostraba que los conocidos frecuentemente como "salvajes" eran en verdad seres racionales, como los ingleses. En este mensaje, Logan decía: "Durante el transcurso de la guerra larga y sangrienta (la Guerra Franco-India), Logan se quedó sin hacer nada en su cabaña y defendió la paz. Tal era mi amor por los blancos: incluso había pensado vivir con vosotros, si no hubiera sido por las heridas de un hombre... fueron las que me hicieron clamar venganza. La he buscado; he matado a muchos; me he saciado de ella; y por mi país me regocijo ante los rayos de luz de la paz."</Spanish>
		<Polish>[H1]Logan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Wódz Mingo[NEWLINE]Żył:[\BOLD] ok. 1725 - 1780</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>