<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CUNHAMBEBE_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people. Help us safe our precious rainforest and you'll have our eternal gratitude!</English>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]! Io sono [OUR_NAME] del popolo [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Aiutaci a salvare la nostra preziosa foresta pluviale e avrai la nostra eterna gratitudine!</Italian>
		<Polish>Witam, [CT_NAME]! Jestem [OUR_NAME] z ludu [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Pomóż nam zachować cenny las deszczowy, a będziemy dozgonnie wdzięczni!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CUNHAMBEBE</Tag>
		<English>Cunhambebe</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CUNHAMBEBE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Cunhambebe[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Chieftain of the Tupinambá tribe[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 16th century[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Cunhambebe was an aboriginal Indian chieftain of the Tupinambá tribe, which dominated the region between present-day Cabo Frio (Rio de Janeiro) and Bertioga (São Paulo). He lived in the village of Ubatuba, in what is today Angra dos Reis.[PARAGRAPH:1]Cunhambebe was also the main force and elected chief of the Tamoyo Confederation, a military alliance between the sea coast tribes against the Portuguese colonists, which waged war against them until the Peace of Iperoig was celebrated with them, in 1567. The fought also the Portuguese forces in alliance with the French invaders commanded by Nicolas Durand de Villegaignon (1510-1571), a Huguenot admiral, in the historical episode which became known as the France Antarctique. According to the description of French priest André de Thevet, the German soldier of fortune and sailor Hans Staden (1525-1579) was a prisoner of Cunhambebe's father (who had the same name) between 1554 and 1557. The Tupinambá were fierce warriors and cannibals, as described by Hans Staden, who narrowly escaped several times of being killed and eaten by Cunhambebe's Indians.[PARAGRAPH:1]The war waged by the Tamoyo Confederation was strongly affecting the Portuguese colonisation efforts, so the two Portuguese Jesuit priests who had founded São Paulo dos Campos de Piratininga (which became the present-day megalopolis of São Paulo), Manoel da Nóbrega (1517-1570) and José de Anchieta (1534-1597) started a peace mission by doing a high risk visit to Cunhambebe's village in Iperoig (present day Ubatuba). Although they were received with mistrust, Anchieta spoke Tupi language very well and they were spared death. Eventually, Anchieta succeeded in celebrating a peace treaty, which was respected by Cunhambebe and the Tupinambás until the attack force led by Portuguese knight D. Estácio de Sá (1520-1567) tried to expel the French invaders. In this occasion, the Tupinambá tribes came to help the Frenchmen, particularly because they felt betrayed by the Portuguese, and also because the Tupiniquim tribes, their traditional and bitter enemies, fought on the side of the Portuguese.[PARAGRAPH:1]Cunhambebe died of bubonic plague just after the arrival of Villegaigon's fleet to the Guanabara Bay in Rio de Janeiro, so he took no part in the following events which eventually led to the almost complete destruction of the Tupinambás towards the end of the 16th century.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Cunhambebe[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Wódz plemienia Tupi[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] XVI wiek[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Cunhambebe was an aboriginal Indian chieftain of the Tupinambá tribe, which dominated the region between present-day Cabo Frio (Rio de Janeiro) and Bertioga (Săo Paulo). He lived in the village of Ubatuba, in what is today Angra dos Reis.[PARAGRAPH:1]Cunhambebe was also the main force and elected chief of the Tamoyo Confederation, a military alliance between the sea coast tribes against the Portuguese colonists, which waged war against them until the Peace of Iperoig was celebrated with them, in 1567. The fought also the Portuguese forces in alliance with the French invaders commanded by Nicolas Durand de Villegaignon (1510-1571), a Huguenot admiral, in the historical episode which became known as the France Antarctique. According to the description of French priest André de Thevet, the German soldier of fortune and sailor Hans Staden (1525-1579) was a prisoner of Cunhambebe's father (who had the same name) between 1554 and 1557. The Tupinambá were fierce warriors and cannibals, as described by Hans Staden, who narrowly escaped several times of being killed and eaten by Cunhambebe's Indians.[PARAGRAPH:1]The war waged by the Tamoyo Confederation was strongly affecting the Portuguese colonisation efforts, so the two Portuguese Jesuit priests who had founded Săo Paulo dos Campos de Piratininga (which became the present-day megalopolis of Săo Paulo), Manoel da Nóbrega (1517-1570) and José de Anchieta (1534-1597) started a peace mission by doing a high risk visit to Cunhambebe's village in Iperoig (present day Ubatuba). Although they were received with mistrust, Anchieta spoke Tupi language very well and they were spared death. Eventually, Anchieta succeeded in celebrating a peace treaty, which was respected by Cunhambebe and the Tupinambás until the attack force led by Portuguese knight D. Estácio de Sá (1520-1567) tried to expel the French invaders. In this occasion, the Tupinambá tribes came to help the Frenchmen, particularly because they felt betrayed by the Portuguese, and also because the Tupiniquim tribes, their traditional and bitter enemies, fought on the side of the Portuguese.[PARAGRAPH:1]Cunhambebe died of bubonic plague just after the arrival of Villegaigon's fleet to the Guanabara Bay in Rio de Janeiro, so he took no part in the following events which eventually led to the almost complete destruction of the Tupinambás towards the end of the 16th century.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>