<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ITZCOATL_1</Tag>
		<English>Hello [CT_NAME], I am [OUR_NAME], conqueror of the Tepenecs and liberator of the mighty [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people. Tell me, friend, what blood type are you?</English>
		<Polish>Witaj [CT_NAME], Jestem [OUR_NAME], zdobywca Tepaneków i wyzwoliciel potęznego ludu [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Powiedz mi, przyjacielu, jakiej grupy krwi jesteś?</Polish>
		<Russian>Приветствую, [CT_NAME], я - [OUR_NAME], покоритель Тепенеков и освободитель могущественного племени [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Поведай нам, друг, какая у тебя группа крови?</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ITZCOATL</Tag>
		<English>Itzcoatl</English>
		<Russian>Èöêîàòëü</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ITZCOATL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Itzcoatl[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Tlatoani of the Aztecs[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c. 1400 - 1440[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Itzcoatl, meaning "Obsidian Serpent", was the fourth tlatoani (emperor) of the Aztecs, ruling from 1427 (or 1428) to 1440, the period when the Mexica threw off the domination of the Tepanecs and laid the foundations for the eventual Aztec Empire.[PARAGRAPH:1]Itzcoatl was an illegitimate son of Acamapichtli, the first Aztec tlatoani. He himself was elected as tlatoani when his predecessor, Chimalpopoca, was killed by Maxtla of the nearby Tepanec city-state of Azcapotzalco. Allying with Nezahualcoyotl of Texcoco, Itzcoatl went on to defeat Maxtla and end the Tepanec domination of central Mexico.[PARAGRAPH:1]After this victory, Itzcoatl, Nezahualcoyotl, and Totoquilhuaztli, tlatoani of Tlacopan, forged what would become known as the Aztec Triple Alliance, forming the basis of the eventual Aztec empire. Itzcoatl next turned his attention to the chinampas districts on the south shores of Lakes Xochimilco and Chalco. Fresh water springs lining these shores had allowed the development of extensive raised gardens, or chinampas, set on the shallow lake floors. Successful campaigns against Xochimilco (1430), Mixquic (1432), Cuitlahuac (1433), and Tezompa would secure agricultural resources for Tenochtitlan and, along with the conquest of Culhuacan and Coyoacan, would cement the Triple Alliance's control over the southern half of the Valley of Mexico.[PARAGRAPH:1]With this string of victories, Itzcoatl took the title Culhua tecuhtli, "Lord of the Culhua" while Totoquilhuaztli, tlatoani of Tlacopan, took the title Tepaneca tecuhtli, "Lord of the Tepanecs". In 1439, Itzcoatl undertook a campaign outside the Valley of Mexico against Cuauhnahuac (modern day Cuernavaca). According to the Madrid Codex, Itzcoatl ordered the burning of all historical codices because it was "not wise that all the people should know the paintings". Among other purposes, this allowed the Aztec state to develop a state-sanctioned history and mythos that venerated Huitzilopochtli.[PARAGRAPH:1]Itzcoatl also continued the building of Tenochtitlan: during his reign temples, roads, and a causeway were built. Itzcóatl established the religious and governmental hierarchy that was assumed by Moctezuma I upon his death in 1440.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Itzcoatl[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Tlatoani Azteków[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] c. 1400 - 1440[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Czwarty władca (tlatoani) Azteków, rządzący w latach 1427 (albo 1428) do 1440. Stworzył podwaliny późniejszego Imperium, za jego rządów Aztekowie odrzucili zwierzchnictwo Tepaneków.</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Ицкоатль[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Тлатоани ацтеков[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни: [\BOLD] ок. 1400 - 1440[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Ицкоатль, что означает «Обсидиановый Змей», был четвертым тлатоани (императором) ацтеков, правившим с 1427 (или 1428) по 1440 год, в период, когда Мексика сбросила господство тепанеков и заложила основы для возможной ацтекской империи.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ицкоатль был незаконнорожденным сыном Акамапичтли, первого ацтекского тлатоани. Сам он был избран тлатоани, когда его предшественник, Чимальпопока, был убит Макстлой из соседнего города-государства Тепанек Аскапоцалько. В союзе с Нецауалькойотлем из Тескоко, Ицкоатль победил Макстлу и положил конец господству тепанеков в центральной части Мексики.[PARAGRAPH:1]После этой победы Ицкоатль, Нецауалькойотль и Тотокилуацтли, тлатоани из Тлакопана, создали то, что впоследствии стало известно как Тройственный союз ацтеков, сформировав основу будущей империи ацтеков. Затем Ицкоатль обратил свое внимание на районы чинампас на южных берегах озер Сочимилько и Чалко. Источники пресной воды, окружающие эти берега, позволили развить обширные сады, или чинампы, расположенные на неглубоком дне озера. Успешные кампании против Ксочимилько (1430 г.), Микскика (1432 г.), Куитлахуака (1433 г.) и Тезомпы обеспечат сельскохозяйственные ресурсы для Теночтитлана и, наряду с завоеванием Кулуакана и Койоакана, укрепят контроль Тройственного союза над южной половиной долины.[PARAGRAPH:1]Благодаря этой череде побед Ицкоатль получил титул Кулуа текутли, «Повелитель Кульхуа», а Тотокилуазтли, тлатоани Тлакопана, получил титул Тепанека текутли, «Повелитель тепанеков». В 1439 году Ицкоатль предпринял кампанию за пределами Мексиканской долины против Куаухнахуака (современная Куэрнавака). Согласно Мадридскому кодексу, Ицкоатль приказал сжечь все исторические кодексы, потому что «неразумно, что все люди должны знать картины». Среди прочего, это позволило ацтекскому государству разработать утвержденную государством историю и мифы, почитающие Уицилопочтли.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ицкоатль также продолжил строительство Теночтитлана: во время его правления были построены храмы, дороги и дамба. Ицкоатль установил религиозную и правительственную иерархию, которую принял Монтесума I после его смерти в 1440 году.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>