<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ABUBAKR_1</Tag>
		<English>What you will need to understand, [CT_NAME], is that anyone who fights on behalf of Allah, when he dies, the first drop of blood that comes out, all of his sins will be forgiven.</English>
		<French>Ce que vous aurez besoin de comprendre, [CT_NAME], est que toute personne qui se bat au nom d'Allah, lorsqu'il meurt, à la première goutte de sang versé, est pardonné de tous ses péchés.</French>
		<Polish>[CT_NAME], musisz zrozumieć, że ten kto walczy w imię Allaha, kiedy umiera, z pierwsza kroplą przelanej krwi, wszystkie jego grzechy zostają odpuszczone.</Polish>
		<Russian>Что вам нужно понять, [CT_NAME], так это то, что любому, сражающемуся от имени Аллаха, после смерти простятся все грехи единственной каплей крови.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ABUBAKR</Tag>
		<English>Abu Bakr</English>
		<Russian>Àáó Áàêð</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ABUBAKR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Abu Bakr Abdallah ibn Abi Quhafa As-Siddiq[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Caliph of Arabia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Zyl:[\BOLD] c. 573 CE-634[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Abu Bakr Abdallah ibn Abi Quhafa As-Siddiq was an early convert to Islam and a senior companion (Sahaba) of the Islamic prophet Muhammad. Throughout his life, Abu Bakr remained a friend and confidante of Muhammad. Upon Muhammad's death he became the first Muslim ruler (632–634), regarded in Sunni Islam as the first of the Rashidun (righteously guided Caliphs). His caliphate lasted two years and three months, during which time he consolidated the Muslim state. Upon the death of Muhammad, some tribes rebelled, and in return he fought the Ridda wars against these Arab tribes to establish Islamic rule over all of Arabia. He also conquered the lands of Syria and Iraq.[PARAGRAPH:1]Abu Bakr became the Caliph on the 8 June 632 C.E. and he died on 23 August 634 C.E. Though the period of his caliphate covers two years, two months and fifteen days only, his achievements were remarkable. His glorious triumph in Ridda Wars and successful invasions of the two most powerful empires of the time the Sassanid Empire and Byzantine Empire.[PARAGRAPH:1]Abu Bakr had the distinction of being the first Caliph in the history of Islam. He was the first Caliph to nominate a successor. He was the only Caliph in the history of Islam who refunded to the state treasury at the time of his death the entire amount of the allowance that he had drawn during the period of his caliphate.[PARAGRAPH:1]He was the first Muslim ruler to establish Bayt al-mal. He was the first Muslim ruler to establish crown pasture. He was the first Muslim ruler to establish 'Ijtihad'. He has the distinction of purchasing the land for Al-Masjid al-Nabawi. According to Sunni Muslims, in the matter of virtue, Abu Bakr excelled all other Sahaba. Both Abu Bakr and Uthman ibn Affan had relinquished drinking wine even in the time before Islam. He was the foremost genealogist of the Quraysh and the best of them at interpreting dreams after Muhammad according to Ibn Sirin.[PARAGRAPH:1]On 8 August 634, Abu Bakr fell sick, and never recovered. There are two accounts about the sickness of Abu Bakr. One account is that the 8 August 634 was a cold day and when Abu Bakr took a bath, he caught a chill. Another account is that about a year before, along with some other companions, Harith bin Kaladah, and Attab bin Usaid, he had eaten some food which was poisoned, and which was not to affect him for a year. On Monday 23 August 634 Abu Bakr died. The funeral prayer was led by Umar. He was buried the same night by the side of Muhammad's grave in Aisha's house ner Al-Masjid al-Nabawi.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Abu Bakr Abdallah ibn Abi Quhafa As-Siddiq[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Kalif Arabii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Źył:[\BOLD] ok. 573 CE-634[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Abu Bakr urodził się w roku 573 w Mekce w plemieniu Kurajszytów. O jego życiu przed nawróceniem się na islam właściwie nic pewnego nie wiadomo, chociaż muzułmańska tradycja twierdzi, że był zamożnym kupcem, co zdają się potwierdzać późniejsze wydarzenia, podczas których miał wielokrotnie wspierać materialnie ubogą gminę muzułmańską podczas pierwszego okresu jej istnienia. Był jednym z pierwszych nawróconych na islam, według niektórych tradycji trzecią osobą po żonie proroka Chadidży i Alim, chociaż większość z nich umieszcza go mniej zaszczytnie wśród kilkunastu pierwszych nawróconych, a jedna z nich powiada nawet: "Było przed nim ponad pięćdziesięciu" aby zaraz dodać: "ale on był najznakomitszy". Stało się to około roku 610. Jego majątek, pozwalający mu np. wykupywać nawróconych na islam niewolników, oraz osobisty autorytet i charyzma, były znaczącym wsparciem w misji Mahometa. Pozycję Abu Bakra jako najbliższego obok Alego towarzysza Proroka wzmocniło w dodatku małżeństwo Mahometa z jego córką, Aiszą, która miała się stać jego ulubioną żoną. O znaczeniu Abu Bakra świadczy choćby fakt powierzenia mu przez Mahometa zadania wygłoszenia chutby podczas hadżdżu w 631 roku.</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Абу Бакр Абдаллах ибн Аби Хухафа Ас-Сиддик[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Первый халиф Аравии[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни: [\BOLD] ок. 573 - 634 гг.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Абу Бакр Абдаллах ибн Аби Кухафа Ас-Сиддик был одним из первых обращенных в ислам и старшим соратником (сахабом) исламского пророка Мухаммеда. На протяжении всей своей жизни Абу Бакр оставался другом и доверенным лицом Мухаммеда. После смерти Мухаммеда он стал первым мусульманским правителем (632–634), которого в суннитском исламе считают первым из Рашидунов (праведных халифов). Его халифат длился два года и три месяца, в течение которых он объединил мусульманское государство. После смерти Мухаммеда некоторые племена восстали, и в ответ он вел войны Ридда против этих арабских племен, чтобы установить исламское правление над всей Аравией. Он также завоевал земли Сирии и Ирака.[PARAGRAPH:1]Абу Бакр стал халифом 8 июня 632 года н. Э. И умер 23 августа 634 года н.э. Хотя период его халифата охватывает только два года, два месяца и пятнадцать дней, его достижения были замечательными. Его славный триумф в войнах Ридда и успешные вторжения в две самые могущественные империи того времени - Сасанидскую империю и Византийскую империю.[PARAGRAPH:1]Абу Бакр имел честь быть первым халифом в истории ислама. Он был первым халифом, назначившим преемника. Он был единственным халифом в истории ислама, который вернул в государственную казну на момент своей смерти всю сумму денежного пособия, полученного им в период своего халифата.[PARAGRAPH:1]Он был первым мусульманским правителем, установившим Байт ал-мал. Он был первым мусульманским правителем, основавшим пастбище короны. Он был первым мусульманским правителем, установившим «иджтихад». Он имеет честь купить землю для Аль-Масджид ан-Набави. По мнению мусульман-суннитов, в вопросе добродетели Абу Бакр превосходил всех других сахабов. И Абу Бакр, и Усман ибн Аффан отказались от вина еще до ислама. Он был ведущим специалистом по генеалогии курайшитов и лучшим из них в толковании снов после Мухаммеда согласно Ибн Сирину.[PARAGRAPH:1]8 августа 634 года Абу Бакр заболел и так и не поправился. Есть два рассказа о болезни Абу Бакра. Согласно одной из версий, 8 августа 634 года был холодным днем, и когда Абу Бакр принял ванну, он простудился. Другой рассказ состоит в том, что около года назад вместе с некоторыми другими товарищами, Харитом бин Каладом и Аттабом бин Усаидом, он съел отравленную пищу, которая не влияла на него в течение года. В понедельник 23 августа 634 года Абу Бакр скончался. Погребальную молитву возглавил Умар. Он был похоронен в ту же ночь рядом с могилой Мухаммеда в доме Аиши в Аль-Масджид ан-Набави.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>