<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_CAPTIVES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>As a result of combat you may capture some enemy units. The chance of this depends on both your and their civics and [LINK=CONCEPT_WORLD_VIEW]World Views[\LINK]. These units will be [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_MILITARY]Captive - Military[\LINK] or [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_NEANDERTHAL]Captive - Neanderthal[\LINK]. If you destroy or sack a city you may also get [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_CIVILIAN]Captive - Civilian[\LINK] and [LINK=UNIT_FREED_SLAVE]Captive - Freed Slave[\LINK].[PARAGRAPH:2]What you can do with these units depends on what World Views you are running. If you are running Slavery then you can sell the captives as slaves or have them join your city as [LINK=SPECIALIST_SETTLED_SLAVE]Settled Slaves[\LINK]. If you are running Cannibalism you can butcher them. If you are running Human Sacrifice you can sacrifice them for culture or happiness.</English>
		<French>A l'issue d'un combat, il est possible de capturer vos ennemis. La probabilité dépend des vos doctrines respectives et de vos [LINK=CONCEPT_WORLD_VIEW]Visions du Monde[\LINK]. Ces unités seront des [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_MILITARY]Prisonnier - Militaire[\LINK] ou [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_NEANDERTHAL]Prisonnier - Néanderthal[\LINK]. En détruisant ou capturant une ville, il est possible d'obtenir un [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_CIVILIAN]Prisonnier - Civilian[\LINK] et [LINK=UNIT_FREED_SLAVE]Prisonnier - Esclave libéré[\LINK].[PARAGRAPH:2]Ce que vous pouvez faire avec ces unités dépends de votre vision du monde: si vous avez l'esclavage, vous pouvez les vendre comme esclaves ou leur faire rejoindre un ville en tant qu'[LINK=SPECIALIST_SETTLED_SLAVE]Esclave sédentaire[\LINK]. Si vous avec la cannibalisme, vous pouvez les manger. Si vous avez le sacrifice humain, vous pouvez les tuer pour obtenir de la culture ou du bonheur.</French>
		<Italian>Come risultato delle battaglie potresti catturare alcune unità nemiche. La possibilità di una cattura dipende sia dalle tue forme di governo che da quelle del tuo nemico, oltre che dalle vostre [LINK=CONCEPT_WORLD_VIEW]Concezioni del mondo[\LINK]. Queste unità saranno [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_MILITARY]Prigiionieri - Militari [\LINK] o [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_NEANDERTHAL]Prigionieri - Neanderthal[\LINK]. Se distruggi o saccheggi di una città potresti anche ottenere [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_CIVILIAN]Prigionieri - Civili[\LINK] e [LINK=UNIT_FREED_SLAVE]Prigionieri - Schiavi liberati[\LINK].[PARAGRAPH:2]Cosa puoi ottenere da queste unità dipende dalle tue concezione del mondo attive. Se la schiavitù è legale nella tua nazione allora puoi vendere i prigionieri come schiavi o unirli alla tua città come [LINK=SPECIALIST_SETTLED_SLAVE]Schiavi sedentari[\LINK]. Se il cannibalismo è legale puoi uccidere i prigionieri per mangiarli. Se i sacrifici umani sono legali puoi perfino sacrificare i prigionieri in cambio di cultura o felicità.</Italian>
		<German>Während eines Kampfes können einige Gegner gefangen werden. Die Chance hängt von den jeweiligen Statsformen und [LINK=CONCEPT_WORLD_VIEW]Weltansichten[\LINK]beider Seiten ab. Diese Einheiten werden [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_MILITARY]Kriegsgefangene[\LINK] oder [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_NEANDERTHAL]Gefangene - Neanderthal[\LINK].Wenn du eine Stadt nieder brennst, kannst du zusätzlich [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_CIVILIAN]Gefangene - Zivilisten[\LINK] und [LINK=UNIT_FREED_SLAVE]Gefangene - Befreite Sklaven[\LINK] erhalten.[PARAGRAPH:2]Was man mit diesen Einheiten machen kann hängt von der vorherschenden Weltanschauung ab. Wenn Sklaverei vorherrscht, können die Gefangenen als Sklaven verkauft werden oder der Stadt als [LINK=SPECIALIST_SETTLED_SLAVE]ansessiger Sklave[\LINK]zugewiesen werden. Wenn Kanibalismus vorherrscht können sie geschlachtet werden. Wenn Menschenopfer durchgeführt werden, können sie für Kultur und Zufriedenheit geopfert werden.</German>
		<Polish>W rezultacie zwycięskiej walki masz szansę pojmać wrogą jednostkę. Szansa na to zależy od wielu czynników, w tym od aktywnego ustroju w Twoim i przeciwnika imperium oraz od
		The chance of this depends on both your and their civics and [LINK=CONCEPT_WORLD_VIEW]Swiatopoglądu[\LINK]. Te jednostki będą [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_MILITARY]Jeńcamy Wojennymi[\LINK] lub [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_NEANDERTHAL]Jeńcami - Neandertylczykami[\LINK]. Jeśli zajmiesz lub zniszczysz miasto masz także szansę na [LINK=UNIT_CAPTIVE_CIVILIAN]Jeńców - Cywili[\LINK] i [LINK=UNIT_FREED_SLAVE]Wyzwolonych Niewolników[\LINK].[PARAGRAPH:2]To co zrobisz z pojmanymi jednostkami zależy od aktywnego Swiatopoglądu jaki posiada Twoje imperium. Jeśli akceptujesz Niewolnictwo możesz sprzedać Jeńców, lub dołączyć do ludności miasta jako [LINK=SPECIALIST_SETTLED_SLAVE]Osiadli Niewolnicy[\LINK]. Jeśli Twoi ludzi akceptują kanibalizm możesz przeznaczyć jeńców na pożywienie, a jeśli składasz ofiary z ludzi to możesz ofiarować jeńców na ołatarzu co dodaje troche kultury i szczęścia.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_CAPTIVES_TEXT</Tag>
		<English>Captives, Prisoners of War and Slaves</English>
		<French>Prisonniers et esclaves</French>
		<Italian>Prigionieri e schiavi</Italian>
		<Polish>Jeńcy, więźniowie i niewolnicy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_WORLD_VIEW_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The World Views are like civics, but they only have two states on and off. They are an experiment and are implemented as buildings rather than civics due to the number we are thinking of having. Current World Views are:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Cannibalism[\BOLD] - allows the butchering of captives like animals.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Human Sacrifice[\BOLD] - allows the sacrifice of captives.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Slavery[\BOLD] - allows selling or settling captives as slaves.</English>
		<French>Les Visions du monde sont comme les doctrines, mais en étant soit activés ou non. Il s'agit d'un essai expérimental, et sont implémentées en tant que batiment. Les visions du monde actuelles sont:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Cannibalisme[\BOLD] - Permet de manger les prisonniers comme des animaux.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Sacrifice Humain[\BOLD] - Permet le sacrifice des prisonniers.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Esclavage[permet la vente des prisonnier comme esclaves.</French>
		<Italian>Le concezioni del mondo sono come forme di governo, e come tali possono essere attive o no. Sono ancora in fase sperimentale e sono state introdotte come edifici dato che sono poche in confronto alle forme di governo. Le attuali concezioni sono:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Cannibalismo[\BOLD] - permette di uccidere e macellare i prigionieri coome gli animali.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Sacrifici umani[\BOLD] - permette di sacrificare i prigionieri.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Schiavismo[\BOLD] - permette di vendere o utilizzare i prigionieri come schiavi.</Italian>
		<German>Weltanschauung sind wie Gesellschaftsformen, außer das es nur zwei Zustände gibt, aktiv und inaktiv. Diese sind ein Experiment und eher als Gebäude umgesetzt statt als Gesellschaftsformen aufgrund der Anzahl welche wir erwarten. Aktuelle Weltanschauungen sind:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Kannibalismus[\BOLD] - Erlaubt das Schlachten von Gefangenen wie Tiere.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Menschenopfer[\BOLD] - Erlaubt das Opfern von Gefangenen.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][BOLD]Sklaverei[\BOLD] - Erlaubt das Verkaufen oder Ansiedeln von Gefangenen als Sklaven.</German>
		<Polish>Swiatopogląd jest podobny do ustroju. Obecnie istnieją 3 światopoglądy w grze: Kanibalizm, Ofiary z ludzi oraz Niewolnictwo.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_WORLD_VIEW_TEXT</Tag>
		<English>World View</English>
		<French>Vision du Monde</French>
		<Italian>Concezioni del mondo</Italian>
		<German>Weltanschauung</German>
		<Polish>Swiatopogląd</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>