<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 Beyond the Sword -->
<!-- Modified by the World of Civilization Team -->
<!-- Game Text Infos -->
<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_CRYSTAL_GLASSWARE</Tag>
		<English>Crystal Glassware</English>
		<French>Verrerie en cristal</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_CRYSTAL_GLASSWARE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Lead glass is a variety of glass in which lead replaces the calcium content of a typical potash glass. Lead glass contains typically 18-40 weight% lead(II) oxide (PbO), while modern [BOLD]lead crystal[\BOLD], historically also known as flint glass due to the original silica source, contains a minimum of 24% PbO. Lead glass is desirable owing to its decorative properties.[PARAGRAPH:2]Originally discovered by Englishman George Ravenscroft in 1674, the technique of adding lead oxide (in quantities of between 10 and 30%) improved the appearance of the glass and made it easier to melt using sea-coal as a furnace fuel. This technique also increased "working period" making the glass easier to manipulate.[PARAGRAPH:2]The term lead crystal is, by technicality, not an accurate term to describe lead glass, as glass, an amorphous solid, lacks a crystalline structure. The use of the term lead crystal remains popular for historical and commercial reasons. It is retained from the Venetian word cristallo to describe the rock crystal imitated by Murano glassmakers. This naming convention has been maintained to the present day to describe decorative hollow-ware.[PARAGRAPH:2]Lead crystal glassware was formerly used to store and serve drinks, but due to the potential health risks of lead, this is rare nowadays. One alternative material is [BOLD]crystal glass[\BOLD], in which barium oxide, zinc oxide, or potassium oxide are employed instead of lead oxide. Lead-free crystal has a similar refractive index to lead crystal, but it is lighter and it has less dispersive power.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source: Wikipedia</English>
		<French>Le verre au plomb est une variété de verre dans laquelle le plomb remplace la teneur en calcium d'un verre de potasse typique. Le verre au plomb contient généralement 18 à 40% en poids d'oxyde de plomb (PbO), tandis que le cristal au plomb moderne [BOLD] [\ BOLD], historiquement également appelé verre de silex en raison de la source de silice d'origine, contient au moins 24% de PbO . Le verre au plomb est souhaitable en raison de ses propriétés décoratives. [PARAGRAPH:2] Découverte à l'origine par l'Anglais George Ravenscroft en 1674, la technique consistant à ajouter de l'oxyde de plomb (en quantités comprises entre 10 et 30%) améliora l'apparence du verre et le rendit plus facile à fondre en utilisant du charbon marin comme combustible de fournaise. Cette technique a également augmenté la «période de travail», ce qui rend le verre plus facile à manipuler. [PARAGRAPH:2] Le terme cristal au plomb n'est pas, par technicité, un terme précis pour décrire le verre au plomb, car le verre, un solide amorphe, n'a pas de structure cristalline. L'utilisation du terme cristal au plomb reste populaire pour des raisons historiques et commerciales. Il est retenu du mot vénitien cristallo pour décrire le cristal de roche imité par les verriers de Murano. Cette convention de dénomination a été maintenue jusqu'à nos jours pour décrire les articles creux décoratifs.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source: Wikipedia</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_FAKE_GEMS</Tag>
		<English>Fake Gems</English>
		<French>Fausses Gemmes</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_FAKE_GEMS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Faience beads were common in the ancient world, being similar to glaze they were made by grinding quartz, mixing it with a colouring agent and fireing. The Harappan craftsmen made fake Tourquise and Lapis beads that were considered better than the natural stone because they did not tarnish.</English>
		<French>Les perles de faïence étaient courantes dans le monde antique, étant similaires au glacis, elles étaient fabriquées en broyant du quartz, en le mélangeant avec un colorant et en cuisant. Les artisans Harappan fabriquaient de fausses perles Tourquise et Lapis qui étaient considérées comme meilleures que la pierre naturelle car elles ne ternissaient pas.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_MING_VASE</Tag>
		<English>Ming Vase</English>
		<French>Vase Ming</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_MING_VASE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Ming dynasty (1368-1644) saw an extraordinary period of innovation in ceramic manufacture. Kilns investigated new techniques in design and shapes, showing a predilection for colour and painted design, and an openness to foreign forms. The Yongle Emperor (1402-24) was especially curious about other countries (as evidenced by his support of the eunuch Zheng He's extended exploration of the Indian Ocean), and enjoyed unusual shapes, many inspired by Islamic metalwork. During the Xuande period, a technical refinement was introduced in the preparation of the cobalt used for underglaze blue decoration.[PARAGRAPH:2]Prior to this the cobalt had been brilliant in colour, but with a tendency to bleed in firing; by adding manganese the colour was duller, but the line crisper. Xuande porcelain is now considered among the finest of all Ming output. Enamelled decoration (such as the one at left) was perfected under the Chenghua Emperor (1464-87), and greatly prized by later collectors. Indeed, by the late 16th century, Chenghua and Xuande era works  especially wine cups  had grown so much in popularity, that their prices nearly matched genuine antique wares of the Song dynasty or even older. This esteem for relatively recent ceramics excited much scorn on the part of literati scholars (such as Wen Zhenheng, Tu Long, and Gao Lian, who is cited below); these men fancied themselves arbiters of taste and found the painted aesthetic 'vulgar'[PARAGRAPH:2]In addition to these decorative innovations, the late Ming dynasty underwent a dramatic shift towards a market economy, exporting porcelain around the world on an unprecedented scale. Thus aside from supplying porcelain for domestic use, the kilns at Jingdezhen became the main production centre for large-scale porcelain exports to Europe starting with the reign of the Wanli Emperor (1572-1620). By this time, kaolin and pottery stone were mixed in about equal proportions. Kaolin produced wares of great strength when added to the paste; it also enhanced the whiteness of the body - a trait that became a much sought after property, especially when form blue-and-white wares grew in popularity. Pottery stone could be fired at a lower temperature (1,250 °C; 2,280 °F) than paste mixed with kaolin, which required 1,350 °C (2,460 °F). These sorts of variations were important to keep in mind because the large southern egg-shaped kiln varied greatly in temperature. Near the firebox it was hottest; near the chimney, at the opposite end of the kiln, it was cooler.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source: Wikipedia</English>
		<French>La dynastie Ming (1368-1644) a connu une période extraordinaire d'innovation dans la fabrication de la céramique. Les fours ont exploré de nouvelles techniques de conception et de formes, montrant une prédilection pour la couleur et le design peint, et une ouverture aux formes étrangères. L'empereur Yongle (1402-24) était particulièrement curieux au sujet des autres pays (comme en témoigne son soutien à l'eunuque Zheng He, exploration étendue de l'océan Indien), et jouissait de formes inhabituelles, dont beaucoup s'inspiraient de la métallurgie islamique. Pendant la période Xuande, un raffinement technique a été introduit dans la préparation du cobalt utilisé pour la décoration du bleu sous glaçure. [PARAGRAPH:2] Avant cela, le cobalt avait une couleur brillante, mais avec une tendance à saigner lors de la cuisson; en ajoutant du manganèse, la couleur était plus terne, mais la ligne était plus nette. La porcelaine de Xuande est désormais considérée comme l'une des plus belles sorties Ming. La décoration émaillée (comme celle de gauche) a été perfectionnée sous l'empereur Chenghua (1464-87), et très appréciée par les collectionneurs ultérieurs. En effet, à la fin du XVIe siècle, les œuvres de l'ère Chenghua et Xuande, en particulier les tasses à vin, avaient tellement gagné en popularité, que leurs prix correspondaient presque à de véritables objets antiques de la dynastie Song ou même plus anciens. Cette estime pour les céramiques relativement récentes a suscité beaucoup de mépris de la part des érudits lettrés (tels que Wen Zhenheng, Tu Long et Gao Lian, qui est cité ci-dessous); ces hommes s'imaginaient arbitres du goût et trouvaient l'esthétique peinte «vulgaire»[PARAGRAPH:2]Source: Wikipedia</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_TERRA_SIGILLIATA</Tag>
		<English>Terra Sigilliata</English>
		<French>Céramique sigillée</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_TERRA_SIGILLIATA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Terra Sigillata is a term with at least three distinct meanings: as a description of medieval medicinal earth; in archaeology, as a general term for some of the fine red Ancient Roman pottery with glossy surface slips made in specific areas of the Roman Empire; and more recently, as a description of a contemporary studio pottery technique supposedly inspired by ancient pottery. Usually roughly translated as 'sealed earth', the meaning of 'terra sigillata' is 'clay bearing little images' (Latin sigilla), not 'clay with a sealed (impervious) surface'. The archaeological term is applied, however, to plain-surfaced pots as well as those decorated with figures in relief.[PARAGRAPH:2]Terra sigillata as an archaeological term refers chiefly to a specific type of plain and decorated tableware made in Italy and in Gaul (France and the Rhineland) during the Roman Empire. These vessels have glossy surface slips ranging from a soft lustre to a brilliant glaze-like shine, in a characteristic colour range from pale orange to bright red; they were produced in standard shapes and sizes and were manufactured on an industrial scale and widely exported. The sigillata industries grew up in areas where there were existing traditions of pottery manufacture, and where the clay deposits proved suitable. The products of the Italian workshops are also known as Arretine ware, and have been collected and admired since the Renaissance. The wares made in the Gaulish factories are often referred to by English-speaking archaeologists as samian ware. Closely related pottery fabrics made in the North African and Eastern provinces of the Roman Empire are not usually referred to as terra sigillata, but by more specific names, e.g. African red slip wares. All these types of pottery are significant for archaeologists: they can often be closely dated, and their distribution casts light on aspects of the ancient Roman economy.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source: Wikipedia</English>
		<French>La Céramique sigillée, ou Terra sigillata est un terme ayant au moins trois significations distinctes: comme description de la terre médicinale médiévale; en archéologie, comme un terme général pour certains de la fine poterie romaine rouge antique avec des glissements de surface brillants réalisés dans des zones spécifiques de l'Empire romain; et plus récemment, comme description d'une technique de poterie d'atelier contemporaine supposément inspirée de la poterie ancienne. Généralement grossièrement traduit par «terre scellée», le sens de «terra sigillata» est «argile portant de petites images» (sigilla latin), et non «argile avec une surface scellée (imperméable)». Le terme archéologique s'applique cependant aux pots à surface lisse ainsi qu'à ceux décorés de figures en relief.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source: Wikipedia</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GLAZE_MAKER</Tag>
		<English>Glaze Maker</English>
		<French>Confectionneur d'émail</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GLAZE_MAKER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Glaze is used to cover pottery and other earthernware.</English>
		<French>La Glaçure, ou émail est utilisé pour couvrir la poterie et autres faïences.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GLAZE_MAKER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Improve your citys health</English>
		<French>Améliore la santé de vos villes</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HARAPPAN_FAKE_GEMS</Tag>
		<English>Harappan Fake Gems</English>
		<French>Fausses Gemmes harappéennes</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HARAPPAN_FAKE_GEMS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Harappan civilization was in the Indus region 3,000BC</English>
		<French>La civilisation harappéenne était dans la région de l'Indus 3000 avant JC</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HARAPPAN_FAKE_GEMS_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Provides Fake Gems</English>
		<French>Produit des fausses Gemmes</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MING_VASE_WORKSHOP</Tag>
		<English>Ming Vase Workshop</English>
		<French>Atelier de Vase Ming</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MING_VASE_WORKSHOP_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build this to provide you with some trade goods.</English>
		<French>Construisez-le pour vous fournir des biens commerciaux.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MURANO_GLASSMAKERS</Tag>
		<English>Murano Glassmakers</English>
		<French>Verrier de Murano</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MURANO_GLASSMAKERS_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Provides Crystal Glass</English>
		<French>Produit des verreries de Crystal</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TERRA_SIGILLIATA_WORKSHOP</Tag>
		<English>Terra Sigilliata Workshop</English>
		<French>Atelier de Céramique sigillée</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TERRA_SIGILLIATA_WORKSHOP_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build this to provide you with some trade goods.</English>
		<French>Construisez-le pour vous fournir des biens commerciaux.</French>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
