<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STRATEGIC_GRAIN_RESERVE</Tag>
		<English>Strategic Grain Reserve</English>
		<French>La Réserve Stratégique de Céréales</French>
		<German>Strategische Kornreserve</German>
		<Polish>Strategiczne Rezerwy Ziarna</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STRATEGIC_GRAIN_RESERVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Strategic Grain Reserve allows a population to store food in huge grain silos as a hedge against possible starvation during times of severe drought.</English>
		<French>La Réserve Stratégique de Céréales permet à la population de stocker de la nourriture dans des immenses silos à grains, comme précaution contre les famines qui pourraient advenir.</French>
		<Polish>Rezerwy żywności przygotowywane na wypadek klęsk żywiołowych, wojny, epidemii itp.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STRATEGIC_GRAIN_RESERVE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Strategic Grain Reserve[COLOR_REVERT] provides a free Ganary in all of your cities and a 20% food bonus in the founding city.  It increases it's city's odds of generating a Great Engineer.</English>
		<French>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]La Réserve Stratégique de Céréales[COLOR_REVERT] fournit un grenir gratuit dans chaque ville, et un bonus de 20% de nourriture lors de l'établissement d'une ville. Elle augmente la probabilité de donner naissance à un ingénieur illustre.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE</Tag>
		<English>Topkapi Palace</English>
		<French>Le Palais Topkapi</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Palazzo Topkapi</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pałac Topkapi</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Topkapi Palace is a palace in Istanbul, Turkey, which was the official and primary residence in the city of the Ottoman Sultans, from 1465 to 1853. The palace was a setting for state occasions and royal entertainments and is a major tourist attraction today. The name directly translates as "Cannongate Palace", from the palace being named after a nearby, now lost gate.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Initial construction started in 1459, ordered by Sultan Mehmed II, the conqueror of Byzantine Constantinople. The palace is a complex made up of four main courtyards and many smaller buildings. At the height of its existence as a royal residence, the palace was home to as many as 4,000 people, formerly covering a larger area with a long shoreline. The complex has been expanded over the centuries, with many renovations such as after the 1509 earthquake and 1665 fire.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Topkapi Palace gradually lost its importance at the end of the 17th century, as the Sultans preferred to spend more time in their new palaces along the Bosporus. In 1853, Sultan Abdül Mecid I decided to move the court to the newly built Dolmabahçe Palace, the first European-style palace in the city. Some functions, such as the imperial treasury, the library, mosque and mint, were retained though.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]After the end of the Ottoman Empire in 1921, Topkapi Palace was transformed by government decree on April 3, 1924 into a museum of the imperial era. The Topkapi Palace Museum is under the administration of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism. The palace complex has hundreds of rooms and chambers, but only the most important are accessible to the public today. The complex is guarded by officials of the ministry as well as armed guards of the Turkish military. The palace is full of examples of Ottoman architecture and also contains large collections of porcelain, robes, weapons, shields, armor, Ottoman miniatures, Islamic calligraphic manuscripts and murals, as well as a display of Ottoman treasure and jewelry.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Topkapi Palace is among those monuments belonging to the "Historic Areas of Istanbul", which became a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1985, and is described in Criterion iv as "the best example[s] of ensembles of palaces [...] of the Ottoman period."</English>
		<Italian>Il Palazzo Topkapi è un palazzo di Istanbul, in Turchia, che fu usato dei sultani Ottomani come residenza dal 1465 al 1853; il palazzo era il luogo designato per gli incontri di stato e l'intrattenimento della famiglia reale, mentre al giorno d'oggi è una grande attrazione turistica. Il nome viene tradotto con "Palazzo della Porta del Cannone", basandosi su una porta vicina ora distrutta.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]La costruzione iniziò nel 1459 su ordine del Sultano Mehmed II, il conquistatore di Costantinopoli. Il palazzo è un complesso formato da 4 cortili principlai e molti edifici più piccoli; nel suo periodo di massimo splendore il palazzo ospitava più di 4,000 persone, occupando un'area sempre più grande lungo la costa; il complesso si è quindi ingrandito nel corso dei secoli, con molti restauri come il territorio del 1509 e l'incendio del 1665.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Il Palazzo Topkapi perse gradualmente importanza alla fine del XVII secolo, quando i Sultani iniziarono a trascorrere più tempo nei loro nuovi palazzi lungo il Bosforo. Nel 1853 il Sultano Abdül Mecid I decise di spostare la propria corte nel Palazzo Dolmabahçe, il primo palazzo in stile europeo della città. Alcune funzioni rimasero però al Palazzo Topkapi, come il tesoro, la biblioteca, la moschea e la zecca.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Dopo la fine dell'Impero Ottomano nel 1921 il palazzo Topkapi fu trasformato dal decreto governativo del 3 aprile 1924 nel museo dell'Era imperiale. Il Museo del Palazzo Topkapi è sotto la giurisdizione del Ministero della cultura e del turismo; il complesso ha centinaia di stanze, ma solo le più importanti possono essere visitate. Il complesso è sorvegliato da ufficiali del ministero e da guardie armate dell'esercito turco. Il palazzo è pieno di esampi di architettura e contiene grandi collezioni di porcellane, abiti, armi, scudi, armature, miniature Ottomane, manoscritti di calligrafia islamica e murali, oltre a mostre del tesoro e dei gioielli ottomani.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Il Palazzo Topkapi è uno dei monumenti appartenenti alla "Area storica di Istanbul", che fu dichiarato dall'UNESCO Patrimonio dell'umanità nel 1985, descritto da Criterion IV come "the best example[s] of ensembles of palaces [...] of the Ottoman period."</Italian>
		<Polish>Topkapi Sarayi - pałac w centrum Stambułu, który był rezydencją sułtanówprzez ponad 380 lat, od 1453 roku. Budowę rozpoczęto za panowania sułtanaMehmeda II Zdobywcy w 1453 roku, zaraz po zdobyciu Konstantynopola, a zakończono w 1465 roku. Ostatnim używającym pałacu sułtanem byłMahmud II (do 1839 roku). Sułtan Abdulmecid I przeniósł siedzibę władców do pałacu DolmabahCe.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Topkapi Palace[COLOR_REVERT] strengthens all vassals under your rule by granting them a gold and combat experience bonus every turn. Additionally, you will have a 20% chance of training your vassal's UU instead of the standard unit when training a unit of the same unit class.</English>
		<Italian>Il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Palazzo Topkapi[COLOR_REVERT] rinforza i tuoi vassalli fornendo loro oro e bonus all'esperienza in combattimento ogni turno. In più, hai una chance del 20% di addestrare l'unità unica del tuo vassallo quando addestri un'unità standard delle stessa categoria.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_YELLOW]HELP: [COLOR_REVERT]Strengthens Vassals, 20% Chance to Train a Vassal's Unique Unit</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Renforce les vassaux[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]20% Chance d'enrôler une unité unique de Vassal</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Rinforza i vassalli[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]20% Chance di addestrare l'unità unica di un vassallo</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UN_MISSION</Tag>
		<English>UN Mission</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mission de l'ONU</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>UNO Mission:UNO Missionen</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Missione ONU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Misión de la ONU</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Misja ONZ</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UN_MISSION_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>UN Missions allow for the construction of UN Peacekeeping Forces.</English>
		<French>Les Missions de l'ONU permettent la formation de soldats de la Paix de l'ONU.</French>
		<German>UNO Missionen erlauben den Einsatz von UN Friedenstruppen.</German>
		<Italian>La missione ONU permette la costruzione delle forze di pace ONU</Italian>
		<Spanish>Las Misiones de la ONU permiten el entrenamiento de las Fuerzas pacificadoras de la ONU.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Organizacja Narodów Zjednoczonych – uniwersalna organizacja międzynarodowa. ONZ stawia sobie za cel zapewnienie pokoju i bezpieczeństwa międzynarodowego, rozwój współpracy między narodami oraz popieranie przestrzegania praw człowieka. Idea powołania nowej organizacji, powstała jeszcze w czasie trwania II wojny światowej, na konferencji w Teheranie w 1943. Jej głównym pomysłodawcą był prezydent USA Franklin Delano Roosevelt, a jej nazwę zaproponował premier Wielkiej Brytanii Winston Churchill (określenie "narody zjednoczone" w trakcie wojny stosowano nieraz dla Aliantów). W drugiej połowie 1944 przedstawiciele Francji, Chin, Wielkiej Brytanii, USA oraz ZSRR spotkali się w Waszyngtonie, gdzie przedyskutowano zakres, cele i sposoby działania nowej organizacji. 25 kwietnia 1945 roku zwołano pierwszą konferencję ONZ w San Francisco, w której uczestniczyło 50 państw z całego świata – pierwszych członków organizacji. Za członka ONZ od założenia uznawana jest też Polska, której przedstawiciele z powodów politycznych nie mogli uczestniczyć w konferencji w San Francisco. Podczas konferencji, 26 czerwca, podpisano Kartę Narodów Zjednoczonych, akt prawny regulujący działalność ONZ. Organizację Narodów Zjednoczonych powołano do życia 24 października 1945, kiedy postanowienia konferencji ratyfikowało pięciu przyszłych stałych członków Rady Bezpieczeństwa (Chiny, Francja, ZSRR, Wielka Brytania i USA), oraz większość pozostałych państw członkowskich. Powołanie ONZ położyło jednocześnie kres działalności Ligi Narodów, która rozwiązała się formalnie 18 kwietnia 1946, przekazując pełnienie swej misji nowej organizacji. W grudniu 1945 Kongres USA wystosował propozycję, aby siedziba ONZ mieściła się w Nowym Jorku, co zostało przez organizację zaakceptowane. Budynek siedziby głównej otwarto 9 stycznia 1951 roku na terenach podarowanych ONZ przez Johna Rockefellera, gdzie mieści się do dziś. Część instytucji funkcjonuje jednak w innych miastach świata, m.in. w Genewie, Hadze, Nairobi i Wiedniu.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UN_MISSION_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The United Nations (UN) is an international organization whose stated aims are to facilitate cooperation in international law, international security, economic development, social progress and human rights issues. The UN was founded in 1945 to replace the League of Nations, to stop wars between nations and provide a platform for dialogue.</English>
		<French>L'Organisation des Nations unies (ONU) est une organisation internationale, regroupant, à quelques exceptions près, tous les états de la planète. Distincte des états qui la composent, l'organisation a pour finalité la paix internationale. Ses objectifs sont de faciliter la coopération dans les domaines du droit international, de la sécurité internationale, du développement économique, du progrès social et des Droits de l'homme. L'ONU est fondée en 1945 en remplacement de la Société des Nations (SDN), qui n'avait pas tenu son rôle en n'évitant pas la Seconde Guerre mondiale, pour mettre fin aux guerres entre les pays et pour fournir une plateforme de dialogue.</French>
		<German>Die Vereinten Nationen (UNO) ist eine internationale Organisation, deren festgesetzte Ziele die Unterstützung der internationalen Zusammenarbeit in Bereichen des Rechts, der Sicherheit, Wirtschaftsentwicklung, des sozialen Fortschritts und der Menschenrechte sind. Die UNO wurde im Jahre 1945 gegründet, um die Liga der Nationen ersetzen, aber vor allem um die Kriege zwischen den Nationen zu beenden und eine Plattform für den Dialog zu ermöglichen.</German>
		<Italian>L'organizzazione delle Nazioni Unite (ONU) è un'organizzazione internazionale i cui scopi sono di facilitare la cooperazione nelle leggi internazionali, la sicurezza internazionale, lo sviluppo economico, progresso sociale e la difesa dei diritti umanitari. L'ONU fo fondata nel 1945 per sostituire la Società delle Nazioni, per fermare le guerre tra le nazioni e fornire una piattaforma di dialogo.</Italian>
		<Polish>Misja ONZ pozwala na budowę sił pokojowych ONZ.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>