<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HEALTH_SPA</Tag>
		<English>Health Spa</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Station Thermale</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Polish>Spa</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HEALTH_SPA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Often found at natural springs Health Spas are places for taking the waters and hopefully getting healthy.  they have existed since antuquity.</English>
		<Polish>Uzdrowisko - miejscowość dysponująca naturalnymi czynnikami leczniczymi, do których zalicza się wody mineralne oraz właściwości klimatyczne. Warunkiem powstania miejscowości uzdrowiskowej jest występowanie walorów przyrodniczych. Wody mineralne służą do kąpieli leczniczych i do kuracji pitnej, a właściwości klimatyczne stosowane są wklimatoterapii.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HEALTH_SPA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>An Health Spa provides a health boost to the city it is built in plus provides some protection against disease.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- Universal -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UNIVERSAL_HEALTH_CARE</Tag>
		<English>Universal Health Care</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Couverture Santé Universelle</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Polish>Powszechna Opieka Zdrowotna</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UNIVERSAL_HEALTH_CARE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Universal health care is a socialist government system that seeks to provide health care access and coverage to all members of society.  It is implemented through legislation, regulation and increased taxation (Redistribution of Wealth).</English>
		<Polish>Opieka zdrowotna - ogół środków mających na celu zapobieganie i leczenie chorób. Realizowana jest za pomocą systemu opieki zdrowotnej.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UNIVERSAL_HEALTH_CARE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Universal Health Care[COLOR_REVERT] National Wonder increases the population in every city by 1.</English>
		<French>La [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Couverture Santé Universelle[COLOR_REVERT] est une Merveille Nationale qui augment d'1 la population de chaque Ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UNIVERSAL_HEALTH_CARE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_YELLOW]HELP: [COLOR_REVERT]All cities receive a one time +1 Population increase.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Chaque ville reçoit un bonus de +1 en Population.</French>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Populacja we wszystkich miastach jednorazowo zwiększa się o 1.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- End Universal -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PERSIAN_APOTHECARY</Tag>
		<English>Persian Cusine Supply Store</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Magasin de Cuisine Perse</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Polish>Perska Restauracja</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WISE_WOMAN</Tag>
		<English>Wise Woman</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Vieille Femme</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WISE_WOMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>As gatherers explored their surroundings and what the results of consuming various native substances they began to learn what would make a person sick, what would provide sustenance, and what would assist in alleviating various symptoms of disease, injury and discomfort.  The wise women who had spent their younger years gathering, keeping and sharing verbal records of what was beneficial for various purposes would often be turned to by the tribe as a source of healing and guidance.  This role grew in significance as the human mind evolved into more and more advanced forms deepening the capacity for knowledge retention and application.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WISE_WOMAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Use the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Wise Woman[COLOR_REVERT] to heal units, develop early healing experience awards, and aid in keeping disease under control in your earliest cities. They are extremely useful, but expensive to produce and maintain.  Additionally, Wise Women require Wild Herbs in the city in which they are built. The Wise Woman can be upgraded to an [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Healer[COLOR_REVERT], after discovering Naturopathy.</English>
		<French>Utilisez les [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Vieilles femmes[COLOR_REVERT] pour soigner vos unités, développer de l'expérience en soin, et garder sous contrôle la prolifération de maladies dans vos villes primitives. Elles sont extrêmement utiles, mais cher à produire et entretenir. De plus, il est nécessaire d'avoir une parcelle d'herbes sauvages pour pouvoir recruter une vieille femme. Après la découverte de la Naturopathie, elles peuvent être améliorées en [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Guérisseurs[COLOR_REVERT].</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEALER</Tag>
		<English>Healer</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Guérisseur</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEALER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Healer provides his patients with medicinal herbs, which were very effective in healing the allergies, and raising and renewing the body vitality.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEALER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Use the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Healer[COLOR_REVERT] to heal troops. They are fast moving, but expensive to produce and maintain.  Additionally, Healers require the Healer's Hut in the city in which they are built. The Healer can be upgraded to an [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Apothecary[COLOR_REVERT], after discovering Education.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Guérisseur[COLOR_REVERT] permet de guérir les troupes. Ils se déplacent rapidement, mais sont coûteux à produire et à entretenir. En outre, les guérisseurs ont besoin d'une cabane de Guérisseur dans la ville dans laquelle ils sont construits. Le guérisseur peut être amélioré en [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT] Apothicaire [COLOR_REVERT], après avoir découvert l'éducation.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOTHECARY</Tag>
		<English>Apothecary</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Apothicaire</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOTHECARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Apothecary provides his patients with medicinal herbs, which were very effective in healing the allergies, and raising and renewing the body vitality.</English>
		<French>L'Apothicaire fournit à ses patients des plantes médicinales, très efficaces pour la guérison des allergies, et permettant d'am renouveler la vitalité du corps.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOTHECARY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Use the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Apothecary[COLOR_REVERT] to heal troops. They are fast moving, but expensive to produce and maintain. The Apothecary starts out with the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Medic1[COLOR_REVERT] promotion.  Additionally, Apothecary require the Apothecary's Shop in the city in which they are built. The Apothecary can be upgraded to an [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Medic[COLOR_REVERT], after discovering Medicine.</English>
		<French>L'[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Apothicaire[COLOR_REVERT] permet de guérir les troupes. Il se déplace rapidement, mais est plutôt coûteux à produire et à entretenir. Il commence avec la promotion Médecine I. En outre, les Apothicaires ont besoin d'une Herboristerie dans la ville dans laquelle ils sont construits. L'Apothicaire peut être amélioré en [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Médecin[COLOR_REVERT], après avoir découvert la Médecine.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HEALERHUT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Healers Hut contains a collection of various herbs and spices that are used to help cure ailments and restore health.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_APOTHECARY_SHOP</Tag>
		<English>Apothecary Shop</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Boutique de l'Apothicaire</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<Polish>Apteka</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_APOTHECARY_SHOP_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In colonial times, the apothecary was more than simply a druggist. An apothecary often provided medical treatment, prescribed medicine, trained apprentices, performed surgery and served as man-midwives. Records kept by 18th-century Williamsburg's apothecaries show they practiced as doctor and even made house calls to treat patients.  Williamsburg apothecaries also sold cooking spices, candles, salad oil, anchovies, toothbrushes, and tobacco, making them true precursors of today's drugstores.</English>
		<Polish>Apteka - placówka handlowa zajmująca się sprzedażą leków i innych produktów medycznych (np. opatrunków, środków higienicznych). Apteki recepturowe zajmują się także przygotowywaniem leków recepturowychzgodnie z przepisaną przez lekarza receptą. W praktyce pacjencikorzystają w aptekach także z konsultacji medycznych w sprawie stosowania poszczególnych leków w przypadku konkretnych dolegliwości, a nawet, w nagłych przypadkach, z najbardziej podstawowej pomocy medycznej, polegającej na udzieleniu pierwszej pomocy i wezwaniu innego wykwalifikowanego personelu (lekarza, felczera, zespołupogotowia ratunkowego itp.).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_APOTHECARY_SHOP_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[SPACE]The Apothecary shop provides health to your city and heals units a small amount.</English>
		<French>La Boutique de l'Apothicaire procure de la santé à votre ville, et améliore la guérison des unités.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_HERBAL_CURES</Tag>
		<English>Herbal Cures</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Remèdes à base de plantes</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<Polish>Leczenie Ziołami</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNITCOMBAT_HEALTH_CARE</Tag>
		<English>Health Care Units</English>
		<French>Unités de soins</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_SPECIALIST_DOCTOR</Tag>
		<English>Doctor</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Docteur en médecine</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Arzt:Arztes:Arzt:Arzt:Ärzte:Ärzte:Ärzten:Ärzte</Text>
			<Gender>male:male:male:male:male:male:male:male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0:0:1:1:1:1</Plural>
		</German>
	</TEXT>
		<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_SPECIALIST_GREAT_DOCTOR</Tag>
		<English>Great Doctor</English>
				<French>
			<Text>Médecin Illustre</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DOCTOR</Tag>
		<English>Great Doctor</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Médecin Illustre</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_SPECIALIST_DOCTOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build the [LINK=BUILDING_HEALERHUT]Healer's Hut[\LINK], [LINK=BUILDING_APOTHECARY_SHOP]Apothecary Shop[\LINK], or a [LINK=BUILDING_HOSPITAL]Hospital[\LINK] to add specialist doctors and increase the odds of getting a Great Doctor.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_DOCTOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Use the Great Doctor to build the [LINK=BUILDING_UNIVERSAL_HEALTH_CARE]Universal Health Care[\LINK] National Wonder, discover a new technology or add to a city as a super specialist.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_BATH</Tag>
		<English>Great Bath of Mohenjo-daro</English>
		<French>Le Grand Bain de Mohenjo-daro</French>
		<Polish>Wielka Łaźnia w Mohenjo-daro</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_BATH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The "great bath" is without doubt the earliest public water tank in the ancient world. The tank itself measures approximately 12 meters north-south and 7 meters wide, with a maximum depth of 2.4 meters. Two wide staircases lead down into the tank from the north and south and small sockets at the edges of the stairs are thought to have held wooden planks or treads. At the foot of the stairs is a small ledge with a brick edging that extends the entire width of the pool. People coming down the stairs could move along this ledge without actually stepping into the pool itself.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB] The floor of the tank is water tight due to finely fitted bricks laid on edge with gypsum plaster and the side walls were constructed in a similar manner. To make the tank even more water tight, a thick layer of bitumen (natural tar) was laid along the sides of the tank and presumably also beneath the floor. Brick colonnades were discovered on the eastern, northern and southern edges. The preserved columns have stepped edges that may have held wooden screens or window frames. Two large doors lead into the complex from the south and other access was from the north and east. A series of rooms are located along the eastern edge of the building and in one room is a well that may have supplied some of the water needed to fill the tank. Rainwater also may have been collected for this purposes, but no inlet drains have been found.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB] The floor of the tank is water tight due to finely fitted bricks laid on edge with gypsum plaster and the side walls were constructed in a similar manner. To make the tank even more water tight, a thick layer of bitumen (natural tar) was laid along the sides of the tank and presumably also beneath the floor. Brick colonnades were discovered on the eastern, northern and southern edges. The preserved columns have stepped edges that may have held wooden screens or window frames. Two large doors lead into the complex from the south and other access was from the north and east. A series of rooms are located along the eastern edge of the building and in one room is a well that may have supplied some of the water needed to fill the tank. Rainwater also may have been collected for this purposes, but no inlet drains have been found.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB] Most scholars agree that this tank would have been used for special religious functions where water was used to purify and renew the well being  of the bathers.</English>
		<French>The "great bath" is without doubt the earliest public water tank in the ancient world. The tank itself measures approximately 12 meters north-south and 7 meters wide, with a maximum depth of 2.4 meters. Two wide staircases lead down into the tank from the north and south and small sockets at the edges du stairs are thought to have held wooden planks or treads. At the foot du stairs is a small ledge with a brick edging that extends the entire width du pool. People coming down the stairs could move along this ledge without actually stepping into the pool itself.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB] The floor du tank is water tight due to finely fitted bricks laid on edge with gypsum plaster and the side walls were constructed in a similar manner. To make the tank even more water tight, a thick layer of bitumen (natural tar) was laid along the sides du tank and presumably also beneath the floor. Brick colonnades were discovered on the eastern, northern and southern edges. The preserved columns have stepped edges that may have held wooden screens or window frames. Two large doors lead into the complex from the south and other access was from the north and east. A series of rooms are located along the eastern edge du building and in one room is a well that may have supplied some du water needed to fill the tank. Rainwater also may have been collected for this purposes, but no inlet drains have been found.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB] The floor du tank is water tight due to finely fitted bricks laid on edge with gypsum plaster and the side walls were constructed in a similar manner. To make the tank even more water tight, a thick layer of bitumen (natural tar) was laid along the sides du tank and presumably also beneath the floor. Brick colonnades were discovered on the eastern, northern and southern edges. The preserved columns have stepped edges that may have held wooden screens or window frames. Two large doors lead into the complex from the south and other access was from the north and east. A series of rooms are located along the eastern edge du building and in one room is a well that may have supplied some du water needed to fill the tank. Rainwater also may have been collected for this purposes, but no inlet drains have been found.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB] Most scholars agree that this tank would have been used for special religious functions where water was used to purify and renew the well being  du bathers.</French>
		<Polish>Wielka Łaźnia, położona w obrębie cytadeli miejskiej. Był to kompleks wielu komnat i ośmiu łazienek usytuowanych wokół basenu o wymiarach 12 x 7 x 2,5 metra. Na krótszych bokach basenu znajdowały się schody ułatwiające wejście i wyjście z basenu. Woda napływała z wykładanej cegłami studni. Dno basenu było pochyłe i strome.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_BATH_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Great Bath[COLOR_REVERT] turns your city plot into a source of fresh water and grants +1 population to all newly built cities until the wonder obsoletes. The fresh water bonus does not obsolete.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Grand Bain[COLOR_REVERT] transforme votre ville en source d'eau douce, et garanti à toutes les nouvelles Villes +1 de population jusqu'à ce qu'il soit obsolète. La source d'eau douce n'est jamais obsolète.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_BATH_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_YELLOW]HELP: [COLOR_REVERT]Creates a Source of Fresh Water. New Cities Built with +1 Population. Fresh Water Bonus does not Obsolete[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Créé une source d'eau douce[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Les Nouvelles Villes construites ont +1 Population[NEWLINE][COLOR_NEGATIVE_TEXT]Le Bonus d'eau douce n'est jamais obsolète[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HIPOCRATIC_OATH</Tag>
		<English>Hippocratic Oath</English>
		<French>Serment d'Hippocrate</French>
		<Polish>Przysięga Hipokratesa</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HIPOCRATIC_OATH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Hippocratic Oath is an oath traditionally taken by physicians pertaining to the ethical practice of medicine. It is widely believed that the oath was written by Hippocrates, the father of western medicine, in the 4th century BC.[PARAGRAPH:2]Hippokrates was an ancient Greek physician of the Age of Pericles, and was considered one of the most outstanding figures in the history of medicine. He is referred to as the "father of medicine".</English>
		<French>The Hippocratic Oath is an oath traditionally taken by physicians pertaining to the ethical practice of medicine. It is widely believed that the oath was written by Hippocrates, the father of western medicine, in the 4th century BC.[PARAGRAPH:2]Hippokrates was an ancient Greek physician du Age of Pericles, and was considered one du most outstanding figures in the history of medicine. He is referred to as the "father of medicine".</French>
		<Polish>Przysięga Hipokratesa - składana przez lekarzy w starożytności, zawierała podstawy dzisiejszej etyki lekarskiej. Wbrew powszechnej opinii jej autorem nie był sam Hipokrates, lecz jego uczniowie, należący do kręgupitagorejczyków (stąd między innymi niechęć do leczenia operacyjnego). Zaś samo sformułowanie podstawowych zasad etycznych zawodu lekarza wielu przypisuje Imhotepowi.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HIPOCRATIC_OATH_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Hippocratic Oath[COLOR_REVERT] provides a free  [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]healer's hut[COLOR_REVERT] in all your cities.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Serment d'Hippocrate[COLOR_REVERT] procure une [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]cabane de guérisseur [COLOR_REVERT] dans chacune de vos villes.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SURGEON</Tag>
		<English>Surgeon</English>
		<French>Chirurgien</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SURGEON_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>More skilled than a medic, surgeons can heal soldiers in the battlefield better and faster.</English>
		<French>Plus expérimenté que le médecin, les Chirurgiens peuvent soigner plus rapidement les soldats sur le champ de bataille.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SURGEON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In medicine, a surgeon is a specialist in surgery. Surgery is a broad category of invasive medical treatment that involves the cutting of a body, whether that of a human or a other animal, for a specific reason such as the removal of diseased tissue or to repair a tear or breakage. Surgeons may be physicians, podiatrists, dentists, or veterinarians. Surgeons usually train for longer than other medical specialists.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HOSPITAL_SHIP</Tag>
		<English>Hospital Ship</English>
		<French>Navire Hôpital</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HOSPITAL_SHIP_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A hospital ship is a ship designated for primary function as a floating medical treatment facility or hospital. Most are operated by the military forces (mostly navies) of various countries, as they are intended to be used in or near war zones. Although attacking a hospital ship is a war crime, belligerent navies have the right to board such ships for inspections.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HOSPITAL_SHIP_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Hospital Ship[COLOR_REVERT] is medical navy unit which heal every unit in the same tile.</English>
		<German>Hospital Ships are used to heal units.  Graphics by Aungi and Nsftpoeopas.</German>
		<Italian>Hospital Ships are used to heal units.  Graphics by Aungi and Nsftpoeopas.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hospital Ships are used to heal units.  Graphics by Aungi and Nsftpoeopas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HOSPITAL_SHIP_2</Tag>
		<English>Hospital Ship II</English>
		<French>Navire Hôpital II</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HOSPITAL_SHIP_2_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Hospital Ship II[COLOR_REVERT] is medical navy unit which heal every unit in the same tile.</English>
		<German>Hospital Ships are used to heal units.  Graphics by Aungi and Nsftpoeopas.</German>
		<Italian>Hospital Ships are used to heal units.  Graphics by Aungi and Nsftpoeopas.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hospital Ships are used to heal units.  Graphics by Aungi and Nsftpoeopas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AMBULANCE</Tag>
		<English>Ambulance (WWI)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AMBULANCE_II</Tag>
		<English>Ambulance (WWII)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AMBULANCE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Ambulances are used to heal units.  Graphics by 	Aungi and Nuvoloblu.</English>
		<French>Les Ambulances sont utilisés pour soigner les unités.  Graphiques: Aungi et Nuvoloblu.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- Immigration Mod -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_IMMIGRANT</Tag>
		<English>Immigrant</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_IMMIGRANT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>City must have a population of at least 10 and will loose 2 population points to train 1 immigrant.  The Immigrant will add 1 population point when joined to a city having a population of less than 7.  The maintenance cost of 2 gold per turn ends when the immigrant joins a city.</English>
		<French>La Ville doit avoir une population d'au moins 2, et perdra 2 de population pour entrainer un immigrant. L'Immigrant ajoute 1 de population à une ville de population inférieure à 7. Le cout d'entretien de 2 or par tour s'applique jusqu'à ce que l'immigrant a rejoint une ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_IMMIGRANT_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build immigrants in cities that are suffering from unrest due to over population.  Use the Immigrant to increase the population and the productive capacity of a new city.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_IMMIGRANT_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_YELLOW]HELP: [COLOR_REVERT]Adds 1 population point when joined to a city.[NEWLINE]Decreases the population in the city where it is built by 2</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Ajoute 1 de population lorsqu'il rejoint une ville.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MESSAGE_IMMIGRATION</Tag>
		<English>%s1_city welcomes the new immigrants with open arms.</English>
		<French>%s1_city accueille les nouveaux immigrants à bras ouverts.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_JOIN_CITY_MOUSE_OVER</Tag>
		<English>Join City</English>
		<French>Rejoindre la Ville</French>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- End Immigration Mod -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ISHTAR</Tag>
		<English>The Ishtar Gate</English>
		<French>La Porte d'Ishtar</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Porta di Ishtar</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Brama Isztar</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ISHTAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Ishtar Gate was the eighth gate to the inner city of Babylon. It was constructed in about 575 BC by order of King Nebuchadnezzar II on the north side of the city. Dedicated to the Assyrian goddess Ishtar, the Gate was constructed of blue glazed tiles with alternating rows of bas-relief sirrush (dragons) and aurochs. The roof and doors of the gate were of cedar, according to the dedication plaque. Through the gate ran the Processional Way which was lined with walls covered in lions on glazed bricks (about 120 of them). Statues of the gods were paraded through the gate and down the Processional Way each year during the New Year's celebration. It was originally considered one of the Seven Wonders of the world until, in the 6th century AD, it was replaced with the Lighthouse of Alexandria.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]A reconstruction of the Ishtar Gate and Processional Way was built at the Pergamon Museum in Berlin out of material excavated by Robert Koldewey and finished in the 1930s. It includes the inscription plaque. It stands 47 feet high and 100 feet wide (14 meters by 30 meters). The excavation ran from 1902-1914 and during that time 45 ft of the foundation of the gate was uncovered. Parts of the gate and lions from the Processional Way are in various other museums around the world. A reproduction of the gate was built in Iraq as the entrance to a museum that was never completed. Damage to the gate has supposedly occurred since the Iraq war.</English>
		<French>La porte d'Ishtar est une des huit portes de la cité intérieure de Babylone, elle fut construite au nord de la cité aux alentours de -575 (empire néobabylonien) sur ordre du roi Nabuchodonosor II. Cette porte est dédiée à la déesse éponyme Ishtar. La porte d'Ishtar est l'aboutissement de la voie processionnelle au nord de Babylone. Elle est le symbole même de Babylone. Son nom cultuel est "Ishtar Sakipat Tebisha", ou "Ishtar est victorieuse de ses ennemis". La porte est construite selon le principe de la double porte, c'est-à-dire qu'il y a un mur extérieur et un mur intérieur. La première porte (intérieure) fait 28m de large, 11m de long et est flanquée de deux tours de part et d'autre du passage. La seconde porte (extérieure) est la plus grande. Elle est encastrée dans le rempart intérieur, et est flanquée de deux tours de 9,50m de haut. Entre les deux tours se trouve une cour ouverte. Il y a eu différentes phases de constructions pour la porte d'Ishtar, qui ont à chaque fois modifié son décor: La première phase est caractérisée par un décor émaillé, et la dernière par des bas-reliefs en brique émaillée et colorée. Sur les murs des portes, on trouve des rangées de taureau et de dragons. Le taureau symbolise le dieu Adad (dieu de l'orage). Le dragon est une créature hybride: une queue et un corps de serpent, les pattes arrières en serres d'aigle. La tête du dragon (Mushkhushu) est une représentation du dieu Marduk (et le dragon lui-même est un attribut du dieu Marduk). On note que le lion d'Ishtar n'est pas présent dans les représentations. Sur la porte on peut également noter la présence d'une inscription de Nabuchodonosor II signifiant les détails de la construction, comme sur la voie processionnelle.</French>
		<German>Das Ischtar-Tor - eines der Stadttore von Babylon - sowie die Prozessionsstrasse wurde von Nebukadnezar II. (605-562 v. Chr.) errichtet. Babylon war die Hauptstadt Babyloniens und lag am Euphrat im heutigen Zentral-Irak. Das Ischtar-Tor befindet sich heute im Vorderasiatischen Museum, das im Pergamonmuseum in Berlin untergebracht ist, und ist dort seit 1930 zugänglich. Das Ischtar-Tor befand sich in Babylon am Ende einer von Mauern umgebenen Prozessionsstrasse, die ursprünglich zwischen 20 und 24 Meter breit war und eine Länge von etwa 250 Metern hatte. Diese Prozessionsstrasse wurde von den Babyloniern alljährlich für das Neujahrsfest im Frühling benutzt. Die Mauern, die mit hauptsächlich blau glasierten Ziegeln verkleidet war, war mit Tierdarstellungen verziert, wie sie sich auch am Ischtar-Tor selbst befanden. Das Tor bewachte den Zugang zu einer 90 m hohen Zikkurat, die von einem Marduk-Schrein gekrönt war. Das Ischtar-Tor und die Prozessionsstrasse wurden im Pergamonmuseum unter Verwendung der glasierten Originalziegel rekonstruiert. Die Wände des Tors sind ausgeschmückt mit Darstellungen von Löwen, Stieren und Drachen, die Symbole für die Hauptgottheiten Babylons sind. Die dargestellten Löwen sind Symbole der Göttin Ischtar, Herrin des Himmels, Liebesgöttin und Beschützerin der Armee. Die schlangenähnliche Drachen stellen Muschku (auch Bel genannt), den Gott der Stadt und der Fruchtbarkeit dar, der ewiges Leben schenkte. Die wilden Stiere symbolisierten den Wettergott Adad. "Für Gott Muschku und Nabu befestigte ich das Innere der Strasse und darüber legte ich eine mächtige Anfüllung aus glänzendem Staub. Möget ihr Götter fröhlich wandeln auf diesem Weg", steht auf den ca. 20000 Ziegeln.</German>
		<Italian>La Porta di Ishtar era l'ottavo cancello nel centro urbano di Babilonia; venne costruita intorno al 575 a.C. per ordine del re Nebuchadrezzar II sul lato nord della città. Dedicato alla dea Ishtar, il cancello venne costruito con mattonelle lustrate blu con file alternate di bassorilievi di draghi e tori. Il tetto e le porte del cancello erano di cedro, secondo la piastra di dedica. Attraverso il cancello passava la Via Processionale, delimitata da pareti ornate con circa 120 leoni. Le statue degli dei venivano portate in processione attraverso il cancello e lungo la Via Processionale ogni anno durante la celebrazione del nuovo anno. Una ricostruzione del cancello di Ishtar e della Vua Processionale è stata realizzata al Museo di Pergamo a Berlino, grazie a materiale scavato nelle vicinanze da Robert Koldewey e rifinito negli anni '30, tra cui la piastra dell'iscrizione. Era alta circa 47 piedi e larga 32 piedi. Lo scavo durò dal 1902 al 1914 e durante quel tempo vennero rimossi 45 piedi di terreno fino alle fondamenta del cancello. Le parti del cancello e dei leoni della Via Processionale sono divise in vari musei intorno al mondo: soltanto due musei hanno acquistato i draghi mentre i leoni sono andato a parecchi musei. Ad esempio il museo di archeologia di Costantinopoli ha i leoni, i draghi e i tori; l'Istituto delle arti di Detroit possiede un drago; il Louvre, il Museo metropolitano di arte a New York, l'Istituto orientale di Chicago, la Scuola del Rhode Island di disegno e il Museo delle arti di Boston hanno ciascuno dei leoni. Una riproduzione del cancello è stata realizzata in Irak come entrata ad un museo, che però non è mai stato completato.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La Puerta de Istar (o de Ishtar) era originalmente una de las 8 puertas monumentales  (14 metros de altura por 10 de ancho) de la muralla interior de Babilonia, a través de la cual se accedía al templo de Bel, donde se celebraban las fiestas propias del año nuevo. El nombre de Istar lo recibe de la diosa del mismo nombre a la cual estaba consagrada. Fue construida en el año 575 adC por Nabucodonosor II en el lado norte de la ciudad. Se compone de numerosos ladrillos de adobe, la mayoría pintados de color azul (lo que la hacía contrastar fuertemente con todos los edificios de su alrededor), mientras que otros son dorados o rojizos. éstos últimos se disponen dibujando la silueta de dragones, toros, leones y seres mitológicos. La parte inferior y el arco de la puerta están decoradas por filas de grandes flores semejantes a margaritas. La Puerta de Istar contaba originalmente con dos esfinges dentro del arco de la puerta, que se han perdido hoy en día. Los restos de la puerta original fueron descubiertos en Babilonia durante las campañas arqueológicas alemanas de 1902 a 1914. La mayoría se trasladó a Alemania, donde se reconstruyó la puerta en el Museo Pergamon de Berlín, en 1930, que sigue actualmente en exposición. Algunos de los relieves originales de leones, dragones y toros se encuentran actualmente en el Museo Arqueológico de Estambul, el Instituto de Artes de Detroit, el Museo Metropolitano de Arte de Nueva York, el Instituto Oriental de Chicago, el Museo de la Escuela de Diseño de Rhode Island y el Museo de Bellas Artes de Boston.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Brama Isztar - brama w Babilonie, wzniesiona za panowania królaNabuchodonozora II i poświęcona była bogini Isztar. Była ona północną bramą miasta, otwierającą tzw. drogę procesyjną, która ciągnęła się aż doE-sagili - świątyni boga Marduka. Obiekt tworzyły w zasadzie dwie bramy połączone przejściem, czyli był to tzw. obiekt bramy, składający się z czterech wież na planie kwadratu, zwieńczonych krenelażem, który zresztą był również na murach łączących wieże. Taka konstrukcja miała swoje konkretne, obronne cele i wynikała m.in. z techniki obrony przejścia umieszczonego w dwóch rzędach murów obronnych, w których odrębne bramy połączono dla skuteczniejszej obrony przed napastnikami. Poza tym pozwalało to lepiej kontrolować przybyszów przechodzących przez bramę.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ISHTAR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ishtar Gate[COLOR_REVERT] allows you to contact and trade with all civilizations on your continent in addition to granting you espionage for buildings belonging to your state religion.</English>
		<French>La [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Porte d'Ishtar[COLOR_REVERT] vous permet de prendre contact et de faire du commerce avec toutes les civilisations de votre continent, et augmente la production d'espionnage pour tous les bâtiments liés à votre Religion d'Etat.</French>
		<Italian>La [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Porta di Ishtar[COLOR_REVERT] permette di contattare tutte le civiltà presenti sul tuo stesso continente; inoltre, fornisce spionaggio dagli edifici della tua religione di stato.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ISHTAR_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_YELLOW]HELP: [COLOR_REVERT]Establishes Contact With All Civilizations on Same Continent</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Etablit le contact avec toutes les Civilisations du Continent</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Stabilisce un contatto con tutte le civiltà nello stesso continente</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]Constrúyela para añadir comercio y +1 ruta comercial</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Zwiększa dochód oraz +1 do Szlaków Handlowych</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_JAGUAR_TEMPLE</Tag>
		<English>Temple of Ah Cacao</English>
		<French>Temple de Ah Cacao</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Tempio di Ah Cacao</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Świątynia Ah Cacao</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_JAGUAR_TEMPLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Tikal (or Tik'al, according to the more current orthography) is the largest of the ancient ruined cities of the Mayan civilization. It is located in the El Petén department of Guatemala. Now part of Guatemala's Tikal National Park, it is a UNESCO World Heritage Site and a popular tourist spot. The closest large towns are Flores and Santa Elena, approximately 64 kilometres (40 mi) by road to the southwest.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Tikal Temple I is the designation given to one of the major structures at Tikal, one of the largest cities and archaeological sites of the pre-Columbian Maya civilization in Mesoamerica, located in the Petén Basin region of northern Guatemala. Informally also known as the Temple of the Giant Jaguar or Temple of Ah Cacao, Temple I is a typically Petén-styled limestone stepped pyramid structure which is dated to approximately 730 CE.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]The structure is associated with Jasaw Chan K'awiil I, a Classic-era ruler of the polity based at Tikal, who ruled from 682-784. The tomb of this ruler has been located by archaeologists within the structure, although it is presently unclear whether it was built for this specific purpose, or this use was a later adaptation.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Temple I reaches a height of approximately 44 m (144.4 ft) over a series of nine steep levels, from a base measuring only 30 by 34 m (98.4 by 111.5 ft). The nine levels may be a reference to the nine "Lords of the Night" in Maya mythology and Initial Series inscriptions. The main chamber of the temple depicts Kukulcan, a feathered serpent god.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Situated at the heart of a World Heritage Site, the temple is surmounted by a typical roofcomb, a distinctive Maya architectural feature.</English>
		<French>Tikal (or Tik'al, according to the more current orthography) is the largest du ancient ruined cities du Mayan civilization. It is located in the El Petén department of Guatemala. Now part of Guatemala's Tikal National Park, it is a UNESCO World Heritage Site et un popular tourist spot. The closest large towns are Flores and Santa Elena, approximately 64 kilometres (40 mi) by road to the southwest.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Tikal Temple I is the designation given to one du major structures at Tikal, one du largest cities and archaeological sites du pre-Columbian Maya civilization in Mesoamerica, located in the Petén Basin region of northern Guatemala. Informally also known as the Temple du Giant Jaguar or Temple of Ah Cacao, Temple I is a typically Petén-styled limestone stepped pyramid structure which is dated to approximately 730 CE.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]The structure is associated with Jasaw Chan K'awiil I, a Classic-era ruler du polity based at Tikal, who ruled from 682-784. The tomb of this ruler has been located by archaeologists within the structure, although it is presently unclear whether it was built for this specific purpose, or this use was a later adaptation.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Temple I reaches a height of approximately 44 m (144.4 ft) over a series of nine steep levels, from a base measuring only 30 by 34 m (98.4 by 111.5 ft). The nine levels may be a reference to the nine "Lords du Night" in Maya mythology and Initial Series inscriptions. The main chamber du temple depicts Kukulcan, a feathered serpent god.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Situated at the heart of a World Heritage Site, the temple is surmounted by a typical roofcomb, a distinctive Maya architectural feature.</French>
		<Italian>Tikal (o Tik'al, a seconda dell'ortografia più comune) è la più grande rovina della civiltà Maya. Si trova nel dipartimento di El Petén, in Guatemala. Ora parte del Guatemala's Tikal National Park, è un sito dell'UNESCO dichiarato patrimonio dell'umanità e una grande attrazione turistica. e città più vicine sono Flores e Santa Elena, circa 64 km a sud-ovest.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Tikal Temple I è la designazione inglese di una delle strutture più grandi di Tikal, una delle città più grandi costruite dalla civiltà pre-colombiana dei maya nell'America Centrale, situata nella regione del Bacino di Petén nel nord del Guatemala. Conosciuto anche come tempio del Grande Giaguaro o Tempio di Ah Cacao, Temple I ha uno stile tipico della regione, con una struttura a piramide in pietra risalente circa al 730 d.C..[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]La struttura è associata a Jasaw Chan K'awiil I, un governatore dell'era classica che era stanziato a Tikal, che goernò dal 682 al 784. La tomba di questo governatore è stata localizzata dagli archeologi all'interno della struttura, anche se al momento non è chiaro de la piramide fu costruita per questo scopo preciso o se questo uso sia stato un adattamento successivo.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Temple I ha un'altezza di circa 44 m su una serie di nove livelli, da una base di misure 30x34 m. I nove livelli potrebbero essere un riferimento ai nove "Signori della notte" della mitologia Maya mythology e alle iscrizioni delle Serie iniziali. La camera principale del tempio rappresenta Kukulcan, il dio-serpente piumato.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Al centro del sito UNESCO, il tempio è sormontato da un elemento architettonico tipico della cultura maya.</Italian>
		<Polish>Świątynia Ah Cacao to kompleks światynny Majów.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_JAGUAR_TEMPLE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Temple of Ah Cacao[COLOR_REVERT] grants your units a 20% chance to fully heal after a combat victory.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Temple de Ah Cacao[COLOR_REVERT] permet à vos unités de se soigner complètement après une victoire (20% de chances).</French>
		<Italian>Il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Tempio di Ah Cacao[COLOR_REVERT] fornisce alle tue unità il 20% di chance di guarire dopo una vittoria in combattimento.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_JAGUAR_TEMPLE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_YELLOW]HELP: [COLOR_REVERT]20% Chance for Units to Heal after Combat Victory</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]20% de Chances de se soigner après une victoire</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]20% Chance di guarire per le unità dopo le vittorie in combattimento</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_MARAUDER</Tag>
		<English>Marauder</English>
		<French>Maraudeur</French>
		<Italian>Predone</Italian>
		<Polish>Maruder</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_MARAUDER_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Plunders 4% of Enemy [ICON_GOLD] Reserves on Combat Victory</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Pille 4% de la réserve d'[ICON_GOLD] en cas de Victoire au Combat</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ruba 4% delle riserve nemiche di [ICON_GOLD] quando vince una battaglia</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Po zwycięstwie w walce grabi 4% rezerw wrogiego [ICON_GOLD]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MARAUDER_YOU</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]You have plundered %d2 [ICON_GOLD] from %s1![COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]Vous avez pillé %d2 [ICON_GOLD] à %s1![COLOR_REVERT]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MARAUDER_FROM</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]%s1 has plundered %d2 [ICON_GOLD] from you![COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]%s1 vous a volé %d2 [ICON_GOLD]![COLOR_REVERT]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CAPTURED_WONDER</Tag>
		<English>%s1 has captured the wonder %s2!</English>
		<French>%s1 a capturé la merveille: %s2!</French>
		<German>%s1 hat das Wunder %s2 erobert!</German>
		<Italian>%s1 ha catturato la meraviglia %s2!</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_YOU_CAPTURED_WONDER</Tag>
		<English>You have captured the wonder %s2!</English>
		<French>Vous avez capturé la merveille: %s2!</French>
		<German>Ihr habt das Wunder %s2 erobert!</German>
		<Italian>Hai catturato la meraviglia %s2!</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DESTROYED_WONDER</Tag>
		<English>%s1 has destroyed the wonder %s2!</English>
		<French>%s1 a détruit la merveille: %s2!</French>
		<German>%s1 hat das Wunder %s2 zerstört!</German>
		<Italian>%s1 ha distrutto la meraviglia %s2!</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_YOU_DESTROYED_WONDER</Tag>
		<English>You have destroyed the wonder %s2!</English>
		<French>Vous avez détruit la merveille: %s2!</French>
		<German>Ihr habt das Wunder %s2 zerstört!</German>
		<Italian>Hai distrutto la meraviglia %s2!</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- Library of Nineveh-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NINEVEH</Tag>
		<English>Library of Nineveh</English>
		<French>La Bibliothèque de Ninive</French>
		<Polish>Biblioteka Aszurbanipala</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NINEVEH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Royal Library of Ashurbanipal was discovered in a palace in ancient Nineveh, capital of Assyria, in northern Mesopotamia (modern day Iraq).  The of King Ashurbanipal (668 - 627 BC) was the last great king of the Neo-Assyrian Empire and the palace is the second most important library discovery of the ancient world.  The library is a collection of thousands of clay tablets and fragments containing texts of all kinds from the 7th century BC. Among its holdings was the famous Epic of Gilgamesh. Due to the sloppy handling of the original material much of the library is irreparably jumbled, making it impossible for scholars to discern and reconstruct many of the original texts, although some have survived intact.</English>
		<French>La Bibliothèque royale d'Assurbanipal a été découverte dans un palais de l'ancienne Ninive, capitale de l'Assyrie, dans le nord de la Mésopotamie (l'Irak de jour). Le roi Assurbanipal (668 à 627 avant JC) fut le dernier grand roi de l'empire néo-assyrien et le palais constitue la deuxième découverte libraire la plus importante du monde antique. La bibliothèque est une collection de milliers de tablettes d'argile et de fragments contenant des textes de toutes sortes à partir de la 7ème siècle avant JC. Parmi ses artefacts se trouvait la célèbre épopée de Gilgamesh. En raison de la manipulation bâclée du matériau d'origine une grande partie de la bibliothèque est irrémédiablement brouillée, ce qui les chercheurs incapables de discerner et de reconstruire la plupart des textes originaux, bien que certains aient survécu presque en intégralité.</French>
		<Polish>Biblioteka Aszurbanipala w Niniwie - założona przez asyryjskiegokróla Aszurbanipala w połowie VII w. p.n.e. Została odkryta w dwóch fazach w czasie prac wykopaliskowych prowadzonych od 1849 roku przez Austena H. Layarda w Niniwie na wzgórzu Kujundżyk, które kryło w sobie pozostałości pałaców: Sennacheryba i Aszurbanipala. Kolekcja zawiera łącznie ok. 20 000 glinianych tabliczek z obydwu pałaców. W wyniku zaniedbania pracowników Muzeum Brytyjskiegotabliczki odkryte w pałacu Sanheriba uległy wymieszaniu ze zbiorem odkrytym w 1852 w pałacu Aszurbanipala przez Hormuzda Rassama, dlatego nie można przyporządkować poszczególnych tabliczek do określonej biblioteki pałacowej któregoś z obu władców.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NINEVEH_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]The Library of Nineveh[COLOR_REVERT] is a World Wonder that provides both a FREE [LINK=BUILDING_TABLET_MAKER]Tablet Maker[\LINK] and +5 percent research in every city.  Additionally, the city, in which it is produced receives a 15% increase in research and is more likely to produce a Great Scientist.</English>
		<French>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]La Bibliothèque de Ninive[COLOR_REVERT]est une merveille du monde qui offre à la fois un [LINK = BUILDING_TABLET_MAKER] Fabricant de Tablettes [\ LINK] GRATUIT et +5 pourcent de recherche dans chaque ville. En outre, la ville dans laquelle elle est construite reçoit une augmentation de 15% dans la recherche et est plus susceptible de produire un Savant Illustre.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- End Library of Nineveh -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_REAL_FAVORITE_RELIGION_HEADER</Tag>
		<English>A new mysticism</English>
		<French>Un nouveau Mystique</French>
		<German>Ein neuer Kult</German>
		<Italian>Un nuovo culto</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_REAL_FAVORITE_RELIGION_TEXT</Tag>
		<English>A wandering man has arrived in your capital, and he's talking about a religion, founded in the recent years in a far away land. The new religion is called %s1, and the wise man is so amazed by this religion, that he has decided to found a new school in your city to teach it to your citizens.</English>
		<French>Un vagabond est arrivé dans votre capitale, et il parle d'une religion, fondée récemment dans un pays lointain. La découverte de cette nouvelle religion appelée %s1 a convaincu cet homme de fonder une école dans votre ville, pour y enseigner les préceptes à vos cityoens.</French>
		<German>Ein Reisender hat deinen Palast erreicht, und er erzählt von einer Religion, die in den letzten Jahren in einem fernen Land begründet wurde. Die neue Religion wird %s1 genannt, und der weise Mann ist so sehr von ihr begeistert, dass er beschlossen hat, eine neue Schule in euerer Stadt zu errichten, um eure Bürger diese Religion zu lehren.</German>
		<Italian>Un uomo è arrivato nella tua capitale e sta parlando di una nuova religione, fondata di recente in una terra lontana. La nuova religione è chiamata %s1 e l'uomo è cos' ammirato da questa religione che ha deciso di fondare una scuola nella tua città per diffonderla tra i tuoi cittadini.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_SNEAK</Tag>
		<English>Sneak</English>
		<French>Furtif</French>
		<German>Schleichen</German>
		<Italian>Furtivo</Italian>
		<Polish>Skradanie się</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_SNEAK_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Plunders 4% of Enemy [ICON_ESPIONAGE] Reserves on Combat Victory</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Pille 4% de la réserve d'[ICON_ESPIONAGE] après une Victoire au Combat</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Plündert 4% der gegnesichen [ICON_ESPIONAGE] anch einem Sieg im Kampf</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ruba 4% delle riserve nemiche di [ICON_ESPIONAGE] vincendo una battaglia</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Po zwycięstwie grabi 4% wrogich zapasów [ICON_ESPIONAGE]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_SNEAK_YOU</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]You have plundered %d2 [ICON_ESPIONAGE] from %s1![COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]Vous avez pillé %d2 [ICON_ESPIONAGE] à %s1![COLOR_REVERT]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_SNEAK_FROM</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]%s1 has plundered %d2 [ICON_ESPIONAGE] from you![COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]%s1 vous a volé %d2 [ICON_ESPIONAGE]![COLOR_REVERT]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_SNEAK_HIDDEN</Tag>
		<English>An Unknown Nation</English>
		<French>Une Nation inconnue</French>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- Strategic Grain Reserve Wonder -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STRATEGIC_GRAIN_RESERVE</Tag>
		<English>Strategic Grain Reserve</English>
		<French>La Réserve Stratégique de Céréales</French>
		<German>Strategische Kornreserve</German>
		<Polish>Strategiczne Rezerwy Ziarna</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STRATEGIC_GRAIN_RESERVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Strategic Grain Reserve allows a population to store food in huge grain silos as a hedge against possible starvation during times of severe drought.</English>
		<French>La Réserve Stratégique de Céréales permet à la population de stocker de la nourriture dans des immenses silos à grains, comme précaution contre les famines qui pourraient advenir.</French>
		<Polish>Rezerwy żywności przygotowywane na wypadek klęsk żywiołowych, wojny, epidemii itp.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STRATEGIC_GRAIN_RESERVE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Strategic Grain Reserve[COLOR_REVERT] provides a free Ganary in all of your cities and a 20% food bonus in the founding city.  It increases it's city's odds of generating a Great Engineer.</English>
		<French>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]La Réserve Stratégique de Céréales[COLOR_REVERT] fournit un grenir gratuit dans chaque ville, et un bonus de 20% de nourriture lors de l'établissement d'une ville. Elle augmente la probabilité de donner naissance à un ingénieur illustre.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- END Strategic Grain Reserve Wonder -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE</Tag>
		<English>Topkapi Palace</English>
		<French>Le Palais Topkapi</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Palazzo Topkapi</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pałac Topkapi</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Topkapi Palace is a palace in Istanbul, Turkey, which was the official and primary residence in the city of the Ottoman Sultans, from 1465 to 1853. The palace was a setting for state occasions and royal entertainments and is a major tourist attraction today. The name directly translates as "Cannongate Palace", from the palace being named after a nearby, now lost gate.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Initial construction started in 1459, ordered by Sultan Mehmed II, the conqueror of Byzantine Constantinople. The palace is a complex made up of four main courtyards and many smaller buildings. At the height of its existence as a royal residence, the palace was home to as many as 4,000 people, formerly covering a larger area with a long shoreline. The complex has been expanded over the centuries, with many renovations such as after the 1509 earthquake and 1665 fire.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Topkapi Palace gradually lost its importance at the end of the 17th century, as the Sultans preferred to spend more time in their new palaces along the Bosporus. In 1853, Sultan Abdül Mecid I decided to move the court to the newly built Dolmabahçe Palace, the first European-style palace in the city. Some functions, such as the imperial treasury, the library, mosque and mint, were retained though.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]After the end of the Ottoman Empire in 1921, Topkapi Palace was transformed by government decree on April 3, 1924 into a museum of the imperial era. The Topkapi Palace Museum is under the administration of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism. The palace complex has hundreds of rooms and chambers, but only the most important are accessible to the public today. The complex is guarded by officials of the ministry as well as armed guards of the Turkish military. The palace is full of examples of Ottoman architecture and also contains large collections of porcelain, robes, weapons, shields, armor, Ottoman miniatures, Islamic calligraphic manuscripts and murals, as well as a display of Ottoman treasure and jewelry.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Topkapi Palace is among those monuments belonging to the "Historic Areas of Istanbul", which became a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1985, and is described in Criterion iv as "the best example[s] of ensembles of palaces [...] of the Ottoman period."</English>
		<French>The Topkapi Palace is a palace in Istanbul, Turkey, which was the official and primary residence in the city du Ottoman Sultans, from 1465 to 1853. The palace was a setting for state occasions and royal entertainments and is a major tourist attraction today. The name directly translates as "Cannongate Palace", from the palace being named after a nearby, now lost gate.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Initial construction started in 1459, ordered by Sultan Mehmed II, the conqueror of Byzantine Constantinople. The palace is a complex made up of four main courtyards and many smaller buildings. At the height of its existence as a royal residence, the palace was home to as many as 4,000 people, formerly covering a larger area with a long shoreline. The complex has been expanded over the centuries, with many renovations such as after the 1509 earthquake and 1665 fire.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Topkapi Palace gradually lost its importance at the end du 17th century, as the Sultans preferred to spend more time in their new palaces along the Bosporus. In 1853, Sultan Abdül Mecid I decided to move the court to the newly built Dolmabahçe Palace, the first European-style palace in the city. Some functions, such as the imperial treasury, the library, mosque and mint, were retained though.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]After the end du Ottoman Empire in 1921, Topkapi Palace was transformed by government decree on Avril  3, 1924 into a museum du imperial era. The Topkapi Palace Museum is under the administration du Ministry of Culture and Tourism. The palace complex has hundreds of rooms and chambers, but only the most important are accessible to the public today. The complex is guarded by officials du ministry as well as armed guards du Turc military. The palace is full of examples of Ottoman architecture and also contains large collections of porcelain, robes, weapons, shields, armor, Ottoman miniatures, Islamic calligraphic manuscripts and murals, as well as a display of Ottoman treasure and jewelry.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Topkapi Palace is among those monuments belonging to the "Historic Areas of Istanbul", which became a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1985, and is described in Criterion iv as "the best example[s] of ensembles of palaces [...] du Ottoman period."</French>
		<Italian>Il Palazzo Topkapi è un palazzo di Istanbul, in Turchia, che fu usato dei sultani Ottomani come residenza dal 1465 al 1853; il palazzo era il luogo designato per gli incontri di stato e l'intrattenimento della famiglia reale, mentre al giorno d'oggi è una grande attrazione turistica. Il nome viene tradotto con "Palazzo della Porta del Cannone", basandosi su una porta vicina ora distrutta.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]La costruzione iniziò nel 1459 su ordine del Sultano Mehmed II, il conquistatore di Costantinopoli. Il palazzo è un complesso formato da 4 cortili principlai e molti edifici più piccoli; nel suo periodo di massimo splendore il palazzo ospitava più di 4,000 persone, occupando un'area sempre più grande lungo la costa; il complesso si è quindi ingrandito nel corso dei secoli, con molti restauri come il territorio del 1509 e l'incendio del 1665.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Il Palazzo Topkapi perse gradualmente importanza alla fine del XVII secolo, quando i Sultani iniziarono a trascorrere più tempo nei loro nuovi palazzi lungo il Bosforo. Nel 1853 il Sultano Abdül Mecid I decise di spostare la propria corte nel Palazzo Dolmabahçe, il primo palazzo in stile europeo della città. Alcune funzioni rimasero però al Palazzo Topkapi, come il tesoro, la biblioteca, la moschea e la zecca.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Dopo la fine dell'Impero Ottomano nel 1921 il palazzo Topkapi fu trasformato dal decreto governativo del 3 aprile 1924 nel museo dell'Era imperiale. Il Museo del Palazzo Topkapi è sotto la giurisdizione del Ministero della cultura e del turismo; il complesso ha centinaia di stanze, ma solo le più importanti possono essere visitate. Il complesso è sorvegliato da ufficiali del ministero e da guardie armate dell'esercito turco. Il palazzo è pieno di esampi di architettura e contiene grandi collezioni di porcellane, abiti, armi, scudi, armature, miniature Ottomane, manoscritti di calligrafia islamica e murali, oltre a mostre del tesoro e dei gioielli ottomani.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Il Palazzo Topkapi è uno dei monumenti appartenenti alla "Area storica di Istanbul", che fu dichiarato dall'UNESCO Patrimonio dell'umanità nel 1985, descritto da Criterion IV come "the best example[s] of ensembles of palaces [...] of the Ottoman period."</Italian>
		<Polish>Topkapi Sarayi - pałac w centrum Stambułu, który był rezydencją sułtanówprzez ponad 380 lat, od 1453 roku. Budowę rozpoczęto za panowania sułtanaMehmeda II Zdobywcy w 1453 roku, zaraz po zdobyciu Konstantynopola, a zakończono w 1465 roku. Ostatnim używającym pałacu sułtanem byłMahmud II (do 1839 roku). Sułtan Abdulmecid I przeniósł siedzibę władców do pałacu DolmabahCe.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Topkapi Palace[COLOR_REVERT] strengthens all vassals under your rule by granting them a gold and combat experience bonus every turn. Additionally, you will have a 20% chance of training your vassal's UU instead of the standard unit when training a unit of the same unit class.</English>
		<French>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Topkapi Palace[COLOR_REVERT] strengthens all vassals under your rule by granting them a gold and combat experience bonus every turn. Additionally, you will have a 20% chance of training your vassal's UU instead du standard unit when training a unit du same unit class.</French>
		<Italian>Il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Palazzo Topkapi[COLOR_REVERT] rinforza i tuoi vassalli fornendo loro oro e bonus all'esperienza in combattimento ogni turno. In più, hai una chance del 20% di addestrare l'unità unica del tuo vassallo quando addestri un'unità standard delle stessa categoria.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_YELLOW]HELP: [COLOR_REVERT]Strengthens Vassals, 20% Chance to Train a Vassal's Unique Unit</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Renforce les vassaux[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]20% Chance d'enrôler une unité unique de Vassal</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Rinforza i vassalli[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]20% Chance di addestrare l'unità unica di un vassallo</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- UNIT KEY SECTION -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UN_MISSION</Tag>
		<English>UN Mission</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mission de l'ONU</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>UNO Mission:UNO Missionen</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Missione ONU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Misión de la ONU</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Misja ONZ</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- STRATEGY SECTION -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UN_MISSION_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>UN Missions allow for the construction of UN Peacekeeping Forces.</English>
		<French>Les Missions de l'ONU permettent la formation de soldats de la Paix de l'ONU.</French>
		<German>UNO Missionen erlauben den Einsatz von UN Friedenstruppen.</German>
		<Italian>La missione ONU permette la costruzione delle forze di pace ONU</Italian>
		<Spanish>Las Misiones de la ONU permiten el entrenamiento de las Fuerzas pacificadoras de la ONU.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Organizacja Narodów Zjednoczonych – uniwersalna organizacja międzynarodowa. ONZ stawia sobie za cel zapewnienie pokoju i bezpieczeństwa międzynarodowego, rozwój współpracy między narodami oraz popieranie przestrzegania praw człowieka. Idea powołania nowej organizacji, powstała jeszcze w czasie trwania II wojny światowej, na konferencji w Teheranie w 1943. Jej głównym pomysłodawcą był prezydent USA Franklin Delano Roosevelt, a jej nazwę zaproponował premier Wielkiej Brytanii Winston Churchill (określenie "narody zjednoczone" w trakcie wojny stosowano nieraz dla Aliantów). W drugiej połowie 1944 przedstawiciele Francji, Chin, Wielkiej Brytanii, USA oraz ZSRR spotkali się w Waszyngtonie, gdzie przedyskutowano zakres, cele i sposoby działania nowej organizacji. 25 kwietnia 1945 roku zwołano pierwszą konferencję ONZ w San Francisco, w której uczestniczyło 50 państw z całego świata – pierwszych członków organizacji. Za członka ONZ od założenia uznawana jest też Polska, której przedstawiciele z powodów politycznych nie mogli uczestniczyć w konferencji w San Francisco. Podczas konferencji, 26 czerwca, podpisano Kartę Narodów Zjednoczonych, akt prawny regulujący działalność ONZ. Organizację Narodów Zjednoczonych powołano do życia 24 października 1945, kiedy postanowienia konferencji ratyfikowało pięciu przyszłych stałych członków Rady Bezpieczeństwa (Chiny, Francja, ZSRR, Wielka Brytania i USA), oraz większość pozostałych państw członkowskich. Powołanie ONZ położyło jednocześnie kres działalności Ligi Narodów, która rozwiązała się formalnie 18 kwietnia 1946, przekazując pełnienie swej misji nowej organizacji. W grudniu 1945 Kongres USA wystosował propozycję, aby siedziba ONZ mieściła się w Nowym Jorku, co zostało przez organizację zaakceptowane. Budynek siedziby głównej otwarto 9 stycznia 1951 roku na terenach podarowanych ONZ przez Johna Rockefellera, gdzie mieści się do dziś. Część instytucji funkcjonuje jednak w innych miastach świata, m.in. w Genewie, Hadze, Nairobi i Wiedniu.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- PEDIA SECTION -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UN_MISSION_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The United Nations (UN) is an international organization whose stated aims are to facilitate cooperation in international law, international security, economic development, social progress and human rights issues. The UN was founded in 1945 to replace the League of Nations, to stop wars between nations and provide a platform for dialogue.</English>
		<French>L'Organisation des Nations unies (ONU) est une organisation internationale, regroupant, à quelques exceptions près, tous les états de la planète. Distincte des états qui la composent, l'organisation a pour finalité la paix internationale. Ses objectifs sont de faciliter la coopération dans les domaines du droit international, de la sécurité internationale, du développement économique, du progrès social et des Droits de l'homme. L'ONU est fondée en 1945 en remplacement de la Société des Nations (SDN), qui n'avait pas tenu son rôle en n'évitant pas la Seconde Guerre mondiale, pour mettre fin aux guerres entre les pays et pour fournir une plateforme de dialogue.</French>
		<German>Die Vereinten Nationen (UNO) ist eine internationale Organisation, deren festgesetzte Ziele die Unterstützung der internationalen Zusammenarbeit in Bereichen des Rechts, der Sicherheit, Wirtschaftsentwicklung, des sozialen Fortschritts und der Menschenrechte sind. Die UNO wurde im Jahre 1945 gegründet, um die Liga der Nationen ersetzen, aber vor allem um die Kriege zwischen den Nationen zu beenden und eine Plattform für den Dialog zu ermöglichen.</German>
		<Italian>L'organizzazione delle Nazioni Unite (ONU) è un'organizzazione internazionale i cui scopi sono di facilitare la cooperazione nelle leggi internazionali, la sicurezza internazionale, lo sviluppo economico, progresso sociale e la difesa dei diritti umanitari. L'ONU fo fondata nel 1945 per sostituire la Società delle Nazioni, per fermare le guerre tra le nazioni e fornire una piattaforma di dialogo.</Italian>
		<Polish>Misja ONZ pozwala na budowę sił pokojowych ONZ.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MATNU</Tag>
		<English>Matnu</English>
		<French>Archer Matnu</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MATNU_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Matnu is the unique Composite Bowman of the Akkadian culture. It has an extra 50% defence bonus in a city, extra 25% defence on a hill, and more uniquely, is immune to collateral damage from all siege units. Additionally, it starts with City Garrison I. Quite simply the best city defender until the longbow, and perhaps even beyond...</English>
		<French>The Matnu is the unique Composite Bowman du Akkadian culture. It has an extra 50% defence bonus in a city, extra 25% defence on a hill, and more uniquely, is immune to collateral damage from all siege units. Additionally, it starts with City Garrison I. Quite simply the best city defender until the longbow, and perhaps even beyond.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MATNU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>If you want to take an Akkadian city, you will need overwhelming superiority of numbers, or else a miracle...  The Akkadian Matnu is the best city defence archer in the known world.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SPIRIT_WALKER</Tag>
		<English>Spirit Walker</English>
		<French>Marcheur des Esprits</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Spirito camminatore:Spiriti camminatori</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SPIRIT_WALKER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Spirit Walker replaces the Spearman for the Anasazi culture.  They start with a Desert Combat promotion, and double movement.  Thus they are great for defence or attack on desert maps/regions, especially against mounted units.</English>
		<Italian>Lo spirito camminatore sostituisce il lanciere per la cultura Anasazi; inizia con la promozione Combattente del deserto I e con un movimento doppio rispetto ai normali lancieri. Perciò, sono ottimi per attaccare e difendere nelle regioni desertiche, specialmente contro le unità montate.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SPIRIT_WALKER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Spirit Walkers were warriors imbued with native spirituality, and were feared and respected by the rival tribes in the region. All the Four Corners tribes greatly respected the Spirit Walkers as a threat, and even the Apache (famed desert warriors themselves) were careful not to underestimate them.</English>
		<Italian>Gli spiriti camminatori erano guerrieri intrisi di spiritualità, che erano temuti e rispettati dalle tribù rivali nella regione. Tutte le tribù dei quattro angoli (un'area nel sudovest degli Stati Uniti, caratterizzata dal confine tra quattro diversi stati) rispettavano gli spiriti camminatori come una minaccia, e anche gli Apache (loro stessi guerrieri del deserto di fama) erano attenti a non sottovalutarli.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_YURUPARI</Tag>
		<English>Yurupari</English>
		<French>Lancier Yurupari</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_YURUPARI_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Yurupari[COLOR_REVERT] are Arawak culture unit. They are like [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Stone Spearmans[COLOR_REVERT] with bonuses to combat in forests and in looting.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_YURUPARI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In many of the Indian cultures these rites take a central position among other important ceremonies such as funerals and fertility rites. In the Guianas and the northwest Amazon region, the initiation of the boys is very complex. The Yurupary celebration inducts the boys into the secret society of mature men. Special rites are revealed to them; they are shown the sacred trumpets or the masks representing ancestral spirits. They are subjected to violent whippings, which they must tolerate without the least expression of pain. </English>
		<French>In many du Indian cultures these rites take a central position among other important ceremonies such as funerals and fertility rites. In the Guianas and the northwest Amazon region, the initiation du boys is very complex. The Yurupary celebration inducts the boys into the secret society of mature men. Special rites are revealed to them; they are shown the sacred trumpets or the masks representing ancestral spirits. They are subjected to violent whippings, which they must tolerate without the least expression of pain. </French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_THORAX_HOPLITE</Tag>
		<English>Thorax Hoplite</English>
		<French>Hoplite Thorax</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Oplita:Opliti</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_THORAX_HOPLITE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Thorax Hoplite is the unique Spearman alternative for the Athenian culture. It starts with Mobility and Formation I.  This means a headstart over even the standard Spearman against mounted units.</English>
		<Italian>L'oplita sostituisce il lanciere nella cultura ateniese; inizia con le promozioni Mobilità e Formazione I. Questo significa che è ancora più forte dei normali lancieri contro le unità montate.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_THORAX_HOPLITE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Hoplite was the heavy infantryman of Classical-era Greece.  Thorax refers to the breastplate that the Athenian hoplite achieved a superiority by wearing later in the period.</English>
		<Italian>L'oplita costituiva il fante pesante nella Grecia dell'era classica; indossava una corazza toracica che permise agli ateniesi di ottenere una superiorità militare in quel periodo.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BRIGADE_PIRON</Tag>
		<English>Brigade Piron</English>
		<French>Brigadier Piron</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Brigata Piron:Brigata Piron</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BRIGADE_PIRON_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Brigade Piron is the unique Trench Infantry unit of the Belgian culture. It starts with the promotions Trench I and City Raider I and II.</English>
		<French>The Brigade Piron is the unique Trench Infantry unit du Belgian culture. It starts with the promotions Trench I and City Raider I and II.</French>
		<Italian>La Brigata Piron è la fanteria da trincea unica della cultura belga; comincia con le promozioni Trincea I, Razziatore I e Razziatore II.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BRIGADE_PIRON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Brigade Piron is a Belgian unique unit, an alternative to Trench Infantry.  Its starting promotions are Trench I (giving a reduction in collateral damage) and City Raider I and II.  Thus it is an ideal unit for storming cities in the early Modern era.</English>
		<Italian>La Brigata Piron è l'unità unica belga, sostituzione della fanteria da trincea. Le sue promozioni iniziali forniscono una riduzione dei danni collaterali e un bonus all'attacco contro le città, perciò è un'unità ideale per guidare una forza d'assalto contro le città all'inizio dell'era moderna.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BLOOD_WARRIOR</Tag>
		<English>Blood Warrior</English>
		<French>Guerrier de sang</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guerriero sanguinario</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BLOOD_WARRIOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Blood Warrior is the unique Axeman alternative for the Blackfoot culture.  It starts with Shock I and Camouflage promotions.  Send regular melee units up against them, and you may be in for a surprise...</English>
		<Italian>Il guerriero sanguinario è l'unità unica per la cultura Blackfoot, che sostituisce il guerriero con ascia; inizia con le promozioni Shock I e Mimetica. Se provi ad usare delle unità da combattimento ravvicinato contro di loro, potresti avere una spiacevole sorpresa...</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BLOOD_WARRIOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Kainai Blackfoot were seen as particularly bloodthirsty by their neighbours the Plains Cree, who called them 'Miko-Ew', literally, 'stained with blood'.  Thus the Blood Warrior, this elite unit of their braves, is attributed with almost supernatural abilities in the minds of their enemies - the ability to appear as if from nowhere and fight like men possessed...</English>
		<Italian>I Kainai dei Blackfoot erano ritenuti particolarmente assetati di sangue da parte dei loro vicini Cree, che li chiamavano 'Miko-Ew', ovvero 'pieni di sangue'. Perciò i guerrieri sanguinari, unità di elite di questa tribù, erano ritenuti avere abilità quasi soprannaturali nelle menti dei loro nemici: la capacità di apparire dal nulla e di combattere come posseduti...</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FORTY_NINER</Tag>
		<English>Forty-Niner</English>
		<French>Ouvrier 'Forty-Niner'</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Forty-Niner</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FORTY_NINER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Forty-Niner is the unique Industrial-era Worker of the Californian culture. It starts with three Hill Worker promotions, so if you've changed your mind about that mine, he's your man.</English>
		<French>The Forty-Niner is the unique Industrial-era Worker du Californian culture. It starts with three Hill Worker promotions, so if you've changed your mind about that mine, he's your man.</French>
		<Italian>Il Forty-Niner è il lavoratore dell'era industriale tipico della cultura Californiana. Inizia con tutte e tre le promozioni Lavoratore delle colline, per cui se hai cambiato idea riguardo a quella miniera questo ragazzo fa proprio al caso tuo.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FORTY_NINER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The hardy fortune-seeking miners of the California goldrush became known as Forty-Niners.</English>
		<French>The hardy fortune-seeking miners du California goldrush became known as Forty-Niners.</French>
		<Italian>I cercatori d'oro della corsa all'oro in California divenero noti come Forty-Niners.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DAHOMEY_MINO</Tag>
		<English>Mino</English>
		<French>Fusillier Mino</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Mino</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DAHOMEY_MINO_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Mino[COLOR_REVERT] is a [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Rifleman[COLOR_REVERT] who starts with Drill I and II and is immune to first strikes.</English>
		<French>Mino</French>
		<German>Mino</German>
		<Italian>La [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Mino[COLOR_REVERT] è un [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Fuciliere[COLOR_REVERT] che inizia con le promozioni Addestramento I e Addestramento II, oltre ad essere immune agli attacchi improvvisi.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mino</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DAHOMEY_MINO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Dahomey Amazons or Mino were a Fon all-female military regiment of the Kingdom of Dahomey (now Benin) which lasted until the end of the 19th century. They were so named by Western observers and historians due to their similarity to the semi-mythical Amazons of ancient Anatolia and the Black Sea. For many years, the Black Sea was called the Amazon.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Origins of the Dahomey Amazons were from a group of elephant hunters organized by king Houegbadja. They were soon professionaly trained and some even ended up as his bodyguards. During the rule of Houegbadja's son, Agadja, the bodyguard were further developed into a milita and used when deafeating the neighbouring Savi. For the next hundred years, they got a reputation as fearless warriors.[PARAGRAPH:1]The group of female warriors was referred to as Mino, meaning "Our Mothers" in the Fon language by the male army of Dahomey. From the time of King Ghezo (ruling from 1818 to 1858), Dahomey became increasingly militaristic. Ghezo placed great importance on the army and increased its budget and formalized its structures. The Mino were rigorously trained, given uniforms, and equipped with Danish guns (obtained via the slave trade). By this time the Mino consisted of between 4000 and 6000 women, about a third of the entire Dahomey army.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Mino were recruited from among the ahosi ("king's wives") of which there were often hundreds. Some women in Fon society became ahosi voluntarily, while others were involuntarily enrolled if their husbands or fathers complained to the King about their behaviour. Membership among the Mino was supposed to hone any aggressive character traits for the purpose of war. During their membership they were not allowed to have children or be part of married life. Many of them were virgins. The regiment had a semi-sacred status, which was intertwined with the Fon belief in Vodun.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Mino trained with intense physical exercise. Discipline was emphasised. In the latter period, they were armed with Winchester rifles, clubs and knives. Units were under female command. Captives who fell into the hands of the Amazons were often decapitated.[PARAGRAPH:1]During the Franco-Dahomey Wars in the late 19th Century, the French, who tried to invade the country, suffered heavy casulties and lost several battles to the amazons, described as "the equal of every contemporary body of male elite soldiers from among the colonial powers". Ultimately, bolstered by the Foreign Legion, and armed with superior weaponry, including machine guns, as well as cavalry and Marine infantry, the French inflicted casualties that were ten times worse on the Dahomey side. After several battles, the French prevailed. The Legionnaires later wrote about the "incredible courage and audacity" of the Amazons. The last surviving Amazon of Dahomey died in 1979.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
		<French>Mino</French>
		<German>Mino</German>
		<Italian>Le Amazzoni del Dahomey, note anche come Mino, erano un reggimento militare di sole donne del Regno del Dahomey (oggi Benin), che durò fino alla fine del 19° secolo. Vennero chiamate cos' dagli osservatori e storici occidentali per la loro somiglianza con le semi-mitiche Amazzoni dell'antica Anatolia e del Mar Nero; per molti anni infatti il Mar Nero venne chiamato Amazzonia.[PARAGRAPH:1] Le origini delle Amazzoni del Dahomey erano da un gruppo di cacciatrici di elefanti organizzato dal re Houégbadja. Erano professionalmente addestrate fin da giovani, e alcune diventavano addirittura sue guardie del corpo. Durante il regno del figlio di Houégbadja, Agadja, le guardie del corpo vennero trasformate in una milizia che venne utilizzata nella guerra contro i Savi. Nei seguenti cento anni ottennero la fama di guerrieri impavidi.[PARAGRAPH:1] Il gruppo di donne guerriere veniva indicato come Mino, che significa "Le nostri Madri" nella lingua Fon da parte dell'esercito maschile del Dahomey. Dal tempo del re Ghezo (che regnò nel periodo 1818-1858), il Dahomey divenne sempre più militarista. Ghezo pose grande importanza nell'esercito, aumentando il suo budget e formalizzando le sue strutture. Le Mino erano rigorosamente addestrate, dotate di uniformi e equipaggiate con armi danesi (ottenute tramite il commercio degli schiavi). A questo punto le Mino erano tra 4000 e 6000 donne, circa un terzo di tutto l'esercito Dahomey.[PARAGRAPH:1]Le Mino venivano reclutate tra le ahosi ("mogli del re") che erano spesso centinaia. Alcune donne nella società Fon divennero ahosi volontariamente, mentre altre venivano involontariamente arruolate se i loro mariti o padri si lamentavono con il Re per il loro comportamento. Per essere una Mino era necessario un carattere aggressivo per andare in guerra. Durante la loro adesione non erano autorizzate ad avere figli o avere una vita coniugale. Molte di loro erano vergini. Il reggimento aveva uno status semi-sacro, intrecciato con la credenza Fon nel Vodun.[PARAGRAPH:1]Le Mino si allenavano con un intenso esercizio fisico. La disciplina veniva enfatizzata. Negli ultimi periodi, erano armati di fucili Winchester, bastoni e coltelli. Le unità erano sotto il comando di sesso femminile. I Prigionieri caduti nelle mani delle Amazzoni venivano spesso decapitati.[PARAGRAPH:1]Durante le guerre tra Francia e Dahomey nel tardo 19° secolo i francesi, che tentarono di invadere il paese, subirono pesanti perdite e persero diverse battaglie contro le amazzoni, descritte come "alla pari di ogni corpo contemporaneo di soldati d'elite di sesso maschile tra le potenze coloniali". Alla fine, sostenuta dalla Legione Straniera e armata con armi superiori, tra cui mitragliatrici, cavalleria e fanteria marina, i francesi inflissero perdite che erano dieci volte peggiori sul lato Dahomey. Dopo varie battaglie vinsero i francesi. I Legionari in seguito scrisse di un "incredibile coraggio e audacia" da parte delle Amazzoni. L'ultima Amazzone del Dahomey superstite mor' nel 1979.[PARAGRAPH:1]</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mino</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DENE_SLED_DOGS</Tag>
		<English>Dene Sled Dogs</English>
		<French>Chien d'attelage</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DENE_SLED_DOGS_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Dene Sled Dogs unit is the unique Trained Dogs equivalent from the Dene culture.  It starts with three Arctic Combat promotions.  Thus it is the perfect Trained Dog for patrolling the icier regions of your territory... and beyond!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DENE_SLED_DOGS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Dene are expert at breeding dogs for their bitterly cold environment.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AGRIANIAN_AXEMAN</Tag>
		<English>Agrianian Axeman</English>
		<French>Guerrier avec hache Agrianien</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guerriero con ascia Agriano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AGRIANIAN_AXEMAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Agrianian Axeman is the unique Axeman alternative from the culture of Epirus. It starts with Rugged Combat and City Raider I.  It is thus the specialist axeman for barren-type terrains, and also superior to most when rushing cities.</English>
		<Italian>Il guerriero con ascia agriano è l'unità unica della cultura dell'Epiro. Inizia con le promozioni Combattente del terreno aspro e Razziatore I; perciò è ottimo per i combattimenti in un terreno aspro, oltre ad essere superiore ad altre unità attaccando le città nemiche.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AGRIANIAN_AXEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Agrianes were a Thracian tribe.  They flourished between the late 6th and mid-2nd century BC.  They were loyal allies to many larger neighbours in their time, including Epirus.  They formed an elite axe unit in support of their allies, and were specialists in the difficult barren/rocky terrain of what is today northern Greece.</English>
		<Italian>Gli Agriani erano una tribù della Tracia; fiorirono tra la fine del 6° secolo e la metà del 2° secolo a.C.; erano alleati fidati di molte tribù più importanti del loro tempo, incluso l'Epiro. Formavano un'unità di guerrieri con ascia d'elite che supportava i loro alleati ed era specializzata nei combattimenti sui terreni aspri e rocciosi della Grecia settentrionale.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HAIDA_WAR_CANOE</Tag>
		<English>Haida War Canoe</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Canoé de Guerre Haida</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HAIDA_WAR_CANOE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Haida War Canoe is obviously the unique War Canoe of the Haida culture.  It starts with one Coastal Assault promotion.  Unless you are attacking a lot of rafts, or can afford to build large numbers of these, or to promote one highly, you are unlikely to derive any benefit from this unit.  Nevertheless, if you are building a War Canoe anyway, it is worth building this one for its free promo.</English>
		<French>The Haida War Canoe is obviously the unique War Canoe du Haida culture.  It starts with one Coastal Assault promotion.  Unless you are attacking a lot of rafts, or can afford to build large numbers of these, or to promote one highly, you are unlikely to derive any benefit from this unit.  Nevertheless, if you are building a War Canoe anyway, it is worth building this one for its free promo.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HAIDA_WAR_CANOE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Haida specialize in pouncing on their neighbours in waterborne attacks.  In attacking small boats they were particularly proficient.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PLUMED_ARCHER</Tag>
		<English>Plumed Archer</English>
		<French>Archer à Plumes</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Arciere piumato</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PLUMED_ARCHER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Plumed Archer[COLOR_REVERT] is the unique Archer of the Huastec culture. It has a 50% bonus in City and Hill Defence, and starts with the Mobility promotion.</English>
		<French>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Plumed Archer[COLOR_REVERT] is the unique Archer du Huastec culture. It has a 50% bonus in City and Hill Defence, and starts with the Mobility promotion.</French>
		<Italian>[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]L'arciere piumato[COLOR_REVERT] è l'unità unica della cultura huasteca. Ha un bonus del 50% alla difesa in città e sulle colline, oltre alla promozione Mobilità.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PLUMED_ARCHER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The natives of Central America had developed the bow and used it in combat. Their bow technology was not far advanced, however, in comparison to the Asian composite bow or English longbow. Archers could be ordered to wound when capture of enemies was more important than killing. Like all other Mayan warriors, archers wore distinctive costumes so commanders could distinguish their troops and place the right group where needed. The status of archers was low in comparison to other warrior ranks, so men of lower standing and skill entered their ranks. Men of status and ambition joined the ranks of the Eagle Warrior where they could have the opportunity to take captives. The better skilled and experienced bowmen became Elite Plumed Archers. They were especially important when absolute victory was required because they had the ability to kill enemies quickly and break enemy army morale under a barrage of well-aimed arrows.</English>
		<French>The natives of Central America had developed the bow and used it in combat. Their bow technology was not far advanced, however, in comparison to the Asian composite bow or English longbow. Archers could be ordered to wound when capture of enemies was more important than killing. Like all other Mayan warriors, archers wore distinctive costumes so commanders could distinguish their troops and place the right group where needed. The status of archers was low in comparison to other warrior ranks, so men of lower standing and skill entered their ranks. Men of status and ambition joined the ranks du Eagle Warrior where they could have the opportunity to take captives. The better skilled and experienced bowmen became Elite Plumed Archers. They were especially important when absolute victory was required because they had the ability to kill enemies quickly and break enemy army morale under a barrage of well-aimed arrows.</French>
		<Italian>L'arciere piumato è un'unità unica della cultura huasteca che sostituisce l'arciere standard; oltre alle normali ailità di un arciere, ottiene anche la promozione Mobilità.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LEIDANG</Tag>
		<English>Leidang</English>
		<French>Guerrier Leidang</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Leidang</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LEIDANG_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Leidang is the unique Heavy Axeman of the Icelandic culture. Like the Axeman line in general, it has a hefty 50% bonus against all melee units. It starts with the Amphibious and City Raider I promotions.</English>
		<French>The Leidang is the unique Heavy Axeman du Icelandic culture. Like the Axeman line in general, it has a hefty 50% bonus against all melee units. It starts with the Amphibious and City Raider I promotions.</French>
		<Italian>Il Leidang sostituisce il guerriero con ascia corazzato nella cultura islandese; come tutti i guerrieri con ascia, ha un bonus del 50% contro le unità da combattimento ravvicinato. Inizia con le promozioni Anfibio e Razziatore I.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LEIDANG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Leidang is an Icelandic unique unit, a replacement for the Heavy Axeman.  Because of the Norse specialization in seaborne raids, it starts with the Amphibious promotion. Its other starting promotion, City Raider I, is for much the same reason.  Thus it makes an ideal "Marine" for the Medieval and Renaissance eras.</English>
		<French>The Leidang is an Icelandic unique unit, a replacement for the Heavy Axeman.  Because du Norse specialization in seaborne raids, it starts with the Amphibious promotion. Its other starting promotion, City Raider I, is for much the same reason.  Thus it makes an ideal "Marine" for the Medieval and Renaissance eras.</French>
		<Italian>Il Leidang è l'unità unica islandese che sostituisce il guerriero con ascia corazzato. Le sue promozioni, Anfibio e Razziatore I, derivano dal fatto che i popoli norreni di discendenza vichinga erano specializzati nei raid dal mare contro le città nemiche. Per questo motivo il Leidang è un perfetto "Marine" per le età medievali e rinascimentali.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAROON</Tag>
		<English>Maroon</English>
		<French>Marron Jamaïcain</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Maroon</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAROON_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Maroon is the unique Musketman of the Jamaican culture. It starts with Guerrilla I, Guerrilla II and Hillsman.  Once he gets up in the hills, he's hard to dislodge.</English>
		<French>The Maroon is the unique Musketman du Jamaican culture. It starts with Guerrilla I, Guerrilla II and Hillsman.  Once he gets up in the hills, he's hard to dislodge.</French>
		<Italian>Il Maroon è il moschettiere unico della cultura Giamaicana; inizia con le promozioni Guerriglia I, Guerriglia II e Guerriero delle Colline. Una volta che si rintana su una collina, è difficile da stanare.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAROON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The escaped slaves of the Caribbean region became known as Maroons.  They formed their own communities in the inaccessible jungles, and in many cases proved impossible to recapture.</English>
		<French>The escaped slaves du Caribbean region became known as Maroons.  They formed their own communities in the inaccessible jungles, and in many cases proved impossible to recapture.</French>
		<Italian>Gli schiavi che scappavano nelle regioni Caraibiche divennero noti come Maroon. Formarono le loro comunità nelle giungle più inaccessibili e in molti casi non vennero più ricatturati.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEADHUNTER</Tag>
		<English>Headhunter</English>
		<French>Chasseur de têtes</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cacciatore di teste</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEADHUNTER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Headhunter is the Jivaro culture's version of the Hunter...but with a twist. As the name suggests, he hunts humans rather than animals.  His bonus is therefore not in animal combat, but against other hunters!</English>
		<French>The Headhunter is the Jivaro culture's version du Hunter...but with a twist. As the name suggests, he hunts humans rather than animals.  His bonus is therefore not in animal combat, but against other hunters!</French>
		<Italian>Il cacciatore di teste è le versione dei Jivaro del cacciatore, ma invece di animali lui caccia gli uomini. Perciò i suoi bonus si riferiscono non agli animali, ma ad altri cacciatori!</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEADHUNTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The pursuit of head-hunting is central to Jivaro culture.  The Jivaro warrior's collection of heads is one of the most important indicators of his status and martial prowess.</English>
		<French>The pursuit of head-hunting is central to Jivaro culture.  The Jivaro warrior's collection of heads is one du most important indicators of his status and martial prowess.</French>
		<Italian>La caccia delle teste è molto importante nella cultura Jivaro; la collezione di teste di un guerriero Jivaro è uno degli indicatori più importanti del suo status sociale.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_JADE_AXEMAN</Tag>
		<English>Jade Axeman</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Guerrier avec hache de jade</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_JADE_AXEMAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Jade Axeman is the Obsidian Axe replacement for the Liangzhu, a Neolithic culture from what subsequently became China. It starts with the Wetland I and II promotions.  Thus they have the early superiority of weapon due to the Liangzhu skill with jade, the standard axeman's advantage against melee opponents, and an extra headstart in lush and muddy terrain.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_JADE_AXEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The so-called Liangzhu culture of ancient China used their skill at crafting the local jade, so as to make their axemen peerless among their rivals.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HYPASPISTAI</Tag>
		<English>Hypaspistai</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Hypaspistai</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Hypaspistai</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Hypaspistai</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Hypaspistai</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HYPASPISTAI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Hail, Basileu! Before you stand your Hypaspistai: the elite of the elite and your personal guard. They are armed and armored in the finest equipment of the traditional hoplite: aspis, greaves, cuirass, helmet, spear, and sword. They are the best and richest of your men; far too worthy to risk in unwise actions. And yet they are without a doubt capable of multiplying the power of your army. Forming the right wing of the battle line or leading the assault on fortifications their heavy armor and weapons allow them to stand against even the hardiest of opponents and triumph with ease. They should be deployed where the fighting will be at its absolute thickest or nearby to fight with and to protect you.[NEWLINE][TAB]Historically, the Hypaspistai (shield-bearers) first appear with Alexandros at the beginning of his reign as his elite troops and bodyguard. He used them extensively throughout his anabasis for special missions, assault of fortifications, and in support of light troops in rough terrain; however, details of the unit seem to disappear by the time Alexandros reaches India and remain as such until appearing in various sources for the three remaining Diadochoi kingdoms in different forms and perhaps briefly in Epeiros with Pyrrhos. Such examples of their deployment count them as possibly numbering a fifth of the 10,000 Argyraspides corps of the Seleukid kings or as the military police and closest guard of the Makedonian kings. Yet, despite their prowess, the Hypaspistai were either forced to evolve past the antiquated hoplite model as in the east or vanish with the fall of their kingdom as in the west.</English>
		<French>Historically, the Hypaspistai (shield-bearers) first appear with Alexandros at the beginning of his reign as his elite troops and bodyguard. He used them extensively throughout his anabasis for special missions, assault of fortifications, and in support of light troops in rough terrain; however, details du unit seem to disappear by the time Alexandros reaches India and remain as such until appearing in various sources for the three remaining Diadochoi kingdoms in different forms and perhaps briefly in Epeiros with Pyrrhos. Such examples of their deployment count them as possibly numbering a fifth du 10,000 Argyraspides corps du Seleukid kings or as the military police and closest guard du Makedonian kings. Yet, despite their prowess, the Hypaspistai were either forced to evolve past the antiquated hoplite model as in the east or vanish with the fall of their kingdom as in the west.</French>
		<German>Historically, the Hypaspistai (shield-bearers) first appear with Alexandros at the beginning of his reign as his elite troops and bodyguard. He used them extensively throughout his anabasis for special missions, assault of fortifications, and in support of light troops in rough terrain; however, details of the unit seem to disappear by the time Alexandros reaches India and remain as such until appearing in various sources for the three remaining Diadochoi kingdoms in different forms and perhaps briefly in Epeiros with Pyrrhos. Such examples of their deployment count them as possibly numbering a fifth of the 10,000 Argyraspides corps of the Seleukid kings or as the military police and closest guard of the Makedonian kings. Yet, despite their prowess, the Hypaspistai were either forced to evolve past the antiquated hoplite model as in the east or vanish with the fall of their kingdom as in the west.</German>
		<Italian>Storicamente gli Hypaspistai (portatori di scudi) comparvero all'inizio del regno di Alessandro Magno come truppe d'elite e guardie del corpo. Venivano usati molto in missioni speciali, assalti, fortificazioni e come supporto alle truppe leggere nei terreni più accidentati; tuttavia, scomparvero quasi del tutto quando Alessandro raggiunse l'India. Soldati simili esistevano con nomi diversi all'interno dei successivi regni ellenistici, forse anche in Epiro durante il regno di Pirro. Probabilmente costituivano circa un quinto dei 10000 Argiraspidi dei re Seleucidi, oltre alle forze di polizia e alle guardie del corpo dei re di Macedonia. Nonostante la loro forza, gli Hypaspistai furono costretti ad evolversi dall'antiquato modello di oplita o a scomparire con la caduta dei regni ellenistici.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Historically, the Hypaspistai (shield-bearers) first appear with Alexandros at the beginning of his reign as his elite troops and bodyguard. He used them extensively throughout his anabasis for special missions, assault of fortifications, and in support of light troops in rough terrain; however, details of the unit seem to disappear by the time Alexandros reaches India and remain as such until appearing in various sources for the three remaining Diadochoi kingdoms in different forms and perhaps briefly in Epeiros with Pyrrhos. Such examples of their deployment count them as possibly numbering a fifth of the 10,000 Argyraspides corps of the Seleukid kings or as the military police and closest guard of the Makedonian kings. Yet, despite their prowess, the Hypaspistai were either forced to evolve past the antiquated hoplite model as in the east or vanish with the fall of their kingdom as in the west.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HYPASPISTAI_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>This powerful melee unit (the Macedonian replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Spearman[COLOR_REVERT]) comes with City Raider I and II.  This means you will need fewer - if any - Light Swordsmen in your rush stacks.</English>
		<Italian>Questa potente unità da combattimento ravvicinato (il sostituto macedone del [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Lanciere[COLOR_REVERT]) inizia con Razziatore I e Razziatore II.  Questo significa che possono facilmente sostituire gli spadaccini leggeri.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SAKA_CATAPHRACT</Tag>
		<English>Saka Cataphract</English>
		<French>Cataphracte Saka</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Catafratta di Saka</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SAKA_CATAPHRACT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Massagetae culture copied the Byzantine Cataphract, but their cavalry tended to specialize in surprising and routing enemy melee units (who in this theatre were mainly swordsmen and spearmen).</English>
		<Italian>I Massageti copiarono la catafratta dai bizantini, ma la loro cavalleria era specializzata nel sorprendere ed aggirare le unità da nemiche, che erano spesso lancieri e spadaccini.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SAKA_CATAPHRACT_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Saka Cataphract is the unique substitute for the Knight from the Massagetae culture.  They start with the first two Shock promotions, so naturally they are most lethal against melee units.</English>
		<Italian>La catafratta di Saka sostituisce il cavaliere nella cultura dei Massageti. Inizia con le promozioni Shock I e Shock II, perciò è decisamente letale contro le unità da combattimento ravvicinato.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CUACHIC</Tag>
		<English>Cuachic</English>
		<French>Guerrier Cuachic</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cuachic</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CUACHIC_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Cuachic is the unique Stone or Obsidian Swordsman of the Mixtec culture. Like the Swordsman line in general, it has bonuses to City Attack. It starts with Mobility and Shock I.</English>
		<French>The Cuachic is the unique Stone or Obsidian Swordsman du Mixtec culture. Like the Swordsman line in general, it has bonuses to City Attack. It starts with Mobility and Shock I.</French>
		<Italian>Il Cuachic è il guerriero con spada in ossidiana unico della cultura Mixteca; ha un bonus all'attacco contro le città. Inoltre, inizia anche con le promozioni Mobilità e Shock I.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CUACHIC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Cuachic is a Mixtec warrior wielding a wooden club lined with Stone or Obsidian blades on either side.  It is a Mixtec unique unit, and starts with Shock I and Mobility, in addition to the standard swordsman's city attack bonus.</English>
		<Italian>Il Cuachic è un guerriero Mixteco che utilizza un'asta di legno con lame di pietra o ossidiana. Si tratta dell'unità unica Mixteca ed ottiene bonus contro le unità da combattimento ravvicinato e attaccando le città, oltre a muoversi più velocemente sul terreno.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SI_WARRIOR</Tag>
		<English>Si Warrior</English>
		<French>Guerrier Si</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guerriero Si</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SI_WARRIOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Si Warrior is the Moche culture's equivalent of the Maceman. It starts with the promotions Shock I and II, in addition to its bonuses in city attack and against melee units.  Thus it is likely to be your best unit against melee opposition, and as good as any before the Light Swordsman against cities.</English>
		<French>The Si Warrior is the Moche culture's equivalent du Maceman. It starts with the promotions Shock I and II, in addition to its bonuses in city attack and against melee units.  Thus it is likely to be your best unit against melee opposition, and as good as any before the Light Swordsman against cities.</French>
		<Italian>Il guerriero Si è l'equivalente Moche del guerriero con mazza. Inizia con le promozioni Shock I e Shock II, oltre ai bonus all'attacco contro le città e contro le unità da combattimento ravvicinato. Perciò è l'unità ideale per attaccare le città prima degli spadaccini leggeri.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SI_WARRIOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Si Warrior is a unique unit of the Moche culture, equivalent to the Maceman.  It starts with the promotions Shock I and II, and additional bonuses in city attack and against melee.</English>
		<French>The Si Warrior is a unique unit du Moche culture, equivalent to the Maceman.  It starts with the promotions Shock I and II, and additional bonuses in city attack and against melee.</French>
		<Italian>Il guerriero Si è l'equivalente Moche del guerriero con mazza. Inizia con le promozioni Shock I e Shock II, oltre ai bonus all'attacco contro le città e contro le unità da combattimento ravvicinato.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PICTISH_WARRIOR</Tag>
		<English>Pictish Warrior</English>
		<French>Guerrier Picte</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PICTISH_WARRIOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Pictish Warrior is the Pict culture's equivalent of the Light Swordsman. It starts with the Formation I and Goad I promotions, and has the standard swordsman's bonus when attacking a city.</English>
		<French>The Pictish Warrior is the Pict culture's equivalent du Light Swordsman. It starts with the Formation I and Goad I promotions, and has the standard swordsman's bonus when attacking a city.</French>
		<Italian>Il guerriero pict sostituisce lo spadaccino leggero. Inizia con le promozioni Formazione I e Goad I, oltre ad avere i bonus standard degli spadaccini attaccando una città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PICTISH_WARRIOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Pictish Warrior is a unique unit of the Pict culture, equivalent to the Light Swordsman.  This warpainted ('picti' is Latin for 'painted [ones]') savage 'barbarian' was a formidable opponent, doubly so in the rugged terrain of his familiar homeland.  He was the reason that the Romans never conquered modern-day Scotland, and instead built Hadrian's and the Antonine Wall.</English>
		<French>The Pictish Warrior is a unique unit du Pict culture, equivalent to the Light Swordsman.  This warpainted ('picti' is Latin for 'painted [ones]') savage 'barbarian' was a formidable opponent, doubly so in the rugged terrain of his familiar homeland.  He was the reason that the Romans never conquered modern-day Scotland, and instead built Hadrian's and the Antonine Wall.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_QIANG_PIKEMAN</Tag>
		<English>Qiang Pikeman</English>
		<French>Piquier Qiang</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Picchiere Qiang:Picchieri Qiang</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_QIANG_PIKEMAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Qiang Pikeman is the unique Heavy Pikeman of the Quang culture. It starts with promotions Formation I and II, which almost doubles its standard Pikeman bonus against mounted units.</English>
		<French>The Qiang Pikeman is the unique Heavy Pikeman du Quang culture. It starts with promotions Formation I and II, which almost doubles its standard Pikeman bonus against mounted units.</French>
		<Italian>Il picchiere Qiang è il picchiere pesante unico della cultura Quang. Inizia con le promozioni Formazione I e Formazione II, che raddoppiano le sue abilità contro le unià montate.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_QIANG_PIKEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Pikeman of the Qiang culture in China developed the art of the pike to a level comparable with the legendary pikemen of Switzerland.</English>
		<French>The Pikeman du Qiang culture in China developed the art du pike to a level comparable with the legendary pikemen of Switzerland.</French>
		<Italian>I picchieri della cultura Qiang svilupparono la costruzione di picche ad un livello comparabile a quello dei leggendari picchieri svizzeri.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AXEMAN_ROXOLANI</Tag>
		<English>Roxolani Axeman</English>
		<French>Guerrier Roxolani avec Hache</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guerriero con ascia Rossolano:Guerrieri con ascia Rossolani</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AXEMAN_ROXOLANI_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Roxolani Axeman is the unique Axeman alternative from the Roxolani culture. It starts with two Formation promotions, and thus meets both melee and mounted units of its era at a considerable advantage.</English>
		<Italian>Il guerriero con ascia Rossolano inizia con le promozioni Formazione I e Formazione II: per questo motivo, ha un discreto vantaggio sia contro le unità da combattimento ravvicinato, sia contro le unità montate.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AXEMAN_ROXOLANI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Roxolani were a people of the Wallachian plain, near the mouth of the Danube on the Black Sea (modern-day Romania/Moldova).  They were enemies of the Romans from around 100 BC until being conquered by the Huns in the 4th century.  The Romans found their axemen to be especially potent adversaries, especially the Legio XXI Rapax, which was destroyed by a combined force of Roxolani and Dacians in 92 AD.</English>
		<French>The Roxolani were a people du Wallachian plain, near the mouth du Danube on the Black Sea (modern-day Romania/Moldova).  They were enemies du Romans from around 100 BC until being conquered by the Huns in the 4th century.  The Romans found their axemen to be especially potent adversaries, especially the Legio XXI Rapax, which was destroyed by a combined force of Roxolani and Dacians in 92 AD.</French>
		<Italian>I Rossolani erano un popolo delle pianure della Valacchia, vicino alla foce del Danubio nel Mar Nero (gli attuali Romania e Moldavia). Furono nemici dei Romani dal 100 a.C. fino a quando furono conquistati dagli Unni nel 4° secolo. I Romani scopriorno che i loro guerrieri con ascia erano avversari estremamente pericolosi, in particolare quando la Legio XXI Rapax venne annientata da una forza congiunta di Rossolani e Daci nel 92 d.C.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SAVARAN</Tag>
		<English>Savaran Cavalry</English>
		<French>Chevaliers Savaran</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cavalleria Savaran</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>Caballeros Savaran</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SAVARAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Savaran Cavalry is the unique Knight alternative from the Sassanian (or Sassanid) culture. A specially-trained, elite unit, it starts with Combat I and II, and of course Commando.  That leaves plenty of starting experience for Shock, Formation, and other specialist promotions.</English>
		<Italian>La cavalleria Savaran sostituisce il cavaliere nella cultura sassanide. Essendo un'unità d'elite altamente addestrata, inizia con le promozioni Combattimento I, Combattimento II e Commando. Questo permette di scegliere dall'inizio promozioni per specializzare quest'unità.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SAVARAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Sassanid Savaran were the knights who formed the armour guard of the emperor himself.  Unlike knights elsewhere who were born into the role - or were there because they could afford a horse - the Savaran were highly trained, as only the best were selected for this coveted role.</English>
		<French>The Sassanid Savaran were the knights who formed the armour guard du emperor himself.  Unlike knights elsewhere who were born into the role - or were there because they could afford a horse - the Savaran were highly trained, as only the best were selected for this coveted role.</French>
		<Italian>I Savaran sassanidi erano i cavalieri che formavano la guardia dell'imperatore sassanide. A differenza dei cavalieri europei, che diventavano tali per nascita, i Savaran erano altamente addestrati, poichè solo i migliori potevano essere scelti per questo ruolo.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SCYTHIAN_HORSE_ARCHER</Tag>
		<English>Scythian Horse Archer</English>
		<French>Archer monté Scythe</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Arciere a cavallo scita:Arcieri a cavallo sciti</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SCYTHIAN_HORSE_ARCHER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Scythian Horse Archer, unsurprisingly, is the unique supplementary Horse Archer from the Scythian culture. In addition to Commando, it starts with Hit and Run and Marksmanship I.  These make it faster cross-country, and stronger overall and especially against mounted units.  The two additional First Strike Chances, and a Withdrawal Chance that with all bonuses starts at 55%, make it a force to be reckoned with.</English>
		<French>The Scythian Horse Archer, unsurprisingly, is the unique supplementary Horse Archer from the Scythian culture. In addition to Commando, it starts with Hit and Run and Marksmanship I.  These make it faster cross-country, and stronger overall and especially against mounted units.  The two additional First Strike Chances, et un Withdrawal Chance that with all bonuses starts at 55%, make it a force to be reckoned with.</French>
		<Italian>L'arciere a cavallo Scita inizia con le promozioni Mordi e fuggi, Commando e Tiratore scelto I. Queste promozioni lo rendono più veloce nelle tue campagne, oltre a più forte in generale e in particolare contro le unità montate. Le due chance di attacchi improvvisi supplementari, oltre alle chance di ritirarsi, lo rendono una forza decisamente temibile sul campo di battaglia.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SCYTHIAN_HORSE_ARCHER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Horse Archers of the Scythians would appear out of nowhere, striking where you least expected it.  Their accuracy with the bow was also the stuff of legend, and rendered them even more lethal.</English>
		<French>The Horse Archers du Scythians would appear out of nowhere, striking where you least expected it.  Their accuracy with the bow was also the stuff of legend, and rendered them even more lethal.</French>
		<Italian>Gli arcieri a cavallo Sciti comparivano dal nulla, colpendo in luoghi inaspettati. La loro accuratezza con l'arco era leggendaria, e li rendeva ancora più letali.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SIBERIAN_TRACKER</Tag>
		<English>Siberian Tracker</English>
		<French>Traqueur Sibérien</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cercatore di tracce Siberiano:Cercatori di tracce Siberiani</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SIBERIAN_TRACKER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Siberian Tracker is the Siberian culture's version of the Warden. Completely at home no matter how low the temperature, it starts with the promotions Arctic Combat I, II and III, as well as Hunting Sight I and II. The ideal hunter for extreme latitudes. Useful also in battle, but not against cities, where it gets a large penalty.</English>
		<French>The Siberian Tracker is the Siberian culture's version du Warden. Completely at home no matter how low the temperature, it starts with the promotions Arctic Combat I, II and III, as well as Hunting Sight I and II. The ideal hunter for extreme latitudes. Useful also in battle, but not against cities, where it gets a large penalty.</French>
		<Italian>Il cercatore di tracce Siberiano è la versione Siberiana del guardiacaccia. Si trova a su agio con temperature estremamente basse, perciò inizia con le promozioni Combattente artico I, Combattente artico II e Combattente artico III, oltre a Occhio del cacciatore I e Occhio del cacciatore II. E' il cacciatore ideale delle alte latitudini; è utile anche in battaglia ma non per assaltare le città, dove riceve delle gravi penalità.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SIBERIAN_TRACKER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Siberian Tracker is a unique unit of the Siberian culture, equivalent to the Warden.  It starts with the Arctic Combat promotions I, II and III, as well as the standard Warden's Hunting Sight I and II.</English>
		<French>The Siberian Tracker is a unique unit du Siberian culture, equivalent to the Warden.  It starts with the Arctic Combat promotions I, II and III, as well as the standard Warden's Hunting Sight I and II.</French>
		<Italian>Il cercatore di tracce siberiano è l'equivalente siberiano del guardiacaccia; come tale, ottiene le abilità del guardiacaccia e le promozioni per combattere nei terreni artici.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MIG_29</Tag>
		<English>MiG-29</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MIG_29_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The MiG-29 is the unique Modern Fighter of the Soviet culture. It starts with Air-to-air I, Air-to-air II and Range I.  Naturally this will give it air supremacy over less advanced (ie. less promoted) modern fighters.</English>
		<French>The MiG-29 is the unique Modern Fighter du Soviet culture. It starts with Air-to-air I, Air-to-air II and Range I.  Naturally this will give it air supremacy over less advanced (ie. less promoted) modern fighters.</French>
		<Italian>Il MiG-29 è il caccia moderno della cultura Sovietica. Inizia con le promozioni Missili aria-aria I, Missili aria-aria II e Raggio d'azione I; per questo motivo ottiene facilmente la supremazia aerea contro i caccia meno avanzati (o con meno esperienza).</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MIG_29_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Mikoyan-Gurevich (MiG) 29 (codename 'Fulcrum') represents the pinnacle of Soviet jet fighter technology.</English>
		<Italian>Il Mikoyan-Gurevich (MiG) 29 (nome in codice 'Fulcrum') rappresenta l'apice della tecnologia sovietica nei caccia a reazione.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KUOMINTANG</Tag>
		<English>Kuomintang</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KUOMINTANG_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Kuomintang is the unique Infantry unit of the Taiwanese culture. It starts with the promotions Patrol I and II and Dedication.  It is thus an excellent city defender, with the added bonus of discouraging rebellion.</English>
		<French>The Kuomintang is the unique Infantry unit du Taiwanese culture. It starts with the promotions Patrol I and II and Dedication.  It is thus an excellent city defender, with the added bonus of discouraging rebellion.</French>
		<Italian>Il Kuomintang è la fanteria unica della cultura taiwanes. Inizia con le promozioni Pattuglia I, Pattuglia II e Dedicazione; perciò è eccellente per difendere le città, con il bonus di scoraggiare le ribellioni.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KUOMINTANG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Originally a revolutionary league working for the overthrow of the Chinese monarchy, the Nationalists became a political party in the first year of the Chinese republic (1912). The party participated in the first Chinese parliament, which was soon dissolved by a coup d'état (1913). This defeat moved its leader, Sun Yat-sen, to organize it more tightly, first (1914) on the model of a Chinese secret society and, later (1923-24), under Soviet guidance, on that of the Bolshevik party. The Nationalist Party owed its early successes largely to Soviet aid and advice and to close collaboration with the Chinese communists (1924-27).</English>
		<French>Originally a revolutionary league working for the overthrow du Chinese monarchy, the Nationalists became a political party in the first year du Chinese republic (1912). The party participated in the first Chinese parliament, which was soon dissolved by a coup d'état (1913). This defeat moved its leader, Sun Yat-sen, to organize it more tightly, first (1914) on the model of a Chinese secret society and, later (1923-24), under Soviet guidance, on that du Bolshevik party. The Nationalist Party owed its early successes largely to Soviet aid and advice and to close collaboration with the Chinese communists (1924-27).</French>
		<Italian>Il Kuomintang è l'unità taiwanese che sostituisce la fanteria. Inizia con le promozioni Pattgulia I, Pattuglia II e Dedicazione.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TLATILCO_WAR_PRIEST</Tag>
		<English>Tlatilco War Priest</English>
		<French>Prêtre-Guerrier Tlatilco</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Sacerdote guerriero Tlatilco:Sacerdoti guerrieri Tlatilco</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TLATILCO_WAR_PRIEST_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Tlatilco War Priest is the Tlatilco culture's equivalent of the Obsidian Swordsman. As a priestly unit, it starts with the Fanatic and Herbal Cures promotions, while retaining the standard swordsman's bonus when attacking a city.  Thus it needs favourable terrain if it is to defend, but excels all others for rushing early cities.</English>
		<French>The Tlatilco War Priest is the Tlatilco culture's equivalent du Obsidian Swordsman. As a priestly unit, it starts with the Fanatic and Herbal Cures promotions, while retaining the standard swordsman's bonus when attacking a city.  Thus it needs favourable terrain if it is to defend, but excels all others for rushing early cities.</French>
		<Italian>Il sacerdote guerriero tlatilco sosituisce il guerriero con spada d'ossidiana. Inizia con le promozioni Fanatico ed Erbe mediche, oltre a mantenere i bonus standard degli spadaccini quando attacca una città. Non è ottimo in un ruolo difensivo, ma è l'ideale per razziare le città nemiche appena fondate.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TLATILCO_WAR_PRIEST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Tlatilco War Priest is a unique unit of the Tlatilco culture, equivalent to the Obsidian Swordsman.  It starts with the Fanatic and Herbal Cures promotions, and the standard swordsman's bonus for city attack.</English>
		<French>The Tlatilco War Priest is a unique unit du Tlatilco culture, equivalent to the Obsidian Swordsman.  It starts with the Fanatic and Herbal Cures promotions, and the standard swordsman's bonus for city attack.</French>
		<Italian>Il sacerdote guerriero tlatilco sosituisce il guerriero con spada d'ossidiana. Inizia con le promozioni Fanatico ed Erbe mediche, oltre a mantenere i bonus standard degli spadaccini quando attacca una città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TLAXCALTEC_WARRIOR</Tag>
		<English>Tlaxcaltec Warrior</English>
		<French>Guerrier Tlaxcaltec</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guerriero Tlaxcalteco:Guerrieri Tlaxcaltechi</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TLAXCALTEC_WARRIOR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Tlaxcaltec Warrior is the Tlaxcaltec culture's equivalent of the Light Swordsman. It starts with the Shock I and Drill I promotions, and has the standard swordsman's bonus when attacking a city.</English>
		<French>The Tlaxcaltec Warrior is the Tlaxcaltec culture's equivalent du Light Swordsman. It starts with the Shock I and Drill I promotions, and has the standard swordsman's bonus when attacking a city.</French>
		<Italian>Il guerriero tlaxcalteco sostituisce lo spadaccino leggero. Inizia con le promozioni Shock I e Addestramento I, oltre ad avere i bonus standard degli spadaccini attaccando una città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TLAXCALTEC_WARRIOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Tlaxcaltec Warrior is a unique unit of the Tlaxcaltec culture, equivalent to the Light Swordsman (even though he wields a sword of obsidian).  It starts with the Shock I and Drill I promotion, and the standard swordsman's bonus for city attack.  Thus it will be especially effective for storming a Classical city defended mostly by Melee units.</English>
		<French>The Tlaxcaltec Warrior is a unique unit du Tlaxcaltec culture, equivalent to the Light Swordsman (even though he wields a sword of obsidian).  It starts with the Shock I and Drill I promotion, and the standard swordsman's bonus for city attack.  Thus it will be especially effective for storming a Classical city defended mostly by Melee units.</French>
		<Italian>Il guerriero tlaxcalteco equivale allo spadaccino leggero, anche se utilizza una spada di ossidiana. Inizia con le promozioni Shock I e Addestramento I, oltre ad avere i normali bonus attaccando le città. Perciò è l'ideale per attaccare una città difesa principalmente da unità da combattimento ravvicinato.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOLLONIAN_GUARD</Tag>
		<English>Apollonian Guard</English>
		<French>Garde Apollinien</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guardia Apolloniana</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOLLONIAN_GUARD_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Apollonian Guard is the unique Spearman of the Trojan culture. Like the Spearman line in general, it starts with a bonus against Mounted units (and against animals in general). It starts with the Policing I and City Garrison I promotions.</English>
		<French>The Apollonian Guard is the unique Spearman du Trojan culture. Like the Spearman line in general, it starts with a bonus against Mounted units (and against animals in general). It starts with the Policing I and City Garrison I promotions.</French>
		<Italian>La guardia Apolloniana è il lanciere unico della cultura troiana; come tutti i lancieri, ottiene un bonus contro le unità montate e gli animali. Inizia con le promozioni Polizia I e Guarnigione I.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APOLLONIAN_GUARD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Apollonian Guard is a Trojan unique unit, an alternative to the Spearman.  Because it is a palace guard type of unit, it comes with the promotions Policing I and City Garrison I.  Thus it is the ideal unit for defending cities against mounted units, and better than the Town Watchmen at keeping Crime in check.</English>
		<Italian>La guardia Apolloniana è l'unità unica troiana, sostituta del lanciere. Dato che era assegnata alla difesa di un palazzo, inizia con le promozioni Polizia I e Guarnigione I. Per questo motivo è l'unità ideale per difendere le città dalle unità montate, oltre ad essere meglio delle sentinelle cittadine a tenere sotto controllo il crimine.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CHROME_INFANTRY</Tag>
		<English>Chrome Infantry</English>
		<French>Infanterie Chrome</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CHROME_INFANTRY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Chrome Infantry is the first genetically-enhanced infantry unit of the Transhuman era.  You can expect them to give you an edge over the Modern Infantry of your rivals.  Welcome... to the Future!...</English>
		<French>The Chrome Infantry is the first genetically-enhanced infantry unit du Transhuman era.  You can expect them to give you an edge over the Modern Infantry of your rivals.  Welcome... to the Future!...</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CHROME_INFANTRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Years of secret experimentation with "discarded" IVF foetuses has led us to this.  We can now reliably enhance the genetic makeup of a pre-born human... so as to better suit our purposes.  Forget cloning (cos we can't do that yet...) - we will enhance each human killing machine individually for you.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CLONE_INFANTRY</Tag>
		<English>Clone Infantry</English>
		<French>Infanterie Clonée</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CLONE_INFANTRY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Clone Infantry is the most basic infantry unit of the Transhuman 'clone era'.  Time to upgrade your garrison top defenders yet again.</English>
		<French>The Clone Infantry is the most basic infantry unit du Transhuman 'clone era'.  Time to upgrade your garrison top defenders yet again.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CLONE_INFANTRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Now that cloning is a mainstream technology, it was only a matter of time before the mad scientists of the 'defence' sector got their hands on it.  At first activists were up in arms about people bred in labs purely as killing machines.  However, the clones themselves pointed out that they are not automatons, even going so far as to claim that the military was their chosen profession.  Of course, not everyone was convinced, but - what can you do?</English>
		<French>Now that cloning is a mainstream technology, it was only a matter of time before the mad scientists du 'defence' sector got their hands on it.  At first activists were up in arms about people bred in labs purely as killing machines.  However, the clones themselves pointed out that they are not automatons, even going so far as to claim that the military was their chosen profession.  Of course, not everyone was convinced, but - what can you do?</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SHOCKWAVE_APC</Tag>
		<English>Shockwave APC</English>
		<French>Blindé APC à ondes de choc</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SHOCKWAVE_APC_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>This is the Armoured Personnel Carrier upgraded to Shockwave propulsion - thus it does not require oil-based fuel.  It is also somewhat stronger than its predecessor.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SHOCKWAVE_APC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Now that the Internal Shockwave Engine has largely superseded internal combustion, it is only natural that an armoured personnel carrier has been developed using the new technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_UNMANNED_TRIKE</Tag>
		<English>Unmanned Trike</English>
		<French>Trike sans pilote</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_UNMANNED_TRIKE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Unmanned Trike is an autonomous, fast, motorcycle-sized recon unit.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_UNMANNED_TRIKE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The recent advances in robotics have led to the development of this marvellous recon unit.  All the benefits of conventional motorbike recon, but without risking any valuable men.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_UNMANNED_HELICOPTER</Tag>
		<English>Drone Helicopter</English>
		<French>Drone Hélicoptère</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_UNMANNED_HELICOPTER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Drone Helicopter is a generation more advanced than the Stealth Gunship, and operates without the need for a costly aircrew.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_UNMANNED_HELICOPTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Drone Helicopter is a more maneuvrable - and more intelligent - version of the fixed-wing drones that you may have heard about...</English>
		<French>The Drone Helicopter is a more maneuvrable - and more intelligent - version du fixed-wing drones that you may have heard about...</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DROID_HELICOPTER</Tag>
		<English>Droid Helicopter</English>
		<French>Hélicoptère Droïde</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DROID_HELICOPTER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Another upgrade of the 'drone' aircraft - this rotary-winged machine has all the tactical nous of a true robot.</English>
		<French>Another upgrade du 'drone' aircraft - this rotary-winged machine has all the tactical nous of a true robot.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DROID_HELICOPTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Those jaded Drone Copters are really showing their age.  Well never mind, because here's a smarter, fully robotic helicopter to replace them with.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAMEL_CUIRASSIER</Tag>
		<English>Camel Cuirassier</English>
		<French>Cuirassier à dos de Chameau</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAMEL_CUIRASSIER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The mounted matchlock unit for when you've got camels but no horses. Generally slightly weaker than the standard cuirassier, except in desert of course.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAMEL_CUIRASSIER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Even in the age of gunpowder, desert civilizations, especially those of the Sahara, found that the camel's endurance - and its sand-adapted hooves - gave it a slight edge over the horse as a mount for desert campaigns.</English>
		<French>Even in the age of gunpowder, desert civilizations, especially those du Sahara, found that the camel's endurance - and its sand-adapted hooves - gave it a slight edge over the horse as a mount for desert campaigns.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAMEL_CAVALRY</Tag>
		<English>Camel Cavalry</English>
		<French>Cavalerie à dos de Chameau</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAMEL_CAVALRY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The mounted rifle-equipped unit for when you've got camels but no horses. Generally slightly weaker than horse cavalry, except in desert of course.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAMEL_CAVALRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Even in the age of the rifle, desert civilizations, especially those of the Sahara, found that the camel's endurance - and its sand-adapted hooves - gave it a slight edge over the horse as a mount for desert campaigns.  Of course it has its disadvantages, but if camels are all that is readily available to you, you find them a very competitive substitute.</English>
		<French>Even in the age du rifle, desert civilizations, especially those du Sahara, found that the camel's endurance - and its sand-adapted hooves - gave it a slight edge over the horse as a mount for desert campaigns.  Of course it has its disadvantages, but if camels are all that is readily available to you, you find them a very competitive substitute.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAMEL_TRENCH_CAVALRY</Tag>
		<English>Camel Trench Cavalry</English>
		<French>Cavalerie Camélidée des Tranchées</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAMEL_TRENCH_CAVALRY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>If you've camels but no horses, in the twilight era of mounted warfare, this is the unit you need. Generally slightly weaker than the standard trench cavalry, except in desert of course.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAMEL_TRENCH_CAVALRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Even in the late Industrial era, to the extent that mounted warfare was persisted with, it was believed that the camel's endurance - and its sand-adapted hooves - gave it a slight edge over the horse as a mount for desert campaigns.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- National Archives -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARCHIVES</Tag>
		<English>National Archives</English>
		<French>Les Archives Nationales</French>
		<German>Nationalarchiv</German>
		<Polish>Archiwum Narodowe</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARCHIVES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The National Archives is a repository that preserves important documents and historical records.</English>
		<Polish>Archiwum - gromadzony zbiór, miejsce gromadzenia tego zbioru, w pewnych znaczeniach również instytucja zajmująca się gromadzeniem. Archiwizacja jest to proces tworzenia, zabezpieczania i klasyfikowania zbioru</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARCHIVES_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]The National Archives[COLOR_REVERT] is a National Wonder that increases research by +15 percent for the city in which it is produced. It also provides a free scientist and increases the amount of scientists the city may have by 1.  The city, in which it is produced, is also more likely to produce a Great Scientist.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- End National Archives -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARK</Tag>
		<English>Ark of the Covenant</English>
		<French>L'Arche des Covenants</French>
		<German>Bundeslade</German>
		<Polish>Arka Przymierza</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Ark of the Covenant was a vessel described in the Bible as containing the Tablets of Stone on which the Ten Commandments were inscribed, along with Aaron's rod and manna.  The Ark was built at the command of God, in accord with the prophetic vision of Moses on Mount Sinai. God communicated with Moses, from between the two cherubim, on the Ark's cover.  The Ark was carried by the priests some 2,000 cubits in advance of the Israelite people and their army, or host. When the Ark was borne by priests into the bed of the Jordan, water in the river separated, opening a pathway for the entire host to pass through. The city of Jericho was taken with no more than a shout after the Ark of Covenant was paraded for seven days around its wall by seven priests sounding seven trumpets of rams' horns. When carried, the Ark was always wrapped in a veil, in tachash skins and a blue cloth, and was carefully concealed, even from the eyes of the priests who carried it.</English>
		<French>The Ark du Covenant was a vessel described in the Bible as containing the Tablets of Stone on which the Ten Commandments were inscribed, along with Aaron's rod and manna.  The Ark was built at the command of God, in accord with the prophetic vision of Moses on Mount Sinai. God communicated with Moses, from between the two cherubim, on the Ark's cover.  The Ark was carried by the priests some 2,000 cubits in advance du Israelite people and their army, or host. When the Ark was borne by priests into the bed du Jordan, water in the river separated, opening a pathway for the entire host to pass through. The city of Jericho was taken with no more than a shout after the Ark of Covenant was paraded for seven days around its wall by seven priests sounding seven trumpets of rams' horns. When carried, the Ark was always wrapped in a veil, in tachash skins et un blue cloth, and was carefully concealed, even from the eyes du priests who carried it.</French>
		<Polish>Arka Przymierza - obiekt będący dla Żydów jednym z elementów ich przymierza z BogiemJahwe. Według hebrajskiej Biblii, do momentu wybudowania pierwszej świątyni przez króla Salomona arka była przewożona na specjalnym wozie z zasłonami podczas wszystkich kampanii wojskowych prowadzonych przez Izraelitów. Stanowiła ona centrum kultu w czasie wędrówki Izraelitów do ziemi Kanaan. Wierzono, że armia posiadająca arkę jest niezwyciężona. W czasie oblężenia Jerycha obnoszono ją wokół murów miasta. Później przechowywana była w Miejscu Świętym Przybytku Mojżeszowego w Szilo. Następnie zdobyć ją mieli Filistyni lecz, jak twierdzi Biblia, zwrócili, widząc w niej przyczynę swoich klęsk. Król Dawid miał przenieść ją na wzgórze Syjon w Jerozolimie, a Salomon po wybudowaniu świątyni do specjalnego pomieszczenia, do którego nie miał wstępu nikt prócz arcykapłana.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARK_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ark of the Covenant[COLOR_REVERT] has no unhappiness in the city in which it is built and provides +1 happines in all cities.  It also provides +1 gold from ALL state religious buildings and it increases it's city's odds of generating a Great Prophet.</English>
		<French>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ark du Covenant[COLOR_REVERT] has no unhappiness in the city in which it is built and provides +1 happines in all cities.  It also provides +1 gold from ALL state religious buildings and it increases it's city's odds of generating a Great Prophet.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_INDUSTRYESPIONAGE</Tag>
		<English>Industry Espionage</English>
		<French>Espionnage Industriel</French>
		<German>Industrie-Spion</German>
		<Italian>Spionaggio industriale</Italian>
		<Polish>Szpiegostwo Przemysłowe</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_INDUSTRYESPIONAGE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Plunders 4% of Enemy [ICON_RESEARCH] Reserves on Combat Victory</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Pille 4% de la réserve de [ICON_RESEARCH] ennemie en cas de Victoire au Combat</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Plündert 4% der feindlichen [ICON_RESEARCH] nach einem Sieg im Kampf</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ruba 4% delle risorse nemiche di [ICON_RESEARCH] quando vince una battaglia</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Po zwycięstwie w walce grabi 4% rezerw wrogiego [ICON_RESEARCH]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_INDUSTRYESPIONAGE_YOU</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]You have plundered %d2 [ICON_RESEARCH] from %s1![COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]Vous avez pillé %d2 [ICON_RESEARCH] à %s1![COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<Polish>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]Złupiłeś %d2 [ICON_RESEARCH] z Imperium %s1![COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_INDUSTRYESPIONAGE_FROM</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]%s1 has plundered %d2 [ICON_RESEARCH] from you![COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]%s1 vous a volé %d2 [ICON_RESEARCH]![COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<Polish>[COLOR_SELECTED_TEXT]%s1 złupił %d2 [ICON_RESEARCH] z Twojego imperium![COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILD_EARLY_QUARRY</Tag>
		<English>Build [LINK=IMPROVEMENT_EARLY_QUARRY]Early Quarry[\LINK]</English>
		<French>Construire une [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]carrière antique[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<Polish>Zbuduj Wczesny Kamieniołom</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_EARLY_QUARRY</Tag>
		<English>Early Quarry</English>
		<French>Carrière antique</French>
		<Polish>Wczesny Kamieniołom</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_SPECIALIST_GREAT_MILITARY_INSTRUCTOR</Tag>
		<English>Great Military Instructor</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Instructeur militaire illustre</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Großer Militärausbilder</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Grande istruttore militare:Grandi istruttori militari</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Gran instructor militar:Grandes instructores militares</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GLOBELAYER_RESOURCES_ALL</Tag>
		<English>All Resources</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GLOBELAYER_RESOURCES_GROWTH</Tag>
		<English>Growth</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GLOBELAYER_RESOURCES_LUXURY</Tag>
		<English>Luxury</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GLOBELAYER_RESOURCES_MISC</Tag>
		<English>Misc</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GLOBELAYER_RESOURCES_PRODUCTION</Tag>
		<English>Production</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GLOBELAYER_RESOURCES_STRATEGIC</Tag>
		<English>Strategic</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>