<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ABYSSINIANS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Abyssinian</English>
		<French>
			<Text>abyssinien:abyssinienne:abyssiniens:abyssiniennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>abessinisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>abissino:abissina:abissini:abissine</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>abisinio:abisinia:abisinios:abisinias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Abisyńczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ABYSSINIANS_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Abyssinian Empire</English>
		<French>Empire abyssinien</French>
		<German>Reich der Abessinier</German>
		<Italian>Impero Abissino</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio Abisinio</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Abisyńskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ABYSSINIANS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>According to tradition, the Abyssinian kingdom was founded (10th century B.C.) by Solomon's first son, Menelik I, whom the Queen of Sheba is supposed to have borne. Thus this makes Ethiopia the oldest independent country in Africa and one of the most ancient in the world. For centuries Abyssinia controlled much of the Red Sea coast and had links with the Mediterranean world. In the 4th Century under King Ezana, Abyssinia was converted to Christianity.[PARAGRAPH:2]With the rise of Islam in the 7th century, Abyssinia declined, mainly because its land contacts with the Byzantine Empire were severed and its control of the Red Sea trade routes was ended. In 1530-31, Ahmad Gran, a Muslim Somali leader, conquered much of Ethiopia. The Ethiopian emperor Lebna Dengel appealed to Portugal for help against the Somalis (a Portuguese embassy had reached the Ethiopian court in 1520). The Somali war exhausted Ethiopia, ending a period of cultural revival and exposing the empire to incursions by the Oromo. For the next two centuries the Ethiopian kingdom, centered at Gondar, was beset by ruinous civil wars among princes and again isolated from the outside world.[PARAGRAPH:2]The reunification of Ethiopia was begun in the 19th century by Tewodros II, who conquered Amhara, Gojjam, Tigray, and Shoa, and in 1855 had himself crowned emperor as Tewodros II. He began to modernize and centralize the legal and administrative systems. In 1867 tensions developed with Great Britain, and a British military expedition under Robert Napier was sent out. The emperor's forces were easily defeated near Magdala and to avoid capture, Tewodros committed suicide. A brief civil war followed, and in 1872 a chieftain of Tigray became emperor as Yohannes IV.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1889 a succession crisis ensued, eventually resulting in the king of Shoa crowned as emperor Menelik II. Italy invaded Ethiopia in 1895 but was decisively beaten by Menelik's forces at the battle of Adwa, March 1, 1896. Legend has it that Ethiopian nomadic mountain warriors of the Galla tribe since before 1000 A.D. would mix berries (coffee) with animal fat to give them energy before battles. These "Galla" warriors were noted for being among the most ferocious in Abyssinia, much like the ones that dealt the Italians their defeat.[PARAGRAPH:2]During his reign, Menelik greatly expanded the size of Ethiopia, adding the provinces of Harar, Sidamo, and Kaffa. After making Addis Ababa his capital in 1896, he began to modernize his military, government, developed the economy and built his country's first railroad. Menelik died in 1913, he is widely acknowledged has one of history's greatest African Leaders.[PARAGRAPH:2]On Oct. 3, 1935, Italy invaded Ethiopia once more. The Italians quickly defeated the Ethiopians, Addis Ababa was captured and Haile Selassie fled the country. In 1941, during World War II, Haile Selassie regained his throne with the help of British and South African Forces. In 1945, Ethiopia became a charter member of the United Nations.[PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
		<Polish>Abisynia – dawna nazwa Etiopii, wywodząca się najprawdopodobniej od nazwy plemienia południowo arabskiego Habesz, które przywędrowało do Afryki przypuszczalnie jeszcze p.n.e. Uważa się, iż jedną z przyczyn, dla których Etiopczycy zrezygnowali z nazwy Abisynia i wprowadzili nową (Etiopia) jest pogardliwe znaczenie formy "habesz" w języku arabskim, oznaczające mieszańca, włóczykija. Słowo to było używane w okresach waśni przez mieszkających w kraju wyznawców islamu na określenie chrześcijan.[PARAGRAPH:2]Starą nazwę Abisynia zastąpiono formą Etiopia, występującą m.in. w tekstach biblijnych, gdzie nazwą tą opatrywany jest ten właśnie afrykański kraj. Wyraz Etiopia wywodzi się z greckiego aithiopes, tj. "brunatne twarze". Mianem tym greccy podróżnicy określali ludy zamieszkujące obszar północno-wschodniej Afryki (tj. Sudan, Nubię oraz Etiopię właściwą). Ponieważ nazwa ta występuje w oryginalnych tekstach biblijnych pisanych greką, została ona zaakceptowana jako oficjalna nazwa państwa.[PARAGRAPH:2]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ABYSSINIANS_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Abyssinia</English>
		<French>Abyssinie</French>
		<German>Abessinien</German>
		<Italian>Abissinia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Abisinia</Spanish>
		<Polish>Abisynia</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AMERICA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>American</English>
		<French>
			<Text>américain:américaine:américains:américaines</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>amerikanisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>americano:americana:americani:americane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>estadounidense:estadounidense:estadounidenses:estadounidenses</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Amerykanów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AMERICA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>American Empire</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire américain</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Amerikaner</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Americano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Estadounidense</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Amerykańskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AMERICA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>America</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Américains</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Amerika</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>L'America:l'America:dell'America:d'America</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Estados Unidos</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Ameryka</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_BEAST_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Beastly</English>
		<French>Bêtes</French>
		<German>animalisch</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_BEAST_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Fauna Beasts</English>
		<French>Faune Bestiale</French>
		<German>Bestien</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_BEAST_DESC_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Beasts</English>
		<French>Bêtes</French>
		<German>Bestien</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_BEAST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Fauna Beasts, or 'Beasts', are atypical predators that either prey on all animals alike or are both predator and prey at the same time. While usually not the most aggressive animals of the wild they are often as deadly as your typical predator, if not more so.</English>
		<French>Les bêtes de la faune, ou «bêtes», sont des prédateurs atypiques qui s'attaquent à tous les animaux ou sont à la fois prédateurs et proies en même temps. Bien qu'ils ne soient généralement pas les animaux sauvages les plus agressifs, ils sont souvent aussi mortels que votre prédateur typique, sinon plus.</French>
		<German>Unter Bestien werden bei Caveman2Cosmos all jene Kreaturen zusammengefasst, die gleichzeitig Räuber und Beute sind. In den meisten Fällen handelt es sich nicht um besonders aggressive Tiere, die aber trotzdem genauso gefährlich wie ein typisches Raubtier sein können, wenn nicht gar noch gefährlicher.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_PREDATOR_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Predatory</English>
		<French>Prédateur</French>
		<German>räuberisch</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_PREDATOR_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Fauna Predators</English>
		<French>Faune prédatrice</French>
		<German>Raubtiere</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_PREDATOR_DESC_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Predators</English>
		<French>Prédateurs</French>
		<German>Raubtiere</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_PREDATOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Fauna Predators, or 'Predators', are the dangerous entities of the wild that would attack or prey on not only man but other species.</English>
		<French>Les prédateurs de la faune, ou «prédateurs», sont les entités dangereuses de la nature qui attaqueraient ou s'attaqueraient non seulement à l'homme mais à d'autres espèces.</French>
		<German>Raubtiere sind gefährliche wilde Bestien, die nahezu alle anderen Spezies einschließlich Menschen als ihre Beute betrachten oder zumindest bei Sichtkontakt gnadenlos angreifen.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_PREY_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Creaturely</English>
		<French>Créatures</French>
		<German>tierisch</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_PREY_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Fauna Creatures</English>
		<French>Faune - Créatures</French>
		<German>Kreaturen</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_PREY_DESC_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Creatures</English>
		<French>Créatures</French>
		<German>Kreaturen</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANIMAL_PREY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Fauna Creatures, or 'Creatures', are the peacefully observable denizens of nature that, while capable of sometimes becoming hostile, and certainly often up to the task of defending themselves, are more commonly likely to be indifferent or flighty at best. They are often the 'prey' for more aggressive predatory species but since many predators can also BE prey for something larger or stronger than them, nature is not so simple as to divide animals purely into predator and prey camps. Nevertheless, there ARE animals that are not hostile in general and these creatures are those.</English>
		<French>Les créatures de la faune, ou "créatures", sont les habitants de la nature pacifiquement observables qui, bien que capables de devenir parfois hostiles, et certainement souvent à la hauteur de se défendre, sont le plus souvent susceptibles d'être au mieux indifférents ou volants. Ils sont souvent la "proie"d'espèces prédatrices plus agressives, mais comme de nombreux prédateurs peuvent également ÊTRE la proie de quelque chose de plus grand ou plus fort qu'eux, la nature n'est pas si simple qu'elle divise les animaux uniquement en camps de prédateurs et de proies. Néanmoins, il y a des animaux qui ne sont pas hostiles en général et ces créatures sont celles-là.</French>
		<German>Unter Kreaturen werden bei Caveman2Cosmos friedliche und harmlose Tiere zusammengefasst, die in den meisten Fällen einem Kampf durch Flucht aus dem Weg gehen, die aber durchaus auch in der Lage sind, sich im Notfall zu verteidigen.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ARABIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Arabian</English>
		<French>
			<Text>arabe:arabe:arabes:arabes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>arabisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>arabo:araba:arabi:arabe</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>árabe:árabe:árabes:árabes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Arabów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ARABIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Arabian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire arabe</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Araber</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Arabo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Árabe</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Arabskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ARABIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Arabia</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Arabes</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Arabien</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>L'Arabia:l'Arabia:dell'Arabia:d'Arabia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Arabia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ASSYRIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Assyrian</English>
		<French>Assyrien</French>
		<German>assyrisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>assiro:assira:assiri:assire</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>asirio:asiria:asirios:asirias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Asyryjczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ASSYRIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Assyrian Empire</English>
		<French>Empire assyrien</French>
		<German>Reich der Assyrer</German>
		<Italian>Impero Assiro</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio Asirio</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Asyryjskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ASSYRIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Assyria was an ancient empire of W Asia. It developed around the city of Ashur, or Assur, on the upper Tigris River and south of the later capital, Nineveh.[PARAGRAPH:1]The nucleus of a Semitic state was forming by the beginning of the 3d millennium B.C., but it was overshadowed by the greatness of Sumer and Akkad. Ashur was Assyria's chief god, but the gods of the Babylonians and Hittites were also honoured. In the 17th cent. B.C., Assyria expanded briefly, but it soon relapsed into weakness. The 13th cent. B.C. saw Assyria threatening the surrounding states, and under Tiglathpileser I Assyrian soldiers entered the kingdom centred about Urartu, took Babylonia, and crossed N Syria to reach the Mediterranean. This empire was, however, only ephemeral.[PARAGRAPH:1]Assyrian greatness was to wait until the 9th cent., when Ashurnasirpal II came into power. He was not only a vigorous and barbarously cruel conqueror who pushed his conquests N to Urartu and W to Lebanon and the Mediterranean, but he was also a shrewd administrator. Instead of merely making conquered kings pay tribute, he installed Assyrian governors so that he could have more control over the empire.[PARAGRAPH:1]Shalmaneser III attempted to continue this policy, but, although he exacted heavy tribute from Jehu of Israel and claimed many victories, he failed to establish hegemony over the Hebrews and their Aramaic-speaking allies. The basalt obelisk, called the Black Obelisk (British Mus.), describes the expeditions and conquests of Shalmaneser III. Raids from Urartu were resumed and grew more destructive after the death of Shalmaneser. Calah, the capital of Assyria during the reigns of Ashurnasirpal II and Shalmaneser III, has been excavated.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 8th cent. B.C. conquest was pursued by Tiglathpileser III. He subdued Babylonia, defeated the king of Urartu, attacked the Medes, and established control over Syria. As an ally of Ahaz of Judah (who became his vassal), he defeated his Aramaic-speaking enemies centring at Damascus. His successor, Shalmaneser V, besieged Samaria, the capital of Israel, in 722-721 B.C., but it was Sargon, his son, who completed the task of capturing Israel. Sargon's victory at Raphia (720 B.C.) and his invasions of Armenia, Arabia, and other lands made Assyria indisputably one of the greatest of ancient empires.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sargon's son Sennacherib devoted himself to retaining the gains his father had made. He is particularly remembered for his warfare against his rebellious vassal, Hezekiah of Judah. Sennacherib's successor, Esar-Haddon, defeated the Chaldaeans, who threatened Assyria and carried his conquests (673-670) to Egypt, where he deposed Taharka and established Necho in power. Under Assurbanipal, Assyria reached its zenith and approached its fall. When Assurbanipal was fighting against the Chaldaeans and Elamites, an Egyptian revolt under Psamtik I was successful.[PARAGRAPH:1]Assurbanipal's reign saw the Assyrian capital of Nineveh reach the height of its splendour. The library of cuneiform tablets he collected ultimately proved to be one of the most important historical sources of antiquity. The magnificent Assyrian bas-reliefs reached their peak. The royal court was luxurious. Assyrian culture owed much to earlier Babylonian civilization, and in religion Assyria seems to have taken much from its southern neighbour and subject.[PARAGRAPH:1]Despite the magnificence of Assurbanipal's court, Assyria began a rapid decline during his reign. The military aspect of the empire was its most prominent feature, for Assyria was prepared for conflict from beginning to end. Because of the ever-present need for men to fight the incessant battles, agriculture suffered, and ultimately the Assyrians had to import food. The division of society into a fairly rigid three-class system was not unlike that of other early western Asian peoples (e.g., Babylonia), but it did not supply a solid base for the overgrown Assyrian state.[PARAGRAPH:1]The lavish expenditures of Assurbanipal on warfare and building drained the resources of the empire and contributed to its weakness. The king of the Medes, Cyaxares, and the Babylonian ruler Nabopolassar, joined forces and took Nineveh in 612 B.C. Under the son of Nabopolassar, Nebuchadnezzar, Babylonia was renewed in power, and the great-grandson of Cyaxares, Cyrus the Great, was to establish the Persian Empire, which owed much to the earlier Assyrian state.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
		<Polish>Asyria – starożytne państwo semickie w północnej Mezopotamii, które doszło do znacznej potęgi w II tysiącleciu p.n.e. i w pierwszej połowie I tysiąclecia p.n.e., podbijając znaczne obszary Bliskiego Wschodu.[PARAGRAPH:1]Mieszkańcy Asyrii, leżącej na północ od ośrodków wcześniejszych cywilizacji, Sumeru i Akadu, byli przez setki lat kulturowo zacofani w stosunku do swoich sąsiadów z południa. W czasach Sargona Wielkiego i Urnammu tylko chwilowo ziemie asyryjskie zostały zjednoczone z dolną Mezopotamią. Spowodowało to późniejsze wytworzenie się państwowości. Jak informują zapiski asyryjskie, pierwsi królowie tego ubogiego kraju byli nomadami i mieszkali w namiotach. Trudne warunki egzystencji wymusiły poniekąd stworzenie państwa o charakterze wojskowym. Dzięki położeniu na północy Mezopotamii rozwój Asyrii opierał się na handlu, gdyż przez miasta asyryjskie przebiegały główne szlaki handlowe łączące Zatokę Perską z Morzem śródziemnym. W czasach pokoju chłopi asyryjscy uprawiali rolę. U zarania dziejów Asyrii istniały w tym kraju trzy znaczące państwa-miasta: Arbela, Aszur i Niniwa. Zachowywały one niezależność, ale panowały tylko nad najbliższą okolicą. Ok. roku 2000 p.n.e. na Mezopotamię najechali Amoryci i założyli liczne dynastie. Przedstawiciel jednej z nich, Szamsziadad I z Terki (panował w latach 1813-1781 p.n.e.), założył pierwsze państwo asyryjskie, które było przez krótki czas największą potęgą w Mezopotamii. Swój sukces gospodarczy opierał Szamsziadad I na handlu. Asyria w tym czasie miała nawet swoją kolonię handlową w Kanesz w Azji Mniejszej. Po śmierci Szamsziadada jego państwo zostało podbite przez Hammurabiego. Jako że Szamsziadad nie był Asyryjczykiem i nie rezydował w Aszur, niektórzy historycy skłaniają się do nazywania tego państwa królestwem Górnej Mezopotamii. W XVII w. p.n.e. ziemie asyryjskie zostały podbite przez przybyłe z północy plemiona Hurytów, którzy około 1490 p.n.e. założyli w Górnej Mezopotamii państwo Mitanni.[PARAGRAPH:1]W X w. p.n.e. powstało państwo nowoasyryjskie. Szybki wzrost jego potęgi zaczął się w roku 884 p.n.e. za panowania Aszurnasirapli II. Jego syn Salmanasar III został królem Babilonu i nałożył haracz na kraje Lewantu i Izrael. Po pewnym okresie zastoju do energiczniejszych podbojów przystąpił Tiglatpilesar III (od połowy VIII w. p.n.e.). Podboje jego i jego następców doprowadziły do powstania największego imperium, jakie dotychczas widziano. Asyryjczycy opanowali całą Mezopotamię, Lewant (745-720 p.n.e.), Palestynę, Cypr, a także Egipt (około roku 671 p.n.e.), który jednak utracili po 15 latach. Na zdobycznych terenach utworzone zostały prowincje zarządzane przez urzędników wyznaczanych przez króla Asyrii, i zobowiązane do składania corocznych danin. Dla komunikowania się odległych prowincji ze stolicą budowano drogi, na których uruchomiono konną pocztę kurierską. Szczyt potęgi Asyria osiągnęła za panowania króla Sargona II (721-705 p.n.e.) i jego dynastycznych następców zwanych Sargonidami. Rozbudowano wówczas znacznie sieć kanałów nawadniających i urządzano liczne ogrody i sady. Te zamiłowania i osiągnięcia w ogrodnictwie przeniesione zostały do legendy w postaci "wiszących ogrodów Semiramidy", zaliczanych do siedmiu cudów świata, a faktycznie będących ogrodami zakładanymi na płaskich dachach i tarasach pałaców w Babilonie. Imperium tym Asyryjczycy rządzili bardzo surowo, deportując i mordując buntowników. Wiele miast zostało zniszczonych. Los taki spotkał między innymi Babilon zniszczony w roku 689 p.n.e. przez króla Sanheriba. Asyryjczycy potrafili również budować (rękami niewolników i na koszt podbitych ludów) wspaniałe miasta, ogromne pałace ze wspaniałymi płaskorzeźbami i wielkie biblioteki, co miało duży wpływ na zachowanie się wiedzy o ich czasach. W kilkadziesiąt lat po osiągnięciu maksymalnych rozmiarów zaczęły się dla Asyrii poważne kłopoty wywołane najprawdopodobniej niemożnością zapanowania nad tak ogromnym obszarem i wycieńczeniem państwa ciągłymi wojnami.[PARAGRAPH:1]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ASSYRIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Assyria</English>
		<French>Assyrie</French>
		<German>Assyrien</German>
		<Italian>Assiria</Italian>
		<Spanish>Asiria</Spanish>
		<Polish>Asyria</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AUSTRALIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Australian</English>
		<French>Australien</French>
		<German>australisch</German>
		<Italian>Australiano</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>australiano:australiana:australianos:australianas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1:0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Australijczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AUSTRALIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Australian Empire</English>
		<French>Empire australien</French>
		<German>Reich der Australier</German>
		<Italian>Impero Australiano</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio Australiano</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Australijskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AUSTRALIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The first human habitation of Australia is estimated to have occurred between 42,000 and 48,000 years ago. The first Australians were the ancestors of the current Indigenous Australians; they arrived via land bridges and short sea-crossings from present-day Southeast Asia. Most of these people were hunter-gatherers, with a complex oral culture and spiritual values based on reverence for the land and a belief in the Dreamtime. The Torres Strait Islanders, ethnically Melanesian, inhabited the Torres Strait Islands and parts of far-north Queensland; they possess distinct cultural practices from the Aborigines.[PARAGRAPH:2]The British Crown Colony of New South Wales started with the establishment of a settlement at Port Jackson by Captain Arthur Phillip on 26 January 1788. This date was later to become Australia's national day, Australia Day. Van Diemen's Land, now known as Tasmania, was settled in 1803 and became a separate colony in 1825. The United Kingdom formally claimed the western part of Australia in 1829. Separate colonies were created from parts of New South Wales: South Australia in 1836, Victoria in 1851, and Queensland in 1859. The Northern Territory (NT) was founded in 1863 as part of the Province of South Australia. South Australia was founded as a "free province" - that is, it was never a penal colony. Victoria and Western Australia were also founded "free", but later accepted transported convicts. The transportation of convicts to Australia was phased out between 1840 and 1864.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Indigenous Australian population, estimated at about 350,000 at the time of European settlement, declined steeply for 150 years following settlement, mainly because of infectious disease combined with forced re-settlement and cultural disintegration. The removal of children, that some historians and Indigenous Australians have argued could be considered to constitute genocide by today's understanding, may have made a small contribution to the decline in the indigenous population. Such interpretations of Aboriginal history are disputed by some as being exaggerated or fabricated for political or ideological reasons. This debate is known within Australia as the History Wars. Following the 1967 referendum, the Federal government gained the power to implement policies and make laws with respect to Aborigines. Traditional ownership of land? native title? was not recognised until the High Court case Mabo v Queensland (No 2) overturned the notion of Australia as terra nullius at the time of European occupation.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Australian Capital Territory (ACT) was formed from New South Wales in 1911 to provide a location for the proposed new federal capital of Canberra (Melbourne was the capital from 1901 to 1927). The Northern Territory was transferred from the control of the South Australian government to the Commonwealth in 1911. Australia willingly participated in World War I; many Australians regard the defeat of the Australian and New Zealand Army Corps (ANZACs) at Gallipoli as the birth of the nation - its first major military action. Much like Gallipoli, the Kokoda Track Campaign is regarded by many as a nation-defining battle from World War II.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Statute of Westminster 1931 formally ended most of the constitutional links between Australia and the United Kingdom, but Australia did not adopt the Statute until 1942. The shock of the United Kingdom's defeat in Asia in 1942 and the threat of Japanese invasion caused Australia to turn to the United States as a new ally and protector. Since 1951, Australia has been a formal military ally of the US under the auspices of the ANZUS treaty. After World War II, Australia encouraged mass immigration from Europe; since the 1970s and the abolition of the White Australia policy, immigration from Asia and other parts of the world was also encouraged. As a result, Australia's demography, culture and image of itself were radically transformed. The final constitutional ties between Australia and the United Kingdom ended in 1986 with the passing of the Australia Act 1986, ending any British role in the Australian States, and ending judicial appeals to the UK Privy Council. Australian voters rejected a move to become a republic in 1999 by a 55% majority. Since the election of the Whitlam Government in 1972, there has been an increasing focus on the nation's future as a part of the Asia-Pacific region.</English>
		<Polish>Australia (Związek Australijski, Commonwealth of Australia) – kraj położony na półkuli południowej, obejmujący najmniejszy kontynent świata, wyspę Tasmanię i inne znacznie mniejsze wyspy na Oceanie Indyjskim i Spokojnym. Australia nie posiada granic lądowych z żadnym państwem, ale ma sąsiadów poprzez morza. Od północy są to: Indonezja, Timor Wschodni i Papua-Nowa Gwinea; na północnym wschodzie: Wyspy Salomona, Vanuatu oraz Nowa Kaledonia; na południowym wschodzie: Nowa Zelandia. Australia jest jedynym państwem, które jest również kontynentem. Stanowi szóste pod względem powierzchni państwo świata. Australia jest krajem wysoko rozwiniętym, z wielokulturowym społeczeństwem. W porównaniu z innymi państwami (Wskaźnik Rozwoju Społecznego) Australia jest notowana bardzo wysoko, jeśli chodzi o jakość życia, opiekę zdrowotną, przeciętną długość życia, poziom wykształcenia, swobodę działalności ekonomicznej, wolność osobistą i prawa polityczne i obecnie znajduje się na 2 miejscu po Norwegii. Miasta australijskie są w światowej czołówce w dziedzinie życia kulturalnego. Australia jest członkiem ONZ, Wspólnoty Narodów, G20, OECD, ANZUS, APEC, Pacific Islands Forum oraz WTO.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AUSTRALIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Australia</English>
		<French>Australie</French>
		<German>Australien</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AZTEC_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Aztec</English>
		<French>
			<Text>aztèque:aztèque:aztèques:aztèques</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>aztekisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>azteco:azteca:aztechi:azteche</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>azteca:azteca:aztecas:aztecas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Azteków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AZTEC_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Aztec Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire aztèque</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Azteken</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Azteco</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Azteca</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Azteków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AZTEC_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Aztec</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Aztèques</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Aztekenreich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>L'Impero Azteco:l'Impero Azteco:dell'Impero Azteco</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Aztlán</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Aztekowie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BABYLONIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Babylonian:Babylonians</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>babylonien:babylonienne:babyloniens:babyloniennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>babylonisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>babilonese:babilonese:babilonesi:babilonesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>babilonio:babilonia:babilonios:babilonias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Babilończyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BABYLON_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Babylonian:Babylonians</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>babylonien:babylonienne:babyloniens:babyloniennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>babylonisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>babilonese:babilonesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>babilonio:babilonia:babilonios:babilonias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Babilończyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BABYLON_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Babylonian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire babylonien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Babylonier</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero babilonese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Babilonio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Babilońskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BABYLON_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Babylon</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Babyloniens</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Babylonien</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Babilonia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Babilonia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Babilonia</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BARBARIAN_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Barbarian</English>
		<French>
			<Text>barbare:barbare:barbares:barbares</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>barbarisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>barbaro:barbari:barbara:barbare</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>bárbaro:bárbara:bárbaros:bárbaras</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Barbarzyńców</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BARBARIAN_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Barbarian State</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire barbare</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Barbaren</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Territorio Barbaro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Territorio de los bárbaros</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Terytorium barbarzyńskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BARBARIAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The term "barbarian" was created by the Greeks; it was originally used to denote any foreigner. Since then it has gained a more negative connotation, and it is commonly applied to civilizations deemed "inferior" to one's own. The Chinese, for instance, thought of all foreign cultures - everybody from the Manchus to the Turks to the Europeans - as barbarians. Rome applied it to the Huns and the Germanic tribes, as well as to the more advanced Gauls.[PARAGRAPH:2]In Civilization IV, the term denotes people that are not part of any organized civilization appearing in the game, but are instead old-style hunter-gatherers who prey on the "weak" civilized world. Though some barbarians may have acquired fairly advanced weaponry - swords and axes, for example - and though they may occasionally capture or even build their own cities, they remain at heart brigandic nomads, destroying everything that comes in their path. Barbarians cannot be bargained with or appeased: they must be destroyed - before they destroy you!</English>
		<French>Le terme "Barbare" est à l'origine un critère linguistique utilisé par les Grecs pour désigner toute personne étrangère à la civilisation grecque. Depuis, ce terme a pris une connotation péjorative et s'applique aux civilisations jugées "inférieures". Les Chinois, par exemple, considéraient toutes les cultures étrangères, des Mandchous aux Turcs en passant par les Européens, comme des barbares. Rome utilisait ce terme pour désigner les Huns, les Gaulois et les tribus germaniques.[PARAGRAPH:2]Dans Civilization IV, le terme "Barbares" désigne des gens qui ne font partie d'aucune civilisation organisée du jeu. Il s'agit de chasseurs-cueilleurs qui n'ont pas peur de s'attaquer au monde civilisé. Bien que certains barbares aient pu acquérir un armement assez avancé, avec notamment des épées et des haches, et bien qu'ils puissent à l'occasion capturer ou même fonder leurs propres villes, ils restent avant tout des "bandits-nomades", détruisant tout sur leur passage. Il est impossible de négocier avec des barbares ni même de les apaiser: il faut les éliminer avant qu'ils ne vous éliminent!</French>
		<German>Die Bezeichnung "barbarisch" stammt aus dem alten Griechischen und bedeutete "roh, unkultiviert, fremdsprachlich und ungebildet". Der Ausdruck wurde ursprünglich für Ausländer verwendet und hat seitdem an negativer Bedeutung gewonnen. Er wird auf Zivilisationen angewendet, die der eigenen Kultur als "unterlegen" betrachtet werden. Die Chinesen erachteten beispielsweise alle ausländischen Kulturen als barbarisch - von den tungisischen Bewohnern der Mandschurei über die Turkvölker bis hin zu den Europäern. Das Römische Reich wandte den Ausdruck sowohl auf die Hunnen und die germanischen Stämme als auch auf die fortschrittlicheren Gallier an.[PARAGRAPH:2]In Civilization IV erscheinen diejenigen als Barbaren, die nicht einer der organisierten Zivilisationen des Spiels angehören, sondern als Jäger und Sammler einer älteren Lebensweise folgen und die "schwache" zivilisierte Welt als Beute betrachten. Obwohl einige Barbaren recht fortschrittliche Waffen erwerben können, wie Schwerter und Äxte, und obwohl sie gelegentlich in eroberten Städten leben oder gar eigene erbauen, bleiben sie im Herzen unstete Nomaden, die alles plündern, was ihnen in den Weg kommt. In Civilization IV lassen Barbaren nicht mit sich verhandeln - sie bilden eine ständige Gefahr, die für die eigene Sicherheit neutralisiert werden muss.</German>
		<Italian>Il termine "barbaro" venne coniato dai Greci e inizialmente veniva utilizzato per indicare qualsiasi straniero. Da allora, la parola ha assunto una connotazione negativa e viene associato a quelle civiltà definite "inferiori". I Cinesi, per esempio, identificavano tutte le culture straniere come "barbare" dai Manciù ai Turchi agli Europei. Roma bollò con questo termine gli Unni e le popolazioni germaniche, così come i Galli che erano culturalmente evoluti.[PARAGRAPH:2]In Civilization IV, questo termine indica le popolazioni che non fanno parte di una civiltà organizzata, vecchi cacciatori che predano i "deboli" nel mondo. Malgrado alcuni barbari abbiano conquistato armamenti più evoluti come spade e asce, e talvolta possano conquistare o fondare delle città, i Barbari rimangono prevalentemente nomadi che distruggono e saccheggiano tutto ciò che capita a tiro. Non si può trattare con i Barbari: devono essere distrutti prima che loro distruggano te!</Italian>
		<Spanish>El término "bárbaro" fue acuñado por los griegos, y originalmente se utilizaba para referirse a cualquier extranjero. Pero desde entonces ha adquirido unas connotaciones negativas, pues suele emplearse al hablar de las civilizaciones a las que se considera "inferiores" a la propia. Los chinos, por ejemplo, pensaban que todas las culturas extranjeras (desde los manchúes a los turcos, pasando por los europeos) eran bárbaras. En Roma se empleaba el término para referirse a los hunos y las tribus germanas, así como a los galos, que eran más avanzados.[PARAGRAPH:2]En Civilization IV, este término engloba a todos los pueblos que no forman parte de ninguna civilización organizada del juego, y en lugar de eso se componen de cazadores-recolectores que atacan al "débil" mundo civilizado. Aunque algunos bárbaros pueden llegar a adquirir armas bastante avanzadas (espadas y hachas, por ejemplo), y aunque de vez en cuando pueden capturar ciudades o construir las suyas propias, en el fondo siguen siendo unos nómadas bandidos que lo destruyen todo a su paso. No se puede negociar con ellos, ni es posible aplacarlos: ¡hay que destruirlos antes de que ellos te destruyan a ti!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BARBARIAN_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Barbarians</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Barbares</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Barbarenreich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Il Territorio Barbaro:il Territorio Barbaro:del Territorio Barbaro:del Territorio Barbaro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Barbaria</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Barbarzyńcy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BYZANTINE_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Byzantine</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Byzantin</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>byzantinisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Bizantino:Bizantina:Bizantini:Bizantine</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>bizantino:bizantina:bizantinos:bizantinas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Bizantyjczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BYZANTINE_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Byzantine Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire Byzantin</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Byzantiner</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Bizantino</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Bizantino</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Bizantyjskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BYZANTINE_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Byzantines</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Byzance</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Byzanz</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Bisanzio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Bizancio</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Bizancjum</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BYZANTIUM_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Byzantine:Byzantines</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>byzantin:byzantine;byzantins:bizantines</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>byzantinisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>bizantino:bizantina:bizantini:bizantine</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>bizantino:bizantina:bizantinos:bizantinas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Bizantyjskie:0:1:1</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BYZANTIUM_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Byzantine Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire byzantin</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Byzantiner</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero bizantino</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Bizantino</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Bizantyjskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BYZANTIUM_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Byzantium</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Byzantins</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Byzanz</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Bisanzio</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Bizancio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Bizancjum</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CARTHAGE_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Carthaginian:Carthaginians</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>carthaginois:carthaginoise:carthaginois:carthaginoises</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>karthagisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>cartaginese:cartaginese:cartaginesi:cartaginesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>cartaginés:cartaginesa:cartagineses:cartaginesas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Kartagińczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CELT_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Celtic:Celts</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>celte:celtique:celtes:celtiques</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>keltisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>celtico:celtica:celtici:celtiche</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>celta:celta:celtas:celtas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Celtów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CHINA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Chinese</English>
		<French>
			<Text>chinois:chinoise:chinois:chinoises</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>chinesisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>cinese:cinese:cinesi:cinesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>chino:china:chinos:chinas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Chińczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CHINA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Chinese Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire du Milieu</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Chinesen</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Cinese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Chino</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Chińskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CHINA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>China</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Chinois</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Cina:la Cina:della Cina:di Cina</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>China</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Chiny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_DENMARK_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Danish</English>
		<French>Danois</French>
		<German>dänisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Danish</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>danés:danesa:daneses:danesas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Duński</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_DENMARK_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Denmark</English>
		<French>Danemark</French>
		<German>Reich der Dänen</German>
		<Spanish>Imperio Danés</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dania</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_DENMARK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Kingdom of Denmark commonly known as Denmark, is a country situated in the Scandinavian region of northern Europe. It is the southernmost of the Nordic countries. The mainland is bordered to the south by Germany; Denmark is located to the southwest of Sweden and the south of Norway. Denmark borders both the Baltic and the North Sea. The country consists of a large peninsula, Jutland (Jylland) and a large number of islands, most notably Zealand (Sjælland), Funen (Fyn), Vendsyssel-Thy, Lolland, Falster and Bornholm as well as hundreds of minor islands often referred to as the Danish Archipelago. Denmark has long controlled the approach to the Baltic Sea, and these waters are also known as the Danish straits. The Faroe Islands and Greenland are autonomous provinces of Denmark with home rule.[PARAGRAPH:2]The earliest mention of a territory called "Denmark" is found in King Alfred the Great's modified translation into Old English of Paulus Orosius' Seven Books of History Against The Pagans ["Historiarum adversum Paganos Libri Septem"], written by Alfred when king of Wessex in the years 871-899. In a passage introduced to the text by Alfred, we read about Ohthere from Hålogalands travels in the Nordic region, during which 'Denmark [Denamearc] was on his [port side]... And then for two days he had on his [port side] the islands which belong to Denmark'.The earliest mention of the word "Denmark" within Denmark itself is found on the two rune stones at Jelling, believed to have been erected by Gorm the Old (c. 955) and Harald Bluetooth (c. 965). The larger stone of the two is often cited as Denmark's birth certificate, though both use the word "Denmark", in the form of (acc.) tanmaurk ['danmrk] (large Jelling stone) and (gen.) tanmarkaR ['danmarka?] (small Jelling stone). The inhabitants of Denmark are there called tani ['dan?] ("Danes" in the acc.).[PARAGRAPH:2]The earliest archaeological findings in Denmark date back to 130,000 - 110,000 BC in the Eem interglacial period. People have inhabited Denmark since about 12,500 BC and agriculture has been in evidence since 3,900 BC. The Nordic Bronze Age (1,800 - 600 BC) in Denmark was marked by burial mounds, which left an abundance of findings including lurs and the Sun Chariot. During the Pre-Roman Iron Age (500 BC? AD 1), native groups began migrating south, although the first Danish people came to the country between the Pre-Roman and the Germanic Iron Age, in the Roman Iron Age (AD 1400). The Roman provinces maintained trade routes and relations with native tribes in Denmark and Roman coins have been found in Denmark. Evidence of strong Celtic cultural influence dates from this period in Denmark and much of northwest Europe and is among other things reflected in the finding of the Gundestrup cauldron. Historians believe that before the arrival of the precursors to the Danes, who came from the east Danish islands (Zealand) and Skåne and spoke an early form of north Germanic, most of Jutland and some islands were settled by Jutes. They were later invited to the British Isles as mercenaries by Brythonic king Vortigern, and were granted the south-eastern territories of Kent, the Isle of Wight, among other areas, where they settled. They were later absorbed or ethnically cleansed by the invading Angles and Saxons, who formed the Anglo-Saxons. The remaining population in Jutland assimilated in with the Danes, due territorial expansions from the south and the east, and the Jutes being initially weakened after their emigrations. The exact origins of the Danish nation have been lost in history. However, a short note about the Dani in "The Origin and Deeds of the Goths" from 551 by historian Jordanes is believed by some to be an early mention of the Danes, one of the ethnic groups from whom the modern Danish people are descended. The Danevirke defense structures were built in phases from the 3rd century forward, and the sheer size of the construction efforts in 737 are attributed to the emergence of a Danish king. The new runic alphabet was first used at the same time and Ribe, the oldest town of Denmark, was founded about 700 AD.[PARAGRAPH:2]King Christian IV attacked Sweden in the 1611-13 Kalmar War but failed to accomplish his main objective of forcing Sweden to return to the union with Denmark. The war led to no territorial changes, but Sweden was forced to pay a war indemnity of 1 million silver riksdaler to Denmark, an amount known as the Älvsborg ransom. King Christian used this money to found several towns and fortresses, most notably Glückstadt (founded as a rival to Hamburg), Christiania (following a fire destroying the original city), Christianshavn, Christianstad, and Christiansand. Christian also constructed a number of buildings, most notably Børsen, Rundetårn, Nyboder, Rosenborg, a silver mine and a copper mill.</English>
		<Polish>Pierwotnie obszar dzisiejszej Danii został zasiedlony przez plemiona germańskie: Cymbrów i Teutonów, a następnie Anglów, Jutów i Sasów. Te 3 plemiona w V i VI wieku po podbiciu części Wysp Brytyjskich (dzisiejsza Anglia) przemieściły się tam, a na ich miejsce napłynął północnogermański lud Duńczyków. W okresie VIII-IX wieku Duńczycy brali udział w morskich wyprawach na wybrzeża Wielkiej Brytanii, państwa Franków i wybrzeża Bałtyku. Postępowało jednoczenie kraju, a w IX wieku kraj został schrystianizowany. Duński król Kanut II Wielki władał państwem, które obejmowało obok Danii, także Anglię, Norwegię, południową Szwecję oraz część Finlandii. W XII wieku Dania rozpoczęła ekspansję w rejonie Morza Bałtyckiego, zajmując m.in. Estonię, Holsztyn i Inflanty. W roku 1397 Dania utworzyła z Norwegią i Szwecją Unię Kalmarską, która przetrwała do 1523 roku, a następnie do roku 1814 istniała unia Danii z Norwegią. W 1448 r. tron objął Chrystian I z dynastii Oldenburgów. W latach 1534-1536 w Danii trwała wojna domowa, w wyniku której religią państwową stał się luteranizm. W drugiej połowie XVI wieku kraj zaangażowany był w wyniszczające wojny o panowanie na Bałtyku ze Szwecją i w ich wyniku utracił mocarstwową pozycję. W wojnie trzydziestoletniej (1618-1648) król Danii Chrystian IV wziął udział po stronieprotestantów. Dania była państwem, które zaprotestowało przeciwko likwidacji Polski po II rozbiorze. W okresie napoleońskim Duńczycy opowiedzieli się po stronie francuskiej. Po klęsce Napoleona, Dania została ostatecznie wyparta z Półwyspu Skandynawskiego i w roku 1814 musiała oddać Norwegię Szwecji. Jednak zachowała norweskie posiadłości: Islandię, Wyspy Owcze i Grenlandię. Od roku 1849 Dania stała się monarchią konstytucyjną. Powojnie duńskiej w 1864 roku z Austrią i Prusami, Dania utraciła Szlezwik i Holsztyn, od tego momentu przestrzegała neutralności politycznej. Podczas I wojny światowej Dania pozostała neutralna, a w roku 1920 w wyniku plebiscytu północny Szlezwik powrócił do Danii. Mimo neutralności Dania została prawie bez oporu zajęta w 1940 r. przez hitlerowskie Niemcy. Przez kilka lat mimo niemieckiej okupacji Dania zachowywała formalną suwerenność - funkcjonował parlament i rząd, ale od roku 1943 rządy bezpośrednie sprawowali już hitlerowcy. W trakcie II wojny światowej w roku 1944 Islandia zerwała unię personalną z Danią, gdyż ogłosiła się republiką. Dania została wyzwolona 5 maja 1945 roku przez wojska brytyjskie. Od razu zaczęto odbudowywać kraj i Duńskie Siły Zbrojne.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_DENMARK_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Denmark</English>
		<French>Danois</French>
		<German>Dänemark</German>
		<Spanish>Dinamarca</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dania</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_EGYPT_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Egyptian</English>
		<French>
			<Text>égyptien:égyptienne:égyptiens:égyptiennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>ägyptisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>egiziano:egiziana:egiziani:egiziane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>egipcio:egipcia:egipcios:egipcias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Egipcjan</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_EGYPT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Egyptian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire égyptien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Ägypter</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Egizio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Egipcio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Egipskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_EGYPT_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Egypt</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Egyptiens</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Ägypten</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>L'Egitto:l'Egitto:dell'Egitto:d'Egitto</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Egipto</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Egipt</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ENGLAND_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>English</English>
		<French>
			<Text>anglais:anglaise:anglais:anglaises</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>englisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>inglese:inglese:inglesi:inglesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>inglés:inglesa:ingleses:inglesas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Brytyjczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ENGLAND_DESC</Tag>
		<English>English Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire britannique</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Engländer</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Inglese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Inglés</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Brytyjskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ENGLAND_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>England</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Britanniques</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>L'Inghilterra:l'Inghilterra:dell'Inghilterra:d'Inghilterra</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Inglaterra</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wielka Brytania</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ETHIOPIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Ethiopian:Ethiopians</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>éthiopien:éthiopienne:éthiopiens:éthiopiennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>äthiopisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>etiope:etiope:etiopi:etiopi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>etíope:etíope:etíopes:etíopes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Etiopczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ETHIOPIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Ethiopian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire éthiopien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Äthiopier</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero etiope</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Etíope</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Etiopskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ETHIOPIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Ethiopia</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Ethiopiens</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Äthiopien</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Etiopia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Etiopía</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Etiopia</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_FRANCE_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>French</English>
		<French>
			<Text>français:française:français:françaises</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>französisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>francese:francese:francesi:francesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>francés:francesa:franceses:francesas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Francuzów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_FRANCE_DESC</Tag>
		<English>French Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire français</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Franzosen</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Francese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Francés</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Francuskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_FRANCE_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>France</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Français</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Frankreich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Francia:la Francia:della Francia:di Francia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Francia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Francja</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_GERMANY_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>German</English>
		<French>
			<Text>allemand:allemande:allemands:allemandes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>deutsch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>tedesco:tedesca:tedeschi:tedesche</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>alemán:alemana:alemanes:alemanas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Niemców</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_GERMANY_DESC</Tag>
		<English>German Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire germanique</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Deutschen</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Tedesco</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Alemán</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Niemieckie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_GERMANY_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Germany</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Allemands</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Deutschland</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Germania:la Germania:della Germania:di Germania</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Alemania</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Niemcy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_GREECE_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Greek</English>
		<French>
			<Text>grec:grecque:grecs:grecques</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>griechisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>greco:greca:greci:greche</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>griego:griega:griegos:griegas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Greków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_GREECE_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Greek Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire grec</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Griechen</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Greco</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Griego</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Greckie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_GREECE_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Greece</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Grecs</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Griechenland</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Grecia:la Grecia:della Grecia:di Grecia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Grecia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Grecja</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HITTITES_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Hittite</English>
		<French>
			<Text>hittite:hittite:hittites:hittites</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>hethitisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>ittita:ittita:ittiti:ittiti</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>hitita:hitita:hititas:hititas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Hetykow</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HITTITES_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Hittite Empire</English>
		<French>Empire hittite</French>
		<German>Reich der Hethiter</German>
		<Italian>Impero Ittita</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio Hitita</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Hetyckie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HITTITES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Hittites (Hebrew Hittim), were ancient people of Asia Minor and the Middle East, inhabiting the land of Hatti on the central plateau of what is now Anatolia, Turkey, and some areas of northern Syria. The Hittites, whose origin is unknown, spoke an Indo-European language. They invaded the region, which became known as Hatti, about 1900 bc and imposed their language, culture, and rule on the earlier inhabitants, a people speaking a non-Indo-European agglutinative language. The first town settled by the Hittites was Nesa, near present-day Kayseri, Turkey. Shortly after 1800 BC they conquered the town of Hattusas, near the site of present-day Bogazkale. Nothing more is known of Hittite history until, in the 17th century bc, the so-called Old Hittite Kingdom was founded by the Hittite leader Labarna (reigned about 1680-1650 bc), or Tabarna, and Hattusas became its capital. Labarna conquered nearly all of central Anatolia and extended his rule to the sea. His successors extended Hittite conquests into northern Syria. Mursili I (reigned about 1620-1590 bc), the second ruler after Labarna, conquered what is now alab (Aleppo), Syria, and raided Babylon about 1595 BC. Mursilis assassination was followed by a period of internal strife and external weakness that ended during the reign of King Telipinu (reigned about 1525-1500 bc). To ensure the stability of the kingdom, he issued strict rules governing the royal succession. The law code may also have been compiled during his reign. Of Telipinus successors only the names are known.[PARAGRAPH:2]About 1450 BC the so-called New Hittite Kingdom was founded. One of its most important members, the royal prince Suppiluliuma (reigned about 1380-1346 bc), usurped the throne during a period of foreign invasions. After liberating his country and defeating his main enemy, the kingdom of Mitanni in northern Mesopotamia, he led his armies farther into Syria. There his conquests were made easier by a weakening of Egyptian power during the reign of the pharaoh Amenhotep IV, or Akhenaton. Thus the Hittite Kingdom under Suppiluliuma became a great empire rivaling the power of Egypt, Babylonia, and Assyria. After the death of Suppiluliuma, the Hittites were largely able to maintain their empire, although only by constant warfare. During the 15th and 14th centuries bc their holdings extended westward to the Aegean Sea, eastward into Armenia, southeastward into upper Mesopotamia, and southward into Syria as far as present-day Lebanon.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the last half of the 14th century bc, the Hittites continued to come into frequent conflict with Egypt. The two great powers struggled for control of Syria until a battle was fought in Kadesh, Syria, between he Hittite king Muwatalli (reigned about 1315-1296 bc) and the Egyptian pharaoh Ramses II. Although Ramses claimed a great victory, the Hittites continued to maintain their hold on Syria. The Hittite king Hattusili III (reigned about 1289-1265 bc) concluded a treaty of peace and alliance with Ramses years later and subsequently gave him his daughter in marriage. Thereafter, relations between the Hittites and Egyptians remained friendly until the Hittite Empire fell shortly after 1200 bc to invaders called the Sea Peoples in Egyptian records.[PARAGRAPH:2]The downfall of the empire was followed by confusion and conflict. Subsequently a number of Hittite city-states, the most famous of which was Carchemish, emerged in southeastern Anatolia and northern Syria. These states were peopled by an intermingled ethnic group, called Syro-Hittites, consisting primarily of the Hittites, of peoples from the former Hittite Empire, and the previous inhabitants of the two areas. The Syro-Hittite rulers used the Luwian language, in which hieroglyphics were employed for writing. Some of these city-states were conquered in the 10th century bc by the Aramaeans. Even after it was conquered, all of Syria was still called Hatti by the Assyrians. Both the city-states that were conquered by the Aramaeans and those that remained independent finally were made provinces of the Assyrian Empire under Sargon II about 715 bc.[PARAGRAPH:2]The primary sources of information about the Hittites came from Egyptian records, notably those of the 19th Dynasty, and from certain passages in the Bible. The earliest of these passages, calling the Hittites "Sons of Heth," possibly refers to the period of the Hittite Kingdom. Later passages allude to the Syro-Hittites.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1906 the royal archives of the Hittites themselves were discovered in excavations at Bogazkale. These discoveries cast doubt on many items of information gathered from Egyptian sources. For example, certain military engagements were mentioned as victories for the Hittites, whereas the Egyptian records identify the engagements as Hittite defeats. The importance of the discovery is that the archives made it possible to decipher the Hittite language, thus revealing information about previously unknown aspects of the culture, such as political organization, legislation, religion, and literature.[PARAGRAPH:2]Most of the texts found in the archives were written in the Hittite language, but treaties and state letters were written in Akkadian, the international language of the period. Other texts were written in the Hurrian language of southeastern Anatolia and northern Mesopotamia, a language unrelated to any known linguistic group. The Hittites used the cuneiform system of writing taken from the Babylonians, but they also employed a system of hieroglyphs to inscribe a language closely related to Hittite, possibly a Luwian dialect. Although the hieroglyphs were used during the period of the empire, most inscriptions belong to the period after its downfall. The literature of the Hittites was highly developed, particularly in the form of historical records and stories.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Hittite king acted as the supreme priest, military commander, and chief judge of the land. During the old kingdom he was assisted by the pankus, an advisory council of nobles, which later disappeared. The empire was administered by provincial governors acting as deputies of the king. Territories beyond the empire were frequently ruled as vassal kingdoms, and formal treaties were made with their rulers.[PARAGRAPH:2]The most outstanding achievements of the Hittite civilization lay in the fields of legislation and the administration of justice. The law codes of the Hittites reveal a strong Babylonian influence, but their administration of justice was far more lenient than that of the Babylonians. The Hittites rarely resorted to the death penalty or to bodily mutilation, both of which were characteristic of other civilizations of the ancient Middle East. Furthermore, Hittite justice rested in the main on the principle of restitution rather than on retribution or vengeance. The penalty for thievery, for example, was restoration of the stolen object and payment of some additional recompense; restitution in kind was gradually replaced by payment of money.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Hittite economy was basically agricultural. The principal crops were wheat and barley, and the chief animals were cattle and sheep. The Hittites also had mineral riches in the form of copper, lead, silver, and iron. Their metallurgical techniques were advanced for the time; they may have been the first people to work iron.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Hittites worshipped a variety of gods. A recurrent phrase in state documents is an invocation to the "thousand gods of Hatti", deities worshipped apparently throughout Asia Minor before and during the period of Hittite domination. Scholars have traced Sumerian, Babylonian, Assyrian, Hurrian, Luwian, and other foreign influences in the Hittite pantheon.[PARAGRAPH:2]In the rock sanctuary of Yazilikaya, near Bogazkale, is a remarkable series of reliefs cut into rock. The reliefs depict two long processions of gods and goddesses advancing toward each other. The majority of the gods remain unidentified, but the two deities heading the procession are the storm god, or weather god, and the sun goddess, the chief deities worshipped by the Hittites. Excavations at the sanctuary revealed a temple built in front of one chamber; the other, smaller chamber seems to have been devoted to the cult of a deceased king.[PARAGRAPH:2]Hittite mythology, like Hittite religion, represents a combination of elements that reflect the diversity of cults within the empire. Of special interest are certain epic poems containing myths, originally Hurrian with Babylonian motifs. These myths deal with several successive generations of gods who ruled the universe and with a monster who challenged the rule of the last king of the gods. They are similar to Greek myths contained in the Theogony by the Greek poet Hesiod and may have been their prototypes. How the myths might have reached Greece is not clear, but it is possible they were transmitted during the Mycenaean ascendancy in Greece (1400-1200 bc). Mycenaean Greeks are known to have been in western Anatolia then and to have traded with Hittite-held Syria. Hittite records refer to contacts between Hittite rulers and those of the kingdom of Ahhiyawa, which some scholars identify with the country of the Achaeans. Whether or not Hittite cultural elements were transmitted abroad, many of them survived in Anatolia until the first Roman penetration into Asia Minor in 190 bc. Such deities as the Great Mother and the storm god (called Jupiter Dolichenus by the Romans) were still worshipped at that time.[PARAGRAPH:2]The art and architecture of the Hittites reveal the influence of nearly all the contemporary cultures of the ancient Near East, and especially of Babylonia. Nevertheless, the Hittites achieved a certain independence of style that renders their art distinct. Their building materials were generally stone and brick, but they also used wooden columns. Their often massive palaces, temples, and fortifications frequently were adorned by stylized and intricate carved reliefs on walls, gates, and entrances.[PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
		<Polish>Hetyci lud posługujący się indoeuropejskim językiem hetyckim, który około XVII w. p.n.e. stworzył potężne państwo z centrum w Hattusa (dzisiejsze Bogazkoy) w Anatolii. Potęga państwa opierała się na znakomicie, jak na owe czasy, uzbrojonej armii (broń z żelaza, zbroje, doskonałe rydwany bojowe). W okresie swojej największej świetności Hetyci kontrolowali Anatolię, północną Mezopotamię, Syrię i Palestynę. Państwo Hetytów upadło około 1200 p.n.e. pod naporem Ludów Morza, chociaż nieliczne hetyckie miasta-państwa w północnej Syrii przetrwały do roku 708 p.n.e.[PARAGRAPH:2]Hetyci pojawili się na ziemiach Anatolii ok. 2000 roku p.n.e., docierając tam z obszarów położonych na północ od Kaukazu przez zachodnie przełęcze gór. Możliwe też, że przybyli ze swoich rdzennych obszarów przez Bałkany i cieśniny Bosfor albo Dardanele. Koczownicze plemiona hetyckie, które dotarły do historycznej krainy Hatti, wchłonęły lub wyparły z tych terenów osiadły lud Hatti (zwany też Protohetytami – był to autochtoniczny lud kaukaski, który zamieszkiwał Anatolię między III a II tysiącleciem p.n.e. i posługiwał się językiem hattili). Hetyci, którzy prawdopodobnie siebie samych nazywali Nesytami (posługiwali się językiem, który określali jako nasili/nesumnili), przeszli swoisty proces akulturacji, przyswajając sobie wierzenia hatyckie wraz z językiem hattili, jako językiem sacrum, wykorzystywanym wyłącznie w celach religijnych. Wpływ autochtonów, jak również innych kultur ościennych, na kulturę Hetytów był tak wyraźny, że przejęli oni nazwę własną od podbitego królestwa – Hatti, pod którą występują we współczesnych sobie źródłach pisanych.[PARAGRAPH:2]W początkowym okresie osadnictwa w Anatolii Hetyci podzieleni byli na małe, autonomiczne miasta-państwa. Pierwszym, znanym z tabliczek hetyckich, księciem, który próbował narzucić swoją władzę sąsiednim państewkom, był Anitta, syn Pithanasa, władca Kussary. Anitta, dysponując 1200 wojownikami i 40 rydwanami, uzależnił od siebie miasto Nesa, które uczynił swoją ufortyfikowaną siedzibą. Jego wojownikom uległy też Zulpawa, Puruszanda oraz Hattusa, którą doszczętnie zburzył. O chronologii powyższych wydarzeń można jedynie spekulować, chociaż należy umieścić działalność Pithanasa i Anittasa na przełomie XVIII i XVII w. p.n.e.[PARAGRAPH:2]Około połowy XVII wieku p.n.e. Labarna, nowy władca z Kussary, otoczył kamiennym murem teren, na którego skrawku istniała dawniejsza Hattusa. Labarna, zmieniając imię na hatyckie Hattusilis, ogłosił odbudowaną Hattusę stolicą swojego państwa. Hattusilis I (1650-1620 p.n.e.), za którego rządów zostało skonsolidowane państwo hetyckie, uważany jest za jego pierwszego króla.[PARAGRAPH:2]Państwo Hattusilisa od południa sąsiadowało z Kizzuwatna i królestwem Arzawa, od północnego zachodu z Troją, od północy z azjanickimi plemionami Kaska, od wschodu z Hurytami, a od południowego wschodu z Amorytami. Hattusilis I skierował ekspansję terytorialną państwa hetyckiego przede wszystkim na tereny północnej Syrii i północnej Mezopotamii (w czasie jednej z wypraw przekroczył nawet Eufrat). Na terytorium Syrii poprowadził kilka wypraw wojennych, zdobywając i łupiąc liczne miasta: Zaruna, Hassu, Hahhu i Zippasna. Jego najwytrwalszym syryjskim przeciwnikiem było leżące w krainie Jamchad bogate miasto Halab (Aleppo), które występowało jako sojusznik innych miast atakowanych przez Hetytów. Hattusilis wyznaczył na króla swego adoptowanego syna – Mursilisa.[PARAGRAPH:2]Mursilis I (1620-1590 p.n.e.) kontynuował politykę poprzednika z jeszcze większymi efektami. Pokonał Halab i ruszył na Mezopotamię, zdobywając i łupiąc około 1595 p.n.e. Babilon, którym władał król Samsu-ditana. Mussilis I stracił życie w wyniku spisku pałacowego, na którego czele stał jego zięć Zidanta oraz Hantilis, który został Wielkim Królem jako Hantilis I (1590-1560 p.n.e.)[PARAGRAPH:2]W czasie jego panowania Huryci odebrali Hetytom północną Syrię. Osłabiony Hantilis wyznaczył niedawnego wspólnika Zidantasa I (1560-1550 p.n.e.) na króla. Ten wcześniej wymordował ewentualnych pretendentów. Po gwałtownej śmierci Zidantasa I z rąk własnego syna Ammunasa (1550-1530 p.n.e.), nastąpił okres znacznego osłabienia królestwa, które utraciło część terytoriów. Po kolejnej gwałtownej śmierci Wielkiego Króla Huzzijasa (1530-1525 p.n.e.) na tron wstąpił Telipinus (1525-1500 p.n.e.) Nowy król ustabilizował stosunki wewnątrz dynastii i w państwie, ustanawiając zasady dziedziczenia tronu (królem miał zostawać najstarszy syn, a w razie braku męskiego potomka, małżonek najstarszej córki). Kolejni królowie Alluwamnas, Hantilis II, Zidantas II i Huzzijas II nie zdołali odbudować potęgi państwa z okresu Mursalisa, tocząc głównie walki z królestwem Kizzuwatny.[PARAGRAPH:2]Od schyłku XV w. p.n.e. państwo hetyckie przeżywało kryzys. Ówcześni władcy hetyccy (Tuthalijas, Arnuwandas i Hattusilis II) koncentrowali się na obronie rdzennych terytoriów hetyckich przed najazdami północnych Kasków. Sytuacja zmieniła się w 1380 roku p.n.e., gdy na tronie zasiadł Suppiluliumas I (1380-1346 p.n.e.), który uczynił z hetyckiego państwa imperium. Suppiluliumas I wyparł z terenów północnej Syrii huryckie garnizony króla Mitanni, Tuszratty, m.in. zdobywając Halab, Mukisz oraz Waszukanni – jedną ze stolic Mitanni. Suppiluliumas I oparł południową granicę swego królestwa o góry Libanu, wkraczając tym samym w egipską strefę wpływów w Azji, a oddziały hetyckie wtargnęły do kraju Amka położonego w dolinie Bekaa. Wykorzystując waśnie dynastyczne w królestwie Mitanni, Suppiluliumas, umieścił na tronie w Waszukanni powolnego sobie króla – Szattiwaza. W 1346 p.n.e. Suppiluliumas I umarł podczas zarazy, która nawiedziła jego państwo.[PARAGRAPH:2] Na tron wstąpił Arnuwandas I (1346-1345 p.n.e.), a następnie Mursilis II (1345-1316 p.n.e.) Prowadził on zwycięskie kampanie wojenne przeciw królestwu Arzawa, Kaskom i zbuntowanemu syryjskiemu miastu Karkemisz. Jego syn, Muwatallis (1315-1296 p.n.e.), odziedziczył potężne i dobrze zorganizowane państwo. Odzyskujący siły Egipt i imperium hetyckie były skazane na zbrojną konfrontację w Syrii. Doszło do niej za panowania faraona Ramzesa II, który starał się odbić z hetyckich rąk warowne miasto Kadesz. Bitwa pod Kadesz rozegrała się około roku 1285 p.n.e. Chociaż obie strony przypisywały sobie zwycięstwo, prawdopodobnie bitwa nie była rozstrzygnięta.[PARAGRAPH:2]Zmagania Hetytów z Egiptem Ramzesa II zakończył pokój zawarty przez tego władcę z hetyckim królem Hattusilisem III w roku 1270 p.n.e., który potwierdził terytorialne status quo. Kolejny król Tuthalijas IV wyprawił się na Cypr, który zdobył. Walczył też z powodzeniem przeciwko państwu Assuwa i z ludem Kaska. Za jego następcy Arnuwandasa III po raz pierwszy dają o sobie znać Ludy Morza, które atakowały hetyckie ziemie z zachodu. Gdy na tron wstąpił ostatni król hetycki Suppiluliumas II, Hatti znalazło się w trudnej sytuacji politycznej. Najazdy Ludów Morza spowodowały klęskę głodu. Zniszczeniu uległa Hattusa i wiele innych miast. Państwo hetyckie już nigdy nie podniosło się z upadku.[PARAGRAPH:2]Nagły upadek państwa hetyckiego (ok. 1190 p.n.e.) spowodowały najazdy tzw. Ludów Morza, ale pewną rolę odegrały też ataki ludu Kasków, zamieszkującego u północno-wschodnich granic państwa hetyckiego, oraz napór Asyryjczyków z południowego wschodu. Zburzenie Hattusa spowodowało, że centra kultury hetyckiej przeniosły się do południowo-wschodniej Anatolii i północnej Syrii, gdzie powstały liczne, acz niewielkie państewka późnohetyckie z przewagą ludności hetyckiej (Karkemisz, Kummuhi, Gurgum, Unqi, Tabal) albo o mieszanej ludności hetycko-aramejskiej (Hamath, Que, Sam'al). Zachowały one polityczną niezależność aż do ostatecznego podboju dokonanego przez asyryjskiego króla Sargona II w VIII w. p.n.e. Karkemisz – stolica najważniejszego hetyckiego państwa uległa Asyrii w 717 p.n.e. Ostatnie niezależne królestwa hetyckie Gurgum, Melid i Kummuhi zostały podbite przez Sargona II w latach 711-708 p.n.e.[PARAGRAPH:2]Społeczeństwo hetyckie miało charakter patriarchalny. Na czele państwa stał namaszczony przez bogów król, który był zwierzchnikiem suwerennych księstw wchodzących w skład państwa hetyckiego. W ważnych sprawach władca mógł się zwrócić o pomoc do rady starszych – pankus, która była zapewne pozostałością po wcześniejszych wiecach plemiennych. Pozycja króla była zależna od aprobaty szlacheckich rodów i być może ta zależność przyczyniła się do anarchizacji polityki dynastycznej w okresie przed reformami Telipinusa. Król – labarna pełnił rozliczne funkcje. Był najwyższym kapłanem, naczelnym dowódcą armii, najwyższym sędzią oraz gwarantem pomyślności swojego ludu. Zaniedbania w sprawowaniu kultu poczytywano za jego największy grzech, który mógł w konsekwencji obrócić się przeciwko poddanym. Małżonka króla, tawananna, posiadała szczególną pozycję. Po śmierci męża królowa pozostawała władczynią, przy boku następcy, aż do swojej śmierci. Tawananna posiadała realną władzę z możliwością pieczętowania dokumentów, a nawet mogła inspirować międzynarodowe kontakty.[PARAGRAPH:2]Niższy poziom w społecznej hierarchii zajmowali przedstawiciele szlacheckich rodów, spośród których wybierano osoby, które sprawowały rozmaite funkcje kapłańskie, dworskie i wojskowe. Posiadacze ziemi dzielili się na dwie kategorie: posiadaczy lennych i wojowników. Lennik był odpowiednikiem wasala i mógł ziemię, otrzymaną od króla, jedynie dziedziczyć, natomiast wojownik miał prawo jej sprzedaży lub kupna. Większość społeczeństwa hetyckiego była ludźmi wolnymi, jednak występowała już jakaś forma niewolnictwa (niewolnik mógł poślubić wolną kobietę) i namra – grupa ludzi przypisanych do ziemi.[PARAGRAPH:2]Prawodawstwo Hetytów było, jak na swoje czasy, bardzo rozwinięte. W przeciwieństwie do zapisów kodeksu Hammurabiego prawo hetyckie dużo częściej korzystało z odszkodowania jako formy zadośćuczynienia za popełnione przestępstwo, niż z odwetu. Jedynymi przestępstwami, za których popełnienie karano śmiercią były cudzołóstwo kobiety zamężnej, gwałt, sodomia i bunt przeciwko władcy. Okaleczenia ciała, jako formę kary, stosowano wyłącznie wobec niewolników. Procesy były prowadzone przez rady starszych poszczególnych miast. Jeśli zachodziła taka potrzeba, to przed radą stawał reprezentant króla, najczęściej dowódca miejskiego garnizonu. Król był najwyższym autorytetem w każdej sprawie.[PARAGRAPH:2]Hetyci, po osiedleniu się w Anatolii, byli ludem rolniczym. Chłopi uprawiali pszenicę, jęczmień, len, winorośl, figi, jabłka, morele. Zwierzęta – bydło, owce, świnie – dostarczały mięsa i skór. W górach pozyskiwano różne surowce. Poza granice państwa eksportowano miedź oraz brąz, który był podstawowym materiałem do produkcji broni i narzędzi. W czasach imperium hetyckiego rzemieślnicy hetyccy prawie zmonopolizowali wytwarzanie wyrobów (głównie ozdób i posągów) z żelaza, które było pięć razy droższe od złota i czterdzieści razy droższe od srebra.[PARAGRAPH:2]Sztuka hetycka nosi ślady połączenia elementów hetyckich, syryjskich i asyryjskich, a także mniej wyraźnych wpływów egipskich i fenickich. Hetyci byli mistrzami płaskiego reliefu, chociaż pozostawili po sobie również rzeźby pełne o różnej skali, wykonane w różnorodnym materiale. Mimo upadku na początku XII w. p.n.e. kultura hetycka, zwłaszcza religia, wywarła poważny wpływ na wierzenia religijne Greków. Głównymi cechami religii hetyckiej były politeizm, antropomorfizm i synkretyzm. Hetyci adoptowali na potrzeby swojego systemu wierzeń elementy religii ludów anatolijskich, religii akadyjskiej oraz religii huryckiej. Większość mitów i rytuałów hetyckich bierze swój początek w tradycji religijnej hatyckiej lub huryckiej. Panteon bogów hetyckich był niezmiernie duży i zagmatwany. Nawet w tekstach hetyckich występują wzmianki o tysiącu bogów Hatti, a współczesnym religioznawcom udało się zidentyfikować wiele imion bogów, demonów i herosów. Powszechnym zjawiskiem było wchłanianie przez religię hetycką kultów związanych z lokalnymi bóstwami podbijanych krain i miast. Liczne bóstwa o podobnych cechach łączono ze sobą, pozostawiając dawne nazwy, np. hatycka bogini-słońce z Arinny (Wurusemu, Ariniti) była również wcieleniem bogini Hebat z huryckiego miasta Halab.[PARAGRAPH:2]Najważniejszym męskim bóstwem w panteonie hetyckim był bóg burzy, który w okresie hatyckim nosi imię Taru, w starohetyckim utożsamiany jest z Tarhunem, a w czasach wpływów huryckich z Teszubem. Bóg burzy władał chmurami, deszczem i błyskawicami. Jego partnerką i zarazem najważniejszą boginią była Tahattanuiti (małżonka Taru), bogini-słońce z Arinny (Tarhun) i Hebat (małżonka Teszuba). Obok boskiej pary szczególnie czczeni byli:Arma - bóstwo lunarne, Istanu – bóg tarczy słonecznej, Wurunkatte – bóg wojny, Kumarbi – ojciec bogów, Tasimmeti i Szauszkę – boginie miłości,Nabarbi – bóg księżyca, Perwę – bóg koni, Hannahanna – matka bogów, Telepinu – bóg urodzaju.[PARAGRAPH:2]Na potrzeby kultu powstało wiele tematów mityczno-rytualnych, z których zachowały się m.in. cykl o bogu Telepinu, o pojedynku boga burzy z wężem Illujanka i o walce Kumarbiego z Teszubem o władzę nad światem. Kosmogonia hetycka opowiada o stworzeniu nieba i ziemi na ramionach giganta Upelluri. Następnie starzy bogowie miedzianym nożem rozdzielili niebo od ziemi. Bogowie zamieszkali w Kuntarra – niebiańskim domu. Świat podziemny przedstawiano jako ponurą krainę, w której znajdowały się morza i dziewięć rzek.[PARAGRAPH:2]W życiu religijnym najważniejszą rolę odgrywał saru, labarna – król, który pełnił zarazem funkcję najwyższego kapłana. Monarcha często był przedstawiany w stroju kapłana – w długim płaszczu z rękawami, w tiarze i z litusem. Królewska władza była darem bogów, a król strzegł boskich porządków w państwie i przestrzegał ceremonialnego roku. Po swojej śmierci, władca, którego pomyślność utożsamiano z dobrobytem narodu, stawał się istotą boską, której następcy oddawali cześć.[PARAGRAPH:2]W początkowym okresie swojego osadnictwa w Azji Mniejszej Hetyci obywali się bez budynków świątynnych. Kamienne stelle – huwasi, które symbolizowały bóstwo, stawiano w jaskiniach albo pod gołym niebem. Dopiero pod wpływem Hurytów zaczęto wznosić świątynie, które stawały się schronieniem bogów. Z czasem wokół świątyni powstawały kompleksy budowli z pomieszczeniami administracyjnymi, skarbcem, spichlerzami, budynkami gospodarczymi, jak np. w centrach kultowych w Arinna i Nerikka. Znaczącą rolę w hetyckiej religijności musiało pełnić sanktuarium skalne w Yazilikaya.[PARAGRAPH:2]Hetyci stosowali birytualny obrządek pogrzebowy. Badania nekropoli hetyckich poświadczają, że stosowali jednocześnie kremację i inhumację. Ciało zmarłego króla wraz z darami zawsze palono na stosie, który gaszono, podobnie jak w Grecji, winem i piwem.[PARAGRAPH:2]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HITTITES_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Hatti</English>
		<French>Hatti</French>
		<German>Hethitien</German>
		<Polish>Hetyci</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HOLYROMAN_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Holy Roman Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Saint Empire Romain</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Heiligen Römischen Nation</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Sacro Romano Impero</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Sacro Imperio Romano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Święte Imperium Rzymskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HOLY_ROMAN_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Holy Roman:Holy Romans</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>romain:romaine:romains:romaines</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>römisch-deutsch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>dei Carolingi:dei Carolingi</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>carolingio:carolingia:carolingios:carolingias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Świętego Cesarstwa Rzymskiego</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HOLY_ROMAN_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Holy Roman Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Saint Empire romain germanique</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Heiligen Römischen Nation</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Sacro Romano Impero</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Sacro Imperio Romano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Św. Ces. Rzymskiego</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HOLY_ROMAN_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Holy Rome</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Romains saints</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Heiliges Römisches Reich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero carolingio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Europa Carolingia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Święte Cesarstwo Rzymskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INCA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Incan</English>
		<French>
			<Text>inca:inca:incas:incas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>inkaisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Incaico:Incaica:Incaici:Incaiche</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>inca:inca:incas:incas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Inków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INCA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Incan Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire inca</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Inka</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Inca</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Inca</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Inków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INCA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Inca</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Incas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Inkareich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>L'Impero Inca:l'Impero Inca:dell'Impero Inca:dell'Impero Inca</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Tawantinsuyu</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Inkowie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INDEPENDENT_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Independent</English>
		<French>
			<Text>indépendant:indépendante:indépendants:indépendantes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>unabhängig</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>indipendente:indipendente:indipendenti:indipendenti</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>autónomo:autónoma:autónomos:autónomas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Niezależny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INDIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Indian</English>
		<French>
			<Text>indien:indienne:indiens:indiennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>indisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>indiano:indiani:indiana:indiane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>hindú:hindú:hindúes:hindúes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Hindusów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INDIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Indian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire indien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Inder</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Indiano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Indio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Indyjskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INDIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>India</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Indiens</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Indien</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>L'India:l'India:dell'India:d'India</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>India</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Indie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INSECTOID_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Insectoids</English>
		<French>Insectoïdes</French>
		<German>insektoid</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INSECTOID_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Insectoids</English>
		<French>Insectoïdes</French>
		<German>Insektoiden</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INSECTOID_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Insects, both Terran and Extra-Terrestrial. In space, they are a terrifyingly evolved horrific foe.</English>
		<French>Insectes terriens et extraterrestres. Dans l'espace, ils sont un ennemi horrible terriblement évolué.</French>
		<German>Ein Insektenvolk, das sowohl terrestrische als auch extraterrestrische Spezies beinhaltet. Im Weltall stellen sie durch ihre fortschrittlichen Einheiten eine ernste Bedrohung dar.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INSECTOID_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Insectoids</English>
		<French>Insectoïdes</French>
		<German>Insektoiden</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_IROQUOIS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Iroquois</English>
		<French>
			<Text>iroquois:iroquois:iroquois:iroquois</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>irokesisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>irochese:irochese:irochesi:irochesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>iroqués:iroquesa:iroqueses:iroquesas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Irokezów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_IROQUOIS_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Iroquois Empire</English>
		<French>Empire iroquois</French>
		<German>Reich der Irokesen</German>
		<Italian>Impero Irochese</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio Iroqués</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Irokeskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_IROQUOIS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Iroquois Confederacy (Haudenosaunee, also known as the League of Peace and Power, Five Nations, or Six Nations) is a group of First Nations/Native Americans. The Confederacy was based, at the time of the arrival of the Europeans, in what is now upstate New York, as well as parts of Pennsylvania, Ontario, and Quebec.[PARAGRAPH:2]This union of nations was established prior to major European contact, replete with a constitution known as the Gayanashagowa (or "Great Law of Peace") recorded with the help of a memory device in the form of special beads called wampum that have inherent spiritual value (wampum has been inaccurately compared to money in other cultures). Most Western anthropologists speculate that this constitution was created between the middle 1400s and early 1600s, but other scholars who account for Iroquois oral tradition argue that the event took place as early as 1100, with many arguing for August 31, 1142 based on a coinciding solar eclipse (see Fields and Mann, American Indian Culture and Research Journal, vol. 21, #2). Some Westerners have also suggested that the Constitution was written with European help, although most dismiss this notion as racism. [PARAGRAPH:2]The two prophets, Hiawatha and "The Great Peacemaker", brought a message of peace to squabbling tribes. The tribes who joined the League were the Seneca, Onondaga, Oneida, Cayuga and Mohawks. Once they ceased (most) infighting, they rapidly became one of the strongest forces in 17th and 18th century northeastern North America. [PARAGRAPH:2]The League engaged in a series of wars against the French and their Iroquoian-speaking Huron or Wyandot allies. They also put great pressure on the Algonquian peoples of the Atlantic coast and what is now subarctic Canada and not infrequently fought the English colonies as well. During the 17th Century, they are also credited with having destroyed the Neutral Indians and Erie Tribe as a way of controlling the fur trade, even though other reasons are often given for these wars. Some survivors of these tribes were absorbed into the Iroquois tribes. [PARAGRAPH:2]The Iroquois were at the height of their power in the 17th century with a population of around 12,000 people. League traditions allowed for the dead to be symbolically replaced through the "Mourning War", raids intended to seize captives and take vengeance on non-members. This tradition was common to native people of the northeast and was quite different from European settlers' notions of combat. In 1720, the Tuscarora fled north from the European colonization of North Carolina and petitioned to become the Sixth Nation. This is a non-voting position, but places them under the protection of the Confederacy. [PARAGRAPH:2]During the French and Indian War, the Iroquois sided with the British against the French and their Algonquin allies, both traditional enemies of the Iroquois. The Iroquois hoped that aiding the British would also bring favours after the war. Practically, few Iroquois joined the fighting and one early skirmish found a group of Mohawk and French ambush a Mohawk-led British column. The British government issued the Royal Proclamation of 1763 after the war, which restricted white settlement beyond the Appalachians, but this was mainly ignored by the settlers and local governments. [PARAGRAPH:2]During the American Revolution, the Oneida and many Tuscarora and Onondaga sided with the Americans, while the Mohawk, Seneca, and Cayuga remained loyal to Great Britain. This marked the first major split among the Six Nations. After a series of successful operations against frontier settlements, led by the Mohawk leader Joseph Brant and his British allies, the United States reacted with vengeance. In 1779, George Washington ordered Col. Daniel Brodhead and General John Sullivan to lead expeditions against the Iroquois nations to "not merely overun, but destroy," the British-Indian alliance. The campaign successfully ended the ability of the British and Iroquois to mount any further significant attacks on American settlements. [PARAGRAPH:2]In 1794, the Confederacy entered into the Treaty of Canandaigua with the United States. After the American Revolutionary War, Captain Joseph Brant and the Six Nations Indians left New York to settle in Canada. As a reward for their loyalty to the English Crown, they were given a large land grant on the Grand River. The original Mohawk settlement was on the south edge of the present-day city at a location favourable for landing canoes. Brant's crossing of the river gave the original name to the area: Brant's ford. By 1847, European settlers began to settle further up the river at a ford in the Grand River and named the village Brantford, Ontario. [PARAGRAPH:2]The combined leadership of the Nations is known as the Haudenosaunee. It should be noted that "Haudenosaunee" is the term that the people use to refer to themselves. The word "Iroquois" is reputed to come from a French version of a Huron (Wendat) name-considered an insult-meaning "Black Snakes." The Iroquois were enemies of the Huron and the Algonquin, who were allied with the French, due to their rivalry in the fur trade. Haudenosaunee means "People Building a Long House." The term is said to have been introduced by The Great Peacemaker at the time of the formation of the Confederacy. It implies that the Nations of the confederacy should live together as families in the same longhouse. Symbolically, the Seneca were the guardians of the western door of the "tribal long house," and the Mohawk were the guardians of the eastern door. [PARAGRAPH:2]There exists another, perhaps more compelling, version explaining the origin of the word "Iroquois," as the French combination of two distinct terms used in the language of the Haudenosaunee. The participants and writers developing the nascent US government compared the Haudenosaunee and their ways to a state of achievement in administrative self-governance that Rome itself never reached, and an ideal that they hoped the US would aspire to and achieve.[PARAGRAPH:2] In this modification by Wyz_sub10, the flag is that of the Iroquois Confederacy.[PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
		<Polish>Konfederacja Irokezów (nazwa własna: Haudenosaunee) liga plemion (Mohawków, Oneidów, Onandagów, Kajugów i Seneków, a od 1712 także Tuskarorów) Indian Ameryki Północnej zamieszkujących tereny na wschód od Wielkich Jezior i na południe od Rzeki św. Wawrzyńca, czyli północną część stanów Nowy Jork, Pensylwanii i Maine, niemal cały stan Vermont oraz południowe obszary kanadyjskich prowincji Quebec i Ontario. Irokezi posługują się językami irokeskimi należącymi do fyli makrosiouańskiej.[PARAGRAPH:2]Irokezi stworzyli jedną z najbardziej zaawansowanych cywilizacyjnie kultur Indian Ameryki Północnej. Prowadzili osiadły tryb życia i swą gospodarkę, do czasu przybycia Europejczyków, opierali na rolnictwie. Uprawiali kilka odmian kukurydzy, fasolę i dynię. Posługiwali się sprawnie metodą wyrębu i wypalania. Mieszkali w tzw. długich domach, (longhouse), które mogły pomieścić kilka rodzin. Na roli pracowały kobiety, podczas gdy mężczyźni zajmowali się polowaniami i wojowaniem. Znani byli jako znakomici i bezlitośni wojownicy. Kobiety Irokezów miały wysoki status społeczny i do nich należał wybór rady plemiennej. Irokezi porywali kobiety sąsiednich plemion na żony i dzieci do adopcji. [PARAGRAPH:2]W chwili gdy zasoby środowiska Mohikanów uległy wyczerpaniu wskutek intensywnych polowań, Holendrzy z Nowej Holandii zwrócili swe zainteresowania w kierunku handlu z Irokezami. Irokezi rozpoczęli intensywne polowania, by zaspokoić popyt, tereny ich nie były jednak zbyt bogate w zwierzynę. Rozpoczęli więc rozszerzanie strefy swych wpływów na północ, na plemiona Huron i Ottawa (w XVI-XVII wieku Huroni byli potęgą traperską). Częściowo siłą, częściowo niezbyt korzystnymi dla tych drugich umowami handlowymi, Irokezi przejęli kontrolę i zdominowali handel skórami. Sytuację skomplikowało pojawienie się Francuzów i powstanie Nowej Francji. Francuzi nie tylko roztoczyli opiekę nad Indianami z północy, lecz także włączyli ich w swój system ekonomiczny, na dużo lepszych warunkach niż zapewniali to Irokezi. Wynikiem tego była długoletnia wojna pomiędzy Irokezami i Francuzami tzw. wojna bobrowa, w której udział brali także indiańscy sprzymierzeńcy Francuzów. W wyniku tych zmagań plemię Huron uległo niemal całkowitej eksterminacji. Konflikt francusko-irokeski zakończył się w 1701 wraz z podpisaniem tzw. wieczystego pokoju pomiędzy stronami. Irokezi, tracąc tereny handlowe na północy, rozpoczęli poszukiwanie nowych na zachodzie. Z czasem podporządkowali sobie ekonomicznie tereny na południe od Wielkich Jezior aż po Missisipi. Przez cały XVIII wiek Irokezi roztropnie pozostali neutralni w czasie szeregu konfliktów pomiędzy Wielką Brytanią (której byli naturalnymi sprzymierzeńcami) a Francją o dominację w Ameryce Północnej. Ze swych ziem zostali wyparci po amerykańskiej wojnie o niepodległość (1775-1785), kiedy to rosnące w siłę Stany Zjednoczone zmusiły ich do ucieczki na brytyjskie obszary Kanady. Schyłek potęgi Irokezów nastąpił w XIX wieku, gdy futra bobrów wyszły w Europie z mody, w związku z czym znaczenie tego handlu dla Irokezów znacznie spadło.[PARAGRAPH:2]Współcześnie Irokezi są jedną z bardziej tradycyjnych społeczności tubylczych Amerykanów, o silnym poczuciu własnej tożsamości. Znaczna część z nich zamieszkuje rezerwaty po obu stronach granicy USA i Kanady, gdzie po części nadal kultywują tradycje Ligi Irokezów, zachowując pewną autonomię polityczną i ekonomiczną, własną kulturę, religię oraz rewitalizując języki poszczególnych plemion. Wielu mężczyzn chętnie zatrudnia się okresowo przy pracach wysokościowych, m.in. przy budowie mostów i wieżowców.[PARAGRAPH:2]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_IROQUOIS_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Iroquois</English>
		<French>Iroquois</French>
		<German>Irokesenreich</German>
		<Italian>Irochesi</Italian>
		<Spanish>Confederación Iroquesa</Spanish>
		<Polish>Irokezi</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_JAPAN_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Japanese</English>
		<French>
			<Text>japonais:japonaise:japonais:japonaises</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>japanisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>giapponese:giapponese:giapponesi:giapponesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>japonés:japonesa:japoneses:japonesas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Japończyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_JAPAN_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Japanese Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire japonais</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Japaner</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Giapponese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Japonés</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Japońskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_JAPAN_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Japan</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Japonais</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Il Giappone:il Giappone:del Giappone: di Giappone</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Japón</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Japonia</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KHMER_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Khmer:Khmer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>khmer:khmer:khmers:khmers</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>khmerisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>khmer:khmer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>jémer:jémer:jémeres:jémeres</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Khmerów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KHMER_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Khmer Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire khmer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Khmer</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero khmer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Jémer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Khmeryjskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KHMER_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Khmer</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Khmers</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Khmer-Reich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Khmer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Jémer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Khmerzy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KOREA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Korean:Koreans</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>coréen:coréenne:coréens:coréennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>koreanisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>coreano:coreana:coreani:coreane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>coreano:coreana:coreanos:coreanas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Koreańczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MALI_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Malinese</English>
		<French>
			<Text>malien:malienne:maliens:maliennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>malinesisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>malinese:malinese:malinesi:malinesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>malí:malí:malíes:malíes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Malijczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MALI_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Malinese Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire malien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Malier</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero del Mali</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Malí</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Malijskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MALI_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Mali</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Maliens</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Il Mali:il Mali:del Mali:del Mali</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Mali</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MAYA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Maya:Maya</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>maya:maya:mayas:mayas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>mayaisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>maya:maya</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>maya:maya:mayas:mayas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Majów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MAYA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Maya Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire maya</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Maya</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero maya</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Maya</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Majów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MAYA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Maya</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mayas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Mayareich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Maya</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>América maya</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Majowie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MINOR_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Minor</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Secondaires</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>kleinstaatlich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Minore:Minore:Minori:Minori</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>menor:menor:menores:menores</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Podrzędne</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MINOR_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Minor Nation</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Nation secondaire</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Konglomerat der Kleinstaaten</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Nazione minore</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>País menor</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Państwo Podrzędne</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MINOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>It's a Small Nation</English>
		<French>C'est une petite Nation</French>
		<German>Es ist eine kleine Nation</German>
		<Spanish>Es una nación menor.</Spanish>
		<Polish>[SPACE]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MINOR_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Minors</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Secondaires</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Kleinstaaten</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Nazione minore:la Nazione minore:della Nazione minore:della Nazione minore</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>País menor</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Podrzędne</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MONGOL_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Mongolian</English>
		<French>
			<Text>mongol:mongole:mongols:mongoles</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>mongolisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>mongolo:mongola:mongoli:mongole</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>mongol:mongola:mongoles:mongolas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Mongołów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MONGOL_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Mongolian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire mongol</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Mongolen</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Mongolo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Mongol</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Mongolskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MONGOL_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Mongolia</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mongolie</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Mongolei</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Mongolia:la Mongolia:della Mongolia:di Mongolia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Mongolia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NATIVE_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Native</English>
		<French>
			<Text>natif:native:natifs:natives</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>eingeboren</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>nativo:nativa:nativi:native</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>nativo:nativa:nativos:nativas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Siuksowie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NATIVE_AMERICA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Sioux:Sioux's</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>amérindien:amérindienne:amérindiens:amérindiennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>indianisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>dei Nativi Americani:dei Nativi Americani</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>amerindio:amerindia:amerindios:amerindias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Indian</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NATIVE_AMERICA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Native American Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire amérindien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Indianer</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero dei Nativi Americani</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Sioux</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Siuksów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NATIVE_AMERICA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Native America</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Amérindiens</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Indianerreich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>America indiana</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Nación sioux</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Siuksów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NETHERLANDS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Dutch:Dutch</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>néerlandais:néerlandaise:néerlandais:néerlandaises</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>holländisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>olandese:olandese:olandesi:olandesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>holandés:holandesa:holandeses:holandesas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Holendrów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NETHERLANDS_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Dutch Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire néerlandais</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Holländer</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero olandese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Holandés</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Holenderskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NETHERLANDS_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Netherlands</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Pays-Bas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Holland</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Olanda</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Holanda</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Holandia</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NPC_NEANDERTHAL_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Neanderthals</English>
		<French>Néanderthaliens</French>
		<German>neandertalisch</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NPC_NEANDERTHAL_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Neanderthals</English>
		<French>Néanderthaliens</French>
		<German>Reich der Neandertaler</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NPC_NEANDERTHAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Neanderthal Barbarians</English>
		<French>Barbares Neanderthal</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NPC_NEANDERTHAL_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Neanderthals</English>
		<French>Néanderthaliens</French>
		<German>Neandertal</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_OTTOMAN_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Turkish:Turks</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>turc:turque:turcs:turques</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>türkisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>turco:turca:turchi:turche</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>turco:turca:turcos:turcas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Turków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_OTTOMAN_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Ottomans</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Ottomans</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Osmanenreich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Ottomani</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Nación otomana</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Turcy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PERSIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Persian</English>
		<French>
			<Text>perse:perse:perses:perses</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>persisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>persiano:persiana:persiani:persiane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>persa:persa:persas:persas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Persów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PERSIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Persian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire perse</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Perser</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Persiano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Persa</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Perskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PERSIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Persia</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Perses</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Persien</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Persia:la Persia:della Persia:di Persia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Persia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Persja</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PERU_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Peruvian</English>
		<French>Péruvien</French>
		<German>peruanisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>peruviano:peruviana:peruviani:peruviane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>peruano:peruana:peruanos:peruanas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Peruwiańczyk</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PERU_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Peruvian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire péruvien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Peruaner</German>
		<Italian>Impero peruviano</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio Peruano</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Peruwiańskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PERU_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Peru</English>
		<French>Pérou</French>
		<Italian>Perù</Italian>
		<Spanish>Perú</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLYNESIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Polynesian</English>
		<French>Polynésien</French>
		<German>Polynesische</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Polinesiano:Polinesiana:Polinesiani:Polinesiane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polinesiano</Spanish>
		<Polish>Polinezyjski</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLYNESIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Polynesian Empire</English>
		<French>Empire polynésien</French>
		<German>Polynesische Reich</German>
		<Italian>Impero Polinesiano</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polinesiano Imperio</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Polinezji</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLYNESIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Polynesia comprises of the island groups of Samoa, the Cook Islands, French Polynesia, and Niue, the islands of Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis, Futuna, Hawaii, and Pitcairn Island.  The original inhabitants of New Zealand, the Maori, are also considered Polynesian.  The island of Fiji is sometimes included in Polynesia because of its high percentage of Polynesian inhabitants.  Archaeological evidence supports that Polynesia was settled by migration from Melanesia beginning about 3,000 to 4,000 years ago.  The Samoans are believed to have settled the Marquesas perhaps as early as 300 AD, and Easter Island may have been settled from the Marquesas as early as 400 AD.  Hawaii was also settled by these voyagers during the second half of the first millennium AD, and then the Society Islanders, who were the point of origin for the Polynesians who settled on Cook Island.  Around 1000 AD, these cultures also inhabited Polynesia. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Prior to European contact, Polynesian settlements were either in hamlets or villages.  Houses were clustered in small groups, and villages contained 30 or more houses.  These villages were primarily found on the islands of Samoa and New Zealand and were often fortified by walls of stone or wooden palisades.  Both of these types of settlements relied on family oriented organization.  The most common type of organization was that power passed from the first born son to firstborn son and so on.  In Polynesian societies, chiefs would be revered as equals to others.  However, they could usually trace their family line back to the creator gods.  In societies where the chief was protected and separate from the people, warfare was common.  Christian missionaries succeeded in overthrowing ancient religious practices only after they had converted the chiefs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Religion and magic played an important role in Polynesian culture.  Each of the gods had their own rituals, which were carried out by the priests.  Among these practices were sacrifice, chanting, feasting, and fertility rites.  Magic was also enveloping, and countless rituals regarding love, war, revenge, agriculture, and fishing were practiced.  Polynesian culture was a largely marine based.  In addition to fish, mollusks and crustaceans were an important source of food.  Fishing was usually a group activity, and Polynesian fishermen explored the vast expanses of ocean around their homes.  Other food could be provided by various plants. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Food plants also provided materials for various reasons.  Breadfruit wood was used in canoe making, for instance, and leaves of some plants were used in weaving mats, clothing, sails, and other household goods.  Both single and double canoes were equipped with mat sails.  Some boats were large enough to transport families, domesticated animals, and plants over long stretches of ocean.  Over time, cultures developed distinct artistic skills.  Ruined stone temples can be found in the Society Islands, Easter Island, and the Marquesas culture.  Good such as canoes, war clubs, shields, and fish hooks were elaborately decorated.  Feather cloaks showed an enormous amount of effort in gathering rare feathers and arranging them in intricate designs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Contact with European culture began in the late 1700s and radically changed Polynesia.  Spanish explorers were eager to search for riches and spread Christianity.  The Dutch and British also explored areas such as New Zealand and the Samoan islands.  Resistance to European intervention occurred in almost all of the Polynesian islands, but such movements were brief.  For much time to come, Polynesia would go under the power of European powers and the United States.  Polynesian culture, however, always remained in these islands.</English>
		<French>Polynésie est composée de groupes de l'île de Samoa, les îles Cook, la Polynésie française, et Niue, les îles de Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis, Futuna, à Hawaii, et l'île de Pitcairn. Les premiers habitants de la Nouvelle-Zélande, les Maoris, les Polynésiens sont également considérés. L'île des Fidji est parfois inclus dans la Polynésie en raison de son fort pourcentage d'habitants polynésiens. Témoignages archéologiques soutient que la Polynésie a été réglée par la migration à partir de début Mélanésie environ 3.000 à 4.000 ans. Les Samoans sont soupçonnés d'avoir réglé les Marquises peut-être dès 300 après J.-C., et l'île de Pâques ont pu être réglées depuis les Marquises dès 400 après Jésus Christ. Hawaii a aussi été réglé par les voyageurs au cours de la seconde moitié du premier millénaire après JC, puis la Société Islanders, qui ont été le point d'origine de l'Polynésiens qui se sont installés sur des îles Cook. Environ 1000 AD, ces cultures aussi habitée Polynésie. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Avant le contact avec les Européens, les Polynésiens colonies étaient soit en hameaux ou villages. Des maisons ont été regroupés en petits groupes, et les villages contient 30 ou plusieurs maisons. Ces villages ont été trouvés principalement sur les îles Samoa et la Nouvelle-Zélande, et sont souvent enrichis par des murs de pierre ou de bois palissades. Ces deux types d'établissements invoqué organisation familiale. Le type le plus courant de l'organisation était que le pouvoir est passé depuis le premier fils né à fils premier-né et ainsi de suite. Dans les sociétés polynésiennes, les chefs serait considéré comme égal aux autres. Toutefois, ils pourraient retrouver leur famille généralement retour à la ligne créateur dieux. Dans les sociétés où le chef était protégé et à l'écart de la population, la guerre était commun. Missionnaires chrétiens ont réussi à renverser les anciennes pratiques religieuses uniquement après avoir converti les chefs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La religion et la magie jouent un rôle important dans la culture polynésienne. Chacun des dieux avaient leurs propres rites, qui ont été perpétrés par des prêtres. Parmi ces pratiques sont le sacrifice, le chant, de fête, de rites et de la fertilité. Magic était aussi enveloppant, et d'innombrables rituels concernant l'amour, la guerre, la vengeance, l'agriculture et la pêche ont été pratiquées. Culture polynésienne était largement fondée marines. En plus des poissons, mollusques et crustacés ont été une source importante de nourriture. La pêche est souvent une activité de groupe, et les pêcheurs polynésiens ont exploré les vastes étendues de l'océan autour de leur maison. Autres produits alimentaires pourraient être fournies par diverses plantes. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Food plantes a également fourni du matériel pour des raisons diverses. Breadfruit bois a été utilisé en canot rendant, par exemple, et les feuilles de certaines plantes ont été utilisés dans le tissage de tapis, les vêtements, voiles, et d'autres biens d'équipement ménager. Les deux simples et doubles canots étaient équipés d'un tapis de voiles. Certains bateaux ont été assez grands pour le transport des familles, les animaux domestiques et les plantes sur de grandes étendues de l'océan. Au fil du temps, développé des cultures distinctes compétences artistiques. Les temples en pierre en ruine peut être trouvée dans les Îles de la Société, l'île de Pâques, les Marquises et de la culture. Bon tels que canots, de la guerre des clubs, des boucliers et des hameçons ont été minutieusement décorés. Plume mantos montré une énorme quantité d'efforts pour recueillir des rares plumes et arrangeant dans les modèles complexes. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Le contact avec la culture européenne a commencé à la fin des années 1700 et radicalement changé la Polynésie. Explorateurs espagnols étaient impatients de recherche de la richesse et à la propagation du christianisme. Le néerlandais et britannique a également étudié des domaines tels que la Nouvelle-Zélande et les îles des Samoa. Résistance à l'intervention européenne a eu lieu dans presque toutes les îles polynésiennes, mais ces mouvements ont été brève. Pour beaucoup de temps à venir, la Polynésie se retrouvera dans le pouvoir des puissances européennes et des états-Unis. Culture polynésienne, cependant, toujours restés dans ces îles.</French>
		<German>Polynesien besteht aus Gruppen von der Insel Samoa, die Cook Inseln, Französisch Polynesien, Niue, die Inseln Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis, Futuna, Hawaii, und Pitcairn Island. Die Ureinwohner Neuseelands, die Maori, sind ebenfalls als polynesischen. Die Insel Fidschi ist manchmal in Polynesien wegen seiner hohen Anteil der polynesischen Einwohner. Archäologische Belege, dass Polynesien wurde von Migration von Melanesien ab etwa 3.000 bis 4.000 Jahren. Die Samoaner sind der Ansicht, dass sich die Marquesas vielleicht so früh wie 300 n. Chr., und Osterinsel Mai geklärt sind von den Marquesas so früh wie 400 n.Chr. Hawaii war auch durch diese Reisenden in der zweiten Hälfte des ersten Jahrtausends n. Chr., und dann der Gesellschaft Islanders, die als Ausgangspunkt für die Polynesier, die sich auf Cook Island. Um 1000 n. Chr., diese Kulturen auch bewohnt Polynesien. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Vor dem Europäischen Kontakt, polynesische Siedlungen wurden entweder in Weiler oder Dörfer. Die Häuser wurden gebündelt in kleinen Gruppen, und Dörfer mit 30 oder mehr Wohnungen. Diese Dörfer waren vor allem auf den Inseln von Samoa und Neuseeland und waren oft von befestigten Mauern aus Stein oder hölzernen Palisaden. Beide Arten von Siedlungen auf Familie ausgerichtete Organisation. Die häufigste Art der Organisation war, dass die Macht vom ersten Sohn geboren Erstgeborenen Sohn, und so weiter. In polynesischen Gesellschaften, Häuptlinge wäre verehrt und gleichberechtigt mit anderen. Allerdings könnten sie meist den Spuren ihrer Familie zurück in die Zeile Schöpfer Götter. In Gesellschaften, in denen der Chef war geschützt und getrennt von den Menschen, Kriegsführung war häufig. Christlichen Missionaren gelang es den Sturz alten religiösen Praktiken nur, nachdem sie konvertiert war die Chefs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Religion und Magie spielte eine wichtige Rolle in der polynesischen Kultur. Jeder der Götter hatten ihre eigenen Rituale, die durchgeführt wurden, indem die Priester. Zu diesen Praktiken waren Opfer, Deklamieren, Schlemmen, Riten und Fruchtbarkeit. Magie war auch Kuvertierung, und zahllose Rituale über Liebe, Krieg, Rache, Landwirtschaft und Fischerei wurden geübt. Polynesischen Kultur war ein weitgehend marinen beruht. Zusätzlich zu Fisch, Muscheln und Krebse waren eine wichtige Quelle von Lebensmitteln. Angeln in der Regel eine Gruppe, und polynesische Fischer erkundet die große Weiten des Ozeans rund um ihr Zuhause. Andere Lebensmittel werden könnten, die von verschiedenen Pflanzen. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Essen Pflanzen auch Materialien für die verschiedenen Gründen. Brotfruchtbaum Holz verwendet wurde im Kanu machen, zum Beispiel, und einige Blätter von Pflanzen wurden in die Weberei Matten, Bekleidung, Segel, und andere Haushaltsgeräte. Sowohl Einzel- und Doppelzimmer Kanus wurden mit Matte Segel. Einige Boote waren groß genug, um Verkehr Familien, domestizierten Tiere und Pflanzen über weite Strecken des Ozeans. Im Laufe der Zeit entwickelte Kulturen unterschiedliche künstlerische Fähigkeiten. Steinruine Tempel finden sich in der Gesellschaft Inseln, die Osterinsel, und die Marquesas Kultur. Gute wie Kanus, Krieg Clubs, Schilde, und Fisch Haken waren aufwendig gestaltet. Feather Mäntel zeigte eine enorme Anstrengungen bei der Erfassung seltener Federn und Vermittlung in komplexen Designs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Kontakt mit der europäischen Kultur begann in den späten 1700er und radikal verändert Polynesien. Spanische Forscher waren eifrig bei der Suche nach Reichtum und der Verbreitung des Christentums. Die niederländischen und britischen auch erkundet Bereichen wie Neuseeland und den samoanischen Inseln. Widerstand der europäischen Intervention in fast allen der polynesischen Inseln, aber solche Bewegungen waren kurz. Für viel Zeit zu kommen, Polynesien würde unter der Macht der europäischen Mächte und die Vereinigten Staaten. Polynesische Kultur, jedoch immer noch in diesen Inseln.</German>
		<Italian>Polinesia comprende l'isola di gruppi di Samoa, Isole Cook, Polinesia francese, e Niue, le isole di Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis, Futuna, Hawaii, e Pitcairn Island. Gli abitanti originari della Nuova Zelanda, i Maori, anche in considerazione della Polinesia. L'isola delle Figi è talvolta inclusi nella Polinesia a causa della sua elevata percentuale di abitanti della Polinesia. Archeologico prove sostiene che la Polinesia è stata regolata dalla migrazione Melanesia iniziate da circa 3.000 a 4.000 anni fa. Il Samoans si ritiene di aver risolto il Marquesas forse già nel 300 dC, e Isola di Pasqua potrebbe essere stata risolta dal Marquesas già nel 400 dC. Hawaii è stata risolta anche da questi viaggiatori durante la seconda metà del primo millennio dC, e poi la società Islanders, che sono stati il punto di origine per i Polinesiani che insediati sul Cook Island. Intorno al 1000 dC, queste culture anche abitato Polinesia. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Prima di contatto europeo, polinesiani erano insediamenti o in frazioni o villaggi. Case sono state raggruppate in piccoli gruppi, e villaggi conteneva 30 o più case. Questi villaggi sono stati trovati soprattutto sulle isole di Samoa e la Nuova Zelanda e sono stati spesso fortificato da mura di pietra o di legno palizzate. Entrambi questi tipi di insediamenti valere famiglia orientata organizzazione. Il tipo più comune di organizzazione di potere che è stato superato dal primo figlio a figlio primogenito, e così via. In Polinesia società, capi sarebbe riverito come uguale agli altri. Tuttavia, di solito si potrebbe risalire la loro famiglia torna alla linea il creatore dei. Nelle società in cui il capo è stato protetto e separato dal popolo, la guerra è stata comune. Missionari cristiani sono riusciti a rovesciare antiche pratiche religiose solo dopo aver convertito capi. [PARAGRAPH: 2] religione e la magia svolto un ruolo importante nella cultura polinesiana. Ciascuno di loro ha avuto dei propri rituali, che sono stati effettuati dai sacerdoti. Tra queste pratiche erano sacrificio, canto, festa, e di riti di fertilità. Magic è stato anche avvolgente, e innumerevoli rituali per quanto riguarda l'amore, la guerra, la vendetta, l'agricoltura, la pesca e sono state praticate. Polinesia cultura è stato un gran marini fonda. Oltre a pesci, molluschi e crostacei sono state un'importante fonte di cibo. La pesca è stata generalmente di un gruppo di attività, e la Polinesia pescatori esplorato il vasto oceano intorno distese di loro case. Altri alimenti possono essere forniti da varie piante. [PARAGRAPH: 2] alimentare impianti anche fornito materiali per vari motivi. Pane di legno è stato usato in canoa fare, per esempio, e le foglie di alcuni impianti sono stati utilizzati in tessitura tappeti, vestiti, vele, e di altri beni. Entrambe le singole e doppie canoe erano equipaggiate con vele tappetino. Alcune imbarcazioni sono state abbastanza grande per il trasporto di famiglie, animali addomesticati, e di impianti per lunghi tratti di mare. Nel corso del tempo, di culture distinte sviluppato capacità artistiche. Rovinato pietra templi si trovano nella Società Isole, Isola di Pasqua, e la cultura Marquesas. Buona come canoe, club di guerra, scudi, e di pesce ganci erano elaboratamente decorato. Piume cloaks mostrato un enorme sforzo nella raccolta di rari piume e organizzare in intricati disegni. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Il contatto con la cultura europea ha avuto inizio alla fine del 1700 e ha cambiato radicalmente la Polinesia. Esploratori spagnoli erano desiderosi di ricerca per la ricchezza e la diffusione del cristianesimo. Gli olandesi e britannici anche esplorare settori come la Nuova Zelanda e le isole Samoa. Resistenza agli europei intervento è avvenuto in quasi tutte le isole della Polinesia, ma tali movimenti sono stati brevi. Per molto tempo a venire, Polinesia andrebbe sotto il potere di potenze europee e gli Stati Uniti. Polinesia cultura, tuttavia, è rimasta sempre in queste isole.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polinesia comprende grupos de la isla de Samoa, las Islas Cook, la Polinesia Francesa, y Niue, las Islas de Tokelau, Tuvalu, Tonga, Wallis y Futuna, Hawaii, y la isla de Pitcairn. Los habitantes originarios de Nueva Zelanda, los maoríes, también se consideran de Polinesia. La isla de Fiji veces se incluyen en la Polinesia, debido a su alto porcentaje de habitantes polinesios. Archaeological pruebas apoyan que la Polinesia fue resuelta por la migración de Melanesia inicio unos 3.000 a 4.000 años atrás. Los samoanos se cree que se han asentado las Marquesas quizás ya en 300 dC, y la Isla de Pascua puede haber sido resuelta de las Marquesas ya en 400 DC. Hawaii fue también reiterada por esas viaje durante la segunda mitad del primer milenio dC, y luego la Sociedad de los isleños, que fueron el punto de origen de los polinesios que se establecieron en las Islas Cook. Alrededor de 1000 DC, estas culturas también habitada Polinesia. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Antes del contacto europeo, de Polinesia fueron los asentamientos, ya sea en aldeas o caseríos. Casas se agruparon en grupos pequeños, y los pueblos que figuran 30 o más viviendas. Estas aldeas se encuentran principalmente en las islas de Samoa y Nueva Zelandia y son a menudo fortificadas por muros de piedra o empalizadas de madera. Ambos de estos tipos de asentamientos se basó en la organización orientada a la familia. El tipo más común de organización es que el poder pasa de la primera a hijo nacido hijo primogénito, etc. En las sociedades de Polinesia, jefes sería venerado como iguales a los demás. Sin embargo, por lo general pueden localizar a sus familiares de nuevo a la línea de dioses creadores. En las sociedades en que el jefe estaba protegida y separada del pueblo, la guerra era común. Misioneros cristianos tenido éxito en derrocar a antiguas prácticas religiosas sólo después de que se habían convertido los jefes. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Religión y magia desempeñado un papel importante en la cultura polinesia. Cada uno de los dioses tienen sus propios rituales, que fueron llevados a cabo por los sacerdotes. Entre estas prácticas se sacrificio, cantando, banquete, y los ritos de la fertilidad. Magic también fue envolviendo, y un sinnúmero de rituales en relación con el amor, la guerra, la venganza, la agricultura y la pesca se practica. Cultura polinesia era un gran marino basada. Además de los peces, moluscos y crustáceos son una fuente importante de alimento. La pesca es generalmente una actividad de grupo, y los pescadores polinesios explorar vastas extensiones de los océanos alrededor de sus hogares. Otros alimentos podría ser proporcionada por diversas plantas. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Alimentación plantas también proporcionó materiales por diversas razones. Pan madera se utiliza en la canoa, por ejemplo, y las hojas de algunas plantas se han utilizado en el tejido de alfombras, ropa, velas, y otros artículos para el hogar. Las dos canoas individuales y dobles equipadas con colchoneta velas. Algunos barcos eran lo suficientemente grandes como para el transporte de las familias, los animales domesticados, plantas y más largas extensiones de océano. Con el tiempo, las culturas desarrolladas aptitudes artísticas distintas. Templos de piedra en ruinas se pueden encontrar en la sociedad de las Islas, la Isla de Pascua, la cultura y las Marquesas. Bueno, como canoas, clubes de la guerra, escudos, y los peces se ganchos elaboradamente decorado. Feather mantos mostró una enorme cantidad de esfuerzo en la recopilación y organización de plumas raras en intrincados diseños. [PARAGRAPH: 2] contacto con la cultura europea comenzó a fines de 1700 y cambió radicalmente la Polinesia. Exploradores españoles que estaban deseosos de búsqueda de la riqueza y difundir el cristianismo. Los holandeses y británicos también se exploraron áreas tales como Nueva Zelanda y las islas de Samoa. La resistencia a la intervención europea se produjo en casi todas las islas de la Polinesia, pero esos movimientos fueron breves. Por mucho tiempo, la Polinesia iría bajo el poder de las potencias europeas y los Estados Unidos. Cultura polinesia, sin embargo, siempre se mantuvo en esas islas.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Polinezja - wschodnia część Oceanii, położona w środkowej części Oceanu Spokojnego, po obu stronach równika i po obu stronach linii zmiany daty. Wyspy Polinezji są pochodzenia wulkanicznego lub koralowego. Klimat wysp jest gorący i wilgotny; porasta je bujna roślinność międzyzwrotnikowa. Języki polinezyjskie - grupa języków oceanicznych (wschodnioaustronezyjskich) z rodziny języków austronezyjskich, którymi posługuje się ok. 1 mln rdzennych mieszkańców wysp Oceanii. Większość z nich używana jest w obrębie tzw. trójkąta polinezyjskiego, którego zasięg wyznaczają Hawaje, Nowa Zelandia i Wyspa Wielkanocna, niektóre jednak, klasyfikowane jako języki peryferyjne (ang. outlier) geograficznie pozostają poza trójkątem, na terenie Mikronezji i Melanezji.Hawaje zostały zaludnione w IV wieku przez Polinezyjczyków z Tahiti, którzy dotarli tutaj po mniej więcej 4 wiekach wypraw podejmowanych śladami lecących w tym kierunku ptaków. Dla Europy odkryte zostały przez Jamesa Cooka w 1778. Początkowo Polinezyjczycy potraktowali Cooka jak bóstwo, które przybyło do nich na ogromnym statku. Kiedy jednak Cook opuścił wyspę i musiał na nią powrócić po parodniowym sztormie, uznali, że jest to świadectwo tego, iż nie jest on bogiem. Podczas zbrojnego starcia zginął wtedy Cook i kilku jego marynarzy.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLYNESIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Polynesia</English>
		<French>Polynésie</French>
		<German>Polynesien</German>
		<Italian>Polinesia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polinesia</Spanish>
		<Polish>Polinezja</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PORTUGAL_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Portuguese:Portuguese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>portugais:portugaise:portugais:portugaises</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>portugiesisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>portoghese:portoghese:portoghesi:portoghesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>portugués:portuguesa:portugueses:portuguesas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Portugalczyków</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PORTUGAL_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Portuguese Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire portugais</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Portugiesen</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero portoghese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Portugués</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Portugalskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PORTUGAL_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Portugal</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Portugais</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Portogallo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Portugal</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Portugalia</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ROME_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Roman</English>
		<French>
			<Text>romain:romaine:romains:romaines</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>römisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>romano:romana:romani:romane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>romano:romana:romanos:romanas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Rzymian</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ROME_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Roman Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire romain</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Römer</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Romano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Romano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Rzymskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ROME_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Rome</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Romains</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Rom</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Roma:Roma:di Roma:di Roma</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Roma</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Rzym</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_RUSSIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Russian</English>
		<French>
			<Text>russe:russe:russes:russes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>russisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>russo:russa:russi:russe</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>ruso:rusa:rusos:rusas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Rosjan</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_RUSSIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Russian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire russe</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Russen</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Russo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Ruso</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Rosyjskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_RUSSIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Russia</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Russes</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Russland</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Russia:la Russia:della Russia:di Russia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Rusia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Rosja</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SIAM_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Siamese</English>
		<French>
			<Text>siamois:siamoise:siamois:siamoises</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>siamesisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>siamese:siamese:siamesi:siamesi</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>siamés:siamesa:siameses:siamesas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Tajów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SIAM_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Siamese Empire</English>
		<French>Empire siamois</French>
		<German>Reich der Siamesen</German>
		<Italian>Impero Siamese</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio Siamés</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Syjamskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SIAM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Siam was a country in Southeast Asia; it is now called Thailand.[PARAGRAPH:1]By the time the name was officially changed in 1939, the borders of the country had been secured, and they have not changed since, except for a brief period during the World War II Japanese occupation of Thailand, when other parts of Japanese-occupied Southeast Asia were transferred to Thailand and briefly swelled the kingdom. Thailand was punished for its bad choice of ally after the war was over, and the borders were returned to their previous locations.[PARAGRAPH:1]But such changes are not uncommon in this little corner of Asia; throughout its long history, Siam has been much larger, and much smaller, than it is today.[PARAGRAPH:1]The mapping of the borders of the country did not in fact occur until the nineteenth century. Previously Siam, like most Southeast Asian polities, was home to a host of waxing and waning kingdoms whose fortunes depended, in large part, on the strategic and tactical prowess of their rulers.[PARAGRAPH:1]It is common in Thai nationalist historiography to trace the origins of the Siamese (and Thai) state back to a kingdom centred around the city of Sukhothai and ruled by the benevolent patriarch Ramkhamhaeng, one of those powerful rulers who was able to subjugate many of his neighbours and greatly expand his territory. However, during Ramkhamhaeng's day and after a powerful kingdom co-existed close by, centred around present-day Chiang Mai, which was founded by Ramkhamhaeng's friend and rival, Mangrai; other nearby powers included Phrae and Luang Phrabang. There were southern kingdoms near what is now Malaysia, and the Burmese and Khmer - now Cambodians - have long been major players in this arena. But all are given short shrift in the drive to identify a unitary lineage which leads to modern Thailand. That lineage moves from Sukhothai to Ayuthaya, and thence to Thonburi and Bangkok.[PARAGRAPH:1]By the nineteenth century European powers were busy colonizing Asia and the king, Chulalongkorn, realized that he better make formal what had previously been rather elastic, so he arranged for some intrepid farang (western) and Thai explorers to map the borders of the kingdom. Chulalongkorn's father Mongkut had already had to cede some Siamese territory to the British, and Chulalongkorn gave away much more to the French. But this was negotiated in return for concessions, not seized or tricked away from the Siamese, and the most important concession Siam was able to demand was independence. Thus the modern kingdom of Siam literally took shape in the nineteenth century, and Siam stood alone in Southeast Asia in being able to avoid colonization.[PARAGRAPH:1]The term Siam itself has been in use for a very long time in Asia.[PARAGRAPH:1]Apparently a twelfth-century Khmer inscription at Angkor Wat mentions syam, "dark brown people", said to be vassals of the Khmer king; they were probably settled around Sukhothai. The term quickly took hold in Europe as well, and farang visitors who visited Ayuthaya in the seventeenth century referred to the kingdom as Siam (or Sayam), but also Ayuthaya (Ayutthaya, Ayuthiya, and lots of other variants), and reported that the inhabitants themselves called their country Meuang Thai, "Land of the Free". This was the convention drawn on when changing the name from Siam to Thailand.[PARAGRAPH:1]The name change was controversial, and some still prefer Siam. However, "Land of the Free" has better connotations than "dark brown people" and the name Thailand, though an English translation, does have clear indigenous roots that the term Siam lacks. In any case, Siam became Thailand, and there the matter rests today.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
		<Polish>Tajlandia (Królestwo Tajlandii) – państwo w południowo-wschodniej Azji, graniczące z Laosem i Kambodżą na wschodzie, z Malezją na południu oraz z Birmą (Myanmarem) i Morzem Andamańskim na zachodzie. Tajlandia jest także nazywana Syjamem, gdyż była to jej oficjalna nazwa do 11 maja 1949. Międzynarodowe określenie "Thai".[PARAGRAPH:1]Tajlandia jest krajem nizinnym położonym na Półwyspie Indochińskim. W środkowej części znajduje się Nizina Menamu, na północnym wschodzie płytowa równina Korat ograniczona od południa pasmem Dongrak, a od Niziny Menamu górami Thiu Khao Phetchabun. Północną i zachodnią część kraju zajmują młode (mezozoiczne) pasma górskie o przebiegu południkowym: Tanen Taunggyi (Doi Inthanon, 2595 m, najwyższy szczyt Tajlandii) i Doi Luang. Długość linii brzegowej wynosi ponad 2600 km. Wybrzeża są nizinne i silnie rozczłonkowane. Największymi wyspami są: Phuket na Morzu Andamańskim, Samui i Phangan w Zatoce Tajlandzkiej.[PARAGRAPH:1]Pierwsze ślady bytności Homo sapiens na terenach Tajlandii pochodzą sprzed 30 000 lat. Najstarsze znaleziska łupin nasion i plew pochodzą z IX tysiąclecia p.n.e. - znalezione były w jaskiniach północnej Tajlandii - Jaskini Ducha (Tam Phii) położonej na północ od Mae Hong Son oraz jaskini w dolinie Banjan. Początek historii Tajlandii wiąże się z migracją Tajów z południowo-zachodniej części Chin. Ludność ta dotarła na terytorium obecnego państwa w X–XII wieku. Tajowie opanowali dorzecze Menamu, zasymilowali się z żyjącymi tu Khmerami, ulegając jednocześnie wpływom ich kultury i ich religii - buddyzmu. W 1350 założono w dolinie Menamu Ajutthaję, stolicę królestwa. Państwo ze stolicą w Ajutthaji objęło prawie cały Półwysep Indochiński. Okres rozkwitu nastąpił w XV wieku, osłabienie w XVI wieku. W XVI i XVII w. rozpoczęły się kontakty z Europejczykami m.in. Portugalczykami, Hiszpanami, Holendrami i Anglikami. W drugiej połowie XVII wieku Birma zajęła Ajutthaję. W 1782 w południowej Tajlandii generał Czakri ogłosił się królem i założył nową dynastię nazwaną jego imieniem. Państwo stale umacniało się, ale próby powiększenia terytorium zostały zahamowane przez rosnące w tym regionie wpływy brytyjskie i francuskie; W latach 60. XIX wieku tajskie państwo było formalnie niepodległe, ale realnie było uzależnione od państw kolonialnych. Europejczycy odebrali krajowi zwierzchnictwo nad Kambodżą (1867) i Laosem (1893) - Indochiny Francuskie. W początkach XX wieku przeprowadzono reformę; władcy zachowali ustrój absolutystyczny. W 1932 nastąpił wojskowo-cywilny zamach stanu, który doprowadził do ustanowienia monarchii konstytucyjnej, a w 1938 władzę objęło wojsko. Rząd Tajlandii w 1940 zawarł pakt o nieagresji z Japonią, a później sojusz wojskowy i polityczny. Tajlandia brała udział w wojnie przeciw aliantom (tylko teoretycznie). W 1944 odsunięto od władzy rząd popierający Japonię po to, aby nie brać odpowiedzialności za udział w wojnie po stronie państw Osi. Po wojnie utrzymywano przyjazne stosunki z USA, wysłano do Wietnamu oddziały wspomagające wojska amerykańskie. W 1974 Zgromadzenie Narodowe uchwaliło konstytucję, ustanawiającą w Tajlandii demokrację parlamentarną. Konstytucję anulowano w 1977 po kolejnym przewrocie wojskowym. Zgromadzenie uchwaliło nową konstytucję w (1978).[PARAGRAPH:1]Tajlandia jest monarchią konstytucyjną. Na podstawie konstytucji z 1997 (unieważnionej po puczu w 2006 roku) głową państwa jest król (Rama IX Bhumibol Adulyadej, od 1946). Władza ustawodawcza należy do 2-izbowego Zgromadzenia Narodowego wybieranego w wyborach powszechnych: Izba Reprezentantów (niższa) – 500 członków, na czteroletnią kadencję; Senat (wyższa) – 200 członków, na kadencję sześcioletnią.[PARAGRAPH:1]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SIAM_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Siam</English>
		<French>Siam</French>
		<Polish>Syjam</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SPAIN_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Spanish</English>
		<French>
			<Text>espagnol:espagnole:espagnols:espagnoles</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>spanisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>spagnolo:spagnola:spagnoli:spagnole</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>español:española:españoles:españolas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Hiszpanów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SPAIN_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Spanish Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire espagnol</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Spanier</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Spagnolo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Español</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Hiszpańskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SPAIN_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Spain</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Espagnols</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Spanien</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Spagna:la Spagna:della Spagna:di Spagna</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>España</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Hiszpania</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SUMERIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Sumerian:Sumerians</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>sumérien:sumérienne:sumériens:sumériennes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>sumerisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>dei Sumeri:dei Sumeri</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>sumerio:sumeria:sumerios:sumerias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Sumerów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SUMERIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Sumerian Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire sumérien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Sumerer</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero sumero</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Sumerio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Sumeryjskie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SUMERIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Sumeria</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Sumériens</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Sumer</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Sumeria</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Sumeria</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Sumer</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_UNITED_STATES_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>American</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Américains</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>amerikanisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Americano:Americana:Americani:Americane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>estadounidense:estadounidense:estadounidenses:estadounidenses</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Amerykanie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_UNITED_STATES_DESC</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>United States</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire américain</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Amerikaner</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Americano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Estadounidense</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Stany Zjednoczone</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_UNITED_STATES_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>America</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Américains</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Amerika</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>L'America:l'America:dell'America:d'America</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Estados Unidos</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Ameryka</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VIKING_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Viking</English>
		<French>
			<Text>viking:viking:vikings:vikings</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>wikingisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Vichingo:Vichinga:Vichinghi:Vichinghe</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>vikingo:vikinga:vikingos:vikingas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wikingów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VIKING_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Viking Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire viking</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Reich der Wikinger</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Vichingo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Vikingo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Imperium Wikingów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VIKING_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Scandinavia</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Scandinavie</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Wikingerreich</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Scandinavia:la Scandinavia:della Scandinavia:di Scandinavia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Escandinavia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Skandynawia</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ZULU_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Zulu:Zulu</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>zoulou:zouloue:zoulous:zouloues</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>zuluisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>zulu</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>zulú:zulú:zulúes:zulúes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Zulusów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ZULU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Zulu came from a group of peoples known as the Nguni, a linguistic subgroup of the Bantu family of languages. The Nguni had been migrating south for almost a thousand years before reaching the region of the White Umfolozi River around 1700 AD. It was here that the Zulu decided to settle and make their home, according to tradition in 1709. The Zulu are named after Zulu kaNtombhela, who was the founder and chief of the tribe. [PARAGRAPH:2]The Zulu were never more than one unremarkable small tribe among many - until the coming of the great warrior Shaka Zulu, who was born sometime around 1787. While growing up, Shaka was exiled by his father and found refuge with Digiswayo, the chief of another neighboring tribe. When his father died around 1816, Digiswayo helped Shaka succeed to the Zulu throne. [PARAGRAPH:2]Once in power Shaka instituted something of a military revolution among the Zulus, replacing the traditional "assegai" (a javelin-like throwing spear) with a shorter stabbing spear called the "lklwa." He also equipped his warriors with a larger shield which covered most of the soldier's body. This change in Zulu weaponry reflected Shaka's innovations in warfare: while previous battles had tended to be somewhat ritualistic - with much chanting and spear-throwing at a distance - and thus did not have decisive results, Shaka taught the Zulu to kill. [PARAGRAPH:2]Under Shaka's command, the Zulu warriors would close to melee range with their opponents, where their shorter stabbing spears were more effective than the opposition's throwing weapons. Shaka also taught his warriors to fight in a new tactical formation known as the "buffalo horns". Under this formation the center of the Zulu line would engage the enemy to hold them in position, while the right and left "horns" would move forward and envelop the enemy. Outflanked on right and left and equipped with inferior weapons, few enemies could stand up to the Zulu assault; the Zulu were soon terrorizing the neighboring tribes. [PARAGRAPH:2]Within a decade, Shaka had accumulated an army of 50,000 warriors, defeated all of the surrounding tribes, and was master over most of the interior of what is now South Africa. Shaka set up a new capital for the Zulu at Bulaweyo, but his arrogance and cruelty caused dissatisfaction among his people. In 1828 Shaka was assassinated by his half-brothers Dingane and Mhlangana. Dingane then immediately killed Mhlangana and began a purge of the pro-Shaka chieftains under his control. [PARAGRAPH:2]It was into this picture of chaos and violence that the European settlers first began appearing onto the scene in the 1830s. The first European settlement in the Zululand region was the English colony of Port Natal (modern Durban). An English missionary went to live with the Zulu in 1837, and was tolerated by King Dingane. However, at the same time a group of Boer settlers known as the "Voortrekkers" (or pioneers) were moving north across the Orange River into the now-empty lands which had been vacated by tribes fleeing the Zulu. Dingane had given the Voortrekkers permission to settle in the area, but in 1838 - either as the result of a misunderstanding or because Dingane had planned it from the start - the Zulus attacked the newcomers. [PARAGRAPH:2]This proved to be a huge mistake. At the Battle of Blood River, the Zulus vastly outnumbered their opposition, having 10,000 warriors fighting 400 Boers. Despite the odds, however, the Boers slaughtered their opponents, their firearms giving them an overwhelming advantage against their spear-wielding opponents. The Zulus were forced to allow the white men to settle in their territory, which became known as the Republic of Utrecht. [PARAGRAPH:2]Following the battle, there was a generation of uneasy peace between the Zulus and the growing British and Boer presence in the region. However, after the discovery of diamond mines in South Africa in 1878, the British cast covetous eyes on the Zulu land, and they began to look for an excuse to attack and displace the natives. Following a minor border dispute in 1878, the British declared war and invaded Zululand on three fronts. [PARAGRAPH:2]The Zulu warriors fought bravely (and much to the Europeans' shock managed to slaughter a British force at Isandlwana), but the British rifles and Maxim guns made the ferocity of individual Zulu warriors irrelevant, and the outcome of the war was never in doubt. The Zulu were defeated and Zululand was incorporated into British South Africa. King Cetshwayo was taken to London to meet Queen Victoria as an honored prisoner. However, the rest of the nation did not fare so well, and the Zulus spent the next century under British and Afrikaner domination, forced to live under the racist apartheid laws of South Africa. [PARAGRAPH:2]Following the fall of apartheid in the 1990s, however, today Zulus enjoy full citizenship rights in South Africa. Zulu is the most widely spoken language in the country, and with over 11 million people, the Zulus are the largest ethnic group in South Africa. [PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
		<French>Les Zoulous sont issus d'un peuple appelé Nguni, un sous-groupe linguistique de la famille des langues bantoues. Les Ngunis migrent vers le sud pendant près de mille ans avant d'atteindre la région de la rivière White Umfolozi vers 1700 ap. J.-C. C'est là que les Zoulous décident de s'installer et de construire leur pays selon leur tradition, en 1709. Les Zoulous doivent leur nom à Zoulou kaNtombhela, le fondateur et le chef de la tribu. [PARAGRAPH:2]Avant l'arrivée du grand guerrier Shaka Zoulou, né vers 1787, les Zoulous ne sont pas plus qu'une petite tribu quelconque parmi beaucoup d'autres. En grandissant, Shaka est exilé par son père et trouve alors refuge chez Dinguiswayo, le chef d'une tribu voisine. A la mort de son père vers 1816, Dinguiswayo aide Shaka à accéder au trône zoulou. [PARAGRAPH:2]Une fois au pouvoir, Shaka instaure une sorte de révolution militaire au sein des Zoulous, remplaçant le traditionnel "assegai" (une lance ressemblant à un javelot) par une lance coupante plus courte appelée "lklwa". Il équipe également ses guerriers d'un bouclier plus large qui couvre une grande partie du corps des soldats. Cette modification de l'armement zoulou traduit les innovations introduites par Shaka en matière de guerre. Alors que les combats précédents ont tendance à être des rituels, avec de nombreux chants et des lancers à distance qui ne conduisent pas à des résultats décisifs, Shaka apprend aux Zoulous à tuer. [PARAGRAPH:2]Sous le commandement de Shaka, les guerriers zoulous s'approchent de leur ennemis en rangs s'apparentant à des mêlées, leurs lances coupantes plus courtes étant alors plus efficaces que les armes de leurs opposants, qui doivent être lancées. Shaka apprend également à ses guerriers à combattre dans une nouvelle formation tactique appelée "tête de buffle". Dans cette formation, le centre de la ligne zoulou doit engager le combat avec les ennemis, pour les maintenir en position, tandis que les "cornes" de droite et de gauche avancent de manière à encercler leurs ennemis. Débordés sur la droite et la gauche et équipés d'armes moins sophistiquées, peu d'ennemis peuvent résister à l'assaut des Zoulous, ces derniers devenant bientôt la terreur des tribus voisines. [PARAGRAPH:2]En l'espace d'une décennie, Shaka constitue une armée de 50 000 guerriers, bat toutes les tribus environnantes et contrôle plus de la moitié des terres intérieures constituant aujourd'hui l'Afrique du Sud. Shaka crée une nouvelle capitale pour les Zoulous à Bulawayo, mais son arrogance et sa cruauté mécontentent fortement son peuple. En 1828, Shaka est assassiné par ses demi-frères Dingane et Mhlangana, puis Dingane tue Mhlangana et commence l'épuration de tous les chefs pro-Shaka se trouvant sous son contrôle. [PARAGRAPH:2]C'est dans ce chaos et cette violence que les colons européens apparaissent pour la première fois, dans les années 1830. La première colonisation européenne dans la région Zululand est la colonie britannique de Port Natal (aujourd'hui Durban). En 1837, un missionnaire britannique va vivre avec les Zoulous et est accepté par le roi Dingane. Cependant, à la même époque, un groupe de colons Boers, les "Voortrekkers" (ou pionniers) avancent vers le nord, au-delà de la rivière Orange, dans les territoires désormais abandonnés par les tribus fuyant les Zoulous. Dingane autorise les Voortrekkers à s'installer dans cette région mais, en 1838, suite à un malentendu ou à moins que Dingane ne l'ait planifié ainsi dès le début, les Zoulous attaquent les nouveaux arrivants. [PARAGRAPH:2]Cette attaque se révèle une immense erreur. Lors de la bataille de Blood River, les Zoulous sont bien plus nombreux que leurs opposants, disposant de 10 000 guerriers pour lutter contre 400 Boers. Cependant, contre toute attente, les Boers massacrent leurs opposants, leurs armes à feu leur offrant un avantage écrasant contre leurs ennemis brandissant leurs lances. Les Zoulous sont alors obligés d'accepter que les hommes blancs s'installent sur leur territoire, qui deviendra ensuite la République d'Utrecht. [PARAGRAPH:2]Après cette bataille, une paix difficile s'installe pendant une génération entre les Zoulous, les Britanniques et les Boers qui sont de plus en plus nombreux dans la région. Cependant, après la découverte de mines de diamants en Afrique du Sud, en 1878, les Britanniques se mettent à convoiter la terre des Zoulous et commencent à chercher des excuses pour attaquer et déplacer les indigènes. A la suite d'une petite querelle frontalière en 1878, les Britanniques déclarent la guerre et envahissent le Zululand sur trois fronts. [PARAGRAPH:2]Les guerriers zoulous combattent courageusement et réussissent à choquer les Européens en massacrant des forces britanniques à Isandlwana, mais les fusils britanniques et les mitrailleuses Maxim rendent la férocité des guerriers zoulous inutile et l'issue du conflit ne fait aucun doute. Les Zoulous sont vaincus et le Zululand est intégré à l'Afrique du Sud britannique. Le roi Cetshwayo est amené à Londres comme prisonnier d'honneur pour rencontrer la reine Victoria. Cependant, le reste de la nation ne s'en tire pas aussi bien et les Zoulous passent le siècle suivant sous la domination britannique et afrikaner, obligés de vivre suivant les lois racistes de l'apartheid, de l'Afrique du Sud. [PARAGRAPH:2]Toutefois, depuis la fin de l'apartheid dans les années 1990, les Zoulous bénéficient pleinement des droits liés à la citoyenneté sud-africaine. Le zoulou est la langue la plus parlée dans ce pays et avec plus de 11 millions de personnes, les Zoulous constituent le principal groupe ethnique de l'Afrique du Sud. [PARAGRAPH:2]</French>
		<German>Die Zulu sind ein heute in der östlichen Provinz Natal in Südafrika lebender Volkszweig der Nguni, der einen eigenen Bantu-Dialekt spricht. Die nomadischen Nguni aus dem Norden wanderten über fast tausend Jahre südwärts, bevor sie etwa 1700 n.Chr. in die Region des "White Umfolozi"-Flusses gelangten. Der Überlieferung zufolge beschlossen hier die Zulu im Jahr 1709, sesshaft zu werden. Ihr Name leitet sich von Zulu ka Ntombhela ab, dem Gründer und Häuptling des Stammes. Die Zulu lebten auf dem spärlich bewaldeten Wiesenland ihrer Heimat vom Hirseanbau und von riesigen Rinderherden. Traditionell wohnten sie in kuppelartigen Hütten, die kreisförmig in einem Kral angeordnet waren und in deren Mitte die Rinder gehalten wurden. Zu den handwerklichen Tätigkeiten der Zulu gehörte das Färben von Tierhäuten, die Eisenbearbeitung und die Korbflechterei.[PARAGRAPH:2]Zu dieser Zeit waren die Zulu nur ein unauffälliger kleiner Stamm unter vielen, aber ein Mann brachte ein neues Zeitalter: Shaka wurde als Sohn des Häuptlings Senzengakona und dessen Frau Nandi geboren, der Häuptlingstochter eines nahe gelegenen Stammes. Als Heranwachsender wurde Shaka von seinem Vater verbannt und fand eine Zuflucht bei Digiswayo, dem Häuptling eines Nachbarstammes, welchem er als Krieger diente. Als Shakas Vater etwa 1816 starb, konnte Shaka seine Nachfolge wiederum mithilfe von Digiswayo antreten und ließ dabei seinen Halbbruder zur Sicherheit ermorden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Als König der Zulu reorganisierte Shaka die Streitkräfte der Zulu in eine auf Eroberungen ausgelegte Kriegsmaschinerie mit neuer Bewaffnung und Taktik. Der traditionelle Wurfspeer "Assegai" wurde durch einen kürzeren Nahkampfspeer ersetzt, dem "lklwa". Weiterhin erhielten die Krieger einen größeren Schild, der nahezu den gesamten Körper abdecken konnte. Diese Änderung in der Bewaffnung ging mit taktischen Änderungen einher. Zuvor verliefen Kämpfe größtenteils ritualisiert, indem die feindlichen Truppen sich gegenüberstanden und lauthals sangen und auf ihre Schilde trommelten, während sie aufeinander Speere warfen. Eine Seite verließ schließlich der Mut, worauf sie sich zurückzog und der anderen Seite das Feld überließ. Es gab nur wenige Tote und selten entscheidende Schlachten.[PARAGRAPH:2]Shaka lernte die Zulu dagegen das effektive Töten. Unter seinem Kommando attackierten die Zulu-Krieger den Gegner im Nahkampf, in welchem die Kurzspeere deutlich effektiver als die Wurfspeere waren. Shaka führte weiterhin die "Büffelhorn"-Taktik ein, bei welcher der Feind in der Mitte attackiert und in Schach gehalten wurde, um dann von rechts und links über die Flanken eingeschlossen zu werden. Weiterhin führte Shaka als "Impi" bezeichnete Regimenter ein, deren Einheiten nach Altersstufen organisiert waren, in denen die männliche Jugend in die militärische Gesellschaft hineinwuchs und ausgebildet wurde. Die Einheiten waren in Kasernen stationiert und unterstanden direkt dem König, den Männern einer Einheit wurde nur im Kollektiv die Erlaubnis geteilt, den Militärdienst zu verlassen und zu heiraten. Die Heirat wurde als Belohnung für Tapferkeit im Kampf gewährt. Wer zurückwich oder ohne Beute heimkehrte, wurde hingerichtet.[PARAGRAPH:2]Mithilfe seiner nahezu unbesiegbaren Truppen dehnte Shaka seine Schreckensherrschaft über die ahnungslosen Nachbarstämme Südafrikas aus. Zu Beginn konnte er nur ein sehr begrenztes Truppenkontingent ins Feld führen. Durch geschickte Diplomatie und durchdachte Attentate schuf er sich aber bald Allianzen und Vasallen, und konnte so seine Herrschaft über ein großes Gebiet ausdehnen und damit sehr schnell seine Truppenstärke erhöhen. Wer sich ihm in den Weg stellte, wurde gnadenlos abgeschlachtet. Durch seine blutigen Eroberungszüge löste Shaka enorme Flüchtlingswellen aus, die Völkerwanderungen gleichkamen und als "Mfecane" (Die Verstreuung) bekannt wurden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Shaka gründete eine neue Zulu-Hauptstadt bei Bulaweyo, aber als Regierungschef erwies sich der überaus erfolgreiche Feldherr als weitaus weniger erfolgreich. Seine Grausamkeiten führte zu wachsender Unzufriedenheit unter seinen Leuten, und es wurden zahlreiche erfolglose Attentats- und Putschversuche unternommen. Zweifel an der geistigen Gesundheit Shakas erhärteten sich, als dieser 1827 beim Tod seiner Mutter angeblich Hunderte von Menschen hinrichten ließ, die in seinen Augen nicht genug Trauer zeigten. Im Jahr 1828 wurde Shaka schließlich von seinen Halbbrüdern Dingane und Mhlangana ermordet. Sterbend soll er ihnen prophezeit haben, dass ihre Herrschaft nicht von lange Dauer sein sollte und die Weißen sich des Landes bemächtigen würden. Dingane tötete sofort danach auch Mhlangana und begann eine Säuberungsaktion unter den shakatreuen Ältesten.[PARAGRAPH:2]In dieser Zeit des Chaos und der Gewalttätigkeit erschienen die ersten europäischen Siedler in den 30er Jahren des 19. Jahrhunderts. Die erste europäische Niederlassung war die britische Kolonie Port Natal (heute Durban). Ein englischer Missionar lebte ab 1837 bei den Zulu und wurde von König Dingane toleriert. Zu dieser Zeit zogen die "Buren" als Siedler niederländischer Abstammung zu Tausenden im "Großen Treck" nach Norden, um den Briten am südafrikanischen Kap zu entkommen. König Dingan wurde 1837 von "Voortrekker" (Pionier) Piet Retief im Namen der Buren um Siedlungsland gebeten. Nach einem Loyalitätsbeweis erhielt Retief für die Buren die Erlaubnis, sich in Zululand anzusiedeln. Dingan sah sich aber durch die bereits vorrückenden Massen von Retief hintergangen und ließ ihn und seine Männer ermorden; im Gegenzug metzelten die Buren trotz zahlenmäßiger Unterlegenheit mit ihren überlegenen Schusswaffen am "Blood River" 3000 Zulus nieder. Nach dieser Niederlage liefen einige von Dingans Anhängern zu seinem Bruder Mpande über, der sich 1839 mit den Buren zusammenschloss und Dingan stürzte. Die Buren gründeten nun die neue Republik von Utrecht.[PARAGRAPH:2]Unter König Mpande breiteten sich die Buren weiter aus. 1843 marschierten die Briten in Natal ein und annektierten es. 1878 wurden riesige Diamantenvorkommen in Südafrika entdeckt, und die Briten schickten sich an, das gesamte Land zu unterwerfen. Unter König Cetshwayo, der als Sohn Mpandes 1872 an die Macht gelangt war und noch über ein großes Gebiet in Transvaal herrschte, weigerten sich die Zulu, die Impi aufzulösen und sich den Briten zu unterwerfen. Nach einem geringfügigen Grenzstreit erklärte die Briten daraufhin den Zulu den Krieg und drangen an drei Fronten ein. Die Zulukrieger kämpften tapfer, und zum Schock vieler Europäer wurde eine britische Einheit bei Isandlwana vernichtet. Letztlich hatten die Zulu den britische Feuerwaffen und ersten Maschinengewehren von Typ Maxim aber selbst mit den wildesten Kriegern nichts entgegen zu setzen. Die Zulu wurde unterworfen und ihr König Cetshwayo wurde als Gefangener nach London vor Königin Viktoria gebracht.[PARAGRAPH:2]1887 wurde Zululand zur britischen Kronkolonie unter der Gesetzgebung der Kolonie Natal. 1894 wurden zwei Drittel des Zululands konfisziert und die Bewohner in Reservationen verbannt. Zwei blutige Rebellionen der Zulu wurden 1888 und 1906 niedergeschlagen. 1897 wurde Zululand endgültig Teil der Kolonie Natal. 1902 gingen die Briten als Sieger aus einem Krieg gegen die Buren hervor, Transvaal und der Oranje-Freistaat wurden ebenfalls britische Kronkolonien. 1910 beschloss das britische Parlament die Gründung der Südafrikanischen Union. 1912 schlossen sich, insbesondere als Reaktion auf die Aneignung von Gebieten der Schwarzafrikaner, schwarze Afrikaner zu einer Organisation zusammen, aus welcher der Afrikanische Nationalkongress (ANC) hervorging.[PARAGRAPH:2]Unter der südafrikanischen Politik der Apartheid wurden die Schwarzen ab 1948 wirtschaftlich, politisch, räumlich und sozial ausgegrenzt. Der Widerstand der Schwarzen begann gewaltfrei, führte dann aber zu zahlreichen blutigen Auseinandersetzungen,1960 rief die Regierung den Notstand aus; Tausende von Schwarzen wurden verhaftet und politische Parteien wie der ANC und der Panafrikanische Kongress wurden verboten. 1970 wurde für die Zulu eine Region namens Kwa Zulu auf historischem Zululand eingerichtet ("Schwarzer Staat"). Die 1922 gegründete und 1975 wieder ins Leben gerufene Freiheitspartei Inkatha, der vor allem Zulu angehören, spielte bei der politischen Neustrukturierung Südafrikas eine entscheidende Rolle. Zwischen ihr und dem Afrikanischen Nationalkongreß (ANC) kam es dabei immer wieder zu blutigen Kämpfen. Nach Abschaffung der Apartheid im Jahr 1994 schlossen sich Kwa Zulu und die Provinz Natal zur Provinz Kwa Zulu/Natal zusammen. Die Zulu sind mit über 11 Millionen Menschen die bevölkerungsreichste ethnische Gruppe in Südafrika, und Zulu ist die vorherrschende Sprache. Die Zulu besitzen volle Staatsbürgerschaftsrechte und viele arbeiten als Lohnarbeiter in landwirtschaftlichen Betrieben, Fabriken und Bergwerken, die allerdings oft in Besitz weißer Südafrikaner sind.</German>
		<Italian>Gli Zulu discendono da un gruppo di popoli chiamati Nguni, un sottogruppo della famiglia linguistica Bantu. Gli Nguni migrarono verso sud per circa mille anni prima di raggiungere il fiume Umfolozi Bianco intorno al 1700 d.C.. Fu lì che gli Zulu decisero di insediarsi e di fissare dimora (tradizionalmente, si riporta la data del 1709). Gli Zulu prendono il nome da Zulu Kantombhela, il fondatore e capo della tribù. [PARAGRAPH:2]Gli Zulu non furono che una piccola, irrilevante tribù come le altre fino all'avvento del grande guerriero Shaka Zulu, nato intorno al 1787. Da ragazzo egli venne esiliato dal padre e trovò rifugio presso Digiswayo, capo di una tribù vicina. Quando il padre morì, intorno al 1816, Digiswayo aiutò Shaka a succedergli al trono degli Zulu. [PARAGRAPH:2]Una volta al potere, Shaka diede vita a una sorta di rivoluzione militare tra gli Zulu, sostituendo il tradizionale "assegai" (una lancia simile al giavellotto) con il "iklwa", una lancia più corta e adatta per il corpo a corpo, e introdusse l'utilizzo di uno scudo più grande, che copriva quasi tutto il corpo. A queste modifiche nell'equipaggiamento corrisposero modifiche nelle tecniche di guerra: mentre fino ad allora le battaglie avevano avuto una natura più che altro cerimoniale (si intonavano canti di guerra e si scagliavano le lance dalla distanza) portando quindi a ben poco, Shaka insegnò agli Zulu come uccidere. [PARAGRAPH:2]Sotto il comando di Shaka, i guerrieri Zulu infatti si avvicinarono ai nemici e sfruttarono la maggior efficacia delle proprie armi nel corpo a corpo rispetto ai giavellotti avversari. Shaka inoltre insegnò ai suoi guerrieri a combattere secondo una nuova formazione tattica a "corna di bufalo": il centro della linea degli Zulu ingaggiava il nemico per trattenerlo, mentre i "corni" laterali lo avrebbero affiancato e circondato. Questa manovra, unita alla superiorità delle armi impiegate, rese gli assalti degli Zulu inarrestabili; gli Zulu diventarono il terrore delle tribù vicine. [PARAGRAPH:2]Nel giro di un decennio, Shaka aveva creato un esercito di 50.000 uomini, sconfitto tutte le tribù circostanti e conquistato buona parte di quello che oggi è l'entroterra del Sud Africa e fissò la capitale a Bulaweyo. La sua arroganza e crudeltà gli costarono però l'insoddisfazione del suo popolo: nel 1828 Shaka fu assassinato dai suoi fratellastri Dingane e Mhlangana. Dingane poi uccise anche Mhlangana e iniziò la purga dei capi militari che avevano appoggiato Shaka. [PARAGRAPH:2]Fu questo scenario di caos e violenza che incontrarono i coloni europei quando misero piede in quei territori verso il 1830. Il primo insediamento europeo nella regione dello Zululand fu l'inglese Port Natal (l'odierna Durban). Nel 1837 tra gli Zulu andò a vivere un missionario inglese, che venne tollerato dal re Dingane. Tuttavia in quello stesso periodo un gruppo di coloni boeri noti come "voortrekkers" (o pionieri) stava attraversando a nord il fiume Orange per stabilirsi nelle terre che erano state abbandonate dalle tribù in fuga dagli Zulu. Era stato Dingane a dare ai voortrekker il permesso di insediarsi nell'area, ma nel 1838, o per un'incomprensione o perché quello era stato il piano di Dingane sin dall'inizio, gli Zulu attaccarono i pionieri. [PARAGRAPH:2]Questo si rivelò essere un grosso errore. Nella battaglia del Fiume di Sangue gli Zulu superavano largamente i nemici per numero (10.000 contro 400), ma nonostante ciò i Boeri li massacrarono grazie all'impiego delle armi da fuoco contro le mere lance da combattimento. Gli Zulu furono perciò costretti a permettere agli uomini bianchi di insediarsi nei propri territori, che presero il nome della Repubblica di Utrecht. [PARAGRAPH:2]Dopo quella battaglia, vi fu una generazione di pace instabile tra gli Zulu e i Boeri e i Britannici, sempre più presenti nella regione, ma dopo la scoperta delle miniere di diamanti in Sud Africa del 1878, nei Britannici crebbe l'interesse per quelle terre, tanto da cercare una scusa per attaccare i nativi e occupare la regione. I Britannici dichiararono guerra agli Zulu nel 1878 per via di una piccola disputa territoriale e invasero Zululand da tre fronti. [PARAGRAPH:2]I guerrieri Zulu combatterono valorosamente (e, per lo stupore degli Europei, riuscirono a massacrare un gruppo di Britannici a Isandlwana), ma le armi da fuoco britanniche ebbero la meglio sulla loro ferocia e l'esito della guerra non fu mai messo in dubbio: gli Zulu vennero sconfitti e Zululand venne incorporato nel Sud Africa britannico. Il re Cetshwayo fu portato a Londra per parlare con la regina Vittoria quale prigioniero d'onore, ma ai suoi sudditi toccò una sorte peggiore. Gli Zulu vissero il secolo successivo sotto il dominio dei Britannici e degli Afrikaan, subendo le leggi razziste dell'apartheid sudafricano. [PARAGRAPH:2]Dopo la caduta dell'apartheid negli anni '90 del secolo scorso, oggi anche i discendenti degli Zulu possono godere della piena cittadinanza in Sud Africa. Lo Zulu è la lingua più parlata nel Paese e con i suoi 11 milioni di individui quello degli Zulu è il più numeroso gruppo etnico del Sud Africa. [PARAGRAPH:2]</Italian>
		<Spanish>Los zulúes provenían de un grupo de pueblos conocidos como los nguni, un subgrupo lingüístico de la familia de las lenguas bantúes. Los nguni habían estado casi un milenio migrando en dirección al sur antes de llegar a la región del río Umfolozi (alrededor del 1700 d. C.) Fue allí donde los zulúes decidieron asentarse, en 1709 según la tradición. Deben su nombre a Zulu kaNtombhela, fundador y jefe de la tribu. [PARAGRAPH:2]Sin embargo, solo fueron una más de las numerosas tribus de la zona hasta la llegada del gran guerrero Chaka Zulú, nacido en torno a 1787. En su adolescencia, Chaka fue exiliado por su padre y acogido por Digiswayo, el jefe de una tribu vecina. A la muerte del padre (alrededor de 1816), Digiswayo lo ayudó a hacerse con el trono de los zulúes. [PARAGRAPH:2]Una vez en el poder, Chaka instituyó una especie de revolución militar entre los zulúes. Reemplazó la "assegai" tradicional (una lanza arrojadiza parecida a una jabalina) por un venablo más corto y manejable llamado "iklwa". Además, equipó a sus guerreros con un gran escudo que les cubría la mayor parte del cuerpo. Este cambio en el armamento de los zulúes era el reflejo de las innovaciones introducidas por Chaka en el arte de la guerra. Hasta entonces, las batallas habían sido acontecimientos casi rituales en los que abundaban los cantos y el lanzamiento de jabalinas desde lejos sin que se produjeran desenlaces decisivos, pero Chaka enseñó a los zulúes a matar. [PARAGRAPH:2]Bajo su mando, sus guerreros se acostumbraron a luchar cuerpo a cuerpo, donde sus lanzas cortas eran mucho más eficaces que las armas arrojadizas de sus enemigos. Además, enseñó a sus guerreros a utilizar una nueva formación táctica conocida como "los cuernos del búfalo". En esta formación, el centro de la línea zulú trababa batalla con el enemigo para mantenerlo en posición mientras los "cuernos" derecho e izquierdo avanzaban para envolverlo. Rodeados por ambos flancos y equipados con un armamento inferior, pocos enemigos podían hacer frente a los zulúes; al cabo de poco tiempo, eran el terror de las tribus circundantes. [PARAGRAPH:2]En menos de una década, Chaka había acumulado un ejército de cincuenta mil hombres, derrotado a todas las tribus cercanas y apoderado de la parte interior de lo que hoy en día es Sudáfrica. Fundó una nueva capital para los zulúes en Bulaweyo, pero su arrogancia y crueldad provocaron el descontento de su pueblo. En 1828, fue asesinado por sus hermanastros Dingane y Mhlangana. A continuación, Dingane asesinó a Mhlangana e inició una purga de los caudillos partidarios de Chaka. [PARAGRAPH:2]Fue este cuadro de caos y violencia el que se encontraron los colonizadores europeos a su llegada a la región en la década de 1830. El primer asentamiento europeo en la región de Zululandia fue la colonia británica de Port Natal (la actual Durbar). Un misionero inglés se estableció entre los zulúes en 1837 con el permiso del rey Dingane. Sin embargo, al mismo tiempo, un grupo de colonizadores bóers conocidos como los "voortrekkers" (o pioneros) avanzaban hacia el norte por el río Orange, en dirección a las tierras que habían sido abandonadas por las tribus que huían de los zulúes. Dingane les había dado permiso para establecerse en la zona, pero, en 1838, bien como consecuencia de un malentendido o bien porque Dingane lo hubiera planeado así desde el principio, los zulúes atacaron a los recién llegados. [PARAGRAPH:2]Fue un terrible error. En la batalla del río Blood, los zulúes opusieron diez mil guerreros a cuatrocientos bóers. Sin embargo, a pesar de este desequilibrio de fuerzas, los bóers, que contaban con la abrumadora ventaja de las armas de fuego, masacraron a sus adversarios, armados solo con lanzas. Los zulúes se vieron obligados a permitir que los blancos se establecieran en su territorio, que a partir de entonces pasaría a llamarse República de Utrecht. [PARAGRAPH:2]Tras esta batalla, hubo una década de paz inestable entre los zulúes y la creciente comunidad británica y bóer de la región. Sin embargo, tras el descubrimiento de las minas de diamantes de Sudáfrica (1878), los británicos empezaron a mirar con ojos codiciosos las tierras zulúes y a buscar una excusa para atacar a los nativos y expulsarlos de ellas. Con el pretexto de una insignificante disputa fronteriza ocurrida en 1878, los británicos declararon la guerra e invadieron Zululandia por tres frentes. [PARAGRAPH:2]Los guerreros zulúes lucharon con valentía (y, para asombro de los europeos, lograron masacrar un contingente británico en Isandlwana), pero los rifles y las ametralladoras Maxim de los ingleses convirtieron la ferocidad de los guerreros zulúes en irrelevante y llevaron a la guerra a su conclusión inevitable. Los zulúes fueron derrotados y Zululandia se incorporó a la Sudáfrica británica. El rey Cetshwayo, llevado a Inglaterra como prisionero para conocer a la reina Victoria, fue tratado con todos los honores. Sin embargo, al resto de su nación no le fue tan bien, y los zulúes pasaron el siglo siguiente bajo el dominio de los británicos y los afrikaners, obligados a vivir bajo las leyes discriminatorias de Sudáfrica. [PARAGRAPH:2]No obstante, tras la caída del apartheid en la década de 1990, los zulúes de nuestros días disfrutan de plenos derechos civiles en Sudáfrica. El zulú es la lengua más hablada del país y, con más de once millones de personas, los zulúes forman el grupo étnico más importante de Sudáfrica. [PARAGRAPH:2]</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>