<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_NIKITA_KHRUSHCHEV_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Nikita Khrushchev[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Russian politician who led the Soviet Union during part of the Cold War. He served as First Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union from 1953 to 1964. Khrushchev was responsible for the de-Stalinization of the Soviet Union, for backing the progress of the early Soviet space program, and for several relatively liberal reforms in areas of domestic policy.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Nikita Chruszczow[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Radziecki polityk, działacz partyjny i państwowy, I sekretarz KC Komunistycznej Partii Związku Radzieckiego (KPZR) w latach 1953-1964 i premier ZSRR w latach 1958-1964.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_JAMES_MADISON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]James Madison[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an American statesman, political theorist. He was the fourth President of the United States (1809-17). He is hailed as the "Father of the Constitution" for being instrumental in the drafting of the U.S. Constitution and as the key champion and author of the Bill of Rights. He served as a politician much of his adult life.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]James Madison[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Amerykański polityk i prawnik; 4. prezydent USA (1809-1817), wcześniej członek Izby Reprezentantów (1789-1797) i 5. sekretarz stanu USA (1801-1809). Sygnatariusz Konstytucji Stanów Zjednoczonych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_JOSEPH_STALIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Joseph Stalin[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was the leader of the Soviet Union from the mid-1920s until his death in 1953. Holding the post of the General Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, he was effectively the dictator of the state.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Józef Stalin[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Radziecki polityk pochodzenia gruzińskiego, formalnie pełniący obieralne, kadencyjne funkcje sekretarza generalnego KPZR i jej poprzedniczek oraz premiera ZSRR, a faktycznie dożywotni dyktator Związku Radzieckiego, posiadający nieograniczoną władzę. Jako metodę rządzenia stosował masowy, państwowy wewnętrzny i zewnętrzny terror, który pochłonął, według różnych ocen, od kilku do kilkudziesięciu milionów ofiar śmiertelnych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_EMPEROR_AKIHITO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Emperor Akihito[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Is the reigning Emperor of Japan, the 125th Emperor of his line according to Japan's traditional order of succession. He acceded to the Chrysanthemum Throne on 7 January 1989. Despite being strictly constrained by his constitutional position, he also issued several wide-ranging statements of remorse to Asian countries, for their suffering under Japanese occupation.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Cesarz Akihito[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Cesarz, głowa państwa Japonii. Jego rola i obowiązki zostały określone w rozdziale I Konstytucji. 7 stycznia 1989 zmarł cesarz Hirohito i Akihito został 125. cesarzem Japonii, kontynuatorem nieprzerwanej od setek lat dynastii. Ceremonia intronizacji Akihito odbyła się w Tokio 12 listopada 1990. Nowy cesarz ogłosił okres swego panowania erą Heisei, czyli budowaniem pokoju.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_VLADIMIR_LENIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Vladimir Lenin[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Russian communist revolutionary, politician, and political theorist. Under his administration, Russia and then the wider Soviet Union became a one-party communist state governed by the Russian Communist Party. Ideologically a Marxist, his political theories are known as Leninism.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Włodzimierz Lenin[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Rosyjski polityk, organizator i przywódca rewolucji październikowej, a następnie pierwszy przywódca Rosji Radzieckiej. Współzałożyciel i lider partii bolszewickiej. Teoretyk ideologii komunizmu i twórca idei leninizmu.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_AARON_BURR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Aaron Burr[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an American politician. He was the third Vice President of the United States (1801-1805); he served during President Thomas Jefferson's first term. He was elected twice to the New York State Assembly (1784-1785, 1798-1799), was appointed New York State Attorney General (1789-1791), was chosen as a United States Senator (1791-1797) from the state of New York, and reached the apex of his career as vice president.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Aaron Burr[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Amerykański polityk, 3. wiceprezydent Stanów Zjednoczonych. Jego ojciec, także Aaron, był współzałożycielem Uniwersytetu Princeton. Dziadek ze strony matki Jonathan Edwards był amerykańskim teologiem protestanckim. W czasie kampanii prezydenckiej w 1836 przeciwnicy polityczni przyszłego prezydenta, Martina Van Burena, rozgłaszali plotki, że jest nieślubnym synem Aarona Burra.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_THOMAS_JEFFERSON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Thomas Jefferson[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an American Founding Father who was principal author of the Declaration of Independence (1776). He was elected the second Vice President of the United States (1797-1801) and the third President (1801-1809). Primarily of English ancestry, he was born and educated in Virginia. He graduated from the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg and practiced colonial law.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Thomas Jefferson[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Amerykański prawnik, działacz niepodległościowy, archeolog, architekt, trzeci prezydent USA (1801-1809), jeden z autorów Deklaracji niepodległości Stanów Zjednoczonych, założyciel stanowego Uniwersytetu Wirginii. Na emeryturze zajmował się pisaniem i badaniami naukowymi. Ponadto aktywnie doradzał swoim następcom i przyjaciołom.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_ALEXANDER_HAMILTON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Alexander Hamilton[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Founding Father of the United States, chief staff aide to General George Washington, one of the most influential interpreters and promoters of the U.S. Constitution, the founder of the nation's financial system, the founder of the Federalist Party, the world's first voter-based political party, the Father of the United States Coast Guard, and the founder of The New York Post. </English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Alexander Hamilton[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Amerykański polityk, przywódca Federalistów, twórca dolara amerykańskiego, jeden z ojców założycieli Stanów Zjednoczonych Ameryki. Najprawdopodobniej dzięki protekcji Roberta Morrisa, 11 września 1789, Hamilton został powołany na stanowisko sekretarza skarbu w gabinecie prezydenta Washingtona. </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_NELSON_MANDELA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Nelson Mandela[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a South African anti-apartheid revolutionary, politician, and philanthropist, who served as President of South Africa from 1994 to 1999. He was the country's first black chief executive, and the first elected in a fully representative democratic election. His government focused on dismantling the legacy of apartheid through tackling institutionalised racism and fostering racial reconciliation. </English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Nelson Mandela[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Południowoafrykański polityk, prezydent Republiki Południowej Afryki w latach 1994-1999, jeden z przywódców ruchu przeciw apartheidowi, działacz na rzecz praw człowieka, mąż stanu, laureat pokojowej nagrody Nobla. W Republice Południowej Afryki nazywany również "Madiba" (nazwa jednego z klanów ludu Xhosa), a także "tata", co często rozpisywano jako: "Ojciec Narodu". Był zarówno najstarszym (złożył urząd w wieku 81 lat), jak i najdłużej żyjącym prezydentem RPA (zmarł mając 95 lat).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_MARTIN_VAN_BUREN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Martin Van Buren[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an American politician who served as the eighth President of the United States (1837-1841). A member of the Democratic Party, he served in a number of senior roles, including eighth Vice President (1833-1837) and Secretary of State (1829-1831), both under Andrew Jackson. Van Buren's inability as president to deal with the economic chaos of the Panic of 1837 and with the surging Whig Party led to his defeat in the 1840 election.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Martin Van Buren[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Był ósmym prezydentem USA (1837-1841). Pełnił także funkcję wiceprezydenta (1833-1837) i sekretarza stanu (1829-1831). W 1812 Van Buren został wybrany do stanowego Senatu nowojorskiego i pełnił tę funkcję przez dwie kadencje, do roku 1820, a w czasie drugiej z nich był także stanowym prokuratorem generalnym.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_ROBERT_LIVINGSTON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Robert Livingston[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an American lawyer, politician, diplomat from New York, and a Founding Father of the United States. He was known as "The Chancellor", after the high New York state legal office he held for 25 years. Livingston was appointed Recorder of New York City in October 1773, but soon identified himself with the anti-colonial Whig Party and was replaced a few months later with John Watts, Jr. He was a member of the Committee of Five that drafted the Declaration of Independence, although he was recalled by his state before he could sign the final version of the document.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Robert Livingston[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Amerykański prawnik, polityk i dyplomata. Jeden z twórców Deklaracji Niepodległości i Ojców założycieli Stanów Zjednoczonych. W 1805 Livingston przeszedł na emeryturę. Zajął się wówczas konstrukcją pierwszego statku parowego, który zbudował wraz z Robertem Fultonem. Pierwszy rejs parowca odbył się w 1807 roku roku na rzece Hudson. Robert Livingston zmarł 26 lutego 1813 w Clermont.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_DR._HENRY_KISSINGER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Dr. Henry Kissinger[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Is an American diplomat and political scientist. He served as National Security Advisor and later concurrently as United States Secretary of State in the administrations of Presidents Richard Nixon and Gerald Ford. For his actions negotiating the ceasefire in Vietnam (though never realised), Kissinger received the 1973 Nobel Peace Prize under controversial circumstances,with two members of the committee resigning in protest.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Dr. Henry Kissinger[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Amerykański polityk pochodzenia niemieckiego, dyplomata, laureat Pokojowej Nagrody Nobla 1973. Uważany za jednego z głównych architektów światowej polityki odprężenia (obok m.in. Richarda Nixona, Charles'a de Gaulle'a czy Willy'ego Brandta), dzięki której w dużej mierze zakończono zimną wojnę. Współodpowiedzialny za obalenie z pomocą USA demokratycznie wybranego prezydenta Chile Salvadora Allendego i dojście do władzy junty generała Augusto Pinocheta.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_JOHN_QUINCY_ADAMS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]John Quincy Adams[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an American statesman who served as the sixth President of the United States from 1825 to 1829. He also served as a diplomat, a Senator and member of the House of Representatives. He was a member of the Federalist, Democratic-Republican, National Republican, and later Anti-Masonic and Whig parties.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]John Quincy Adams[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Amerykański prawnik, dyplomata i polityk; ambasador do kilku krajów europejskich, senator, sekretarz stanu, szósty prezydent USA (1825-1829), a także członek Izby Reprezentantów USA. W latach 1803-1808 pełnił rolę senatora USA 1. klasy z Massachusetts. Po rezygnacji z mandatu (na skutek sporu z własnym ugrupowaniem), powrócił do zawodu prawnika i został wykładowcą na Harvardzie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_HAROLD_MACMILLAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Harold Macmillan[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a British Conservative politician and statesman who served as the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 10 January 1957 to 18 October 1963, nicknamed "Supermac" and known for his pragmatism, wit and unflappability. Macmillan served in the Grenadier Guards during the First World War. He was wounded three times, most severely in September 1916 during the Battle of the Somme.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Harold Macmillan[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Polityk brytyjski. Czasami zwany "Supermac" lub "Mac the Knife". Polityk Partii Konserwatywnej. W latach 1957-1963 lider tejże partii oraz premier kraju. Wcześniej minister obrony, spraw zagranicznych, oraz Kanclerz Skarbu. Politykę zagraniczną i obronną opierał na przywróceniu dobrych stosunków ze Stanami Zjednoczonymi i budowie brytyjskich sił jądrowych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_JOHN_F._KENNEDY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]John F. Kennedy[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an American politician who served as the 35th President of the United States from January 1961 until his assassination in November 1963. The Cuban Missile Crisis, The Bay of Pigs Invasion, the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty, the establishment of the Peace Corps, developments in the Space Race, the building of the Berlin Wall, the Civil Rights Movement, the "New Frontier" domestic program, abolition of the federal death penalty in the District of Columbia, and increased U.S. involvement in the Vietnam War all took place during his presidency.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]John F. Kennedy[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]35. prezydent Stanów Zjednoczonych, zginął w zamachu. Zwiększył zaangażowanie w wojnę w Wietnamie. Za jego prezydentury liczba żołnierzy amerykańskich wysłanych do Wietnamu Południowego zwiększyła się z 800 do 16 300. Historycy spierają się, czy kontynuowałby tę politykę w przypadku reelekcji. </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_MIKHAIL_GORBACHEV_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Mikhail Gorbachev[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Is a former Soviet statesman. He was the eighth and last leader of the Soviet Union, having served as General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union from 1985 until 1991 when the party was dissolved. He served as the country's head of state from 1988 until its dissolution in 1991 (titled as Chairman of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet from 1988 to 1989, as Chairman of the Supreme Soviet from 1989 to 1990, and as President of the Soviet Union from 1990 to 1991). He was the only general secretary in the history of the Soviet Union to have been born after the October Revolution.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Michaił Gorbaczow[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Radziecki i rosyjski polityk, ostatni przywódca Komunistycznej Partii Związku Radzieckiego (KPZR) i jedyny prezydent ZSRR, laureat Pokojowej Nagrody Nobla. Po śmierci Andropowa w 1984 mianowany sekretarzem ds. ideologii, pełnił de facto rolę drugiego człowieka w partii po Czernience. W związku ze złym stanem zdrowia Czernienki, często zastępował go w roli prowadzącego obrady Biura Politycznego i Sekretariatu KC.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_MARGARET_THATCHER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Margaret Thatcher[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a British politician, who was the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 1979 to 1990, and the Leader of the Conservative Party from 1975 to 1990. She was the longest-serving British Prime Minister of the 20th century and is currently the only woman to have held the office. A Soviet journalist dubbed her the "Iron Lady", a nickname that became associated with her uncompromising politics and leadership style. As Prime Minister, she implemented policies that have come to be known as Thatcherism.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Margaret Thatcher[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Brytyjska polityk, premier Wielkiej Brytanii w latach 1979-1990, chemiczka, prawniczka. Stanowczość w stosunku do strajkujących górników oraz do państw bloku wschodniego spowodowała nadanie jej przydomku Zelaznej Damy (Iron Lady). Liberalną politykę gospodarczą jej gabinetu ochrzczono mianem taczeryzmu. Jedna z czołowych eurosceptyczek, zwolenniczka ograniczonej integracji europejskiej.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_LEON_TROTSKY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Leon Trotsky[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Marxist revolutionary and theorist, Soviet politician, and the founding leader of the Red Army. Trotsky initially supported the Menshevik Internationalists faction of the Russian Social Democratic Labour Party. He joined the Bolsheviks immediately prior to the 1917 October Revolution, and eventually became a leader within the Communist Party. He was one of the seven members of the first Politburo, founded in 1917 in order to manage the Bolshevik Revolution.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Leon Trocki[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Rewolucjonista rosyjski, socjaldemokrata i komunista. Jeden z twórców i przywódców RFSRR i ZSRR. Przewodniczący Piotrogrodzkiej Rady Delegatów Robotniczych w czasie rewolucji 1905 roku i Piotrogrodzkiej Rady Delegatów Robotniczych i Zołnierskich po rewolucji lutowej i obaleniu caratu. Przewodniczący Komitetu Wojskowo-Rewolucyjnego przy Radzie Delegatów, faktycznie kierujący przejęciem władzy przez bolszewików w Piotrogrodzie (listopad 1917).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_EMILIANO_ZAPATA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Emiliano Zapata[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a leading figure in the Mexican Revolution, the main leader of the peasant revolution in the state of Morelos, and the inspiration of the agrarian movement called Zapatismo. Zapata remains an iconic figure in Mexico, used both as a nationalist symbol as well as a symbol of the neo-Zapatista movement.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Emiliano Zapata[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Meksykański rewolucjonista. Przywódca chłopskiej partyzantki w czasie rewolucji meksykańskiej (1911-1917). W czasie działań partyzanckich, Zapata rozdzielał pomiędzy chłopów posiadłości obszarników, często przy tym palił zdobyte hacjendy, bez żadnych odszkodowań. Członkowie jego oddziałów wykonywali egzekucje na tych wszystkich, którzy sprzeciwiali się żądaniom Zapaty. </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_RONALD_REAGAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Ronald Reagan[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an American politician and actor, who served as the 40th President of the United States from 1981 to 1989. Prior to his presidency, he served as the 33rd Governor of California from 1967 to 1975, following a career as an actor and union leader in Hollywood. Leaving office in 1989, Reagan held an approval rating of sixty-eight percent, matching those of Franklin D. Roosevelt, and later Bill Clinton, as the highest ratings for departing presidents in the modern era.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Ronald Reagan[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]40. prezydent USA (1981-1989) oraz 33. gubernator Kalifornii. Jako przywódca USA udzielił znaczącej pomocy "Solidarności" w walce o obalenie komunizmu w Polsce i Europie. Dwukrotnie - w latach 1980 i 1983 (wspólnie z Jurijem Andropowem) zdobył tytuł Człowieka Roku magazynu "Time". Przed rozpoczęciem kariery politycznej Reagan zajmował się również aktorstwem filmowym.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_QIN_SHI_HUANG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Qin Shi Huang[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was the king of the state of Qin (r. 246-221 BC) who conquered all other Warring States and eventually unified China in 221 BC. Rather than maintain the title of "king" borne by the previous Shang and Zhou rulers, he ruled as the First Emperor of the Qin dynasty from 220 to 210 BC. His self-invented title "emperor" would continue to be borne by Chinese rulers for the next two millennia. During his reign, his generals greatly expanded the size of the Chinese state.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Qin Shi Huang[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Pierwszy władca Cesarstwa Chińskiego, który w 221 r. p.n.e. zjednoczył tzw. Walczące Królestwa na terenie ówczesnych Chin drogą podboju. Karierę polityczną zaczął w wieku 13 lat, wstępując na tron państwa Qin. W ciągu następnych lat armia Qinu podbiła sześć innych państw, kończąc Okres Walczących Królestw. Zjednoczenie przesądziło o losach Chin, które do dziś pozostają jednym państwem, choć rozmiarami dorównują kontynentowi europejskiemu i są bardzo zróżnicowane językowo oraz etnicznie.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_MAO_ZEDONG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Mao Zedong[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Chinese Communist revolutionary and the founding father of the People's Republic of China, which he governed as Chairman of the Communist Party of China from its establishment in 1949 until his death in 1976. His Marxist-Leninist theories, military strategies, and political policies are collectively known as Marxism-Leninism-Maoism or Mao Zedong Thought.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Mao Zedong[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Chiński polityk, przywódca kraju w latach 1949-1976, od 1943 r. szef biura politycznego oraz Przewodniczący Komitetu Politycznego Komunistycznej Partii Chin (aż do śmierci). Ideolog maoizmu. U schyłku życia doprowadził do ocieplenia stosunków ze Stanami Zjednoczonymi.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_PANCHO_VILLA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Pancho Villa[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Mexican Revolutionary general and one of the most prominent figures of the Mexican Revolution. Villa was in alliance with southern revolutionary Emiliano Zapata, who remained fighting in his own region of Morelos; however, the two revolutionary generals briefly came together to take Mexico City after Carranza's forces retreated from it. Later, Villa's heretofore undefeated División del Norte engaged the military forces of Carranza under Carrancista general Álvaro Obregón and was defeated in the 1915 Battle of Celaya. Villa's army then collapsed as a significant military force</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Pancho Villa[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Meksykański przywódca partyzantki chłopskiej, generał z okresu rewolucji meksykańskiej. Przeciwnik reżimów Porfirio Diaza i Victoriano Huerty. Villa i jego zwolennicy w swojej walce posługiwali się szeroko zakrojoną propagandą, na której cele między innymi wywłaszczali wielkich właścicieli ziemskich i rozdzielali zdobytą w ten sposób ziemię pomiędzy chłopów, aby zdobyć sobie ich przychylność. Ich łupem padały liczne pociągi, ponadto villiści drukowali własne pieniądze. </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_PASCUAL_OROZCO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Pascual Orozco[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Mexican revolutionary leader who, after the triumph of the Mexican Revolution, rose up against Francisco I. Madero and recognized the coup d'état led by Victoriano Huerta and the counter-revolutionary government it imposed.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Pascual Orozco[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Meksykańki przywódca polityczny z okresu rewolucji w XIX wieku.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_LORD_CHESTERFIELD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Lord Chesterfield[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a British statesman, and a man of letters, and wit. He was born in London to Philip Stanhope, 3rd Earl of Chesterfield, and Lady Elizabeth Savile, and known as Lord Stanhope until the death of his father, in 1726. Educated at Trinity Hall, Cambridge, he subsequently embarked on the Grand Tour of the Continent, to complete his education as a nobleman, by exposure to the cultural legacies of Classical antiquity and the Renaissance, and to become acquainted with his aristocratic counterparts and the polite society of Continental Europe.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Lord Chesterfield[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Brytyjski pisarz i polityk partii Wigów. Po śmierci jego ojca (1726) tytułowano go Lord Stanhope (lub Lord Chesterfield). W roku 1715 wszedł do parlamentu jako Lord Stanhope of Shelford z okręgu St Germans. Gdy dyskutowano czy przeprowadzić impeachment jednego z innych posłów James Butler, 2. książę Ormonde Stanhope wygłosił (5 VIII 1715) pierwszą ze swych słynnych płomiennych mów. Była ona na tyle gwałtowna, że ściągnęła nań gniew większości posłów i grzywnę w wysokości 500 funtów. Wówczas zdecydował się wyjechać na kontynent. Stanhope, 5. hrabia Chesterfield.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_LORD_MELBOURNE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Lord Melbourne[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a British Whig statesman who served as Home Secretary (1830-1834) and Prime Minister (1834 and 1835-1841). He is best known for his intense and successful mentoring of Queen Victoria, at ages 18-21, in the ways of politics. Historians conclude that Melbourne does not rank high as a prime minister, for there were no great foreign wars or domestic issues to handle, he lacked major achievements, and he enunciated no grand principles. "But he was kind, honest, and not self-seeking." Melbourne was dismissed by the King in 1834, the last Prime Minister to have been dismissed by a Monarch.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Lord Melbourne[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Brytyjski polityk ze stronnictwa wigów, ministrem spraw wewnętrznych (Home Secretary, 1830-1834) i dwukrotnie premierem Wielkiej Brytanii (1834 i 1835-1841), a także mentorem i nauczycielem polityki młodej królowej Wiktorii.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_ALCIBIADES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Alcibiades[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a prominent Athenian statesman, orator, and general. He was the last famous member of his mother's aristocratic family, the Alcmaeonidae, which fell from prominence after the Peloponnesian War. He played a major role in the second half of that conflict as a strategic advisor, military commander, and politician.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Alkibiades[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Ateński strateg. Był kluczową postacią ostatnich 15 lat II wojny peloponeskiej. Charakteryzowany jest jako wybitny polityk i wódz, któremu brak rozwagi, wygórowane ambicje i skłonność do wystawnego trybu życia przysporzyły wielu wrogów. Dla Greków był postacią kontrowersyjną.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_YASSER_ARAFAT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Yasser Arafat[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Palestinian leader. He was Chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), President of the Palestinian National Authority (PNA), and leader of the Fatah political party and former paramilitary group, which he founded in 1959. Originally opposed to Israel's existence, he modified his position in 1988 when he accepted UN Security Council Resolution 242. Arafat and his movement operated from several Arab countries. </English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Jasir Arafat[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Polityk i przywódca palestyński, laureat Pokojowej Nagrody Nobla w 1994 roku, Człowiek Roku 1993 według magazynu Time (obok Nelsona Mandeli, Frederika de Klerka i Icchaka Rabina). Był jednym z najbardziej znanych polityków w świecie arabskim, głównie wśród Palestyńczyków. Brał udział w wojnach wyzwoleńczych z Izraelem. Był współzałożycielem, a później w roku 1965 stanął na czele największej palestyńskiej organizacji zbrojnej Al-Fatah. </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_SIR_FRANCIS_BACON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Sir Francis Bacon[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an English philosopher, statesman, scientist, jurist, orator, and author. He served both as Attorney General and Lord Chancellor of England. After his death, he remained extremely influential through his works, especially as philosophical advocate and practitioner of the scientific method during the scientific revolution.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Sir Francis Bacon[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Angielski filozof, jeden z najwybitniejszych przedstawicieli filozofii epoki odrodzenia i baroku, eseista, polityk oraz prawnik. Uchodzi za jednego z twórców nowożytnej metody naukowej opartej na eksperymencie i indukcji. Jest też uważany za jednego z twórców empiryzmu.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_DAVID_GEN_GURION_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]David Ben Gurion[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was the primary founder of the State of Israel and the first Prime Minister of Israel. Ben-Gurion's passion for Zionism, which began early in life, led him to become a major Zionist leader and Executive Head of the World Zionist Organization in 1946. As head of the Jewish Agency from 1935, and later president of the Jewish Agency Executive, he was the de facto leader of the Jewish community in Palestine, and largely led its struggle for an independent Jewish state in Mandatory Palestine.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]David Ben Gurion[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Zydowski polityk, działacz i przywódca ruchu syjonistycznego, jeden z głównych założycieli państwa żydowskiego oraz pierwszy premier Izraela.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_MENACHEM_BEGIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Menachem Begin[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an Israeli politician, founder of Likud and the sixth Prime Minister of the State of Israel. Before the creation of the state of Israel, he was the leader of the Zionist militant group Irgun, the Revisionist breakaway from the larger Jewish paramilitary organization Haganah. He proclaimed a revolt, on 1 February 1944, against the British mandatory government, which was opposed by the Jewish Agency. </English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Menachem Begin[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Izraelski polityk, lider podziemnej organizacji militarnej Irgun, działacz syjonistyczny, premier Izraela w latach 1977-1983, pierwszy prawicowy szef rządu izraelskiego w historii państwa, laureat Pokojowej Nagrody Nobla za rok 1978 (razem z prezydentem Egiptu Anwarem as-Sadatem).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_WILLY_BRANDT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Willy Brandt[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a German statesman and politician, leader of the Social Democratic Party of Germany (SPD) from 1964 to 1987 and chancellor of the Federal Republic of Germany from 1969 to 1974. He was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1971 for his efforts to strengthen cooperation in western Europe through the EEC and to achieve reconciliation between West Germany and the countries of Eastern Europe. He was the first Social Democrat chancellor since 1930.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Willy Brandt[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Niemiecki polityk, działacz socjaldemokratyczny, członek SPD i jej przewodniczący w latach 1964 - 1987, kanclerz RFN w latach 1969 - 1974, laureat pokojowej Nagrody Nobla w 1971, Człowiek Roku 1970 według magazynu "Time".</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_MARCUS_JUNIUS_BRUTUS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Marcus Junius Brutus[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a politician of the late Roman Republic. After being adopted by his uncle he used the name Quintus Servilius Caepio Brutus, but eventually returned to using his original name. He is best known in modern times for taking a leading role in the assassination of Julius Caesar.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Markus Juniusz Brutus[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Polityk, dowódca wojskowy, mówca i pisarz rzymski. Był zwolennikiem republiki, a przeciwnikiem dyktatur Pompejusza i Cezara. Przyjaźnił się z Markiem Tulliuszem Cyceronem. Należał do przywódców spisku przeciwko Cezarowi i był jednym z zabójców dyktatora. W tradycji europejskiej imię Brutusa stało się symbolem zdrajcy i mordercy walczącego w słusznej sprawie. Przydawano mu miano Tyranobójcy.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_EDMUND_BURKE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Edmund Burke[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an Irish statesman born in Dublin, as well as an author, orator, political theorist and philosopher who, after moving to London, served as a Member of Parliament (MP) for many years in the House of Commons with the Whig Party. Burke is remembered mainly for his support of the cause of the American Revolutionaries, Catholic emancipation, the impeachment of Warren Hastings from the East India Company.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Edmund Burke[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Irlandzki filozof i polityk, twórca nowoczesnego konserwatyzmu, krytyk rewolucji francuskiej, wolnomularz. Wydane w 1790 Rozważania o rewolucji we Francji można uznać za początek doktryny konserwatyzmu-ewolucjonizmu i koniec epoki oświecenia. Jednocześnie znajdujemy w jego doktrynie elementy, które sprawiają, że można go uważać za liberała i demokratę (popieranie zasady równowagi sił politycznych, niezależność parlamentu, prawa kolonii amerykańskich do niepodległości). </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_KEMAL_ATATURK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Kemal Ataturk[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Turkish army officer, revolutionary, and the first President of Turkey. He is credited with being the founder of the Republic of Turkey. His surname, Atatürk (meaning "Father of the Turks"), was granted to him in 1934 and forbidden to any other person by the Turkish parliament.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Kemal Ataturk[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Turecki polityk, wojskowy, współtwórca i pierwszy prezydent Republiki Turcji. W trakcie I wojny światowej był jednym z ważniejszych dowódców armii Imperium Osmańskiego. Po klęsce w wojnie sprzeciwił się rozbiorom Turcji i stanął na czele wojny o niepodległość. W niepodległej Turcji objął urząd prezydenta, przeprowadzając szereg reform politycznych, gospodarczych i kulturalnych, przekształcając Imperium Osmańskie w nowoczesne i świeckie państwo narodowe. Jego działania dały początek ideologii kemalistycznej.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_BIRGER_JARL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Birger Jarl[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Swedish statesman, Jarl of Sweden and a member of the House of Bjelbo, who played a pivotal role in the consolidation of Sweden. Birger also led the Second Swedish Crusade, which established Swedish rule in Finland. Additionally, he is traditionally attributed to have founded the Swedish capital, Stockholm around 1250. Birger used the Latin title of Dux Sweorum which in English equals Duke of Sweden, and the design of his coronet combined those used by continental European and English dukes.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Birger Jarl[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Możnowładca szwedzki, jarl od 1248, regent swego małoletniego syna króla Waldemara od 1250, prawdopodobnie założyciel Sztokholmu. Uznawany za najwybitniejszego męża stanu średniowiecznej Szwecji, twórcę skonsolidowanego Królestwa Szwecji.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_ZHUGE_LIANG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Zhuge Liang[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a chancellor of the state of Shu Han during the Three Kingdoms period. He is recognised as the greatest and most accomplished strategist of his era, and has been compared to another great ancient Chinese strategist, Sun Tzu. Often depicted wearing a Taoist robe and holding a hand fan made of crane feathers (called a 'Kongming fan' after him), Zhuge Liang was an important military strategist, statesman and accomplished scholar and inventor.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Zhuge Liang[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Doradca Liu Beia oraz kanclerz i regent państwa Shu Han. Jeszcze przed swoją śmiercią Liu Bei ponownie zawarł sojusz z Sun Quanem i Zhuge Liang go potwierdził. Następnie w kampaniach przeprowadzonych na południu w latach 224 - 225 podbił on terytoria rozciągające się aż do dzisiejszego Kunmingu. </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_YITZHAK_RABIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Yitzhak Rabin[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an Israeli politician, statesman and general. He was the fifth Prime Minister of Israel, serving two terms in office, 1974-77 and 1992 until his assassination in 1995. He was appointed Prime Minister of Israel in 1974, after the resignation of Golda Meir. In his first term, Rabin signed the Sinai Interim Agreement and ordered the Entebbe raid. He resigned in 1977 in the wake of a financial scandal. Rabin was Israel's minister of defense for much of the 1980s, including during the outbreak of the First Intifada.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Icchak Rabin[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Izraelski polityk i mąż stanu, dowódca wojskowy w stopniu generała porucznika (Rav Aluf), oficer dyplomowany Sił Obronnych Izraela. W latach 1964-1968 był Szefem Sztabu Generalnego Sił Obronnych Izraela. Przez dwie kadencje pełnił obowiązki Premiera Izraela (1974-1977 i 1992-1995).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_SELAHADINE_EYUBI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Selahadine Eyubi[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was the first sultan of Egypt and Syria and the founder of their Ayyubid dynasty, although it was named after his father. A Muslim of Kurdish origin, Saladin led the Muslim opposition to the European Crusaders in the Levant. At the height of his power, his sultanate included Egypt, Syria, Mesopotamia, Hejaz, Yemen and other parts of North Africa.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Saladyn[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Wódz i polityk muzułmański pochodzenia kurdyjskiego, sułtan Egiptu, władca imperium rozciągającego się od Sudanu po Syrię, od Jemenu przez Półwysep Arabski, północny Irak do wschodniej Turcji (Diyarbakir), uważany za założyciela dynastii Ajjubidów.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_PERICLES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Pericles[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was arguably the most prominent and influential Greek statesman, orator and general of Athens during the Golden Age - specifically the time between the Persian and Peloponnesian wars. He was descended, through his mother, from the powerful and historically influential Alcmaeonid family.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Perykles[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Ateński polityk, mówca (ta umiejętność była konieczna do osiągnięcia sukcesu politycznego), reformator ateńskiej demokracji. Syn zwycięzcy spod Mykale Ksantipposa, ze strony matki Agaristy wywodził się z rodu Alkmeonidów. Paradoksalnie, mimo że władza w polis skupiona była w jego rękach, to on stworzył demokrację ateńską. Wystąpił w roku 463 p.n.e. jako oskarżyciel Kimona, obalił z Efialtesem 462 p.n.e. Areopag, przez zaprowadzenie diet dla sędziów itd. dał ludowi większy udział w sprawach państwowych i utwierdził umiarkowaną demokrację. </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_KIMON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Kimon[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an Athenian statesman and strategos in mid-5th century BC Greece, the son of Miltiades, the victor of the Battle of Marathon. Cimon played a key role in creating the powerful Athenian maritime empire following the failure of the Persian invasion of Greece by Xerxes I in 480-479 BC. Cimon became a celebrated military hero and was elevated to the rank of admiral after fighting in the Battle of Salamis.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Kimon[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Wódz i polityk ateński. Kimon był arystokratą, należącym do najbogatszych ludzi w Atenach. We wczesnej młodości zyskał opinię birbanta i człowieka zdeprawowanego, lecz wkrótce odznaczył się nakłaniając Ateńczyków do pomysłu Temistoklesa, by bitwę pod Salaminą stoczyć na morzu. Dążył do sojuszu wszystkich polis greckich i wspólnej walki z Persją. Protestował przeciw antyspartańskiej polityce Temistoklesa i jego następców.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_ARISTIDES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Aristides[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was an ancient Athenian statesman. Nicknamed "the Just", he flourished in the early quarter of Athens' Classical period and is remembered for his generalship in the Persian War. The ancient historian Herodotus cited him as "the best and most honourable man in Athens", and he received similarly reverent treatment in Plato's Socratic dialogues.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Arystydes[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Ateński polityk i wódz, nazywany Sprawiedliwym. Brał udział w bitwie pod Maratonem w 490 p.n.e. jako jeden z dziesięciu strategów, w roku następnym został wybrany archontem-eponimem. Wysunął się wówczas na czoło umiarkowanych demokratów, głównie średniozamożnych chłopów. Kiedy Ateńczycy odkryli nowe żyły srebra w górach Laurion, rozgorzała walka polityczna o to, jak wydatkować wpływy z eksploatacji złóż. </Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_PERSON_MARK_ANTONY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[BOLD][H1]Mark Antony[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Was a Roman politician and general who played a critical role in the transformation of the Roman Republic from an oligarchy into the autocratic Roman Empire. Antony was a supporter of Julius Caesar, and served as one of his generals during the conquest of Gaul and the Civil War. Antony was appointed administrator of Italy while Caesar eliminated political opponents in Greece, North Africa, and Spain.</English>
		<Polish>[BOLD][H1]Marek Antoniusz[\H1][\BOLD][NEWLINE]Wódz i polityk rzymski w latach 61-30 p.n.e. W 31 p.n.e. roku doszło do bitwy morskiej pod Akcjum, w której flota Antoniusza i Kleopatry została zniszczona, a oni sami zmuszeni do ucieczki do Egiptu. W roku następnym Oktawian dokonał inwazji Egiptu. Marek Antoniusz popełnił razem z Kleopatrą samobójstwo.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>