<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOMESTIC_GREAT_GENERAL_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Great Military People Emergence inside Cultural Borders</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Émergence des militaires illustres à l'intérieur des frontières culturelles</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Geburtenrate für Große Feldherren innerhalb der eigenen Grenzen</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ADDITIONAL_NAVAL_MOVES</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%d1[ICON_MOVES] for Naval Units with[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s2</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%d1[ICON_MOVES] pour les unités navales avec[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s2</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%d1[ICON_MOVES] für Marineeinheiten mit[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s2</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%d1[ICON_MOVES] per le unità navali con la tecnologia[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s2</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%d1[ICON_MOVES] para las unidades acuáticas con [NUM2:el:la:los:las][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s2</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%d1[ICON_MOVES] dla jednostek morskich z[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s2</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_AGGRESSIVE</Tag>
		<English>Aggressive</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Agressif:Agressive:Agressifs:Agressives</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Aggressiv</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Aggressivo:Aggressiva</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Agresivo:Agresiva</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Agresywny:Agresywna:Agresywny:Agresywna</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_AGGRESSIVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This is a warmonger's trait. You get a free promotion for most of your units (the best units in the game, really--melee and gunpowder) and cheap barracks and drydocks to provide additional promotions. If you don't go to war when you're Aggressive, you're wasting the trait.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BRONZE_WORKING]Bronze Working[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_IRON_WORKING]Iron Working[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CIVIL_SERVICE]Civil Service[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MACHINERY]Machinery[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_GUNPOWDER]Gunpowder[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CHEMISTRY]Chemistry[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_RIFLING]Rifling[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_STEEL]Steel[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ASSEMBLY_LINE]Assembly Line[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_HEROIC_EPIC]Heroic Epic[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_WEST_POINT]West Point[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_RED_CROSS]Red Cross[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_PENTAGON]The Pentagon[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STATUE_OF_ZEUS]Statue of Zeus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BARRACKS]Barracks[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_DRYDOCK]Drydock[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STABLE]Stable[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_VASSALAGE]Vassalage[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_THEOCRACY]Theocracy[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_NATIONHOOD]Nationhood[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_POLICE_STATE]Police State[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_STATE_PROPERTY]State Property[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]How to use this trait? War. Duh. Am I not making myself clear, here? Put together a horde and go kill somebody already.[NEWLINE]You'll want your forces to mostly be composed of units that benefit from the trait: Melee units (Warriors, Axemen, Swordsmen, Spearmen, Macemen, Pikemen), Gunpowder units (Musketmen, Riflemen, Grenadiers, Infantry, SAM Infantry, Marines, Mechanized Infantry) and their UU variants.[NEWLINE]Drydocks make Steel a priority technology; likewise with technologies that enable one of the aforementioned units. Note that some of the Aggressive leaders have a UU that benefit from the trait (Montezuma, Alexander, Tokugawa, Ragnar, Shaka) and some do not (Genghis, Kublai, Stalin). The latter do benefit from the cheap barracks, however. Also, remember that you'll need more units than just melee and gunpowder--siege weapons and mounted may not receive Aggressive's free Combat I, but they're still essential.[NEWLINE]The Statue of Zeus world wonder is very good to have--mainly so that someone you're attacking doesn't have it. War weariness is bad enough as it is; having it doubled will definitely put a crimp in your world domination plans.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Aggressive in and of itself has no economic advantages and may, in fact, over-encourage you to accrue too many economic liabilities. Every unit has a maintenance cost, remember, and that cost goes up when the unit leaves home turf. In addition, every conquered city has maintenance costs. Over-conquering, especially early in the game, can be just as bad as over-expanding.[NEWLINE]On the plus side, since Aggressive should mean you have better units, hopefully you'll need fewer of them.</English>
		<German>Dies ist eine Eigenschaft für Kriegstreiber. Viele der eigenen Einheiten (tatsächlich die besten Einheiten des Spiels: Nahkampf und Schießpulver) erhalten eine Extra-Beförderung und verbilligte Kasernen und Trockendocks sorgen für zusätzliche Beförderungen. Falls diese Eigenschaft nicht zum Führen von Kriegen verwendet wird, ist sie eigentlich komplett verschwendet.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BRONZE_WORKING]Bronzeverarbeitung[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_IRON_WORKING]Eisenverarbeitung[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CIVIL_SERVICE]Öffentliche Verwaltung[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MACHINERY]Maschinen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_GUNPOWDER]Schießpulver[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CHEMISTRY]Chemie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_RIFLING]Drall[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_STEEL]Stahl[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ASSEMBLY_LINE]Fließband[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_HEROIC_EPIC]Heldenepos[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_WEST_POINT]West Point[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_RED_CROSS]Rotes Kreuz[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_PENTAGON]Pentagon[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STATUE_OF_ZEUS]Zeus-Statue[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BARRACKS]Kaserne[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_DRYDOCK]Trockendock[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STABLE]Stallungen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_VASSALAGE]Vasallentum[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_THEOCRACY]Theokratie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_NATIONHOOD]Nationale Selbstständigkeit[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_POLICE_STATE]Polizeistaat[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_STATE_PROPERTY]Staatseigentum[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Wie diese Eigenschaft eingesetzt werden soll? Im Krieg, natürlich. Immer noch nicht deutlich genug? Eine Horde Einheiten dazu benutzen, um andere Einheiten auszulöschen.[NEWLINE]Die eigenen Streitkräfte sollten am besten aus Einheiten zusammengesetzt sein, die von der Eigenschaft profitieren: Nahkampfeinheiten (Krieger, Axtkämpfer, Schwertkämpfer, Speerkämpfer, Streitkolbenträger, Pikeniere), Schießpulvereinheiten (Musketiere, Schützen, Grenadiere, Infanterie, SAM Infanterie, Marines, Mechanisierte Infanterie) und die Spezialeinheiten, die sie jeweils ersetzen.[NEWLINE]Die Technologie Stahl sollte vordringlich erforscht werden, um Trockendocks errichten zu können; ebenso verhält es sich mit Technologien, die Voraussetzung für die oben genannten Einheiten sind. Es sollte beachtet werden, dass einige der "aggressiven" Oberhäupter über eine Spezialeinheit verfügen, die von der Eigenschaft profitiert (Montezuma, Alexander, Tokugawa, Ragnar, Shaka), während bei anderen dies nicht der Fall ist (Dschinghis Khan, Kublai Khan, Stalin). Trotzdem können die letztgenannten natürlich Nutzen aus den verbilligten Kasernen ziehen. Außerdem sollte nicht vergessen werden, dass für einen Krieg mehr als nur Nahkampf- und Schießpulvereinheiten benötigt werden - Belagerungswaffen und Berittene Einheiten erhalten vielleicht nicht die Extra-Beförderung "Kampf I", sind aber trotzdem unverzichtbar.[NEWLINE]Das Weltwunder "Zeus-Statue" ist eine schöne Ergänzung für die eigene Zivilisation - hauptsächlich deswegen, damit niemand anderes es errichten kann. Kriegsunzufriedenheit ist schon schlimm genug; wenn sie sich aber verdoppelt, hat das desaströse Auswirkungen auf die eigenen Welteroberungspläne.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Die Eigenschaft "Aggressiv" selbst bietet keine wirtschaftlichen Vorteile und könnte den Anreiz zu einem enormen Anwachsen der Kosten liefern. Schließlich verursacht jede Einheit laufende Kosten und diese Kosten erhöhen sich, wenn die Einheit das eigene Hoheitsgebiet verlässt. Zusätzlich verursacht auch jede eroberte Stadt laufende Kosten. Übertriebene Eroberungen, speziell in der Frühphase einer Partie, können ebenso tödlich sein, wie übertriebene Expansion.[NEWLINE]Andererseits: Da "Aggressiv" meist auch bessere Einheiten bedeuten sollte, werden hoffentlich auch weniger von ihnen benötigt.</German>
		<Polish>To jest cecha Agresywny. Otrzymujesz darmową promocję do większości Twoich jednostek oraz tańsze baraki wraz z stocznią. Jeśli nie idziesz na wojnę z tą cechą to tylko ją marnujesz.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Najważniejsze Technologie[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BRONZE_WORKING]Obróbka Brązu[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_IRON_WORKING]Obrózbka Żelaza[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CIVIL_SERVICE]Administracja Państwowa[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MACHINERY]Mechanizacja[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_GUNPOWDER]Proch Strzelniczy[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CHEMISTRY]Chemia[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_RIFLING]Strzelectwo[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_STEEL]Stal[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ASSEMBLY_LINE]Taśma Montażowa[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Użyteczne Cuda:[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_HEROIC_EPIC]Epopeja Heroiczna[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_WEST_POINT]Akademia West Point[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_RED_CROSS]Czerwony Krzyż[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_PENTAGON]Pentagon[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STATUE_OF_ZEUS]Posąg Zeusa[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Najlepsze budowle:[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BARRACKS]Baraki[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_DRYDOCK]Stocznia[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STABLE]Stajnie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Najlepsze doktryny:[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_VASSALAGE]Wasalstwo[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_THEOCRACY]Teokracja[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_NATIONHOOD]Nacjonalizm[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_POLICE_STATE]Państwo Policyjne[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_STATE_PROPERTY]Nacjonalizacja[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Jak tego użyć?[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Jak użyć tej cechy? WOJNA! Nie wyraziłem się dość jasno? Stwórz hordę wojownik i zniszcz kogoś.[NEWLINE]Musisz utworzyć wojsko z różnych jednostek: Piechota, Strzelcy itd.[NEWLINE]Stocznia powoduje że stal jest priorytetową technologią. Agresywny powoduje też że tańsze są baraki.Pamiętaj potrzebujesz więcej piechoty i strzelców niż maszyn wojenych i konnicy z tego powodu że nie otrzumują one promocji ale to nie znaczy że nie używasz ich w ogóle.[NEWLINE]Posąg Zeusa warto mieć z tą cechą, masz miejsze szanse na atak ze strony wroga. Znużenie wojenne jest złe; posiadając tą kartę będzie Ci łatwiej zdominować świat.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Minusy[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Z tą cechą bedziesz miał problemy ekonomiczne. Każda jednostka ma koszt utrzymania, pamiętaj o tym. Dodatkowo każde zdobyte miasto posiada koszt utrzymania. Duże podboje we wczesnych stanach gry nie są za dobre dla Twojej gospodarki.[NEWLINE]Na plus jest to że masz lepsze jednostki i ogólnie potrzebujesz ich mniej.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_AGRICULTURAL</Tag>
		<English>Agricultural</English>
		<French>Agricole</French>
		<German>Agrikulturell</German>
		<Italian>Agricolo</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Agrícola:Agrícola:Agrícolas:Agrícolas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Rolniczy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_AGRICULTURAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_AGRICULTURAL_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Agr</English>
		<French>Agr.</French>
		<Polish>Rol.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_AIR_UNIT_CAPACITY</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Air Unit Capacity in all cities.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount de capacité d'acceuil d'unité aériennes dans toutes les Villes.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount alla capacità aerea in tutte le città.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Ilości możliwych stacjonujących Jednostek Powietrznych we wszystkich miastach.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_CENTAUR</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Centaur</English>
		<French>Ancienne voie du centaure</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_CENTAUR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Centaur Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Mounted Units gain the Way of the Centaur promotion, giving them +1 Strength. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical Lifestyle Technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_CENTAUR_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotCentaur</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_FEATHER</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Feather</English>
		<French>Ancienne Voie de la Plume</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_FEATHER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Feather Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Archery Units gain the Way of the Feather promotion, giving them +1 Strength. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical Lifestyle Technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_FEATHER_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotFeather</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_FIST</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Fist</English>
		<French>Ancienne voie du poing</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_FIST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Fist Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Law Enforcements Units gain the Way of the Fist promotion, giving them an additional 1.5% Investigation (To find local criminals), -4 Crime Turn/City and -2 Crime Turn/Plot. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical Lifestyle Technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_FIST_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotFist</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_LEECH</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Leech</English>
		<French>Ancienne Voie de la Goule</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_LEECH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Leech Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Health Care Units gain the Way of the Leech promotion, giving them Units heal in Same tile Extra 8% Damage/turn, -4 Disease Turn/City and -2 Disease Turn/Plot. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_LEECH_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotLeech</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_SHADOWS</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Shadows</English>
		<French>Ancienne Voie des Ombres</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_SHADOWS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Shadows Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Criminal, Ruffian and Strike Team Units gain the Way of the Shadows promotion, giving them +1 Strength. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical Lifestyle Technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_SHADOWS_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotShadows</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WARRIOR</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Warrior</English>
		<French>Ancienne Voie du Guerrier</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WARRIOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Warrior Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Melee Units gain the Way of the Warrior promotion, giving them +1 Strength. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical Lifestyle Technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WARRIOR_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotWarrior</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WAVES</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Waves</English>
		<French>Ancienne Voie des Vagues</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WAVES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Waves Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Naval Combat Units gain the Way of the Waves promotion, giving them +1 Strength. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical Lifestyle Technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WAVES_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotWaves</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WILD</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Wild</English>
		<French>Ancienne Voie de la Nature Sauvage</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WILD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Wild Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Explorer Units gain the Way of the Wild promotion, giving them +1 Movement, -1 Mobility Cost and +1 Visibility Range. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical Lifestyle Technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WILD_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotWild</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WIND</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Wind</English>
		<French>Ancienne Voie du Vent</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WIND_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Wind Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Throwing Units gain the Way of the Wind promotion, giving them +1 Strength. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical Lifestyle Technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WIND_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotWind</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WOLF</Tag>
		<English>Ancient Way of the Wolf</English>
		<French>Ancienne voie du Loup</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WOLF_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Way of the Wolf Trait is only available with the Ancient Ways Group Wonders. All Canine Units gain the Way of the Wolf promotion, giving them +1 Movement, -1 Mobility Cost and +1 Visibility Range. This promotion is only available during the Ancient era, it will be obsolete with Classical Lifestyle Technology.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANCIENT_WAY_OF_THE_WOLF_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AWotWolf</English>
	</TEXT>
<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANTI_CLERICAL</Tag>
		<English>Anti Clerical</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Anti Clérical</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Anti Clerical</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Anti Clericale</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Ateo:Atea:Ateos:Ateas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Anty-Klerykalny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANTI_CLERICAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This leader finds strong opposition from clergy of his country, due to his actions against the church, heretical ideas or something similar. As clergy doesn't want to voice its support for the ruler great people take a -15% hit. Monasteries all have a negative happiness bonus. Holy Cities in heathen lands cause extra negative revolution implications as do rival religions in your cities. - TR Team.</English>
		<Italian>Questo leader trova una forte opposizione da parte del clero del suo stato, a causa delle sue azioni contro la chiesa, di idee eretiche o cose del genere. Dato che il clero non supporta il leader, i grandi personaggi nascono con una frequenza minore del 15%. Tutti i monasteri hanno delle penalità alla felicità. Le città sante nei territori degli infedeli aumentano i sentimetni rivoluzionari, allo stesso modo in cui le religioni rivali influenzano le tue città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ANTI_CLERICAL_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>AnC</English>
		<French>
			<Text>AnC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>AnC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>AnC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Ate</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>AnK</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ARROGANT</Tag>
		<English>Arrogant</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Arrogant</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Arrogant</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Arrogante</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Arrogante:Arrogante:Arrogantes:Arrogantes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Arogancki</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ARROGANT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This ruler sees other leaders as inferior to himself, and doesn't take them seriously. He tends to adopt a condescending attitude in negotiations and ignores many reports of his spies as exaggerated, confident that his rivals can't really exceed him. - TR Team.</English>
		<Italian>Questo leader vede gli altri leader come inferiori rispetto a lui, e non li prende seriamente. Tende ad adottare un atteggiamento accondiscendente nelle negoziazioni, e ignora molti dei rapporti provenienti dalla sue spie ritenendoli esagerati, ritenendo che i suoi rivali non possano veramente competere con lui.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ARROGANT_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Arr</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Arr</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Arr</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Arr</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Arr</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Aro</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ATTITUDE_MODIFIER_NEGATIVE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Num Diplomacy Penalty (inverts to a bonus with Leaders with same trait)</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Num Pénalité Diplomatique (se compense avec un bonus pour un Leader du meme trait)</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Diplomatische Strafe: %D1_Num (wird zu einem Bonus bei Anführern mit derselben Charaktereigenschaft)</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Num di penalità nei rapporti diplomatici (diventa un bonus nei confronti di leader con lo stesso tratto)</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Num Kary do Dyplomacji (zamienne na bonus do Przywódców z tą samą cechą)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ATTITUDE_MODIFIER_POSITIVE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Num Diplomacy Bonus with other Leaders</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Num Bonus Diplomatique envers les autres Leaders</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Num Diplomatiebonus</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Num nei rapporti diplomatici con gli altri leader</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Num Bonusu do Dyplomacji z innymi Przywódcami</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BAD_RELIGION_MOD</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%s1% Change to Revolution Penalty from Non State [ICON_RELIGION]</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%S1% Pénalité de la religion [ICON_RELIGION] (non d'état)</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%S1% Wechsel zum Revolutionsmalus durch nichtstaatliche [ICON_RELIGION]</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Penalità instabilità: %S1% per [ICON_RELIGION] NON di Stato</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%s1% a la penalización a la estabilidad revolucionaria por [ICON_RELIGION] no oficiales</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%s1% zmiany na kary rewolucyjnej z [ICON_RELIGION] nienarodowej</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BARBARIAN</Tag>
		<English>Barbarian</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Barbare</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Barbarisch</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Barbaro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Bárbaro:Bárbara:Bárbaros:Bárbaras</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dziki</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BARBARIAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A barbarian is an uncivilized person. The word is often used pejoratively, either in a general reference to a member of a nation or ethnos, typically a tribal society as seen by an urban civilization either viewed as inferior, or admired as a noble savage. In idiomatic or figurative usage, a "barbarian" may also be an individual reference to a brutal, cruel, warlike, insensitive person. The term originates in the ancient Greek civilization, meaning "anyone who is not Greek". Comparable notions are found in non-European civilizations.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BARBARIAN_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>BrB</English>
		<French>
			<Text>BrB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BrB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>BrB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Bar</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dzi</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BARBARIC</Tag>
		<English>Barbaric</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Barbare</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Barbaric</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Barbarico</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Bruto:Bruta:Brutos:Brutas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Barbarzyński</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BARBARIC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This leader never got any real education, and sees sponsorship of poets and playwrights as a needless waste of money. They should be happy he doesn't order to execute all those spineless wimps for swaying his troops from their spartan ways! Foreign infidels are viewed as just that, inferior scum who better get down with his ways, or lay down at the hands of his sword.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BARBARIC_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Bar</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Bar</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Bar</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Bar</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Bru</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Barb</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BOMBARD_DEFENSE_MOD</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Mod%% Damage to Defenses and Units from Bombardment and Ranged Assault in all cities</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Mod%% de Protection des Bombardements dans toutes les villes</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Mod%% Schaden an der Verteidigung durch Bombardierung in all cities</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Mod%% di danni dal bombardamento in tutte le tue città</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Mod%% Obrażeń do Obrony przed Bombardowaniem we wszystkich Miastach</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BONUS_HAPPINESS_CHANGE_ADDITIONAL</Tag>
		<English>, [LINK=%s1_Bonus]%s2_Bonus[\LINK]</English>
		<French>, [LINK=%s1_Bonus]%s2_Bonus[\LINK]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BONUS_HAPPINESS_CHANGE_END</Tag>
		<English>Resources</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BONUS_HAPPINESS_CHANGE_FIRST</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change%F2_HappyOrHealth from access to [LINK=%s3_Bonus]%s4_Bonus[\LINK]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change%F2_HappyOrHealth de l'accès aux Ressources : [LINK=%s3_Bonus]%s4_Bonus[\LINK]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_BUILDING_HAPPINESS_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change%F2_HappOrUnhapp from[SPACE]</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change%F2_HappOrUnhapp de[SPACE]</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change%F2_HappOrUnhapp durch Geländeart[SPACE]</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change%F2_HappOrUnhapp per[SPACE]</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change de %F2_HappOrUnhapp por[SPACE]</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change%F2_HappOrUnhapp z[SPACE]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CAPITAL_XP_MODIFIER</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Free Experience to all units trained in a Capital or Government Center</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% EXP gratuite à toutes les unités formées dans la capitale ou un centre gouvernemental</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% esperienza gratuita a tutte le unità addestrate nella capitale</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Darmowego doświadczenia dla jednostek wytrenowanych w Stolicy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CHARISMATIC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Charismatic was introduced with the Warlords expansion pack (along with Imperialistic and Protective) and is definitely the best of the three new traits. It is clearly a warmonger's trait, mainly because of the reduced XP requirement for each promotion. By warring early, you can amass a force of highly-promoted veteran units which you can keep upgrading as the game progresses.[PARAGRAPH:1]The extra happiness from the trait and two buildings also helps with warmongering, since it reduces war weariness. It should also help you financially; whether you run a CE or SE or a hybrid, more population because of an elevated happiness cap always means a stronger economy.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MYSTICISM]Mysticism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_AGRICULTURE]Agriculture[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ANIMAL_HUSBANDRY]Animal Husbandry[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_RADIO]Radio[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MASS_MEDIA]Mass Media[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STONEHENGE]Stonehenge[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_HEROIC_EPIC]Heroic Epic[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_WEST_POINT]West Point[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_EIFFEL_TOWER]The Eiffel Tower[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_PENTAGON]The Pentagon[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_MONUMENT]Monument[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BARRACKS]Barracks[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STABLE]Stable[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_DRYDOCK]Drydock[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BROADCAST_TOWER]Broadcast Tower[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_VASSALAGE]Vassalage[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_THEOCRACY]Theocracy[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]When you're Charismatic, go to war early to collect those promotions and build your army of veterans. Playing with barbs, even raging barbs, turned on allows you to amass more promotions faster, so you will likely have a powerful army by the time you've dealt with the barbarians and are ready to turn on your neighbours.[PARAGRAPH:1]Also be sure to take advantage of the elevated happiness cap. Prioritize growth in the early game: ensure each city has good food resources, bee-line to Pottery so you can build Granaries, and build Workers so you can ensure all your extra citizens have improved tiles to work. Chop Workers and Settlers as much as possible to hurry their builds and get your cities back to growing their populations.[PARAGRAPH:1]Mysticism and Mass Media are obvious tech targets in order to enable the happiness-increasing buildings (which are, unfortunately, not made cheaper by the trait; Charismatic is one of the few traits without a cheap building). Alternatively, you may bee-line to Radio and build the Eiffel Tower, which gives you a free broadcast tower in every one of your cities.[PARAGRAPH:1]Stonehenge is also an attractive wonder, since it gives you a free monument in each city. However, remember that those monuments magically disappear once you discover Calendar (Astronomy in BtS). Broadcast Towers and the Eiffel Tower, in contrast, never become obsolete. Also, any monument you build directly stays put to produce culture, and the culture doubles after 1000 years.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]As mentioned above, while Charismatic enhances the effects of two buildings, it has no cheap building, a limitation it shares only with the Financial and Imperialistic traits.[PARAGRAPH:1]Balancing early growth with the need to have a large number of Workers to ensure those extra citizens have improved tiles to work can be tricky. In addition to ensuring each city has at least one food resource, also try to ensure it has forests for chop-rushing Workers.</English>
		<German>Die Eigenschaft "Charismatisch" wurde mit dem ersten Addon "Warlords" ins Spiel eingeführt (zusammen mit "Imperialistisch" und "Schützend") und ist sicherlich die nützlichste der drei neuen Eigenschaften. Sie ist eindeutig für Kriegstreiber gedacht, hauptsächlich wegen der gesenkten Erfahrungspunkte-Anforderungen für Beförderungen. Indem schon früh Kriege geführt werden, können sehr viele erfahrene, mit Massen von Beförderungen versehene Einheiten angesammelt werden, die im weiteren Spielverlauf noch weiter befördert werden können.[PARAGRAPH:1]Auch die zusätzliche Zufriedenheit dieser Eigenschaft und der zwei Gebäude unterstützt das Führen von Kriegen, da sie die Kriegsunzufriedenheit senkt. Außerdem unterstützt sie auch die eigene Wirtschaft; sei es nun eine Hüttenwirtschaft (CE), eine Spezialistenwirtschaft (SE) oder eine Mischung, eine höhere Bevölkerung auf Grund einer erhöhten Zufriedenheitsobergrenze bedeutet immer auch eine stärkere Wirtschaft.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MYSTICISM]Mystik[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_AGRICULTURE]Landwirtschaft[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ANIMAL_HUSBANDRY]Tierzucht[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_RADIO]Funkwesen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MASS_MEDIA]Massenmedien[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STONEHENGE]Stonehenge[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_HEROIC_EPIC]Heldenepos[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_WEST_POINT]West Point[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_EIFFEL_TOWER]Eiffelturm[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_PENTAGON]Pentagon[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_MONUMENT]Monument[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BARRACKS]Kaserne[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STABLE]Stallungen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_DRYDOCK]Trockendock[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BROADCAST_TOWER]Funkturm[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_VASSALAGE]Vasallentum[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_THEOCRACY]Theokratie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Mit einem Oberhaupt mit der Eigenschaft "Charismatisch" sollten früh Kriege geführt werden, um Beförderungen zu erlangen und eine Armee erfahrener Einheiten aufstellen zu können. Falls die Option "Barbaren", oder sogar "Rasende Barbaren", aktiviert wurde, können mehr Beförderungen noch schneller angesammelt werden, so dass sehr wahrscheinlich nach der Ausrottung der Barbaren eine schlagkräftige Armee zur Verfügung steht, die dann bereit ist, sich den Nachbarzivilisationen zuzuwenden.[PARAGRAPH:1]Außerdem sollte von der erhöhten Zufriedenheitsobergrenze Gebrauch gemacht werden. Der Schwerpunkt sollte bereits früh in der Partie auf Wachstum gelegt werden: es sollte sichergestellt werden, dass jede Stadt über gute Nahrungsressourcen verfügt, die Forschung sollte geradewegs auf "Keramik" ausgerichtet werden, damit "Kornspeicher" errichtet werden können, und Bautrupps sollten aufgestellt werden, damit diese für die Modernisierung der Stadtgeländefelder sorgen können, die dann von den zusätzlichen Bürgern bearbeitet werden können. Bautrupps und Siedler sollten wenn möglich durch das Abholzen von Wäldern beschleunigt werden, damit die Städte schneller wachsen können.[PARAGRAPH:1]"Mystik" und "Massenmedien" stellen offensichtliche Forschungsziele dar, um die Gebäude verfügbar zu machen, die zur Erhöhung der Zufriedenheit beitragen (die durch die Eigenschaft leider nicht verbilligt werden; "Charismatisch" ist eine der wenigen Eigenschaften ohne verbilligtes Gebäude). Wahlweise kann auch das "Funkwesen" erforscht werden und der "Eiffelturm" errichtet werden, der einen kostenlosen "Funkturm" in jeder eigenen Stadt gewährt.[PARAGRAPH:1]"Stonehenge" ist ebenfalls ein attraktives Wunder, da es ein kostenloses "Monument" in jeder Stadt gewährt. Jedoch sollte nicht vergessen werden, dass diese Monumente magischerweise verschwinden, wenn "Kalender" erfoscht wurde ("Astronomie" in BtS). Im Gegensatz dazu veralten Funktürme und der Eiffelturm niemals. Außerdem verbleibt jedes selbst errichtete Monument in einer Stadt und generiert Kulturpunkte, die sich nach 1000 Jahren sogar verdoppeln.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Wie oben erwähnt, erhöht die Eigenschaft "Charismatisch" zwar den Effekt zweier Gebäude, verfügt aber selbst über kein verbilligtes Gebäude, was eine Beschränkung ist, die sie nur mit den Eigenschaften "Finanzorientiert" und "Imperialistisch" teilt.[PARAGRAPH:1]Es kann etwas schwierig sein, das frühe Wachstum mit der Notwendigkeit zu vereinen, viele Bautrupps aufstellen zu müssen, die sicherstellen, dass die zusätzlichen Bürger modernisierte Geländefelder bearbeiten können. Zusätzlich muss jede Stadt mit mindestens einer Nahrungsressource versorgt sein und sollte außerdem in der Nähe von Wäldern gelegen sein, damit die Aufstellung von Bautrupps beschleunigt werden kann.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CITY_START_CULTURE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]New cities begin with %D1 culture</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Les nouvelles Villes commencent avec %D1 culture</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Le nuove città cominciano con %D1 cultura</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Nowe miasta rozpoczynają z: %D1 kultury</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CITY_START_POPULATION</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]New cities begin with %D1 population.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Les nouvelles Villes commencent avec %D1 population.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Le nuove città cominciano con %D1 popolazione.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Nowe miasta rozpoczynają z: %D1 populacji.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CITY_START_STATE_RELIGION</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]New cities begin with the State Religion.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Les nouvelles Villes commencent avec la religion d'Etat.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Le nuove città cominciano con la religione di stato.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Nowe miasta rozpoczynają z: Religią Państwową.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CIVIC_LEVEL_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% XP Needed for Unit Promotions</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% EXP pour la promotion des unités</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% EP für Einheitenbeförderungen erforderlich</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% XP richiesti per la promozione</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% PX necesarios para ascender unidades.</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Potrzebnego Doświadczenia dla Promocji Jednostki</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CIVIC_UPKEEP_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Civic Upkeep</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% d'entretien doctrinal</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Unterhalt für Gesellschaftsform</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% costo di mantenimento della civiltà</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% al mantenimiento de principios</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% do Utrzymania Doktryny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CIVILIZATION</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Civilizations can Earn this Trait - Not available for Leader selections</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Les Civilizations peuvent avoir ce Trait - N'est pas disponible à la sélection</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Le civilà possono ottenere questo tratto; non è disponibile nella selezione dei leader</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Tylko Cywilizacja może otrzymać tą cechę - Niedostępne dla Przywódców</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_COMMERCE_CHANGES_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_commerce/City</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_commerce/ville</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_commerce/Stadt</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_commerce/Città</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 %F2_commerce/ciudad</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_commerce/Miasto</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_COMMERCE_MODIFIERS_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% %F2_commerce</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% au %F2_commerce</French>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% [NUM2:al:a la:a los:a las] %F2_commerce</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CREATIVE</Tag>
		<English>Creative</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Créatif:Créative:Créatifs:Créatives</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Kreativ</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Creativo:Creativa</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Creativo:Creativa</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Kreatywny:Kreatywna:Kreatywny:Kreatywna'</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CREATIVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Creative is powerful early in the game, allowing you to quickly expand your borders and thereby claim territory and resources. The Warlords 2.08 patch added cheap Libraries, one of the best buildings in the game, making this trait even better.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_WRITING]Writing[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_DRAMA]Drama[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CONSTRUCTION]Construction[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]n/a[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LIBRARY]Library[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_THEATRE]Theatre[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_COLOSSEUM]Colosseum[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_FREE_SPEECH]Free Speech[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]The big benefit Creative provides is allowing you more freedom in your city placement and in your early city builds. You don't have to worry about placing a city so a crucial resource is in its first ring of workable tiles so you can access it right away; it will be workable within a few short turns of founding the city. You can also skip monuments, Stonehenge, and spreading a religion (well, you can be a little more relaxed about the latter, at least).[PARAGRAPH:1]In addition, Creative may allow you to win some early game tug-o-war battles with a nearby civ over a key resource tile. By the same token, if the map lends itself to it, you can use the trait to seal off territory at a choke point. Creative is also something of a defensive trait, a cousin to Protective. By expanding your borders earlier and infusing the tiles with your culture, you have more territory that the enemy has to trudge through to attack you. It's also harder for another civilization to take tiles from you by city placement or by conquering cities. Creative also raises the cultural defense of a city faster, making it tougher to conquer.[PARAGRAPH:1]Writing enables the trait's cheap libraries, so it's obviously an even more important tech than before. The cheap theatres and coliseums may or may not be useful, depending on your strategy and circumstances in the game. You may want to warmonger in the mid or late game to get your most out of these buildings, using them to decrease war weariness.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Creative is a trait that is extremely useful in the early game and gets weaker as the game goes on. The +2[ICON_CULTURE] becomes less and less of a factor as the game progresses and more methods of producing culture accrue in each city. Also, the cheap buildings are available early and are all relatively cheap to begin with, so their faster production times will be less noticeable later in the game. By the middle of most games, the Creative trait is mostly a non-factor.</English>
		<German>Die Eigenschaft "Kreativ" ist vor allem in der frühen Phase einer Partie sehr nützlich, da sie die schnelle Erweiterung der eigenen Grenzen und damit die Inbesitznahme von neuen Gebieten und Ressourcen erlaubt. Der Patch 2.08 für das erste Addon "Warlords" fügte der Eigenschaft verbilligte Bibliotheken hinzu, die zu den besten Gebäuden des Spiels zählen, wodurch die Eigenschaft noch weiter aufgewertet wurde.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_WRITING]Schrift[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_DRAMA]Drama[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CONSTRUCTION]Bauwesen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]keine[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LIBRARY]Bibliothek[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_THEATRE]Theater[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_COLOSSEUM]Kolosseum[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_FREE_SPEECH]Meinungsfreiheit[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Der große Vorteil der Eigenschaft "Kreativ" besteht darin, dass mehr Freiheiten bei der Gründung einer Stadt und deren ersten Bauprojekten bestehen. Bei der Gründung einer Stadt muss nicht unbedingt darauf geachtet werden, dass sich eine wichtige Ressource im ersten Stadtfeldring befindet, damit sie sofort zugänglich ist; schon wenige Runden nach Gründung der Stadt steht sie zur Verfügung. Außerdem können Monumente, Stonehenge und die Verbreitung einer Religion außer Acht gelassen werden (nun, die letztere Aufgabe kann zumindest etwas entspannter angegangen werden).[PARAGRAPH:1]Zusätzlich kann die Eigenschaft "Kreativ" dabei helfen, schon früh in einer Partie das Tauziehen mit anderen Zivilisationen um Schlüsselgeländefelder, die mit wichtigen Ressourcen versehen sind, zu gewinnen. Ebenso kann die Eigenschaft, falls die Karte es erlaubt, dazu verwendet werden, um das Gebiet um einen Engpass abzuriegeln. "Kreativ" ist eher eine defensive Eigenschaft, nah verwandt mit der Eigenschaft "Schützend". Durch die frühe Erweiterung der eigenen Grenzen und die Belegung der Geländefelder mit der eigenen Kultur muss sich ein Gegner durch ein großes Gebiet quälen, bevor er angreifen kann. Außerdem wird es für andere Zivilisationen schwieriger, Geländefelder durch die Gründung von Städten oder deren Eroberung für sich zu gewinnen. Durch die Eigenschaft "Kreativ" erhöht sich der kulturelle Widerstand einer Stadt schneller, wodurch sie schwerer zu erobern ist.[PARAGRAPH:1]Die Technologie "Schrift" schaltet die verbilligten Bibliotheken frei, so dass diese Technologie offensichtlich sogar noch wichtiger ist als zuvor. Die verbilligten Theater und Kolosseen können, abhängig von der eigenen Strategie und den Umständen der Partie, hilfreich sein oder auch nicht. Im mittleren bis späten Spielverlauf sollte ein Krieg geführt werden, um den größten Nutzen aus diesen Gebäuden ziehen zu können, indem sie zur Verringerung der Kriegsunzufriedenheit eingesetzt werden.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]"Kreativ" ist eine Eigenschaft, die in der frühen Phase einer Partie sehr nützlich ist und während des weiteren Spielverlaufs seinen Nutzen verliert. Die zusätzlichen +2[ICON_CULTURE] werden immer weniger entscheidend während die Partie fortschreitet und sich in jeder Stadt mehr Möglichkeiten zur Generierung von Kulturpunkten ergeben. Außerdem sind die verbilligten Gebäude schon früh in einer Partie verfügbar und daher gleich zu Anfang relativ günstig, so dass deren schnellere Produktionszeiten später in der Partie weniger von Vorteil sind. In der Mitte der meisten Partien spielt die Eigenschaft "Kreativ" fast keine Rolle mehr.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CRUEL</Tag>
		<English>Cruel</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Cruel</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Cruel</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Crudele</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Cruel:Cruel:Crueles:Crueles</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Okrutny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CRUEL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This leader believes it is better to be feared than to be loved, and diligently works to instill that fear into parts of his society he deems most dangerous to his own dominanace. Constant purges in the army leave its leadership weakened, with less able men eligible for promotions. - TR Team.</English>
		<Italian>Questo leader crede che sia meglio essere temuti che amati, e si impegna diligentemente per instillare la paura nelle parti della società che ritiene più pericolose per il suo governo. Purghe costanti nell'esercito rendono più debole la sua leadership, con pochi uomini abili che possono ottenere le promozioni.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CRUEL_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Cru</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Cru</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Cru</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cru</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Cru</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Okr</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DECEIVER</Tag>
		<English>Deceiver</English>
		<French>Sournois</French>
		<German>Betrüger</German>
		<Italian>Traditore</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Traidor:Traidora:Traidores:Traidoras</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Kłamca</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DECEIVER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DECEIVER_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Dec</English>
		<French>Sou.</French>
		<German>Bet</German>
		<Italian>Tra</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tra</Spanish>
		<Polish>Kła</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DIPLOMACY</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 To Diplomatic Relations</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 de Relations Diplomatiques</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 zu diplomatischen Beziehungen</German>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 a las relaciones diplomáticas</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 do relacji dyplomatycznych</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DISABLED</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Trait disabled until reaching the [COLOR_NEGATIVE_TEXT]%s1_tech Era[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Doctrines inactifs avant l'ère: [COLOR_NEGATIVE_TEXT]%s1_tech Era[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Merkmal deaktiviert bis zum Zeitalter [COLOR_NEGATIVE_TEXT]%s1_tech[COLOR_REVERT]</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Tratti disattivati fino al raggiungimento di [COLOR_NEGATIVE_TEXT]%s1_tech Era[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Rasgo desactivado hasta alcanzar la [COLOR_NEGATIVE_TEXT]%s1_tech[COLOR_REVERT]</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Cecha znika po osiągnięciu Ery: [COLOR_NEGATIVE_TEXT]%s1_tech[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DISABLED_OFF</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]This trait is only for leaders when playing the Developing Leader Option[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Ce trait est uniquement pour les joueurs ayant activé l'option Dévelopement des Leader[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]nur bei aktivierter Einstellung "Führungskräfteentwicklung" verfügbar[COLOR_REVERT]</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Questo tratto è disponibile solo se l'opzione "Personalità in sviluppo" è attivata[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Cecha dostępna tylko dla Przywódców w grze z opcją Ulepszenie Przywódców[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DISABLED_ON</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]This trait is only for leaders when not playing the Developing Leader Option[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Ce trait est uniquement pour les joueurs n'utilisant pas l'option Dévelopement des Leader[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]bei aktivierter Einstellung "Führungskräfteentwicklung" nicht verfügbar[COLOR_REVERT]</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Questo tratto è disponibile solo se l'opzione "Personalità in sviluppo" è disattivata[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Cecha dostępna tylko dla Przywódców bez gry z opcją Ulepszenie Przywódców[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DISALLOWED</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Leaders with this trait may not select %s1_Trait Trait[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Les leaders possédant ce trait ne peuvent pas sélectionner le Trait : %s1_Trait[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]"%s1_Trait" nicht gleichzeitig auswählbar[COLOR_REVERT]</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DISTANCE_MOD</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% change to RevIdx City Distance penalty</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Modif de %D1% à la pénalité de Distance de Ville RevIdx</French>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% a la penalización a la estabilidad revolucionaria por distancia con la capital</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% zmiany kary za odleg3ośae od miasta</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DOUBLE_SPEED_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Double Production Speed of[SPACE]</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Double la vitesse de production de:[SPACE]</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Doppelte Produktionsgeschwindigkeit für:[SPACE]</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Raddoppia la velocità di produzione di[SPACE]</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Dobla la velocidad de producción de[SPACE]</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Podwójna szybkość Produkcji:[SPACE]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_DRAFT_ON_CAPTURE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Automatically Drafts new units in newly conquered cities.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Enrôle automatiquement des unités dans les Villes nouvellement conquises.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Recluta automaticamente nuove unità nelle città appena conquistate.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Automatycznie Powołuje nowe jednostki w nowo podbitych miastach.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_EXCESSIVE</Tag>
		<English>Excessive</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Excessif</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Excessive</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Eccessivo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Exagerado:Exagerada:Exagerados:Exageradas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Przesadny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_EXCESSIVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The opulent court of this ruler is a real strain on the state budget. - TR Team.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_EXCESSIVE_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Exc</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Exc</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Exc</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Ecc</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Exa</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Prze</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_EXPANSIVE</Tag>
		<English>Expansive</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Accessible:Accessible:Accessibles:Accessibles</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Expansionist:Expansionistin</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Espansionista:Espansionista</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Expansionista:Expansionista</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Ekspansywny:Ekspansywna:Ekspansywny:Ekspansywna</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_EXPANSIVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Expansive doesn't look that great at first glance. In fact, it first appears to belong in the category of "weak" traits, like Protective. After all, health is not a big problem; it's happiness that cramps your growth early in the game. And once you get used to those sickly green tendrils floating around your city, you realize that its effects aren't usually that bad. Health problems just slow growth a little.[PARAGRAPH:1]But hang on. Granaries--cheap for Expansive leaders--are one of the most useful buildings in the game. With grains, they provide additional health. But more importantly, they allow you to leverage slavery by growing your sacrificed population back faster.[PARAGRAPH:1]And with the Warlords 2.08 patch, Expansive got a needed boost thanks to slightly cheaper workers. You can always use more workers, especially early in the game.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_POTTERY]Pottery[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_COMPASS]Compass[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BRONZE_WORKING]Bronze Working[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MATHEMATICS]Mathematics[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_HANGING_GARDEN]The Hanging Gardens[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_NOTRE_DAME]Notre Dame[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GRANARY]Granary[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_HARBOR]Harbor[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_SLAVERY]Slavery[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Bee-line to Pottery. Build (or whip) your cheap granaries. Whip some more and keep whipping.[PARAGRAPH:1]Read up on how to best leverage the slavery civic in order to maximize hammer overflow from whipping, making both the build you whip and the following build cheaper. Thanks to the granary, the population will grow back faster, allowing you to whip them again.[PARAGRAPH:1]Obviously, build more Workers since they're cheaper for you, and put them to work. Get your tiles improved and your resources connected faster. Just remember that the +25% for Worker builds is accelerated by hammers, not by food, so you'll need to improve some tiles with good production and work them while the Worker is being built to take advantage of this. Since harbours are cheap, try to claim several coastal cities so you can leverage the advantages of that cheap building.[PARAGRAPH:1]Also look for opportunities to leverage that +2 health. Early on, you can place a city smack-dab in the jungle, for example, or surrounded by flood plains. In addition, you can construct healthreducing buildings like forges and factories with less concern for their impact on health. You can chop more forests because you don't need their health benefits (hence the attractiveness of the Bronze Working and Mathematics techs). Just keep in mind that the trait does not make your cities invincible, and you will have to concern yourself with their health--just later rather than sooner.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Hanging Gardens is an attractive wonder for Expansive. It might not seem so at first--I already have a health boost, why do I need more? Because you're pursuing a strategy that pushes the envelope of your cities' health, that's why. I'm fond of wonders and buildings that further enhance a trait's benefits (which is why I like to try to build the Parthenon when I'm playing as a Philosophical leader, for example). The Hanging Gardens also provides more citizens to whip away. And hey--GPP towards a Great Engineer! You gotta like that.[PARAGRAPH:1]Notre Dame can also be handy. If you're whipping 'til your hands bleed, the big cathedral's happy boost may be very welcome indeed.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Like many other traits such as Creative, the effects of Expansive diminish as the game goes on. Other means of increasing health appear, the cheap buildings are early ones, and by the end of the game, once your railroad network is complete, your plentiful, cheap workers start to become idle. You may also switch away from the Slavery civic, losing one of the principal benefits of the cheap granaries.[PARAGRAPH:1]And as with most other traits, Expansive does not provide any direct economic benefits.</English>
		<German>Die Eigenschaft "Expansiv" sieht auf den ersten Blick nicht besonders interessant aus. Tatsächlich scheint sie, in die Kategorie der "schwachen" Eigenschaften zu gehören, wie beispielsweise "Schützend". Immerhin ist Gesundheit kein großes Problem, schließlich ist es die Zufriedenheit, die früh in einer Partie das eigene Wachstum hemmt. Und sobald diese kränklichen grünen Ranken, die um die eigenen Städte schweben, zur Normalität geworden sind, wird klar, dass ihre Auswirkungen in der Regel nicht so schlimm sind. Probleme mit der Gesundheit einer Stadt verlangsamen das Wachstum nur ein wenig.[PARAGRAPH:1]Aber abwarten. Kornspeicher, die für Oberhäupter mit der Eigenschaft "Expansiv" relativ günstig sind, sind eines der nützlichsten Gebäude im Spiel. Falls eine Getreide-Ressource verfügbar ist, erzeugen sie zusätzliche Gesundheit. Aber, was noch wichtiger ist, sie ermöglichen den wirksamen Einsatz der Gesellschaftsform "Sklaverei", da geopferte Bürger schneller "nachwachsen".[PARAGRAPH:1]Und mit dem Patch 2.08 für das erste Addon "Warlords" erhielt die Eigenschaft "Expansiv" eine dringend nötige Verstärkung durch leicht verbilligte Bautrupps. Es ist immer besser, mehr Bautrupps einsetzen zu können, besonders in der frühen Phase einer Partie.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_POTTERY]Keramik[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_COMPASS]Kompass[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BRONZE_WORKING]Bronzeverarbeitung[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MATHEMATICS]Mathematik[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_HANGING_GARDEN]Hängende Gärten[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_NOTRE_DAME]Notre-Dame[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GRANARY]Kornspeicher[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_HARBOR]Hafen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_SLAVERY]Sklaverei[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Das erste Forschungziel sollte "Keramik" sein. Außerdem sollten die verbilligten Kornspeicher errichtet werden (oder deren Produktion durch Zwangsarbeit beschleunigt werden). Die Produktion sollte immer durch Zwangsarbeit beschleunigt werden und zwar, wenn möglich, während der gesamten Partie.[PARAGRAPH:1]Daher ist es wichtig, sich darüber zu informieren, wie die Gesellschaftsform "Sklaverei" am wirksamsten eingesetzt wird, um den Produktionsüberschuss der Zwangsarbeit zu maximieren und somit sowohl das derzeitige Bauprojekt als auch das folgende schneller fertigstellen zu können. Dank dem Kornspeicher, wird die Bevölkerung schneller nachwachsen, wodurch der erneute Einsatz der Zwangsarbeit ermöglicht wird.[PARAGRAPH:1]Offensichtlich sollten auch mehr Bautrupps aufgestellt und eingesetzt werden, da sie ebenfalls verbilligt verfügbar sind. Eigene Geländefelder sollten so schnell wie möglich mit Modernisierungen ausgestattet und Ressourcen erschlossen werden. Dabei sollte nicht vergessen werden, dass die 25% höhere Produktionsgeschwindigkeit für Bautrupps von der Produktionsleistung abhängt und nicht von der Nahrungsproduktion, so dass einige Geländefelder mit produktionsfördernden Modernisierungen ausgestattet und diese auch während der Produktion eines Bautrupps bearbeitet werden sollten. Da Häfen ebenfalls verbilligt sind, sollte versucht werden, einige Küstenstädte zu erlangen, so dass der Vorteil dieses Gebäudes auch genutzt werden kann.[PARAGRAPH:1]Außerdem sollte nach Möglichkeiten Ausschau gehalten werden, um die zusätzlichen +2 Gesundheit wirksam einsetzen zu können. Beispielsweise kann schon früh eine Stadt mitten im Dschungel oder im Schwemmland platziert werden. Zusätzlich können gesundheitsvermindernde Gebäude wie Schmieden und Fabriken errichtet werden, ohne deren Einfluss auf die Gesundheit einer Stadt berücksichtigen zu müssen. Es können auch mehr Wälder abgeholzt werden, da deren Gesundheitsboni nicht benötigt (deswegen sind die Technologien "Bronzeverarbeitung" und "Mathematik" so interessant). Allerdings macht die Eigenschaft "Expansiv" die eigenen Städte nicht unbesiegbar, die Beschäftigung mit der Gesundheit der eigenen Städte wird nur weiter nach hinten verschoben als sonst üblich.[PARAGRAPH:1]Die "Hängende Gärten" sind ein interessantes Weltwunder für diese Eigenschaft. Auf den ersten Blick erscheint dies nicht so: Ein Gesundheitsbonus ist schon vorhanden. Warum sollte ein zusätzlicher benötigt werden? Weil mit dieser Eigenschaft eine Strategie verfolgt wird, die die Gesundheit der eigenen Städte bis zum Äußersten treibt, deshalb. Es sollten bevorzugt Wunder und Gebäude errichtet werden, die die Vorteile einer Eigenschaft noch weiter erhöhen (deshalb kann beispielsweise bei einem Oberhaupt mit der Eigenschaft "Philosophisch" versucht werden, das "Parthenon" zu errichten). Die "Hängende Gärten" erhöhen außerdem die Bevölkerungszahl, die wiederum für Zwangsarbeit eingesetzt werden können. Und gewähren noch Große Persönlichkeit-Punkte für einen Großen Ingenieur! Das ist großartig.[PARAGRAPH:1]Das Weltwunder "Notre-Dame" kann ebenfalls nützlich sein. Bei wiederholtem Einsatz der Zwangsarbeit, kann der Zufriedenheitsbonus dieser großen Kathedrale tatsächlich sehr angenehm sein.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Wie bei vielen andere Eigenschaften, beispielsweise "Kreativ", lassen die Vorteile der Eigenschaft "Expansiv" im Verlauf einer Partie nach. Andere Methoden, um die Gesundheit zu erhöhen, werden verfügbar, die verbilligten Gebäude sind nur in der frühen Phase einer Partie von Vorteil und sobald das eigene Schienennetz gegen Ende einer Partie vollendet ist, werden die Massen von billigen Bautrupps nutzlos. Außerdem könnte der Wunsch aufkommen, von der "Sklaverei" zu einer anderen Gesellschaftsform zu wechseln, wodurch einer der Hauptvorteile der verbilligten Kornspeicher verloren ginge.[PARAGRAPH:1]Und wie viele andere Eigenschaften gewährt "Expansiv" keine direkten wirtschaftlichen Vorteile.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_EXTRA_GOODY</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Gains a second result from Goody Huts and Islands.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Reçoit un second cadeau des Huttes et Iles.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ottieni un secondo bonus da villaggi tribali e isole sconosciute.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Otrzymujesz drugą nagrodę z Chatek i Nieznanych Wysp.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_EXTRA_YIELD_THRESHOLDS_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]+1%F1_yield on Plots with %d2%F3_yield</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]+1%F1_yield sur les cases avec: %d2%F3_yield</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]+1%F1_yield auf Geländefeldern mit %d2%F3_yield</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]+1%F1_yield su caselle con %d2%F3_yield</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]+1 %F1_yield en las casillas con %d2 %F3_yield</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]+1%F1_yield na polach z: %d2%F3_yield</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FANATICAL</Tag>
		<English>Fanatical</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Fanatique</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Fanatical</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Fanatico</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Fanático:Fanática:Fanáticos:Fanáticas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Fanatyczny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FANATICAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This ruler puts blind faith above all other merits; talented but sceptically minded people will find themselves unwanted at his court. - TR Team.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FANATICAL_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Fan</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Fan</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Fan</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Fan</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Fan</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FINANCIAL</Tag>
		<English>Financial</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Financier:Financière:Financiers:Financières</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Kommerziell</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Economista:Economista</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Financiero:Financiera</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Finansowy:Finansowa:Finansowy:Finansowa'</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FINANCIAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This is quite probably the strongest of the traits, at least at levels below Emperor, so much so that many players consider Financial to be a "crutch" and avoid leaders with this trait because they feel it offers an unfair advantage. The game developers apparently agreed, hence in one of the early patches they removed the double production speed of banks to lessen its power. Even so, Financial remains a truly awesome trait.[PARAGRAPH:1]At first, it seems so subtle: +1[ICON_COMMERCE] on some tiles? So what?[PARAGRAPH:1]The answer, of course, is this: It's the economy, stupid. Say what you want about military, research, religion, and other game elements; ultimately, your civilization requires a robust economy in order to support everything else you do. Military units incur maintenance costs, more so if they're outside of your territory. Cities likewise have maintenance costs, hampering your rate of expansion and requiring you to ensure each city can somehow pay for itself. And to keep up in technology you have to be able to set aside funds to support research. The Financial trait makes all of these tasks a little easier--if handled well, a lot easier.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_POTTERY]Pottery[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CURRENCY]Currency[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_GUILDS]Guilds[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BANKING]Banking[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_LIBERALISM]Liberalism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_PRINTING_PRESS]Printing Press[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_DEMOCRACY]Democracy[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CORPORATION]Corporation[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_COLOSSUS]The Colossus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_WALL_STREET]Wall Street[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_MARKET]Market[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GROCER]Grocer[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BANK]Bank[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LIBRARY]Library[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_UNIVERSITY]University[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_OBSERVATORY]Observatory[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LABORATORY]Laboratory[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_FREE_SPEECH]Free Speech[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_EMANCIPATION]Emancipation[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]The main way to leverage the financial trait is very straightforward: cottage spam. Yes, the tried-and-true Cottage Economy, or CE. Have your [LINK=UNIT_WORKER]Workers[\LINK] lay down as many [LINK=IMPROVEMENT_COTTAGE]cottages[\LINK] as your population can work while still working other worthwhile tiles as well. I'm especially fond of placing cottages on riverside grassland tiles, as the Financial benefit kicks in as soon as the cottage is built, and the 2 food feeds the citizen working the tile (floodplains, with 3 food, are even better for cottages, supporting city growth along with the economy). Just remember you may have to irrigate some of those tiles instead, by placing farms on them, in order to feed and grow your population and/or to chain irrigate another tile. Make sure you have citizens working the cottages steadily, however, as it's the only way to make them grow and increase their revenue.[PARAGRAPH:1]In addition, be on the lookout for resources that provide additional commerce. Gems, gold, and silver are obvious targets, but spices, silk, and wine are good as well; all will earn you the +1[ICON_COMMERCE] benefit in addition to the additional commerce of the resource. You want to claim these resources, ensure they're in a city's fat cross, and are improved and then worked by a citizen. Most of the commerce-rich resources also increase happiness, which means you can grow your other cities larger and, in turn, work more cottages and other commerce-rich tiles.[PARAGRAPH:1]Since you'll have all that extra commerce rolling in, prioritize buildings that do something with it, and the technologies that enable them. Libraries, monasteries, universities, observatories, and laboratories all multiply the amount of research you convert from commerce via the science slider, while markets, grocers, and banks multiply whatever gold is left over. In addition, Printing Press will increase the yield from your cottage investment, as will the Free Speech civic. Emancipation will make any immature cottages grow faster.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]First off, Financial provides no direct benefit to a tile that isn't providing at least 2 commerce. This can make you reluctant to work tiles without the benefit, even though you will need to. This means a production city, which mostly works hammer-rich rather than commerce-rich tiles, gains no direct benefit from the trait. You will, however, need at least one production city, preferably more, so don't overlook them in favour of commerce cities. The same goes for tile improvements. Yes, you can place a cottage on a grassland hill. But should you? A mine would provide much-needed hammers, something commerce cities often chronically lack.[PARAGRAPH:1]The biggest problem with Financial, however, is the vulnerability of your economy, especially as time goes on. It takes a lot of turns to make a cottage grow into a town, but that investment can be quickly undone by a couple of pillaging enemy units. And the not-inconsiderable amount of gold to be gained from pillaging cottages is very tempting to the AI. You will need to garrison your best, oldest commerce cities with anti-pillaging units if you go to war. Also try to have your best commerce cities inland at the heart of your empire, rather than on the more vulnerable borders or coastline.</English>
		<German>This is quite probably the strongest of the traits, at least at levels below Emperor, so much so that many players consider Financial to be a "crutch" and avoid leaders with this trait because they feel it offers an unfair advantage. The game developers apparently agreed, hence in one of the early patches they removed the double production speed of banks to lessen its power. Even so, Financial remains a truly awesome trait.[PARAGRAPH:1]At first, it seems so subtle: +1[ICON_COMMERCE] on some tiles? So what?[PARAGRAPH:1]The answer, of course, is this: It's the economy, stupid. Say what you want about military, research, religion, and other game elements; ultimately, your civilization requires a robust economy in order to support everything else you do. Military units incur maintenance costs, more so if they're outside of your territory. Cities likewise have maintenance costs, hampering your rate of expansion and requiring you to ensure each city can somehow pay for itself. And to keep up in technology you have to be able to set aside funds to support research. The Financial trait makes all of these tasks a little easier--if handled well, a lot easier.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_POTTERY]Keramik[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CURRENCY]Währung[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_GUILDS]Gilden[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BANKING]Bankwesen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_LIBERALISM]Liberalismus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_PRINTING_PRESS]Druckerpresse[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_DEMOCRACY]Demokratie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CORPORATION]Kapitalgesellschaft[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_COLOSSUS]Koloss[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_WALL_STREET]Wall Street[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_MARKET]Markt[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GROCER]Krämer[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BANK]Bank[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LIBRARY]Bibliothek[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_UNIVERSITY]Universität[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_OBSERVATORY]Observatorium[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LABORATORY]Labor[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_FREE_SPEECH]Meinungsfreiheit[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_EMANCIPATION]Emanzipation[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]The main way to leverage the financial trait is very straightforward: cottage spam. Yes, the tried-and-true Cottage Economy, or CE. Have your [LINK=UNIT_WORKER]Workers[\LINK] lay down as many [LINK=IMPROVEMENT_COTTAGE]cottages[\LINK] as your population can work while still working other worthwhile tiles as well. I'm especially fond of placing cottages on riverside grassland tiles, as the Financial benefit kicks in as soon as the cottage is built, and the 2 food feeds the citizen working the tile (floodplains, with 3 food, are even better for cottages, supporting city growth along with the economy). Just remember you may have to irrigate some of those tiles instead, by placing farms on them, in order to feed and grow your population and/or to chain irrigate another tile. Make sure you have citizens working the cottages steadily, however, as it's the only way to make them grow and increase their revenue.[PARAGRAPH:1]In addition, be on the lookout for resources that provide additional commerce. Gems, gold, and silver are obvious targets, but spices, silk, and wine are good as well; all will earn you the +1[ICON_COMMERCE] benefit in addition to the additional commerce of the resource. You want to claim these resources, ensure they're in a city's fat cross, and are improved and then worked by a citizen. Most of the commerce-rich resources also increase happiness, which means you can grow your other cities larger and, in turn, work more cottages and other commerce-rich tiles.[PARAGRAPH:1]Since you'll have all that extra commerce rolling in, prioritize buildings that do something with it, and the technologies that enable them. Libraries, monasteries, universities, observatories, and laboratories all multiply the amount of research you convert from commerce via the science slider, while markets, grocers, and banks multiply whatever gold is left over. In addition, Printing Press will increase the yield from your cottage investment, as will the Free Speech civic. Emancipation will make any immature cottages grow faster.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]First off, Financial provides no direct benefit to a tile that isn't providing at least 2 commerce. This can make you reluctant to work tiles without the benefit, even though you will need to. This means a production city, which mostly works hammer-rich rather than commerce-rich tiles, gains no direct benefit from the trait. You will, however, need at least one production city, preferably more, so don't overlook them in favour of commerce cities. The same goes for tile improvements. Yes, you can place a cottage on a grassland hill. But should you? A mine would provide much-needed hammers, something commerce cities often chronically lack.[PARAGRAPH:1]The biggest problem with Financial, however, is the vulnerability of your economy, especially as time goes on. It takes a lot of turns to make a cottage grow into a town, but that investment can be quickly undone by a couple of pillaging enemy units. And the not-inconsiderable amount of gold to be gained from pillaging cottages is very tempting to the AI. You will need to garrison your best, oldest commerce cities with anti-pillaging units if you go to war. Also try to have your best commerce cities inland at the heart of your empire, rather than on the more vulnerable borders or coastline.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FLIGHT_RANGE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Flight Operation Range for Air units.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount de portée opérationnelle pour les unités aériennes.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount al raggio d'azione per le unità aeree.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Zasięgu Operacyjnego dla jednostek Powietrznych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FOREIGN</Tag>
		<English>Foreign</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Lointain</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Foreign</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Straniero</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Distante:Distante:Distantes:Distantes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Cudoziemski</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FOREIGN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This leader rules his/her nation with the preconception that through a deep understanding of foreign affairs and that by heavily investing in trade and international relations - the nation and its people will ultimately be better off. This is true to an extent, but due to a lack of domestic investment and concentration, certain areas are on the contrary - backward and lacking. This correlates directly in a number of tangible ways, some beneficial, some detrimental - overall it leads to cultural disadvantage and domestic neglect.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FOREIGN_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>For</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Loi</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>For</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Str</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Dis</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Cdz</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FREE_PROMOTION_UNITCOMBAT</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Free [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT][LINK=%s1_PromotionType]%s2_PromotionName[\LINK][COLOR_REVERT] Promotion for[SPACE]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Promotion [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT][LINK=%s1_PromotionType]%s2_PromotionName[\LINK][COLOR_REVERT] gratuite pour[SPACE]</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]freie Beförderung [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT][LINK=%s1_PromotionType]%s2_PromotionName[\LINK][COLOR_REVERT] für[SPACE]</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FREE_SPEC_NW</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Gets a Free Specialist for each National Wonder where built.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Reçoit un Spécialiste gratuit pour chaque Merveille Nationale construite.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ottieni uno specialista gratuito per ogni Meraviglia Nazionale nella città in cui è costruito.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Otrzymujesz darmowego Specjaliste na każdy Cud Narodowy który wybudujesz.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FREE_SPEC_TP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Gets a Free Specialist for each Team Project where built.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Reçoit un Spécialiste gratuit pour chaque Projet d'Equipe construit.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ottieni uno specialista gratuito per ogni Progetto di squadra nella città in cui è costruito.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Otrzymujesz darmowego Specjaliste na każdy Projekt który wybudujesz.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FREE_SPEC_WW</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Gets a Free Specialist for each World Wonder where built.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Reçoit un Spécialiste gratuit pour chaque Merveille Mondiale construite.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ottieni uno specialista gratuito per ogni Grande Meraviglia nella città in cui è costruito.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Otrzymujesz darmowego Specjaliste na każdy Wielki Cud który wybudujesz.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_FREE_UNIT_UPKEEP_MILITARY_PER_100_POP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Free military unit upkeep per 100 population: %D1</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]freie militärische Einheiten pro 100 Bürger: %D1</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_GOLDEN_AGE_ON_BIRTH_OF_GP_TYPE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Starts a Golden Age when a %s1_GP is born in an owned city.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Démarre l'Age d'Or lorsqu'un %s1_GP est né dans la ville.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Comincia un'età dell'oro quando un %s1_GP nasce in una tua città.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Rozpoczyna Złotą Erę gdy: %s1_GP narodzi się w mieście.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_GOOD_RELIGION_MOD</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%s1% to Revolution Bonus from State [ICON_RELIGION]</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%S1% de Bonus de Révolution de la religion d'état [ICON_RELIGION]</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%S1% zu Revolutionsbonus durch Staats-[ICON_RELIGION]</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Bonus stabilità: +%S1% per [ICON_RELIGION] di Stato</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%S1% a la bonificación a la estabilidad revolucionaria por la [ICON_RELIGION] oficial</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]+%S1% do Bonusu Rewolucyjnego z [ICON_RELIGION] narodowej</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_GREAT_GENERAL_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Great Military People Emergence</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Emergen de Général illustre</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Geburtenrate für Große Feldherren</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% ritmo di nascita dei Grandi Generali</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% do Wielkiego Generała</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_GREAT_PEOPLE_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% [ICON_GREATPEOPLE] Birth Rate</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Taux de natalité [ICON_GREATPEOPLE] %D1%%</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Geburtenrate [ICON_GREATPEOPLE]</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% ritmo di nascita [ICON_GREATPEOPLE]</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% a la tasa de natalidad de [ICON_GREATPEOPLE]</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Częstotliwość Narodzin: [ICON_GREATPEOPLE] %D1%%</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HAPPINESS</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/City</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/Ville</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/Stadt</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/Città</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/ciudad</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/Miasto</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HAPPINESS_2</Tag>
		<English>+%d1_Change[ICON_HAPPY]: "Our leader is the best!"</English>
		<French>+%d1_Change[ICON_HAPPY]: "Notre leader est le meilleur!"</French>
		<German>+%d1_Change[ICON_HAPPY]: "Unser Anführer ist der Beste!"</German>
		<Spanish>+%d1_Change[ICON_HAPPY]: "¡Nuestro líder es el más grande!"</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HOLY_CITY_NON_STATE_REL_XP_MODIFIER</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Free Experience to all units trained in Holy Cities of Non-State Religions</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% EXP Gratuite pour toutes les unités formées dans les Villes Saintes des religions non étatiques</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HOLY_CITY_STATE_REL_XP_MODIFIER</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Free Experience to all units trained in the Holy City of your State Religion</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Expérience gratuite pour toutes les unités formées dans la ville sainte de votre religion d'État</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% esperienza gratuita a tutte le unità addestrate nella Città santa della tua religione di stato.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Darmowego doświadczenia dla jednostek wytrenowanych w Świętym Mieście Twojej Religi Narodowej</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HUMANITARIAN</Tag>
		<English>Humanitarian</English>
		<French>Humanitaire</French>
		<German>Humanitär</German>
		<Italian>Umanitario</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Humanitario:Humanitaria:Humanitarios:Humanitarias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Humanitarny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HUMANITARIAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HUMANITARIAN_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Hum</English>
		<French>Hum</French>
		<Italian>Uma</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HUNTER_GATHERER</Tag>
		<English>Hunter-Gatherer</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Chasseur-Cueilleur</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Jäger und Sammler:Jägerin und Sammlerin</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Cacciatore-Raccoglitore</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Naturalista:Naturalista:Naturalistas:Naturalistas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Łowco-Zbieracz</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HUNTER_GATHERER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A hunter-gatherer society is one whose primary subsistence method involves the direct procurement of edible plants and animals from the wild, foraging and hunting without significant recourse to the domestication of either. Up to 80% of the food is obtained by gathering.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_HUNTER_GATHERER_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>H-G</English>
		<French>
			<Text>C-C</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>H-G</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>C-R</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Nat</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Ł-Z</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_IDEALISTIC</Tag>
		<English>Idealistic</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Idéaliste</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Idealistic</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Idealista</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Idealista:Idealista:Idealistas:Idealistas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Perfekcjonista</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_IDEALISTIC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This leader's belief in an exalted ideal leads to strict guidelines to follow. This spills out across the government meaning gross inefficiency, longer civic anarchy and higher upkeep. This exalted ideal does however possess a certain quality that lingers in the minds of the great thinkers from within the nation, meaning a greater affinity towards to desire to actually 'think' and the aspiration to be a 'thinker'.</English>
		<Italian>Le credenze di questo leader negli ideali umanisti gli fa preferire la diplomazia alla forza militare per risolvere i conflitti. Naturalmente, viene criticato dal suo stesso staff militare e dai politici più famelici, che cercano di minare i suoi sforzi.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_IDEALISTIC_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Ide</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Ide</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Ide</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Ide</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Ide</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Perf</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_IMPERIALIST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>After several off-line games as Julius Caesar, my opinion of this trait has improved. I originally included it in the "Weak" category, but now feel it belongs in "Medium"--if it's used properly.[PARAGRAPH:1]Imperialistic supports aggressive expansion in two ways. First of all, Settlers are cheaper to build, allowing you to perform a faster land-grab early in the game. Second, to take advantage of the increased Great General emergence, you're encouraged to expand through aggression.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BRONZE_WORKING]Bronze Working[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MASONRY]Masonry[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MATHEMATICS]Mathematics[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CODE_OF_LAWS]Code of Laws[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_FASCISM]Fascism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]All military technologies[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_WALL]The Great Wall[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_MT_RUSHMORE]Mount Rushmore[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BARRACKS]Barracks[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_VASSALAGE]Vassalage[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_THEOCRACY]Theocracy[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_POLICE_STATE]Police State[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Obviously, pursue a REX (Rapid EXpansion) strategy in the early game, and follow this up with an aggressive, warmonger's expansion policy once your core cities are established. This especially suits Catherine the Great of Russia, since her Creative trait has definite synergy with an early game land-grabbing strategy.[PARAGRAPH:1]Keep in mind that the increased Settler production comes from hammers, not food. This means you'll want to focus as much on mines as farms and pastures when improving tiles in the early game. Chopping and whipping contribute hammers, so those get multiplied by the trait as well--hence the attraction of Bronze Working and Mathematics.[PARAGRAPH:1]You can enhance the increased GG emergence further by building the Great Wall. In addition to keeping barbs away, that wonder also provides +100% Great General emergence from battles that take place within your cultural borders, resulting in a +200% GG boost with the trait when defending within your own territory. Masonry, therefore, and a source of stone are likely to be priorities when playing as a leader with this trait.[PARAGRAPH:1]The chief way to take advantage of the Imperialistic trait once the original period of REX is over is simple: war. War early and war often. It's the only way to generate Great Generals (and remember that battling barbs earns you XPs, but not points towards a Great General.) Great Generals are actually one of the most useful Great People in the game, even if they lack some of the uses of other GPs (such as lightbulbing technologies or starting a Golden Age). You can attach them to units to uber-promote them, put them in cities to provide additional XPs or boost unit production with a military academy. Just remember to prioritize Code of Laws and courthouses to keep your ever-expanding empire economically viable.[PARAGRAPH:1]Many players favour combining the first Great General with a unit and giving it the Medic I, II, and III promotions. This medic unit will heal your stacks faster, allowing them to return to the fray much sooner. You can also use a GG to give a unit the Leadership promotion, which creates synergy with the Imperialistic trait because the promotion results in double XPs for that unit from every battle it survives, and those double XPs are doubled again in their count towards your next Great General. You can also combine the GG with a Caravel to give it Flanking I, Navigation I, and Navigation II in order to practically guarantee winning the circumnavigation bonus.[PARAGRAPH:1]Since you're going after several Great Generals (and likely basing much of your strategy on their benefits), you'll want to snag the free one that you get from researching Fascism first. With all the warmongering you'll be doing, you're going to want to build Mount Rushmore and run Police State to alleviate some of the War Weariness anyway.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Well, for starters, there's no cheap building and no economic advantage. It seems logical that Imperialistic should have cheap courthouses, but Organized has those, and shifting them away would seriously weaken that trait. Perhaps jails would have been a good cheap building for Imperialistic. If Civ IV had useful forts, faster build times of those would have been logical for this trait as well.[PARAGRAPH:1]Instead of a cheap building, however, there's a cheap unit. But Imperialistic's boost to Settler builds comes from hammers, not food. This means you need to work at cross-purposes in the early game, building mines to ensure your Settler builds take advantage of the trait. If food also boosted the Setter's build time, this would be a much stronger trait.[PARAGRAPH:1]The biggest weakness of the trait, however, is that it locks you into a specific strategy. You don't have to play as a warmonger with the Aggressive trait; you could leverage it to build a strong army and military infrastructure (the cheap barracks and drydocks count towards your power rating, after all) so you're left alone to build. With Imperialistic, however, you have to warmonger. There's no other way to earn those Great Generals except by fighting other civs. Don't play with this trait unless you're in the mood to knock heads, or you're wasting it.</English>
		<German>After several off-line games as Julius Caesar, my opinion of this trait has improved. I originally included it in the "Weak" category, but now feel it belongs in "Medium"--if it's used properly.[PARAGRAPH:1]Imperialistic supports aggressive expansion in two ways. First of all, Settlers are cheaper to build, allowing you to perform a faster land-grab early in the game. Second, to take advantage of the increased Great General emergence, you're encouraged to expand through aggression.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BRONZE_WORKING]Bronzeverarbeitung[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MASONRY]Steinmetzkunst[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MATHEMATICS]Mathematik[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CODE_OF_LAWS]Gesetzgebung[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_FASCISM]Faschismus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]All militärischen Technologien[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_WALL]Große Mauer[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_MT_RUSHMORE]Mount Rushmore[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BARRACKS]Kaserne[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_VASSALAGE]Vasallentum[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_THEOCRACY]Theokratie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_POLICE_STATE]Polizeistaat[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Obviously, pursue a REX (Rapid EXpansion) strategy in the early game, and follow this up with an aggressive, warmonger's expansion policy once your core cities are established. This especially suits Catherine the Great of Russia, since her Creative trait has definite synergy with an early game land-grabbing strategy.[PARAGRAPH:1]Keep in mind that the increased Settler production comes from hammers, not food. This means you'll want to focus as much on mines as farms and pastures when improving tiles in the early game. Chopping and whipping contribute hammers, so those get multiplied by the trait as well--hence the attraction of Bronze Working and Mathematics.[PARAGRAPH:1]You can enhance the increased GG emergence further by building the Great Wall. In addition to keeping barbs away, that wonder also provides +100% Great General emergence from battles that take place within your cultural borders, resulting in a +200% GG boost with the trait when defending within your own territory. Masonry, therefore, and a source of stone are likely to be priorities when playing as a leader with this trait.[PARAGRAPH:1]The chief way to take advantage of the Imperialistic trait once the original period of REX is over is simple: war. War early and war often. It's the only way to generate Great Generals (and remember that battling barbs earns you XPs, but not points towards a Great General.) Great Generals are actually one of the most useful Great People in the game, even if they lack some of the uses of other GPs (such as lightbulbing technologies or starting a Golden Age). You can attach them to units to uber-promote them, put them in cities to provide additional XPs or boost unit production with a military academy. Just remember to prioritize Code of Laws and courthouses to keep your ever-expanding empire economically viable.[PARAGRAPH:1]Many players favour combining the first Great General with a unit and giving it the Medic I, II, and III promotions. This medic unit will heal your stacks faster, allowing them to return to the fray much sooner. You can also use a GG to give a unit the Leadership promotion, which creates synergy with the Imperialistic trait because the promotion results in double XPs for that unit from every battle it survives, and those double XPs are doubled again in their count towards your next Great General. You can also combine the GG with a Caravel to give it Flanking I, Navigation I, and Navigation II in order to practically guarantee winning the circumnavigation bonus.[PARAGRAPH:1]Since you're going after several Great Generals (and likely basing much of your strategy on their benefits), you'll want to snag the free one that you get from researching Fascism first. With all the warmongering you'll be doing, you're going to want to build Mount Rushmore and run Police State to alleviate some of the War Weariness anyway.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Well, for starters, there's no cheap building and no economic advantage. It seems logical that Imperialistic should have cheap courthouses, but Organized has those, and shifting them away would seriously weaken that trait. Perhaps jails would have been a good cheap building for Imperialistic. If Civ IV had useful forts, faster build times of those would have been logical for this trait as well.[PARAGRAPH:1]Instead of a cheap building, however, there's a cheap unit. But Imperialistic's boost to Settler builds comes from hammers, not food. This means you need to work at cross-purposes in the early game, building mines to ensure your Settler builds take advantage of the trait. If food also boosted the Setter's build time, this would be a much stronger trait.[PARAGRAPH:1]The biggest weakness of the trait, however, is that it locks you into a specific strategy. You don't have to play as a warmonger with the Aggressive trait; you could leverage it to build a strong army and military infrastructure (the cheap barracks and drydocks count towards your power rating, after all) so you're left alone to build. With Imperialistic, however, you have to warmonger. There's no other way to earn those Great Generals except by fighting other civs. Don't play with this trait unless you're in the mood to knock heads, or you're wasting it.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_INDUSTRIOUS</Tag>
		<English>Industrious</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Travailleur:Travailleuse:Travailleurs:Travailleuses</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Industriell</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Industrioso:Industriosa</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Diligente:Diligente</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pracowity:Pracowita:Pracowity:Pracowita</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_INDUSTRIOUS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>If Aggressive is the warmonger's trait, Industrious is the builder's trait. Wonders are cheaper, enhancing their "ooo--shiny" appeal and giving you a leg up in the competitions to get them built. In addition, forges, a building that makes other buildings faster to build, is, well, faster to build.[PARAGRAPH:1]As of the Beyond the Sword expansion pack, this is now Civilization IV's most exclusive club, though not by much. All the other traits have 9 or 10 leaders who possess them, while Industrious is shared by only 8 leaders. And no, there's still no Industrious/Philosophical trait combination; it's obviously regarded by the game designers as overpowered.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MASONRY]Masonry[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MONOTHEISM]Monotheism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_METAL_CASTING]Metal Casting[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ASSEMBLY_LINE]Assembly Line[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Er... pretty much all of them. Well, maybe except for Chichen Itza.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_FORGE]Forge[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_FACTORY]Factory[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_ORGANIZED_RELIGION]Organized Religion[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_STATE_PROPERTY]State Property[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_CASTE_SYSTEM]Caste System[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_GREEN]Environmentalism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Build wonders, of course. Build them and leverage them and keep them out of the AI's grubby little hands. Also look for and claim the wonder-hurrying resources such as copper, iron, marble, and stone. Remember that the accelerated wonder production applies to the national wonders as well.[PARAGRAPH:1]Also, prioritize the Metal Casting tech in order to access your cheap building. A tactic with a great deal of synergy for Industrious leaders is to build the Oracle (a wonder, so it's cheaper) and select Metal Casting as your free technology. Then go build forges. Remember forges are also required for additional wonders like the Ironworks, the Colossus, the Eiffel Tower, and the Statue of Liberty. Since Metal Casting enables it, the Colossus is usually built right after its future city's forge is finished.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]When you're playing as an Industrious leader, the siren-like allure of being a "buildaholic" is even greater. Even though wonders are cheaper, they're still not dirt cheap. They require a considerable investment of hammers that could be put to better uses. As always, make sure the wonders you choose to build fit into your strategy and the circumstances of the game.</English>
		<German>If Aggressive is the warmonger's trait, Industrious is the builder's trait. Wonders are cheaper, enhancing their "ooo--shiny" appeal and giving you a leg up in the competitions to get them built. In addition, forges, a building that makes other buildings faster to build, is, well, faster to build.[PARAGRAPH:1]As of the Beyond the Sword expansion pack, this is now Civilization IV's most exclusive club, though not by much. All the other traits have 9 or 10 leaders who possess them, while Industrious is shared by only 8 leaders. And no, there's still no Industrious/Philosophical trait combination; it's obviously regarded by the game designers as overpowered.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MASONRY]Steinmetzkunst[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MONOTHEISM]Monotheismus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_METAL_CASTING]Metallguss[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ASSEMBLY_LINE]Fließband[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Hmm... eigentlich so gut wie alle, vielleicht außer Chichén Itzá.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_FORGE]Schmiede[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_FACTORY]Fabrik[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_ORGANIZED_RELIGION]Organisierte Religion[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_STATE_PROPERTY]Staatseigentum[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_CASTE_SYSTEM]Kastensystem[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_GREEN]Umweltschutz[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Build wonders, of course. Build them and leverage them and keep them out of the AI's grubby little hands. Also look for and claim the wonder-hurrying resources such as copper, iron, marble, and stone. Remember that the accelerated wonder production applies to the national wonders as well.[PARAGRAPH:1]Also, prioritize the Metal Casting tech in order to access your cheap building. A tactic with a great deal of synergy for Industrious leaders is to build the Oracle (a wonder, so it's cheaper) and select Metal Casting as your free technology. Then go build forges. Remember forges are also required for additional wonders like the Ironworks, the Colossus, the Eiffel Tower, and the Statue of Liberty. Since Metal Casting enables it, the Colossus is usually built right after its future city's forge is finished.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]When you're playing as an Industrious leader, the siren-like allure of being a "buildaholic" is even greater. Even though wonders are cheaper, they're still not dirt cheap. They require a considerable investment of hammers that could be put to better uses. As always, make sure the wonders you choose to build fit into your strategy and the circumstances of the game.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ISOLATIONIST</Tag>
		<English>Isolationist</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Isolationiste</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Isolationist</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Isolazionista</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Aislacionista:Aislacionista:Aislacionistas:Aislacionistas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Izolacjonista</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ISOLATIONIST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This leader believes in completely self-reliant state to the point where he is ready to cut off most connections to the outside world. - TR Team.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ISOLATIONIST_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Iso</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Iso</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Iso</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Iso</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Ais</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Izo</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_LESS_YIELD_THRESHOLDS_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]-1%F1_yield on Plots with %d2%F3_yield</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]-1%F1_yield sur les cases avec: %d2%F3_yield</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]-1%F1_yield auf Geländefeldern mit %d2%F3_yield</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]-1%F1_yield su caselle con %d2%F3_yield</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]-1 %F1_yield en las casillas con %d2 %F3_yield</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]-1%F1_yield na polach z: %d2%F3_yield</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MAKES_OCEAN_PASSABLE_WITHOUT_TECH</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Ocean is passable</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Peut traverser les océans</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Ozeanfelder können überquert werden</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Può attraversare l'oceano</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Se puede atravesar el Océano</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Ocean jest niedostępny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MAKES_OCEAN_PASSABLE_WITH_TECH</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Ocean becomes passable with[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s1</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Peut traverser les océans avec[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s1</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Ozeanfelder können nach der Erforschung von[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s1 überquert werden</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Può attraversare l'oceano dopo aver ricercato[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s1</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Se puede atravesar el Océano con [NUM1:el:la:los:las][NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s1</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Ocean staje się dostępny z[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_RESEARCH]%s1</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MAX_ANARCHY_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Max %d1 [NUM1:Turn:Turns] of Anarchy</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%d1 [NUM1:tour:tours] d'anarchie maximum</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Max. %d1 [NUM1:Runde:Runden] Unruhen</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%d1 [NUM1:turno massimo:turni massimi] di Anarchia</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]Máx. %d1 [NUM1:turno:turnos] de anarquía</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Maksymalna ilość tur Anarchii: %d1</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MAX_TRADE_ROUTES</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change to Maximum possible Trade Routes ([ICON_TRADE]) per City</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change de nombre maximum de routes commerciales ([ICON_TRADE]) par ville</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change al numero massimo di rotte commerciali ([ICON_TRADE]) per città</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Change do maksymalnej ilości Szlaków Handlowych ([ICON_TRADE]) na Miasto</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MEGALOMANIAC</Tag>
		<English>Megalomaniac</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mégalomaniaque</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Megalomaniac</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Megalomane</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Megalómano:Megalómana:Megalómanos:Megalómanas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Megaloman</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MEGALOMANIAC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Nothing less than the whole world will satisfy this man. He already sees himself as the world's greatest ruler, and demands that every project to immortalize his glory be accordingly grandiose. Or maybe he is just compensating for something? - TR Team.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MEGALOMANIAC_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Meg</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Meg</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Meg</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Meg</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Meg</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MIN_ANARCHY_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Min %d1 [NUM1:Turn:Turns] of Anarchy</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%d1 [NUM1:tour:tours] d'anarchie minimum</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Min. %d1 [NUM1:Runde:Runden] Unruhen</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%d1 [NUM1:turno minimo:turni minimi] di anarchia</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Minimalna ilość tur Anarchii: %d1</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MISSILE_CARGO_SPACE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Cargo Space for all Missile Carrying units.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Espace de chargement pour toutes les unités de transport de missiles.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount allo spazio di trasporto per tutte le unità che trasportano missili.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Miejsc dla Rakiet dla jednostek przewożących rakiety.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MISSILE_RANGE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Mission Operation Range for Missile units.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Portée opérationnelle pour les unités de missiles.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NATIONAL_WONDER_PRODUCTION_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% National Wonder Production</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Construction de merveilles nationales %D1%%</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Produktion Nationaler Wunder</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% produzione di Meraviglie Nazionali</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% a la producción de maravillas nacionales</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% do Budowy Narodowych Cudów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NAVAL_CARGO_SPACE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Cargo Space for all transport-capable Naval units.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Espace de chargement pour toutes les unités navales de transport.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount allo spazio di trasporto per tutte le unità navali da trasporto.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_Amount Miejsc dla wszystkich jednostek transportujących - morskich.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NEGATIVE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]This is a Negative Trait[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]C'est un Trait Négatif[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]negative Charaktereigenschaft[COLOR_REVERT]</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Questo è un tratto negativo[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]To jest Negatywna Cecha[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NOMAD</Tag>
		<English>Nomad</English>
		<French>Nomade</French>
		<German>Nomadisch</German>
		<Italian>Nomade</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Nómada:Nómada:Nómadas:Nómadas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Koczownik</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NOMAD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NOMAD_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Nom</English>
		<French>Nom.</French>
		<Spanish>Nóm</Spanish>
		<Polish>Kcz</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NONSTATE_RELIGIOUS_COMMERCE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Non State [ICON_RELIGION] Still produces base [ICON_CULTURE], [ICON_GOLD], [ICON_RESEARCH] amounts.</English>
		<French>
			<Text>[ICON_BULLET]Le [ICON_RELIGION] (non officielle) produit encore [ICON_CULTURE], [ICON_GOLD], [ICON_RESEARCH]</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>[ICON_BULLET]Nicht-staatliche [ICON_RELIGION] produziert immer noch [ICON_CULTURE], [ICON_GOLD], [ICON_RESEARCH]</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]La [ICON_RELIGION] non di Stato produrrà [ICON_CULTURE], [ICON_GOLD], [ICON_RESEARCH]</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]Las [ICON_RELIGION] no oficiales producirán [ICON_CULTURE], [ICON_GOLD], [ICON_RESEARCH]</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Nie narodowe [ICON_RELIGION] Nadal produkuje [ICON_CULTURE], [ICON_GOLD], [ICON_RESEARCH]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NON_HOLY_CITY_STATE_REL_XP_MODIFIER</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Free Experience to all units trained in the Holy Cities of religions other than your State Religion.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% EXP gratuite pour toutes les unités formées dans les villes saintes des religions autres que votre religion d'État.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% esperienza gratuita a tutte le unità addestrate nella Città santa di una religione diversa dalla tua religione di stato.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Darmowego doświadczenia dla jednostek wytrenowanych w Świętym Mieście wszystkich religi Nie Narodowych</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NON_STATE_REL_SPREAD_MODIFIER</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% chance to Spread Non State Religion with your Missionaries.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% chances de propager la religion non étatique avec vos missionnaires.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% di diffondere una religione non di stato con i tuoi missionari.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% do szansy rozszerzenia Religi Nie-Państwowej przez Misjonarzy.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NOT_ON_GAME_OPTION</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Deactivated when the %s2_Option Game Option is in use[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]désactivé lorsque l'option %s2_Option est active[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Inattivo se l'opzione %s2_Option è attivata[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Dezaktywuje się gdy opcja: %s2_Option jest aktywna[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NO_ANARCHY_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]No Anarchy</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Pas d'anarchie</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Keine Unruhen</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Nessuna Anarchia</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]Sin anarquía</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Brak Anarchii</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_NO_UPKEEP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]No Upkeep Costs for %s1 Civics</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Aucun coût d'entretien pour: %s1</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]keine laufenden Kosten für %s1</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Nessun costo di mantenimento per %s1</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]Sin costes de mantenimiento por %s1</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Brak kosztów Utrzymania dla: %s1</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ON_GAME_OPTION</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Only active when the %s1_Option Game Option is in use[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]actif uniquement lorsque l'option %s1_Option est active[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]nur bei aktivierter Einstellung "%s1_Option" verfügbar[COLOR_REVERT]</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Attivo solo se l'opzione %s1_Option è attivata[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Aktywna tylko gdy opcja: %s2_Option jest aktywna[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_OPTION_EDIT</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Replaces the %s1_Trait when the %s1_Option Game Option is in use[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Remplace le trait %s1_Trait lorsque l'option %s1_Option est active[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Sostituisce la caratteristica %s1_Trait quando l'opzione %s1_Option è attivata[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Zamienia: %s1_Trait gdy opcja %s2_Option jest aktywna[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ORGANIZED</Tag>
		<English>Organized</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Organisé:Organisée:Organisés:Organisées</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Organisiert</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Organizzato:Organizzata</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Organizado:Organizada</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Zorganizowany:Zorganizowana:Zorganizowany:Zorganizowana</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_ORGANIZED_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Although Organized has a direct economic benefit--reducing the overhead of civics--it isn't nearly as big a boost in that regard as Financial. Nevertheless, saved GPT is saved GPT and is nothing to sneeze at.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MONOTHEISM]Monotheism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CODE_OF_LAWS]Code of Laws[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_SAILING]Sailing[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ASSEMBLY_LINE]Assembly Line[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_LIGHTHOUSE]The Great Lighthouse[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_FORBIDDEN_PALACE]The Forbidden Palace[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_CRISTO_REDENTOR]Cristo Redentor[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_COURTHOUSE]Courthouse[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LIGHTHOUSE]Lighthouse[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_FACTORY]Factory[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_SLAVERY]Slavery[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_ORGANIZED_RELIGION]Organized Religion[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_BUREAUCRACY]Bureaucracy[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_POLICE_STATE]Police State[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_STATE_PROPERTY]State Property[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Similar to Spiritual, technologies that enable civics--especially higher cost civics--are priorities. Unlike Spiritual, however, switching civics is not something to do constantly (unless you're Asoka, who has the best of both worlds in this regard). Also remember to choose a civic because you'll benefit from it, not just because it's available or because Organized will make it cheaper.[PARAGRAPH:1]The big benefits from Organized, however, are the cheap buildings--three of the best in the game. To leverage the lighthouses, try to build several coastal cities. Cheap courthouses make new cities cheaper, so you can employ this into a REX strategy or into warmongering or both.[PARAGRAPH:1]In fact, I tend to consider Organized to be a warmonger's trait (especially for Hammurabi, Julius Caesar, and Napoleon, whose companion traits are also warmonger-friendly). This is because my first build in a conquered city is a courthouse to reduce its maintenance cost, and Organized makes those courthouses cheaper to build--or whip.[PARAGRAPH:1]Finally, factories are one of the best late-game buildings, and the 2.08 patch has made them cheap for Organized.[PARAGRAPH:1]Technology priorities are obviously Sailing, Code of Laws, and Assembly Line for the cheap buildings. Other tech targets are those that enable some of the more useful but expensive civics, especially Civil Service for the powerful Bureaucracy civic. Its high upkeep cost will be cut in half for an Organized leader, increasing its utility. The same goes for Organized Religion (enabled by Monotheism) and Police State (enabled by Fascism).[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Like many traits, as the game progresses, Organized gets weaker. Your economy grows and high-upkeep civics gradually become more affordable. As a result, the addition of a late cheap building (factories) in the 2.08 patch was a welcome late-game boost to Organized. Nevertheless, the best period for Organized is definitely the mid-game when you're probably running Bureaucracy and Organized Religion and are still building your economy.</English>
		<German>Although Organized has a direct economic benefit--reducing the overhead of civics--it isn't nearly as big a boost in that regard as Financial. Nevertheless, saved GPT is saved GPT and is nothing to sneeze at.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MONOTHEISM]Monotheismus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CODE_OF_LAWS]Gesetzgebung[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_SAILING]Segeln[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ASSEMBLY_LINE]Fließband[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_LIGHTHOUSE]Großer Leuchtturm[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_FORBIDDEN_PALACE]Verbotene Stadt[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_CRISTO_REDENTOR]Christo Redentor[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_COURTHOUSE]Gerichtsgebäude[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LIGHTHOUSE]Leuchtturm[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_FACTORY]Fabrik[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_SLAVERY]Sklaverei[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_ORGANIZED_RELIGION]Organisierte Religion[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_BUREAUCRACY]Bürokratie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_POLICE_STATE]Polizeistaat[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_STATE_PROPERTY]Staatseigentum[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Similar to Spiritual, technologies that enable civics--especially higher cost civics--are priorities. Unlike Spiritual, however, switching civics is not something to do constantly (unless you're Asoka, who has the best of both worlds in this regard). Also remember to choose a civic because you'll benefit from it, not just because it's available or because Organized will make it cheaper.[PARAGRAPH:1]The big benefits from Organized, however, are the cheap buildings--three of the best in the game. To leverage the lighthouses, try to build several coastal cities. Cheap courthouses make new cities cheaper, so you can employ this into a REX strategy or into warmongering or both.[PARAGRAPH:1]In fact, I tend to consider Organized to be a warmonger's trait (especially for Hammurabi, Julius Caesar, and Napoleon, whose companion traits are also warmonger-friendly). This is because my first build in a conquered city is a courthouse to reduce its maintenance cost, and Organized makes those courthouses cheaper to build--or whip.[PARAGRAPH:1]Finally, factories are one of the best late-game buildings, and the 2.08 patch has made them cheap for Organized.[PARAGRAPH:1]Technology priorities are obviously Sailing, Code of Laws, and Assembly Line for the cheap buildings. Other tech targets are those that enable some of the more useful but expensive civics, especially Civil Service for the powerful Bureaucracy civic. Its high upkeep cost will be cut in half for an Organized leader, increasing its utility. The same goes for Organized Religion (enabled by Monotheism) and Police State (enabled by Fascism).[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Like many traits, as the game progresses, Organized gets weaker. Your economy grows and high-upkeep civics gradually become more affordable. As a result, the addition of a late cheap building (factories) in the 2.08 patch was a welcome late-game boost to Organized. Nevertheless, the best period for Organized is definitely the mid-game when you're probably running Bureaucracy and Organized Religion and are still building your economy.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PEDIA_HAPPINESS</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/City</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/Ville</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/Stadt</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/Città</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 [ICON_HAPPY]/ciudad</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_HAPPY]/Miasto</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PEDIA_UNHAPPINESS</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_UNHAPPY]/City</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_UNHAPPY]/Ville</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_UNHAPPY]/Stadt</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_UNHAPPY]/Città</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 [ICON_UNHAPPY]/ciudad</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1[ICON_UNHAPPY]/Miasto</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PHILOSOPHICAL</Tag>
		<English>Philosophical</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Philosophe:Philosophe:Philosophes:Philosophes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Philosophisch</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Filosofico:Filosofica</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Filosófico:Filosófica</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Filozoficzny:Filozoficzna:Filozoficzny:Filozoficzna</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PHILOSOPHICAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Just as the Financial trait lends itself to the Commerce Economy, the Philosophical trait lends itself to the Specialist Economy (SE). The SE, of course, has many adherents, and the debate over which economy is best rages on.[PARAGRAPH:1]Suffice it to say that the SE is strongest in the hands of a Philosophical leader, since running all those specialists will result in many more Great People. You don't have to run a SE with a Philosophical leader, just as you can run a CE without the Financial trait, but the SE and the Philosophical trait are both at their strongest when combined.[PARAGRAPH:1]Great People have many uses, of course. In the Specialist Economy, they are principally used for "lightbulbing", that is, using the Great Person to discover a technology, usually research-free. You can then trade this "free technology" for techs you need from other civilizations. This allows you to run the research slider at 0% for most of the game while you rely on a combination of scientists and tech trades to keep up in research. (My version of the SE in a nutshell.)[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_WRITING]Writing[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_POLYTHEISM]Polytheism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CODE_OF_LAWS]Code of Laws[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_PHILOSOPHY]Philosophy[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_EDUCATION]Education[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BIOLOGY]Biology[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_PYRAMID]The Pyramids[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_PARTHENON]The Parthenon[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_LIBRARY]The Great Library[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STATUE_OF_LIBERTY]The Statue of Liberty[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_NATIONAL_PARK]National Park[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LIBRARY]Library[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_UNIVERSITY]University[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_PACIFISM]Pacifism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_REPRESENTATION]Representation[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_CASTE_SYSTEM]Caste System[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_MERCANTILISM]Mercantilism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]I won't go into the details on how to run a SE, because that's beyond the scope of this article. Let's just say my recommendation with the Philosophical trait is to run a SE or at least a "hybrid economy" where some cities focus on food and specialists and others focus on cottages and commerce. (A hybrid economy is especially suitable for Elizabeth of England, who has the Financial trait that, as mentioned above, requires a certain amount of cottage spam to take full advantage of it.)[PARAGRAPH:1]Within the SE community, opinions differ as to the importance of building the Pyramids. The appeal of the Pyramids to a SE is to run the Representation civic extremely early in the game. This civic raises the happiness cap of your five largest cities on a standard-sized map (which are probably your only cities early on). This allows you to grow those cities even larger so you can work more farms and run more specialists. In addition, every specialist contributes an additional three research points under Representation beyond whatever research points they normally contribute--even those that normally don't contribute any research, such as engineers, priests, merchants, and ordinary citizen specialists. The science contribution of artists and spies goes up from 1 to 4 under representation, while the contribution of scientists doubles from 3 to 6. Obviously the Pyramids and early Representation hyper-charge the SE, but many maintain the SE can get along without either the wonder or the civic.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Parthenon can also be a useful wonder to a Philosophical leader. You're already relying on Great People for technologies, so why not build a wonder that increases the number of GP you'll get?[PARAGRAPH:1]Writing will be an early priority technology so you can build libraries and run your first scientists. Wonders can be very useful since they all contribute GP points; go after the wonders that contribute GPP towards the types of Great People you most want and need. Since Great Scientists are usually the most useful GPs, that makes the Great Library a very attractive wonder for leaders with the Philosophical trait. Mercantilism contributes a free specialist for each city, as does the Statue of Liberty (and without the "no foreign trade routes" price of Mercantilism). The Caste System civic is a huge boon to the SE and the Philosophical trait, allowing you to run as many merchants, scientists, and/or artists as a city can support. Therefore Code of Laws is a priority technology. Education enables the Philosophical trait's cheap building, the University, so that's a priority as well. Philosophy makes the Pacifism civic available, which provides a further +100% boost to GP production in cities that have your state religion. Biology will allow you to grow larger cities and support more specialists, so prioritize that tech later in the game.[PARAGRAPH:1]The National Park national wonder benefits the SE as it allows 1 free specialist for every forest preserve. It means, though, that you have to be careful to preserve some forests or even jungles in the fat cross of the city where you build it.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Running a specialist economy requires a great deal more micro-management than running the more-straightforward cottage economy. The game will take longer to play and you'll need to manage everything much more closely. That style of play doesn't suit everyone.[PARAGRAPH:1]The benefits of the Philosophical trait and of the SE begin to peter out in the late game. Great People get more expensive to produce and appear less frequently, while technologies become too expensive for your specialists and fewer Great People to research efficiently. You had better be in a position to win by this point or you may quickly find yourself falling behind. Either that, or you will need to transition to a cottage economy; a switch to the Emancipation civic will be essential to pulling this off.[PARAGRAPH:1]Unlike the Financial trait, the Philosophical trait does not provide any direct economic benefits. You'll need to look for other ways to keep your economy afloat.</English>
		<German>Just as the Financial trait lends itself to the Commerce Economy, the Philosophical trait lends itself to the Specialist Economy (SE). The SE, of course, has many adherents, and the debate over which economy is best rages on.[PARAGRAPH:1]Suffice it to say that the SE is strongest in the hands of a Philosophical leader, since running all those specialists will result in many more Great People. You don't have to run a SE with a Philosophical leader, just as you can run a CE without the Financial trait, but the SE and the Philosophical trait are both at their strongest when combined.[PARAGRAPH:1]Great People have many uses, of course. In the Specialist Economy, they are principally used for "lightbulbing", that is, using the Great Person to discover a technology, usually research-free. You can then trade this "free technology" for techs you need from other civilizations. This allows you to run the research slider at 0% for most of the game while you rely on a combination of scientists and tech trades to keep up in research. (My version of the SE in a nutshell.)[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_WRITING]Schrift[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_POLYTHEISM]Polytheismus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CODE_OF_LAWS]Gesetzgebung[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_PHILOSOPHY]Philosophie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_EDUCATION]Bildungswesen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_BIOLOGY]Biologie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_PYRAMID]Pyramiden[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_PARTHENON]Parthenon[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_LIBRARY]Große Bibliothek[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_STATUE_OF_LIBERTY]Freiheitsstatue[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_NATIONAL_PARK]Nationalpark[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_LIBRARY]Bibliothek[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_UNIVERSITY]Universität[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_PACIFISM]Pazifismus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_REPRESENTATION]Repräsentation[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_CASTE_SYSTEM]Kastensystem[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_MERCANTILISM]Merkantilismus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]I won't go into the details on how to run a SE, because that's beyond the scope of this article. Let's just say my recommendation with the Philosophical trait is to run a SE or at least a "hybrid economy" where some cities focus on food and specialists and others focus on cottages and commerce. (A hybrid economy is especially suitable for Elizabeth of England, who has the Financial trait that, as mentioned above, requires a certain amount of cottage spam to take full advantage of it.)[PARAGRAPH:1]Within the SE community, opinions differ as to the importance of building the Pyramids. The appeal of the Pyramids to a SE is to run the Representation civic extremely early in the game. This civic raises the happiness cap of your five largest cities on a standard-sized map (which are probably your only cities early on). This allows you to grow those cities even larger so you can work more farms and run more specialists. In addition, every specialist contributes an additional three research points under Representation beyond whatever research points they normally contribute--even those that normally don't contribute any research, such as engineers, priests, merchants, and ordinary citizen specialists. The science contribution of artists and spies goes up from 1 to 4 under representation, while the contribution of scientists doubles from 3 to 6. Obviously the Pyramids and early Representation hyper-charge the SE, but many maintain the SE can get along without either the wonder or the civic.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Parthenon can also be a useful wonder to a Philosophical leader. You're already relying on Great People for technologies, so why not build a wonder that increases the number of GP you'll get?[PARAGRAPH:1]Writing will be an early priority technology so you can build libraries and run your first scientists. Wonders can be very useful since they all contribute GP points; go after the wonders that contribute GPP towards the types of Great People you most want and need. Since Great Scientists are usually the most useful GPs, that makes the Great Library a very attractive wonder for leaders with the Philosophical trait. Mercantilism contributes a free specialist for each city, as does the Statue of Liberty (and without the "no foreign trade routes" price of Mercantilism). The Caste System civic is a huge boon to the SE and the Philosophical trait, allowing you to run as many merchants, scientists, and/or artists as a city can support. Therefore Code of Laws is a priority technology. Education enables the Philosophical trait's cheap building, the University, so that's a priority as well. Philosophy makes the Pacifism civic available, which provides a further +100% boost to GP production in cities that have your state religion. Biology will allow you to grow larger cities and support more specialists, so prioritize that tech later in the game.[PARAGRAPH:1]The National Park national wonder benefits the SE as it allows 1 free specialist for every forest preserve. It means, though, that you have to be careful to preserve some forests or even jungles in the fat cross of the city where you build it.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Running a specialist economy requires a great deal more micro-management than running the more-straightforward cottage economy. The game will take longer to play and you'll need to manage everything much more closely. That style of play doesn't suit everyone.[PARAGRAPH:1]The benefits of the Philosophical trait and of the SE begin to peter out in the late game. Great People get more expensive to produce and appear less frequently, while technologies become too expensive for your specialists and fewer Great People to research efficiently. You had better be in a position to win by this point or you may quickly find yourself falling behind. Either that, or you will need to transition to a cottage economy; a switch to the Emancipation civic will be essential to pulling this off.[PARAGRAPH:1]Unlike the Financial trait, the Philosophical trait does not provide any direct economic benefits. You'll need to look for other ways to keep your economy afloat.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_POLITICIAN</Tag>
		<English>Politician</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Politicien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Politician</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Politico</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Político:Política:Políticos:Políticas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Polityk</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_POLITICIAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A politician or political leader (from Greek "polis") is an individual who is involved in influencing public policy and decision making. This includes people who hold decision-making positions in government, and people who seek those positions, whether by means of election, coup d'état, appointment, electoral fraud, conquest, right of inheritance or other means. Politics is not limited to governance through public office. Political offices may also be held in corporations, and other entities that are governed by self-defined political processes.</English>
		<Italian>Un politico è un individuo coinvolto nell'influenzare le politiche pubbliche e le deisioni del governo. Questo comprende sia le persone che occupano posizioni di comando, sia quelle che aspirano ad ottenere tali posizioni, per mezzo di elezioni, colpi di stato, frodi elettorali, conquista, diritto di parentela o altri mezzi. La politica non è limitata solo al governo degli affari pubblici. Uffici politici possono esistere anche nelle coprorazioni o anche in altre organizzate da processi politici.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_POLITICIAN_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Pol</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Pol</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Pol</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Pol</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Pol</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_POPULIST</Tag>
		<English>Populist</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Populiste</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Populist</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Populista</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Populista:Populista:Populistas:Populistas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Populista</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_POPULIST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This ruler owes his position to popular support, and he never forgets about it. He diverts more resources than most to keeping the people happy with his reign.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_POPULIST_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Pop</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Pop</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Pop</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Pop</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Pop</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PREREQ_AND_ENTRY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_WARNING_TEXT] and %s1_trait[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[COLOR_WARNING_TEXT] et %s1_trait[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<Italian>[COLOR_WARNING_TEXT] e %s1_trait[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[COLOR_WARNING_TEXT] i %s1_trait[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PREREQ_BEGIN</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]You currently require %s1_trait[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Il vous faut le trait %s1_trait[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Richiede %s1_trait[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Wymaga %s1_trait[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PREREQ_OR_ENTRY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_WARNING_TEXT] (%s1_Trait may substitute for %s2_Trait)[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[COLOR_WARNING_TEXT] (%s1_Trait peut remplacer %s2_Trait)[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<Italian>[COLOR_WARNING_TEXT] (%s1_Trait può sostituire %s2_Trait)[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[COLOR_WARNING_TEXT] (%s1_Trait może być substytutem dla %s2_Trait)[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PRODUCTION_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Production of[SPACE]</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Production %D1%% plus rapide de:[SPACE]</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]%D1%% schnellere Produktion für:[SPACE]</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Produzione più veloce del %D1%% per[SPACE]</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Acelera un %D1%% la producción de[SPACE]</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Szybszej Produkcji:[SPACE]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PROGRESSIST</Tag>
		<English>Progressist</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Progressiste</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Progressist</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Progressista</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Progresista:Progresista:Progresistas:Progresistas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Progresywny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PROGRESSIST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Progressivism is a political attitude favoring or advocating changes or reform. Progressivism is often viewed in opposition to conservative or reactionary ideologies. The Progressive Movement began in cities with settlement workers and reformers who were interested in helping those facing harsh conditions at home and at work. The reformers spoke out about the need for laws regulating tenement housing and child labor. They also called for better working conditions for women.</English>
		<Italian>Il progressivismo è un atteggiamento politico che favorisce o richiede cambiamenti e riforme. Il progressivismo è spesso in contrapposizione con le ideologie conservative o reazionarie. Il movimento progressista iniziò nelle città con insediamenti di lavoratori e di riformatori che erano interessati nell'aiutare coloro che affrontavano condizioni difficili a casa e al lavoro. I riformatori parlavano del bisogno di leggi che regolavano le abitazionie il lavoro minorile; chiedevano anche condizioni di lavoro migliori per le donne.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PROGRESSIST_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Prg</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Prg</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Prg</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Prg</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Pro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pro</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_PROTECTIVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This is another new trait introduced by the Warlords expansion pack, and doesn't seem to be very well-thought out. The fact that I consider this one of the weakest traits should not come as a surprise, since that's an opinion shared by most players--though I grant that Protective does have its fans.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ARCHERY]Archery[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MASONRY]Masonry[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_POLYTHEISM]Polytheism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_SAILING]Sailing[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_FEUDALISM]Feudalism[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MACHINERY]Machinery[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ENGINEERING]Engineering[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_GUNPOWDER]Gunpowder[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CHEMISTRY]Chemistry[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_RIFLING]Rifling[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ASSEMBLY_LINE]Assembly Line[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_TEMPLE_OF_ARTEMIS]The Temple of Artemis[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_LIGHTHOUSE]The Great Lighthouse[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_CHICHEN_ITZA]Chichen Itza[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BARRACKS]Barracks[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_WALLS]Walls[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_CASTLE]Castle[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_VASSALAGE]Vassalage[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_THEOCRACY]Theocracy[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]While Protective is weak, it isn't without its uses. When you capture a city, your freely-promoted units are better equipped to defend your new possession, which is highly likely to come under a counter-attack. In fact, your gunpowder units can potentially perform double-duty as both attackers and defenders. (Most archery units, however, are weak attackers and are best used on defense only.)[PARAGRAPH:1]If you have a source of stone, the walls and castles are even cheaper, making them less of a burden to build. Combined with wonders like the Temple of Artemis and the Great Lighthouse, you could make Protective's cheap castles part of a trade route economy, which can be very helpful in the mid-game period. You can also use the cheap castles to supplement espionage in BtS. In fact, some players have begun playing an EP, or "Espionage Economy", where the science slider is turned down to 0% after Alphabet and most remaining technologies are acquired through tech-stealing.[PARAGRAPH:1]The civilization that probably benefits the most from the trait is China, because its UU is one of the best Archery units in the game--the Cho-Ko-Nu, which can and should be used as an attacking unit. Drill I just enhances its power, giving it an additional first strike chance beyond its 2 free first strikes.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]The problem with the Protective trait is that it's largely defensive in nature. The free City Garrison promotion is only useful when units are under attack while in a city. Walls and castles--which are pretty cheap to begin with, making their double production speed less appealing--are likewise only useful when you're under attack. Only the free Drill I promotion is an attacking promotion, but how often do you attack with archery units? Unless they're Cho-Ko- Nus, of course. (Though it can be beneficial to your more aggressive gunpowder units.)[PARAGRAPH:1]The problem with playing defensively in Civilization IV is that the AI is so fond of pillaging. If your units cower behind city walls, the AI will gleefully send your economy spiraling down into ruin by pillaging every tile improvement in sight. Your units have to venture out of your cities to defend your territory, which makes walls and castles next to useless--ditto with the City Garrison promotion.[PARAGRAPH:1]In many ways, the Protective trait seems to have been added more to benefit the AI than the human player. The AI prefers to play defensively for the most part, so Protective suits its programming. Any human player will tell you that going up against Protective Longbowmen, fortified in a city on a hill with a castle and walls, can be intimidating--though certainly not insurmountable. Just bring more Trebuchets to the party.</English>
		<German>This is another new trait introduced by the Warlords expansion pack, and doesn't seem to be very well-thought out. The fact that I consider this one of the weakest traits should not come as a surprise, since that's an opinion shared by most players--though I grant that Protective does have its fans.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ARCHERY]Bogenschießen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MASONRY]Steinmetzkunst[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_POLYTHEISM]Polytheismus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_SAILING]Segeln[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_FEUDALISM]Feudalismus[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_MACHINERY]Maschinen[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ENGINEERING]Maschinenbau[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_GUNPOWDER]Schießpulver[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_CHEMISTRY]Chemie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_RIFLING]Drall[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_ASSEMBLY_LINE]Fließband[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_TEMPLE_OF_ARTEMIS]Artemis-Tempel[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_LIGHTHOUSE]Großer Leuchtturm[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_CHICHEN_ITZA]Chichén Itzá[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_BARRACKS]Kaserne[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_WALLS]Stadtmauern[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_CASTLE]Schloss[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_VASSALAGE]Vasallentum[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=CIVIC_THEOCRACY]Theokratie[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]While Protective is weak, it isn't without its uses. When you capture a city, your freely-promoted units are better equipped to defend your new possession, which is highly likely to come under a counter-attack. In fact, your gunpowder units can potentially perform double-duty as both attackers and defenders. (Most archery units, however, are weak attackers and are best used on defense only.)[PARAGRAPH:1]If you have a source of stone, the walls and castles are even cheaper, making them less of a burden to build. Combined with wonders like the Temple of Artemis and the Great Lighthouse, you could make Protective's cheap castles part of a trade route economy, which can be very helpful in the mid-game period. You can also use the cheap castles to supplement espionage in BtS. In fact, some players have begun playing an EP, or "Espionage Economy", where the science slider is turned down to 0% after Alphabet and most remaining technologies are acquired through tech-stealing.[PARAGRAPH:1]The civilization that probably benefits the most from the trait is China, because its UU is one of the best Archery units in the game--the Cho-Ko-Nu, which can and should be used as an attacking unit. Drill I just enhances its power, giving it an additional first strike chance beyond its 2 free first strikes.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]The problem with the Protective trait is that it's largely defensive in nature. The free City Garrison promotion is only useful when units are under attack while in a city. Walls and castles--which are pretty cheap to begin with, making their double production speed less appealing--are likewise only useful when you're under attack. Only the free Drill I promotion is an attacking promotion, but how often do you attack with archery units? Unless they're Cho-Ko- Nus, of course. (Though it can be beneficial to your more aggressive gunpowder units.)[PARAGRAPH:1]The problem with playing defensively in Civilization IV is that the AI is so fond of pillaging. If your units cower behind city walls, the AI will gleefully send your economy spiraling down into ruin by pillaging every tile improvement in sight. Your units have to venture out of your cities to defend your territory, which makes walls and castles next to useless--ditto with the City Garrison promotion.[PARAGRAPH:1]In many ways, the Protective trait seems to have been added more to benefit the AI than the human player. The AI prefers to play defensively for the most part, so Protective suits its programming. Any human player will tell you that going up against Protective Longbowmen, fortified in a city on a hill with a castle and walls, can be intimidating--though certainly not insurmountable. Just bring more Trebuchets to the party.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_RECKLESS</Tag>
		<English>Schemer</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Comploteur</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Schemer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Complottista</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Conspirador:Conspiradora:Conspiradores:Conspiradoras</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Intrygant</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_RECKLESS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This leader is known to resort to all means to achieve his goals, including outright lies and betrayal. As this is well-known, he harbors a deep distrust for higher military ranks who don't understand his way of thinking and doing. Without military support, he is relatively inept at strategic command. - TR Team.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_RECKLESS_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Sch</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Com</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Sch</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Com</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Con</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Itr</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_REVIDX_LOCAL</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 to local RevIdx Penalty</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 de pénalité 'RevIdx'</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 zum örtlichen RevIdx Malus</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Penalità al RevIdx locale: %D1</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Penalización de %D1 a la estabilidad revolucionaria local</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 do lokalnej kary RevIdx</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_REVIDX_NATIONAL</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 to National Revolution Stability Bonus</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 de Bonus Stabilité Nationale (Révolutions)</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 zum nationalen Revolutions-Stabilitätsbonus</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Bonus Stabilità Nazionale: %D1</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Bonificación de %D1 a la estabilidad revolucionaria nacional</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 bonus do narodowej stabilności</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_REVOLUTIONARY</Tag>
		<English>Revolutionary</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Révolutionaire</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Revolutionary</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Rivoluzionario</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Revolucionario:Revolucionaria:Revolucionarios:Revolucionarias</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Rewolucyjny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_REVOLUTIONARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This leader came to power through a coup or revolution. This society he leads is therefore in its very nature revolutionary. This affects the nation in a number of ways ; having a natural tolerance to anarchy ; a tendency towards civil disobedience ; a natural affinity to espionage and the covert. Finally, the talents of the individuals here are often latent leading to increased great generals inside his/her borders, free instigator promotion on spies. These attributes come somewhat at a price though. Cities take a hit in there economy and negative revolution implications, are symptomatic of being "Revolutionary".</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_REVOLUTIONARY_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Rev</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Rev</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Rev</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Riv</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Rev</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Rew</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_REV_BAD_HOLY_CITY</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 reduction to RevIdx penalty from Non State [ICON_RELIGION] Holy City</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 de réduction de la pénalité 'RevIdx' des Villes Saintes de la religion [ICON_RELIGION] (non d'état)</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 Reduktion des RevIdx-Malus durch die Heilige Stadt der nicht-Staats-[ICON_RELIGION]</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Penalità al RevIdx: %D1 da Città Santa per [ICON_RELIGION] non di Stato</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Reducción de %D1 a la penalización del RevIndex por Ciudades Santas de [ICON_RELIGION] no oficiales</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 redukuje kare do RevIdx z nienarodowego [ICON_RELIGION] świętego miasta</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_REV_GOOD_HOLY_CITY</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 to RevIdx bonus from State [ICON_RELIGION] Holy City</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 de Bonus 'RevIdx' des Villes Saintes de la religion d'état [ICON_RELIGION]</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 zum RevIdx-Bonus von der Heiligen Stadt der Staats-[ICON_RELIGION]</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Bonus al RevIdx: %D1 da Città Santa per [ICON_RELIGION] di Stato</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Bonificación de %D1 al RevIndex por la Ciudad Santa de la [ICON_RELIGION] oficial</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1 bonusu do RevIdx od narodowej [ICON_RELIGION] Świętego miasta</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_REV_NATIONALITY_MOD</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%s1% Change to Nationality Based Revolution Effects</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%S1% Effets des Révolutions liées à un changement de Nationalité</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%S1% Wechsel zu landesweiten Revolutionseinflüssen</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]Variazione fattori di Rivoluzione su base Nazionale: %S1%</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%s1% a los efectos en la estabilidad revolucionaria de la nacionalidad</Spanish>
		<Polish>[NEWLINE][SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%S1% zmiana na Nacjonalizacje bazowała na efekcie rewolucyjnym</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SCIENTIFIC</Tag>
		<English>Scientific</English>
		<French>Scientifique</French>
		<German>Wissenschaftlich</German>
		<Italian>Scientifico</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Científico:Científica:Científicos:Científicas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Naukowy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SCIENTIFIC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SCIENTIFIC_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Sci</English>
		<French>Sci</French>
		<German>Wis</German>
		<Spanish>Cie</Spanish>
		<Polish>Nau</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SEAFARING</Tag>
		<English>Seafaring</English>
		<French>Marin</French>
		<German>Seefahrend</German>
		<Italian>Marinaio</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Marinero:Marinera:Marineros:Marineras</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Żeglarski</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SEAFARING_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SEAFARING_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Sea</English>
		<French>Mar.</French>
		<German>See</German>
		<Italian>Mar</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mar</Spanish>
		<Polish>Żeg.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SEMI_CIVILIZED</Tag>
		<English>Semi Civilized</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Presque Civilisé</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Semi Civilized</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Semi Civilizzato</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Semicivilizado:Semicivilizada:Semicivilizados:Semicivilizadas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pół-Cywilizowany</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SEMI_CIVILIZED_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This leader has done much to bring the fruits of civilization to his peoples, but it is still not enough. His people is still treated with prejudice, and it will require much effort to win them the respect they deserve. - TR Team.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SEMI_CIVILIZED_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>S-C</English>
		<French>
			<Text>S-C</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>S-C</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>S-C</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>S-C</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>PCw</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SPIRITUAL</Tag>
		<English>Spiritual</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Spirituel:Spirituelle:Spirituels:Spirituelles</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Spirituell</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Spirituale:Spirituale</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Espiritual:Espiritual</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Uduchowiony:Uduchowiona:Uduchowiony:Uduchowiona'</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SPIRITUAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>As with Financial, Spiritual's great strength comes from its positive impact on your economy. Anarchy means that for one turn or more, your cities do not grow or build anything, your culture does not increase, GPP are not accumulated, cottages do not grow, and so on. Spiritual means you avoid those periods of economic stasis; this should result in your being able to research at least one or two additional technologies, build several more units and buildings, produce more Great People, and so on, compared to a non-Spiritual civ.[PARAGRAPH:1]Unlike several other traits, Spiritual's effects do not decrease later in the game. On the contrary, as more civics and religions become available, you may want and need to change civics more often, and Spiritual lets you do so.[PARAGRAPH:1]However, this trait has slipped, in my opinion, from being one of the strongest to being a medium-strength trait. This is mainly because of the Beyond the Sword expansion pack. Frankly, many disputed my inclusion of it in the "Strong" category to begin with. But Beyond the Sword has reduced its strength by making its effects easier to obtain. You now only need to use one Great Person, not two, in order to bring about your first Golden Age; and you can now change civics anarchy-free during a Golden Age. This is just one of many was that Golden Ages have been improved and made more attractive in Beyond the Sword.[PARAGRAPH:1]Furthermore, in the late game, when you have access to all the civics and Spiritual is normally at its strongest, you can now achieve the same effects by building the new Cristo Redentor wonder, which not only gives you Spiritual's ability to change civics anarchy-free; you can also change civics without having to wait for a single turn change, let alone the usual five! (Note: in the BtS 3.13 patch, this has been changed to a 1 turn waiting period between civics changes.)[PARAGRAPH:1]So Spiritual, to my mind, has fallen from strong to medium not through any fault of its own, but through easier access to its benefits to non-Spiritual leaders.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]High-Priority Technologies[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Those that enable civics (e.g. [LINK=TECH_CODE_OF_LAWS]Code of Laws[\LINK])[PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Those that found religions (e.g. [LINK=TECH_MEDITATION]Meditation[\LINK])[PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_DIVINE_RIGHT]Divine Right[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_PAPER]Paper[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Wonders[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_PYRAMID]The Pyramids[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_SANKORE]The University of Sankore[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_SPIRAL_MINARET]The Spiral Minaret[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_APOSTOLIC_PALACE]The Apostolic Palace[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_SHWEDAGON_PAYA]Shwedagon Paya[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_SISTINE_CHAPEL]The Sistine Chapel[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Best Buildings[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Temples[PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Monasteries[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Useful Civics[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Nearly all of them--if it offers a worthwhile benefit and fits your strategy, switch to it.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]How to Use It[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]No anarchy means you can adopt a civic right now, as soon as it's available, and gain its advantages immediately, rather than waiting to change several civics at once as a prudent non-Spiritual leader would do. So if a civic would benefit you, don't hesitate to switch to it. The only restraint you have is waiting five turns until you can change civics again.[PARAGRAPH:1]There are also diplomatic benefits. You can easily convert to a religion or change to a favoured civic to court another civilization. Once you gain what you need from them--say, a tech trade--you can convert religions or civics back just as easily. However, do keep in mind that diplomatic bonuses for shared religions or favoured civics can take several turns to accumulate to a significant level.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Pyramids are an attractive wonder for a Spiritual leader, since they enable all the government civics early on, letting you leverage the trait early in the game. Obviously, any tech that enables a civic is valuable and should be prioritized--provided the civic is worthwhile. In Beyond the Sword, the Shwedagon Paya is also attractive, since it's the religious equivalent of the Pyramids, enabling all religious civics.[PARAGRAPH:1]Temples are modest buildings, producing +1 culture and keeping one citizen happy. However, Spiritual's cheap temples can truly shine if you build the Spiral Minaret (enabled by Divine Right), the University of Sankore (Paper), and the Apostolic Palace (Theology). These wonders make the temples of your state religion produce +1 gold, +2 research, and +2 hammers, respectively. (Please note that if you don't build the AP, you can still get its +2 hammer boost for all religious buildings by adopting the AP religion as your state religion.) Just be aware that building one or more of these wonders makes the Free Religion civic unappealing, and lowers the priority of Computers and Mass Media, which obsolete the wonders.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]The Downside[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Spiritual is the inverse of a trait like Creative: it is very weak early in the game when there are few civics available. Its benefits come later as more civics come on line. Realistically, most of your civics changes will occur in the mid-game, though obviously this can vary, but in most games I find myself taking less advantage of the Spiritual trait in the late game.[PARAGRAPH:1]In addition, while Spiritual may allow you to "save money", unlike Financial, the trait it doesn't directly produce any. You'll need to have a sound economy, as usual.[PARAGRAPH:1]You may be tempted, when playing as a Spiritual leader, to switch to any civic as soon as it's available. Remember that some civics have high maintenance costs compared to others; ensure the civic is worthwhile in some respect before changing. Also remember that just because a civic is made available, that doesn't mean it's necessarily optimal for you at that point in the game. Consider your choices carefully and make sure your civics fit into your overall strategy and the circumstances within the game.[PARAGRAPH:1]To gain the benefits of the cheap temples, you need a state religion. You'll therefore need to either found a religion or have one spread to you. In addition, you may need or want to adopt a state religion very early on, and that may have diplomatic repercussions for you.</English>
		<German>As with Financial, Spiritual's great strength comes from its positive impact on your economy. Anarchy means that for one turn or more, your cities do not grow or build anything, your culture does not increase, GPP are not accumulated, cottages do not grow, and so on. Spiritual means you avoid those periods of economic stasis; this should result in your being able to research at least one or two additional technologies, build several more units and buildings, produce more Great People, and so on, compared to a non-Spiritual civ.[PARAGRAPH:1]Unlike several other traits, Spiritual's effects do not decrease later in the game. On the contrary, as more civics and religions become available, you may want and need to change civics more often, and Spiritual lets you do so.[PARAGRAPH:1]However, this trait has slipped, in my opinion, from being one of the strongest to being a medium-strength trait. This is mainly because of the Beyond the Sword expansion pack. Frankly, many disputed my inclusion of it in the "Strong" category to begin with. But Beyond the Sword has reduced its strength by making its effects easier to obtain. You now only need to use one Great Person, not two, in order to bring about your first Golden Age; and you can now change civics anarchy-free during a Golden Age. This is just one of many was that Golden Ages have been improved and made more attractive in Beyond the Sword.[PARAGRAPH:1]Furthermore, in the late game, when you have access to all the civics and Spiritual is normally at its strongest, you can now achieve the same effects by building the new Cristo Redentor wonder, which not only gives you Spiritual's ability to change civics anarchy-free; you can also change civics without having to wait for a single turn change, let alone the usual five! (Note: in the BtS 3.13 patch, this has been changed to a 1 turn waiting period between civics changes.)[PARAGRAPH:1]So Spiritual, to my mind, has fallen from strong to medium not through any fault of its own, but through easier access to its benefits to non-Spiritual leaders.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Wichtige Technologien[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Diejenigen, die Gesellschaftsformen verfügbar machen (beispielsweise [LINK=TECH_CODE_OF_LAWS]Gesetzgebung[\LINK])[PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Diejenigen, die Religionen begründen (beispielsweise [LINK=TECH_MEDITATION]Meditation[\LINK])[PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_DIVINE_RIGHT]Göttliches Recht[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=TECH_PAPER]Papier[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Wunder[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_GREAT_PYRAMID]Pyramiden[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_SANKORE]Universität von Sankore[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_SPIRAL_MINARET]Spiralminarett[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_APOSTOLIC_PALACE]Apostolischer Palast[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_SHWEDAGON_PAYA]Shwedagon-Pagode[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET][LINK=BUILDING_SISTINE_CHAPEL]Sixtinische Kapelle[\LINK][PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Bevorzugte Gebäude[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Tempel[PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]Klöster[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nützliche Gesellschaftsformen[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1][ICON_BULLET]So gut wie alle. Sobald eine einen lohnenden Vorteil bietet und zur eigenen Strategie passt, sollte zu ihr gewechselt werden.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Einsatzmöglichkeiten[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]No anarchy means you can adopt a civic right now, as soon as it's available, and gain its advantages immediately, rather than waiting to change several civics at once as a prudent non-Spiritual leader would do. So if a civic would benefit you, don't hesitate to switch to it. The only restraint you have is waiting five turns until you can change civics again.[PARAGRAPH:1]There are also diplomatic benefits. You can easily convert to a religion or change to a favoured civic to court another civilization. Once you gain what you need from them--say, a tech trade--you can convert religions or civics back just as easily. However, do keep in mind that diplomatic bonuses for shared religions or favoured civics can take several turns to accumulate to a significant level.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Pyramids are an attractive wonder for a Spiritual leader, since they enable all the government civics early on, letting you leverage the trait early in the game. Obviously, any tech that enables a civic is valuable and should be prioritized--provided the civic is worthwhile. In Beyond the Sword, the Shwedagon Paya is also attractive, since it's the religious equivalent of the Pyramids, enabling all religious civics.[PARAGRAPH:1]Temples are modest buildings, producing +1 culture and keeping one citizen happy. However, Spiritual's cheap temples can truly shine if you build the Spiral Minaret (enabled by Divine Right), the University of Sankore (Paper), and the Apostolic Palace (Theology). These wonders make the temples of your state religion produce +1 gold, +2 research, and +2 hammers, respectively. (Please note that if you don't build the AP, you can still get its +2 hammer boost for all religious buildings by adopting the AP religion as your state religion.) Just be aware that building one or more of these wonders makes the Free Religion civic unappealing, and lowers the priority of Computers and Mass Media, which obsolete the wonders.[PARAGRAPH:1][H1]Nachteile[\H1][PARAGRAPH:1]Spiritual is the inverse of a trait like Creative: it is very weak early in the game when there are few civics available. Its benefits come later as more civics come on line. Realistically, most of your civics changes will occur in the mid-game, though obviously this can vary, but in most games I find myself taking less advantage of the Spiritual trait in the late game.[PARAGRAPH:1]In addition, while Spiritual may allow you to "save money", unlike Financial, the trait it doesn't directly produce any. You'll need to have a sound economy, as usual.[PARAGRAPH:1]You may be tempted, when playing as a Spiritual leader, to switch to any civic as soon as it's available. Remember that some civics have high maintenance costs compared to others; ensure the civic is worthwhile in some respect before changing. Also remember that just because a civic is made available, that doesn't mean it's necessarily optimal for you at that point in the game. Consider your choices carefully and make sure your civics fit into your overall strategy and the circumstances within the game.[PARAGRAPH:1]To gain the benefits of the cheap temples, you need a state religion. You'll therefore need to either found a religion or have one spread to you. In addition, you may need or want to adopt a state religion very early on, and that may have diplomatic repercussions for you.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SPY_MISSION_COST_MODIFIER</Tag>
		<English>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% Cost of Spy Missions</English>
		<French>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% Coût des Missions d'espionnage</French>
		<German>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% Kosten von Spionagemissionen</German>
		<Spanish>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% al coste de las misiones de espionaje</Spanish>
		<Polish>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% do kosztów misji szpiegowskich</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SPY_SUCCESS_MODIFIER</Tag>
		<English>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% Chance of Spying Success</English>
		<French>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% de Succès de l'Espionnage</French>
		<German>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% Erfolgsaussicht von Spionage</German>
		<Spanish>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% a la probabilidad de éxito del espionaje</Spanish>
		<Polish>[SPACE][SPACE][ICON_BULLET]%D1% szansy na udane szpiegowanie</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_STATE_REL_SPREAD_MODIFIER</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% chance to Spread State Religion with your Missionaries.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% de chances de propager la religion d'État avec vos missionnaires.</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% di diffondere la religione di stato con i tuoi missionari.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% do szansy rozszerzenia Religi Państwowej przez Misjonarzy.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TEAM_WONDER_PRODUCTION_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Team Project Production</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Construction de merveilles d'équipe %D1%%</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Teamwunderproduktion</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% produzione di Meraviglie di Squadra</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% a la producción de maravillas de equipo</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% do Budowy Projektów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TECH_PREREQ</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Requires knowledge of %s1_TechName[COLOR_REVERT]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Requiert la connaissance de %s1_TechName[COLOR_REVERT]</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Richiede la conoscenza della tecnologia %s1_TechName[COLOR_REVERT]</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET][COLOR_WARNING_TEXT]Wymaga znajomości: %s1_TechName[COLOR_REVERT]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TECH_RESEARCH_MODIFIER_ADDITIONAL</Tag>
		<English>, [LINK=%s1_Tech]%s2_Tech[\LINK]</English>
		<French>, [LINK=%s1_Tech]%s2_Tech[\LINK]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TECH_RESEARCH_MODIFIER_END</Tag>
		<English>Technologies</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TECH_RESEARCH_MODIFIER_FIRST</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Research %D1_Change%% as fast as normal when researching [LINK=%s2_Tech]%s3_Tech[\LINK]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Recherche %D1_Change%% plus vite que la normale lors de la recherche de [LINK=%s2_Tech]%s3_Tech[\LINK]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TECH_RESEARCH_MODIFIER_NEGATIVE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Researches %s1_TechName slower by %D2_Change</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Recherche la technologie %s1_TechName plus lentement de %D2_Change</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Ricerca la tecnologia %s1_TechName %D2_Change più lentamente</German>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Odkryje Technologię: %s1_TechName o %D2_Change wolniej</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TECH_RESEARCH_MODIFIER_POSITIVE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Researches the %s1_TechName technology %D2_Change Faster</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Recherche la technologie %s1_TechName %D2_Change plus vite</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]Ricerca la tecnologia %s1_TechName %D2_Change più velocemente</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Odkryje Technologię: %s1_TechName o %D2_Change szybciej</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TEMPERAMENTAL</Tag>
		<English>Temperamental</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Tempéré</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Temperamental</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Temperamentale</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Temperamental:Temperamental:Temperamentales:Temperamentales</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wybuchowy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TEMPERAMENTAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Having a leader that is temperamental leads its nation toward general inefficiency. The nation is burdened with a leader whose temperamental differences with certain projects or advancement, comes at a cost. In particular those individuals within his/her nation who are deemed worthy of 'promotion' or a status of greatness are few in the eyes of its leader. The culture of his/her people inevitably suffers and the dedication and training of his/her military will remain unmotivated.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TEMPERAMENTAL_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Tem</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Tem</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Tem</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Tem</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Tem</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wyb</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TEST</Tag>
		<English>Test</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Barbare</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Barbarisch</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Barbaro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Barbarian</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Testowy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TEST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>This is just a fill in for testing trait tags.</English>
		<Italian>Caratteristica ancora da testare.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TEST_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Tst</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Tst</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BrB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Tst</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>BrB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_TRADE_YIELD_MODIFIERS_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% %F2_yield from [ICON_TRADE]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% %F2_yield avec: [ICON_TRADE]</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% %F2_yield durch [ICON_TRADE]</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% %F2_yield da [ICON_TRADE]</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% %F2_yield por [ICON_TRADE]</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% %F2_yield z: [ICON_TRADE]</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_UNHAPPINESS_2</Tag>
		<English>+%d1_Change[ICON_UNHAPPY]: "Our leader is terrible!"</English>
		<French>+%d1_Change[ICON_UNHAPPY]: "Notre leader est terrible!"</French>
		<German>+%d1_Change[ICON_UNHAPPY]: "Unser Anführer ist schrecklich!"</German>
		<Spanish>+%d1_Change[ICON_UNHAPPY]: "¡Nuestro líder es terrible!"</Spanish>
		<Polish>+%d1_Change[ICON_UNHAPPY]: "Nasz przywódca jest okropny!"</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_UNIT_COMBAT_FREE_XP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 Experience to all newly trained %s2_CombatClass Units.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 Experience pour les unités de type %s2_CombatClass nouvellement entraînées.</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 Erfahrungspunkte für alle neu ausgebildeten %s2_CombatClass</German>	
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 XP a tutte le nuove %s2_CombatClass addestrate.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 Doświadczenia dla wszystkich nowo wyszkolonych jednostek %s2_CombatClass.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_UNIT_COMBAT_FREE_XP_ADDITIONAL</Tag>
		<English>, [LINK=%s1_CombatClass]%s2_CombatClass[\LINK]</English>
		<French>, [LINK=%s1_CombatClass]%s2_CombatClass[\LINK]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_UNIT_COMBAT_FREE_XP_END</Tag>
		<English>Unit Types</English>
		<German>[COLOR_TECH_TEXT][COLOR_REVERT]</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_UNIT_COMBAT_FREE_XP_FIRST</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 Experience to all newly trained [LINK=%s2_CombatClass]%s3_CombatClass[\LINK]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 Expérience à tous les nouvelles unités formées de type : [LINK=%s2_CombatClass]%s3_CombatClass[\LINK]</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 Erfahrungspunkte für alle neu ausgebildeten [LINK=%s2_CombatClass]%s3_CombatClass[\LINK]</German>		
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_UNIT_PRODUCTION</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Production speed when training %s2_CombatClass Units.</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Vitesse de Production en entraînant des unités de type: %s2_CombatClass.</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Ausbildungsgeschwindigkeit von %s2:3_CombatClass</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% alla velocità di addestramento di %s2_CombatClass Units.</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Szybkości Produkcji przy szkoleniu jednostek: %s2_CombatClass.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_UNIT_PRODUCTION_ADDITIONAL</Tag>
		<English>, [LINK=%s1_CombatClass]%s2_CombatClass[\LINK]</English>
		<French>, [LINK=%s1_CombatClass]%s2_CombatClass[\LINK]</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_UNIT_PRODUCTION_END</Tag>
		<English>Unit Types</English>
		<German>[COLOR_TECH_TEXT][COLOR_REVERT]</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_UNIT_PRODUCTION_FIRST</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Production speed when training [LINK=%s2_CombatClass]%s3_CombatClass[\LINK]</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Vitesse de production lors de l'entraînement des unités de type : [LINK=%s2_CombatClass]%s3_CombatClass[\LINK]</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Ausbildungsgeschwindigkeit von [LINK=%s2_CombatClass]%s3:3_CombatClass[\LINK]</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_WONDER_PRODUCTION_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Wonder Production</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Construction de merveilles %D1%%</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Wunderproduktion</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% produzione di Meraviglie</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% a la producción de maravillas</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% do Produkcji Cudów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_WORKER_SPEED_NEGATIVE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Workers build improvements with a %D1_Modifier%% speed penalty</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Les Ouvriers construisent les aménagements avec un pénalité de %D1_Modifier%%</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]I lavoratori costruiscono i miglioramenti il %D1_Modifier%% più lentamente</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Robotnicy budują ulepszenia z prędkością: %D1_Modifier%%</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_WORKER_SPEED_POSITIVE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Workers build improvements %D1_Modifier%% faster</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Les Ouvriers construisent les aménagements %D1_Modifier%% plus vite</French>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]I lavoratori costruiscono i miglioramenti il %D1_Modifier%% più velocemente</Italian>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]Robotnicy budują ulepszenia szybciej o: %D1_Modifier%%</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_WORLD_WONDER_PRODUCTION_MODIFIER_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% World Wonder Production</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Construction de merveilles mondiales %D1%%</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% Weltwunderproduktion</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% produzione di Grandi Meraviglie</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% a la producción de maravillas del mundo</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%% do Budowy Wielkich Cudów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRAIT_YIELD_CHANGES_C2C</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_yeild/City</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_yeild/ville</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_yeild/Stadt</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_yeild/Città</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1 %F2_yeild/ciudad</Spanish>
		<Polish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1%F2_yeild/Miasto</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>