<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_YUNUPINGU_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, [CT_NAME]. Know that the [OUR_CIV_SHORT] endeavour to live in peace with this land.</English>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, [CT_NAME]. Sappi che gli [OUR_CIV_SHORT] desiderano vivere in pace con questa terra.</Italian>
		<Polish>Witamy, [CT_NAME]. Wiedz, że głownym celem [OUR_CIV_SHORT] jest życie w harmonii z otaczającym nas światem.</Polish>
		<Russian>Äîáðî ïîæàëîâàòü, [CT_NAME]. Âåäîìî ìíå, ÷òî [OUR_CIV_SHORT] ñòðåìÿòñÿ æèòü â ìèðå íà ýòîé çåìëå.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_YUNUPINGU</Tag>
		<English>Yunupingu</English>
		<Russian>Þíóïèíãó</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_YUNUPINGU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Galarrwuy Yunupingu [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Community Leader, Australian Indigenous Community [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.1948 - present[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Galarrwuy Yunupingu is a leader in the Australian Indigenous community, and has been involved in the fight for Land Rights throughout his career. He was 1978 Australian of the Year.[PARAGRAPH:1]He was born at Melville Bay near Yirrkala on 1948 June 30, and is a member of the Gumatj clan of the Yolngu people. He attended Mission School at Yirrkala in his formative years, and moved to Brisbane to study at the Methodist Bible College for two years, returning to Gove in 1967. In the early 1960's with his father, the Gumatj clan leader Mungurrawuy, he entered the struggle for Land Rights, and helped draw up the Bark Petition at Yirrkala. He came to national attention in the late 1960's for his role in the landmark, but unsuccessful Gove Land Rights Case. This legal action was the first by Indigenous Australians to challenge mining companies' rights to exploit traditional lands. He became a prominent leader and strong voice on behalf of Aboriginal people in the Northern Territory and Australia, gaining respect and admiration from many. In 1969 he was elected to the Yirrkala town council.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1975 he joined the Northern Land Council (NLC), the authority appointed under the Aboriginal Land Rights (NT) Act 1976 to represent traditional Aboriginal landowners and Aboriginal people. He was chairman of the NLC from 1977-1980, an executive member until 1983 when he was re-elected as chairman, and has remained in that position to date (2004). He has led a number of negotiations with mining and government bodies. As chair of the NLC, he led the Gagudju people in negotiations with mining and government bodies. Not opposed to mining in principle, Yunupingu sees it as a way for Aboriginal people to escape the welfare trap if it is conducted on the traditional owners' terms. These include a fair distribution of the economic benefits and respect for the land and specific sacred sites. He said: 'We will continue to fight for the right to make our own decisions about our own land.'[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1978 he was awarded the Honour of Australian of the Year for his negotiations on the Ranger uranium mine agreement. He said the award 'would help him to shake off the image of ratbag and radical' and would give him 'greater strength as an individual and as a leader'. It was also a recognition for Aboriginal people as 'the indigenous people of this country who must share in its future'. In 1985, he was made a Member of the Order of Australia (AM) for his services to the Aboriginal community. Galarrwuy Yunupingu is one of 100 "Australian Living National Treasures" selected by the National Trust as leaders in society "considered to have a great influence over our environment because of the standards and examples they set".</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Galarrwuy Yunupingu [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Przywódca Społeczności Aborygenów[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Urodził się:[\BOLD] ok.1948[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Galarrwuy Yunupingu is a leader in the Australian Indigenous community, and has been involved in the fight for Land Rights throughout his career. He was 1978 Australian of the Year.[PARAGRAPH:1]He was born at Melville Bay near Yirrkala on 1948 June 30, and is a member of the Gumatj clan of the Yolngu people. He attended Mission School at Yirrkala in his formative years, and moved to Brisbane to study at the Methodist Bible College for two years, returning to Gove in 1967. In the early 1960's with his father, the Gumatj clan leader Mungurrawuy, he entered the struggle for Land Rights, and helped draw up the Bark Petition at Yirrkala. He came to national attention in the late 1960's for his role in the landmark, but unsuccessful Gove Land Rights Case. This legal action was the first by Indigenous Australians to challenge mining companies' rights to exploit traditional lands. He became a prominent leader and strong voice on behalf of Aboriginal people in the Northern Territory and Australia, gaining respect and admiration from many. In 1969 he was elected to the Yirrkala town council.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1975 he joined the Northern Land Council (NLC), the authority appointed under the Aboriginal Land Rights (NT) Act 1976 to represent traditional Aboriginal landowners and Aboriginal people. He was chairman of the NLC from 1977-1980, an executive member until 1983 when he was re-elected as chairman, and has remained in that position to date (2004). He has led a number of negotiations with mining and government bodies. As chair of the NLC, he led the Gagudju people in negotiations with mining and government bodies. Not opposed to mining in principle, Yunupingu sees it as a way for Aboriginal people to escape the welfare trap if it is conducted on the traditional owners' terms. These include a fair distribution of the economic benefits and respect for the land and specific sacred sites. He said: 'We will continue to fight for the right to make our own decisions about our own land.'[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1978 he was awarded the Honour of Australian of the Year for his negotiations on the Ranger uranium mine agreement. He said the award 'would help him to shake off the image of ratbag and radical' and would give him 'greater strength as an individual and as a leader'. It was also a recognition for Aboriginal people as 'the indigenous people of this country who must share in its future'. In 1985, he was made a Member of the Order of Australia (AM) for his services to the Aboriginal community. Galarrwuy Yunupingu is one of 100 "Australian Living National Treasures" selected by the National Trust as leaders in society "considered to have a great influence over our environment because of the standards and examples they set".</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Ãàëàðâýé Þíóïèíãó[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ëèäåð çåìëÿ÷åñòâà àâñòðàëèéñêèõ àáîðèãåíîâ [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ãîäû æèçíè: [\BOLD]c.1948 - íàñò. âðåìÿ[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Áèîãðàôèÿ:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Галарву Юнупингу - лидер австралийского коренного населения, на протяжении всей своей карьеры принимавший участие в борьбе за земельные права. Он был австралийцем 1978 года.[PARAGRAPH:1]Он родился в заливе Мелвилл недалеко от Йирркала 30 июня 1948 года и является членом клана Гуматж из народа Йолнгу. В годы становления он посещал миссионерскую школу в Йирркале и переехал в Брисбен, чтобы проучиться в методистском библейском колледже в течение двух лет, а затем вернулся в Гоув в 1967 году. В начале 1960-х вместе со своим отцом, лидером клана Гумати Мунгурравуй, он вступил в борьбу. за земельные права и помог составить петицию Барка в Йирркале. Он привлек национальное внимание в конце 1960-х годов благодаря своей роли в знаковом, но неудачном деле о земельных правах правительства. Этот судебный иск был первым иском коренных австралийцев, который оспорил права горнодобывающих компаний на использование традиционных земель. Он стал выдающимся лидером и сильным голосом от имени аборигенов Северной территории и Австралии, завоевав уважение и восхищение многих. В 1969 году он был избран депутатом городского совета Йирркала.[PARAGRAPH:1]В 1975 году он присоединился к Северному земельному совету (СЗС), органу, назначенному в соответствии с Законом 1976 года о земельных правах аборигенов (СЗ), чтобы представлять традиционных землевладельцев-аборигенов и аборигенов. Он был председателем СЗС с 1977-1980, исполнительным членом до 1983 года, когда он был переизбран председателем, и остается на этой должности до настоящего времени (2004). Он провел ряд переговоров с горнодобывающими и государственными органами. Как председатель СЗС, он руководил людьми Гагуджу на переговорах с горнодобывающими и государственными органами. Юнупингу, в принципе, не возражая против добычи полезных ископаемых, считает, что аборигены могут вырваться из ловушки благосостояния, если она будет вестись на условиях традиционных владельцев. К ним относятся справедливое распределение экономических выгод и уважение к земле и определенным священным местам. Он сказал: «Мы продолжим бороться за право принимать собственные решения относительно нашей собственной земли».[PARAGRAPH:1]В 1978 году он был удостоен звания «Австралиец года» за переговоры по соглашению о урановом руднике «Рейнджер». Он сказал, что эта награда «поможет ему избавиться от образа болвана и радикала» и придаст ему «большую силу как личность и как лидер». Это также было признанием аборигенов как «коренных жителей этой страны, которые должны участвовать в ее будущем». В 1985 году он стал членом Ордена Австралии за заслуги перед сообществом аборигенов. Галарву Юнупингу является одним из 100 «живых национальных сокровищ Австралии», выбранных Национальным фондом в качестве лидеров общества, «имеющих большое влияние на окружающую среду из-за установленных ими стандартов и примеров».</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>