<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BIRD_DANCE</Tag>
		<English>Dance - Bird</English>
		<French>Danse des Oiseaux</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BIRD_DANCE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Some birds are said to dance and these dances inspired early human dances.

Recent studies indicate that humans, parrots and elephants are the only creatures that really dance!</English>
		<French>Certains oiseaux danseraient et ces danses ont inspiré les premières danses humaines.

Des études récentes indiquent que les humains, les perroquets et les éléphants sont les seules créatures qui dansent vraiment!</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DANCE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Dancing improves the chance of inspiring Great Artists.</English>
		<French>La danse améliore les chances d'inspirer de grands artistes.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FOX_DANCE</Tag>
		<English>Dance - Fox</English>
		<French>Danse du Renard</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FOX_DANCE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Young foxes practicing their mouse hunting moves look like they are dancing for the sheer joy of it. This is said to have inspired early human dances.

Recent studies indicate that humans, parrots and elephants are the only creatures that really dance!</English>
		<French>Les jeunes renards qui pratiquent leurs mouvements de chasse à la souris ont l'air de danser pour la joie. On dit que cela a inspiré les premières danses humaines.

Des études récentes indiquent que les humains, les perroquets et les éléphants sont les seules créatures qui dansent vraiment!</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HAKA</Tag>
		<English>Dance - Haka</English>
		<French>Danse - Haka</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HAKA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The haka is a ceremonial dance or challenge in Polynesian culture. It is a posture dance performed by a group, with vigorous movements and stamping of the feet with rhythmically shouted accompaniment.</English>
		<French>Le haka est une danse de cérémonie ou un défi dans la culture polynésienne. C'est une danse de posture exécutée par un groupe, avec des mouvements vigoureux et un estampage des pieds avec un accompagnement rythmé.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HAKA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Strike fear in the hearts of your enemy.</English>
		<French>Inspirez la peur dans le coeur de votre ennemi.</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_CACOPHONY</Tag>
		<English>Shock and Awe - Cacophony</English>
		<French>Choc et stupeur - Cacophonie</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_HAKA</Tag>
		<English>Shock and Awe - Haka</English>
		<French>Choc et stupeur - Haka</French>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_WAR_CRY</Tag>
		<English>Shock and Awe - War Cry</English>
		<French>Choc et stupeur - Cri de guerre</French>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
