<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_RICHELIEU_1</Tag>
		<English>If you give me six lines written by the hand of the most honest of men, [CT_NAME], I will find something in them which will hang him. Perhaps you will feed me only five?</English>
		<French>Si vous me donnez six lignes écrites de la main du plus honnête des hommes, [CT_NAME], je vais trouver quelque chose en eux qui le ferai pendre. Peut-être que vous préférez m'en donner seulement cinq?</French>
		<German>Gebe mir 6 Zeilen, geschrieben von der Hand des ehrenhaftesten Mannes, [CT_NAME], und werde darin etwas darin finden, ihn aufzuhängen. Vielleicht möchtest Du mir nur 5 übermitteln?</German>
		<Spanish>Si me traes seis líneas escritas por la mano del más sincero de los hombres, [CT_NAME], encontraré algo en ellas que le delatará. ¿Tal vez solo necesite cinco contigo?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Jeśli dasz mi sześć linii skreślonych przez uczciwego człowieka, [CT_NAME], znajdę w nich coś za co można go powiesić. Być może pokaż mi tylko pięć linii?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_RICHELIEU</Tag>
		<English>Richelieu</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_RICHELIEU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Armand Jean du Plessis[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Cardinal-Duc de Richelieu[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1585 - 1642[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Consecrated as a bishop in 1607, Richelieu later entered politics, becoming a Secretary of State in 1616. Richelieu soon rose in both the Church and the state, becoming a cardinal in 1622, and King Louis XIII's chief minister in 1624. He remained in office until his death in 1642; he was succeeded by Jules Cardinal Mazarin. The Cardinal de Richelieu was often known by the title of the King's "Chief Minister" or "First Minister". As a result, he is sometimes considered to be the world's first Prime Minister, in the modern sense of the term. He sought to consolidate royal power and crush domestic factions. By restraining the power of the nobility, he transformed France into a strong, centralized state. His chief foreign policy objective was to check the power of the Austro-Spanish Habsburg dynasty. Although he was a cardinal, he did not hesitate to make alliances with Protestant rulers in attempting to achieve this goal.[PARAGRAPH:1]Richelieu's tenure was a crucial period of reform for France. Earlier, the nation's political structure was largely feudal, with powerful nobles and a wide variety of laws in different regions. Parts of the nobility periodically conspired against the King, raised private armies, and allied themselves with foreign powers. This system gave way to centralized power under Richelieu. Local and even religious interests were subordinated to those of the whole nation, and of the embodiment of the nation - the King. Equally critical for France was Richelieu's foreign policy, which helped restrain Habsburg influence in Europe. Richelieu did not survive until the end of the Thirty Years' War. However, the conflict ended in 1648, with France emerging in a far better position than any other power, and the Holy Roman Empire entering a period of decline.[PARAGRAPH:1]Richelieu's successes were extremely important to Louis XIII's successor, King Louis XIV. He continued Richelieu's work of creating an absolute monarchy; in the same vein as the Cardinal, he enacted policies that further suppressed the once-mighty aristocracy, and utterly destroyed all remnants of Huguenot political power with the Edict of Fontainebleau. Moreover, Louis took advantage of his nation's success during the Thirty Years' War to establish French hegemony in continental Europe. Thus, Richelieu's policies were the requisite prelude to Louis XIV becoming the most powerful monarch, and France the most powerful nation, in all of Europe during the late seventeenth century.[PARAGRAPH:1]Richelieu is also notable for the authoritarian measures he employed to maintain power. He censored the press, established a large network of internal spies, forbade the discussion of political matters in public assemblies such as the Parlement de Paris (a court of justice), and had those who dared to conspire against him prosecuted and executed. The Canadian historian and philosopher John Ralston Saul has referred to Richelieu as the "father of the modern nation-state, modern centralised power [and] the modern secret service."[PARAGRAPH:1]As an advocate for Samuel de Champlain and of the retention of Québec, he founded the Compagnie des Cent-Associés and saw the Treaty of Saint-Germain-en-Laye return Québec to French rule under Champlain, after the settlement had been captured by the Kirkes in 1629. This in part allowed the colony to eventually develop into the heartland of Francophone culture in North America.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Armand Jean du Plessis[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Cardinal-Duc de Richelieu[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył: [\BOLD]1585 - 1642[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Francuski diuk, kardynał, pierwszy premier Francji. W 1606 został mianowany przez Henryka IV biskupem Luçon (sakrę otrzymał 17 kwietnia 1607). W 1622 dzięki protekcji królowej-matki Marii Medycejskiej, papież Grzegorz XV mianował go kardynałem. W 1624 został powołany przez Ludwika XIII na pierwszego ministra. Wprowadził szereg reform m.in. zmierzających do osłabienia pozycji arystokracji. W 1630 r. zabronił arystokratom działalności handlowej, wkrótce potem zakazał im prowadzenia prywatnych wojen oraz posiadania zamków warownych (istniejące miały zostać wykupione). W latach 1625-1628 prowadził wojnę z hugenotami, jedną z głównych sił przeciwnych królowi. Pokonawszy hugenotów w 1629 wydał edykt łaski nakazujący hugenotom zrezygnowanie z samodzielności politycznej oraz oddania twierdz, ale gwarantujący jednocześnie wolność wyznania. Pokój ten był przyczyną konfliktu kardynała z Marią Medycejską. Richelieu wyszedł z niego zwycięsko i po tzw. "dniu zawiedzionych" (11 listopada 1630) otrzymał od króla potwierdzenie stanowisk i pełnię zaufania. W celach propagandowych powołał do życia rządową gazetę. W 1635 założył Akademię Francuską, której zadaniem było stworzenie literackiego języka francuskiego. Rozbudował armię i flotę. Podjął politykę podbojów kontynentalnych, współzawodnicząc z Anglią. Chciał osłabić Habsburgów, więc utrzymywał dobre kontakty z Turcją. W czasie wojny trzydziestoletniej (1618-1648) wspierał nastroje anty hiszpańsko-habsburskie, nie angażował jednak Francji w otwarty konflikt. Wspierał działania książąt protestanckich oraz krajów przeciwnych Cesarstwu - szukał sojuszu z Anglią, Niderlandami Północnymi, Danią, później ze Szwecją (to między innymi jego dyplomaci byli odpowiedzialni za doprowadzenie do rozejmu polsko-szwedzkiego w Starym Targu w 1629 roku). Hojnymi subsydiami wspomagał niektóre księstwa protestanckie i włoskie, a również Szwecję. Dopiero 12 maja 1635 roku Francja wypowiedziała otwartą wojnę Hiszpanii. Wcześniej zawarty został w Compičgne układ ze Szwedami, na mocy którego połączone siły francusko-szwedzkie miały zaatakować i cesarza, i króla Hiszpanii. Richelieu jednak nie był zainteresowany konfliktem z Rzeszą i usiłował ograniczyć teatr wojny do terenów Hiszpanii i południowych Niderlandów. W odpowiedzi Szwedzi ograniczyli swoje działania jedynie do terytorium Niemiec. Wysokie koszty prowadzenia wojny zmuszały kardynała do coraz dotkliwszego obciążania ludności podatkami, co skutkowało serią rewolt, które przetaczały się przez Francję w trakcie całej wojny. Najbardziej znanym zrywem ludnościowym był ruch "bosonogich", którą badacz Borys Porszniew określił jako próbę generalną przed Frondą.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
