<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BASIL_1</Tag>
		<English>Salutations [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT], called by some "The father of the Army". Are your intentions noble?</English>
		<French>Salutations [CT_NAME]! Je suis[OUR_NAME] des [OUR_CIV_SHORT], aussi appelé "Le Père de l'Armée". Est-ce que vos intentions sont louables?</French>
		<German>Sei gegrüßt, [CT_NAME]! Ich bin [OUR_NAME] aus [OUR_CIV_SHORT], manche nennen mich "Den Vater der Armee". Hast Du noble Absichten?</German>
		<Spanish>¡Saludos [CT_NAME]! Soy [OUR_NAME] de [OUR_CIV_SHORT], llamado por algunos "el Padre del Ejército". ¿Son nobles tus intenciones?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pozdrawiam [CT_NAME]! Jestem [OUR_NAME] z [OUR_CIV_SHORT], nazywany czasem "Ojcem Armii". Czy Twoje intencje są szlachetne?</Polish>
		<Russian>Приветствую, [CT_NAME]! Мое имя [OUR_NAME] из [OUR_CIV_SHORT], прозванного «Отец войскам». Надеюсь, ваши намерения чисты?</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_BASIL</Tag>
		<English>Basil</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Basile</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Basilius</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Basilio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Basilio</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>
			<Text>Bazyl</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Polish>
		<Russian>Âàñèëèé</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_BASIL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Basil II, The Bulgar-Slayer[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of Byzantium [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 958 - 1025 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Byzantine emperor Basil II ruled from 963 to 1025 and was called Bulgaroctonus (Bulgar-Slayer). He was the last and greatest of the emperors who brought Byzantium to its military zenith.[PARAGRAPH:1]The elder son of Emperor Romanus II, Basil and his younger brother, Constantine, succeeded in title as children upon their father's death in 963. Their position was exploited by two successive military usurpers, Nicephorus Phocas (963-969) and John I Tzimisces (969-976). Upon John's death, while Constantine remained in the background, Basil attempted to rule but became dependent upon his great-uncle, the eunuch Basil the Chamberlain. A cunning politician of long experience, the chamberlain helped Basil face the challenges of two more would-be usurpers, the aristocrats Bardas Sclerus and Bardas Phocas. Amid these struggles the chamberlain's tutelage became intolerable, and Basil drove him from office.[PARAGRAPH:1]The rebellions of the two Bardases eventually drove Basil to seek military help from Prince Vladimir of Kiev; this alliance led to Russia's subsequent conversion to Byzantine Christianity. The unit of Russian soldiers sent by Vladimir helped Basil stop Bardas Phocas in 989, and Bardas Sclerus capitulated shortly afterward. These long struggles to guarantee his throne left deep scars on Basil's personality. Easy-going and dissipated in his youth, he was turned by his ordeals into a dour, stern, self-denying ascetic. His experiences with ambitious warlords also bred in him a passionate hatred for the aristocrats and a determination to curb them.[PARAGRAPH:1]With the aristocracy dominating the military high commands, Basil decided early to establish his own reputation as a soldier. An initial attempt at campaigning against Bulgaria, the deadly northern enemy of Byzantium, in 986 had proved an embarrassing failure. In 990, however, Basil resumed his efforts against Bulgaria, which would become the prime target of his mature military efforts. The 25 years of bitter war between King Samuel of Bulgaria and Basil that followed became both a personal duel and a fight to the death between the two enemy states.[PARAGRAPH:1]With victories, devastation, and bold strategy, Basil wore Samuel down, segmented his territories, and crippled Bulgarian strength. The climax was reached in 1014, when the Byzantines captured the main Bulgarian army of some 14,000 men. Basil had these men blinded but left one in every hundred with one eye to serve as a guide. He sent them back to Samuel, who died from shock at the sight. Basil completed the annexation of Bulgaria and its incorporation into the empire with singular moderation and pragmatic wisdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]The next years of the tireless Emperor's reign were spent in settling the empire's interests in eastern Asia Minor and the Caucasus. He began the dismemberment and annexation of independent Armenia. Then, still restless, Basil turned his attentions further westward. He planned an expedition to reconquer Sicily and expand Byzantine authority in Italy; but before he could undertake this campaign, Basil suddenly took ill and died on Dec. 15, 1025. A bachelor, Basil left the throne to his younger brother, Constantine VIII, during whose reign (1025-1028) began the rapid erosion of the strength Basil had built up.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Bazyl II, Bułgarobójca[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Cesarz Bizantyjski[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył:[\BOLD] 958 - 1025 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Był synem Romana II i cesarzowej Teofano. Bazyli II przywrócił cesarstwu świetność nieznaną od czasów Justyniana Wielkiego. Koronowany na cesarza w wieku 5 lat. Ostrogorski pisze: "Chociaź panowanie Bazylego II oficjalnie rozpoczyna się w r. 976, to w rzeczywistości jego osobiste rządy datują się dopiero od r. 985, tj. po upadku wielkiego eunucha". Dokonał zmian w feudalnej strukturze państwa, konfiskując dobra wielkich moźnowładców, które pózniej rozdał zaufanym, choć mniej zamoźnym ludziom. Prowadził długoletnią wojnę z Bułgarią (szereg kampanii w latach 990-1014 r.), zakończoną w 1014 r. rozbiciem armii cara Samuela pod Biełasicą. Od tej bitwy, która zahamowała rozwój potęgi Bułgarów, wywodzi się jego przydomek - Bazyli rozkazał oślepić tysiące bułgarskich jeńców, zostawiając co setnego z jednym zdrowym okiem, aby mógł zaprowadzić swój oddział do domu. Car Samuel zmarł od szoku wywołanego widokiem powracających wojsk. W 1018 r. wcielił zachodnią Bułgarię do cesarstwa po zwycięskiej bitwie pod Durazzo. Dzięki temu zwycięstwu moźliwe było ponowne wcielenie Serbii do państwa bizantyńskiego. Kolejne zdobycze terytorialne osiągnął pokonując na zachodzie Normanów i ksiąźąt południowych Włoch. Za jego czasów Cesarstwo osiągnęło swoje apogeum, a takźe największe w średnim okresie terytorium rozciągające się od Armenii po Serbię. Zmarł w trakcie przygotowań do planowanej wyprawy na Sycylię.</Polish>
		<Russian>[H1]Василий II Болгаробойца[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Византийский император[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Годы жизни: [\BOLD] 958 - 1025 гг.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Биография: [\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Византийский император Василий II правил с 963 по 1025 год и получил прозвище Bulgaroctonus (Болгаробойца). Он был из числа последних и величайшим из императоров, которые привели Византию к пику ее военного могущества.[PARAGRAPH:1]Старший сын императора Романа II, Василий и его младший брат Константин, взошли на престол после смерти своего отца в 963 году. Их малолетством воспользовались один за другим два узурпатора, Никифор Фока (963-969) и Иоанн I Цимисхий (969-976). После смерти Иоанна, Василий попытался править самостоятельно, в то время как Константин оставался на заднем плане, но в итоге стал зависимым от своего двоюродного деда, евнуха Василия Лакапина. Хитрый царедворец с многолетним опытом, Лакапин помог Василию справиться с проблемами в лице еще двух потенциальных узурпаторов - аристократов Варды Склира и Варды Фока Младшего. После разгрома последнего мятежа отношения между возмужавшим Василием и фактическим правителем заметно охладились. Напряжение, постепенно нараставшее между Василием II и Лакапином завершилось свержением последнего в 985 году. Неприязнь императора к своему деду была настолько велика, что он объявил недействительными все законы, изданные в период их совместного правления.[PARAGRAPH:1]Последние два мятежа в конечном итоге заставили Василия обратиться за военной помощью к киевскому князю Владимиру; этот союз привел к последующему обращению Древней Руси к православию по греческому обряду. Русско-варяжская дружина, присланная в помощь Владимиром, помогло Василию разгромить Варду Фоку в 989 году, и вскоре после этого Варда Склир сдался. Эта долгая борьба за престол оставила глубокие шрамы на личности Василия. Мягкий и податливый в юности, он после пережитых суровых испытаний превратился в жесткого, самоотверженного аскета. Его негативный опыт борьбы с амбициозными полководцами породил в нем ярую ненависть к знати и решимости обуздать их. Первоначальная попытка провести кампанию против Болгарии, смертельного северного врага Византии, в 986 году, оказалась неудачной. Однако в 990 году Василий возобновил нажим против Болгарии, которая станет главной целью его зрелых военных усилий. Последовавшие за этим 25 лет ожесточенной войны между царем Болгарии Самуилом и Василием стали чем-то вроде личного состязания, так и битвой на смерть между двумя непримиримо враждебными государствами.[PARAGRAPH:1]Одерживая одну за другой победы, опустошая территорию противника, Василий решительными мерами измотал Самуила, раздробил территории его царства и совершено сокрушил военную мощь болгар. Кульминация наступила в 1014 году, когда византийцы разгромили в генеральном сражении 14-тысячную болгарскую армию. Василий приказал ослепил пленных болгар, но оставил одного пленника с одним глазом на каждые сто слепцов, чтобы служить им в качестве поводыря. Он отправил их обратно к Самуилу, который умер от разрыва сердца при виде армии калек. Василий завершил аннексию Болгарии и ее включил обескровленную державу в состав своей империи, сочетая жестокость на поле битвы с исключительной умеренностью и прагматической мудростью в административном управлении присоединенными землям.[PARAGRAPH:1]Последующие годы правления неутомимого Императора были потрачены на урегулирование интересов империи в Анатолии, Сирии и на Кавказе. Он начал расчленение и аннексию независимой Армении. Затем, все еще активный, Василий обратил свои аппетиты завоевателя еще дальше на запад. Он планировал экспедицию по завоеванию Сицилии и расширению византийской власти в Италии; но прежде чем он смог предпринять эту кампанию, Василий внезапно заболел и умер 15 декабря 1025 года. Будучи холостым и бездетным, Василий, завещал трон своему младшему брату Константину VIII, во время правления которого (1025-1028) началась смута, приведшая державу к быстрому ослаблению и упадку.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>