<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_HOLLIDAY_1</Tag>
		<English>I come in peace to ask for assistance. What do you say?</English>
		<French>Je suis venu en paix vous demander de l'aide. Qu'avez-vous à répondre?</French>
		<German>Ich komme in Frieden und bitte um Unterstützung. Wie lautet Eure Antwort?</German>
		<Italian>Vengo in pace alla ricerca di aiuto. Cosa mi rispondi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vengo en son de paz a pedir ayuda. ¿Qué me decís?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Przybywam w pokoju. Czy pomożesz mi?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_HOLLIDAY_1</Tag>
		<English>I hold the fate of the [CT_EMPIRE] in my hand. Give me what I demand.</English>
		<French>Je tiens le destin de l'[CT_EMPIRE] dans ma main. Donnez-moi ce que j'exige.</French>
		<German>Ich halte das Schicksal vom [CT_EMPIRE:3] in meinen Händen. Gebt mir, was ich verlange.</German>
		<Italian>Ho nelle mani il destino di [CT_EMPIRE]. Dammi ciò che chiedo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tengo el destino del [CT_EMPIRE] en mis manos. Dadme lo que os exijo.</Spanish>
		<Polish>W moich rękach leży los [CT_EMPIRE]. Daj mi czego się domagam.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_HOLLIDAY_1</Tag>
		<English>My town folks are in need, can the [CT_EMPIRE] help?</English>
		<French>Ma personnes est dans le besoin, l'[CT_EMPIRE] peut-il nous aider?</French>
		<German>Mein Stamm ist in Not, kann uns das [CT_EMPIRE:2] helfen?</German>
		<Italian>I miei concittadini hanno bisogno di aiuto, potete aiutarci?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mi puebla está necesitada. ¿Podrá ayudarnos el [CT_EMPIRE]?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Mieszkańcy mojego imperium potrzebują Twojej pomocy. Pomożesz?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HOLLIDAY_1</Tag>
		<English>Hello. I am [OUR_NAME], a gambler of [OUR_CIV_ADJ] township. I consider you a friend. It is in your best interest that I never change that opinion.</English>
		<Polish>Witam. Jestem [OUR_NAME], szuler z [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Traktuję Cię jak przyjaciela. W Twoim interesie leży nie zmieniać tego statusu.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_HOLLIDAY_1</Tag>
		<English>It is good to hear from the [CT_EMPIRE]. To what do I owe this honor?</English>
		<French>Quel plaisir d'avoir de vos nouvelles! Que me vaut cet honneur?</French>
		<German>Es ist gut, etwas vom [CT_EMPIRE:3] zu hören. Womit haben wir diese Ehre verdient?</German>
		<Italian>È bello avere notizie da [CT_EMPIRE]. A cosa debbo quest'onore?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es un placer oír al [CT_EMPIRE]. ¿A qué debo este honor?</Spanish>
		<Polish>Dobrze usłyszeć znajomy głos z CT_EMPIRE]. Czym mogę służyć?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_HOLLIDAY_1</Tag>
		<English>You have started down a path that will lead to your destruction. Feel free to try to explain yourself.</English>
		<French>Vous vous êtes engagé sur la voie qui menera à votre destruction. J'attends vos explications.</French>
		<German>Ihr habt begonnen, einen Pfad zu beschreiten, der zu Eurer Vernichtung führen wird. Wollt Ihr Euch möglicherweise rechtfertigen?</German>
		<Italian>Ti sei avviato lungo un cammino che porterà alla tua distruzione. Prova pure a cercare di spiegarti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Habéis hollado una senda que os llevará a la destrucción. Intentad explicaros como queráis.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Wstąpiłeś na ściężkę, która doprowadzi Cię do zguby. Masz coś na usprawiedliwienie?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_HOLLIDAY_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace? Never!</English>
		<French>La paix? Jamais!</French>
		<German>Frieden? Niemals!</German>
		<Italian>Pace? Mai!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Paz? ¡Jamás!</Spanish>
		<Polish>Pokój? Nigdy!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_HOLLIDAY_1</Tag>
		<English>You want to talk? It is a little too late for that.</English>
		<French>Vous voulez parler? C'est un peu tard pour ça.</French>
		<German>Ihr wollt reden? Dafür ist es etwas zu spät.</German>
		<Italian>Vuoi parlare? È un po' troppo tardi per farlo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Ahora queréis hablar? Es un poco tarde para eso.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Chcesz rozmawiać? Niestety jest już na to zbyt późno.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HOLLIDAY</Tag>
		<English>
			<Text>Doc Holliday</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Holliday</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Holliday</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Holliday</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Holliday</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HOLLIDAY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]John Henry "Doc" Holliday[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]American gambler[NEWLINE]Lived:[\BOLD] c. August 14, 1851 – November 8, 1887[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]was an American gambler, gunfighter, and dentist of the American Old West who is usually remembered for his friendship with Wyatt Earp and his involvement in the Gunfight at the O.K. Corral.[PARAGRAPH:1]As a young man, Holliday earned a D.D.S. degree and set up a dental practice in Atlanta, Georgia. In 1873 he was diagnosed with tuberculosis, the same disease that had claimed his mother when he was 15. He moved to the American Southwest in hopes that the climate would prolong his life. Taking up gambling as a profession, he subsequently acquired a reputation as a deadly gunman.[PARAGRAPH:1]During his travels, he met and became good friends with Wyatt Earp and his brothers. In 1880, he moved to Tombstone, Arizona, and participated alongside the Earps in the famous gunfight. This did not settle matters between the two sides, and Holliday was embroiled in ensuing shootouts and killings. He successfully fought being extradited for murder and died in bed at a Colorado hotel at the age of 36.[PARAGRAPH:1]The legend and mystique of his life is so great that he has been mentioned in countless books and portrayed by various actors in numerous movies and television series. For the 125-plus years since his death, debate has continued about the exact crimes he may have committed.Holliday was born in Griffin, Georgia, to Henry Burroughs Holliday and Alice Jane Holliday (nee McKey). His father served in the Mexican–American War and the Civil War. His family baptized him at the First Presbyterian Church in 1852.In 1864 his family moved to Valdosta, Georgia. Holliday's mother died of tuberculosis on September 16, 1866, when he was 15 years old. Three months later, his father married Rachel Martin. While in Valdosta, he attended the Valdosta Institute, where he received a strong classical secondary education in rhetoric, grammar, mathematics, history, and languages—principally Latin but also French and some Ancient Greek.In 1870 the 19-year-old Holliday left home to begin dental school in Philadelphia. On March 1, 1872, at the age of 20, he met the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Dental Surgery from the Pennsylvania College of Dental Surgery (which later merged with the University of Pennsylvania School of Dental Medicine). He graduated five months before his 21st birthday, which would have been problematic since this age was needed both to hold a D.D.S. degree and to practice dentistry as anything other than a student under a preceptor in Georgia.Holliday did not go home after graduation but worked as an assistant with a classmate, A. Jameson Fuches, Jr., in St. Louis, Missouri. By the end of July he had moved to Atlanta, where he lived with his uncle and his family while beginning his career as a dentist. A few weeks before his birthday, the Atlanta papers carried an announcement by noted dentist Arthur C. Ford in Atlanta that Holliday would fill his place in the office while he was attending dental meetings. This was the beginning of Holliday's career in private practice as a dentist, but it lasted only a short time, until December. Holliday's cousin by marriage was Margaret Mitchell, who wrote Gone With the Wind.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]John Henry "Doc" Holliday[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Amerykański Szuler[NEWLINE]Żył:[\BOLD] 14 Sierpnia 1851 –- 8 Października 1887[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Amerykański stomatolog, hazardzista i rewolwerowiec, przyjaciel Wyatta Earpa, uczestnik wydarzeń w Tombstone w latach osiemdziesiątych XIX wieku. Był spowinowacony z pisarką Margaret Mitchell. Gdy miał piętnaście lat jego matka umarła na gruźlicę. W 1870 rozpoczął naukę w szkole stomatologicznej. 1 marca 1872 uzyskał stopień doktora stomatologii w Pennsylvania College of Dental Surgery w Filadelfii. W tym samym roku otworzył wraz z Arturem C. Fordem gabinet dentystyczny w Atlancie. Wkrótce po rozpoczęciu własnej praktyki lekarskiej nabawił się gruźlicy, lekarze dawali mu tylko kilka miesięcy życia. Aby ograniczyć rozwój choroby, wyruszył w zachodnie rejony Stanów Zjednoczonych. Pierwszym jego przystankiem było Dallas w Teksasie. Aby zarobić na utrzymanie zaczął uprawiać hazard. Po sprzeczce, w której zabił człowieka, uciekł do Jacksboro w Teksasie. Podczas podróży po południowym zachodzie zaprzyjaźnił się z Wyattem Earpem. Dzięki tej przyjaźni trafił latem 1880 do Tombstone w Arizonie i był czynnym uczestnikiem wydarzeń z lat 1880-1882 (m.in. strzelanina w O.K. Corral).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>