<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SMOKE_JAGUAR_1</Tag>
		<English>Give this to [OUR_CIV_SHORT] or I'll snap your neck like a twig!</English>
		<Polish>Dawaj to nam lub złamię Twój kark jak gałązkę!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SMOKE_JAGUAR_1</Tag>
		<English>Hand this over or the next skull to adorn my necklace will be yours!</English>
		<Polish>Dawaj mi to czego chcę lub dołączę Twoją czaszkę do mojego naszyjnika!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SMOKE_JAGUAR_1</Tag>
		<English>See this necklace? These skulls used to belong to people who didn't pay me tribute. Kinda says something, doesn't it, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<Polish>Widzisz ten naszyjnik? Czaszki z których go zrobiono należały do ludzi, którzy nie płacili mi trybutu. To o czymś świadczy, nieprawdaż?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SMOKE_JAGUAR_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], ruler of and master of the [OUR_EMPIRE].  Will you accept peace, or shall I spill your blood on the streets and wear your head as a trinket?</English>
		<Polish>Witam [CT_NAME]. Jestem [OUR_NAME], władca i pan Imperium [OUR_EMPIRE].  Zaakceptujesz pokój, czy może Twoja krew poleje się po ulicach, a ja będę nosił Twoją głowę jako ozdobę?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SMOKE_JAGUAR_2</Tag>
		<English>Welcome to our land of riches, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</English>
		<Polish>Witamy w naszej krainie bogactw, [CT_NAME]. Jestem [OUR_NAME] z [OUR_EMPIRE].</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SMOKE_JAGUAR_1</Tag>
		<English>Good evening, [CT_NAME]. Let's have fun watching the ball game and then have even more fun sacrificing the losers to the gods!</English>
		<Polish>Dobry wieczór, [CT_NAME]. Obejrzyjmy sobie grę w piłkę, a później zabawmy się w składanie w ofierze zawodników z drużyny która przegrała!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SMOKE_JAGUAR_1</Tag>
		<English>I'd like to sacrifice you to the gods, [CT_NAME], but they probably wouldn't stand that revolting stench of yours... what do you want?</English>
		<Polish>Chciałbym złożyć Cię w ofierze bogom, [CT_NAME], ale podejrzewam, że bogowie nie wytrzymali by Twojego obrzydliwego zapachu.... czego chcesz?</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SMOKE_JAGUAR_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace? What's the word I'm thinking of... It's at the tip of my tongue... oh yeah! NO!!!</English>
		<Polish>Pokój? Co to za słowo o jakim myślę... Jest na końcu języka... a już wiem! NIE!!!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SMOKE_JAGUAR_1</Tag>
		<English>What are YOU doing here? Get out before you get speared, you piece of toucan leavings!</English>
		<Polish>Co TY tutaj robisz? Wynoś się, zanim zostaniesz zabity, Ty kawałku odchodów tukana!</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SMOKE_JAGUAR</Tag>
		<English>Smoke Jaguar</English>
		<French>Jaguar Nébuleux</French>
		<Polish>Dymiący Jaguar</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SMOKE_JAGUAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Chan Imix K'awiil ("Smoke Jaguar")[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Xukpi ruler[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]628 - 695 [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Smoke Jaguar (628-695AD) was one of the greatest leaders of the Maya and he built the city of Copán into a major military and commercial power.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Pre-Columbian city today known as Copán is a locale in western Honduras, in the Copán Department, near to the Guatemalan border. It is the site of a major Maya kingdom of the Classic era (5th through 9th Centuries). The kingdom, anciently named Xukpi (Corner-Bundle), flourished from the 5th century AD to the early 9th century, with antecedents going back to at least the 2nd century AD. Its name is an apparent reference to the fact that it was situated at the far southern and eastern end of Maya territory. The nearby modern village of Copán Ruinas itself may have anciently been known as Oxwitik. [PARAGRAPH:1]Xukpi grew into one of the most important Maya sites, becoming a regional power, and large monuments dated with hieroglyphic texts were erected in the city from 435 to 822. The development of the site was aided by a long period of stability, particularly during the long reign of Smoke Jaguar (628-695), whose 67 years on the throne was remarkable in a society where the average life expectancy was 35 years and whose stela is in the grassy courtyard of the West Court. It suffered a catastrophic defeat at the hands of its former vassal state Quirigua in 738 but, after a period of decline, Copán's rulers began to build monumental structures again within a few decades. In the ninth century Copan, like other cities in the region, withered in the as a result of unsustainable population growth bringing about the depletion of natural resources. The area continued to be occupied by squatters after the last major ceremonial structures and royal monuments were erected and the population declined from perhaps over 20,000 in the city to less than 5,000. The ceremonial center was abandoned and the surrounding valley contained only a few farming hamlets when the Spanish arrived in the 16th century.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Chan Imix K'awiil ("Dymiący Jaguar")[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Władca Xukpi[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył: [\BOLD]628 - 695 [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Smoke Jaguar (628-695AD) was one of the greatest leaders of the Maya and he built the city of Copán into a major military and commercial power.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Pre-Columbian city today known as Copán is a locale in western Honduras, in the Copán Department, near to the Guatemalan border. It is the site of a major Maya kingdom of the Classic era (5th through 9th Centuries). The kingdom, anciently named Xukpi (Corner-Bundle), flourished from the 5th century AD to the early 9th century, with antecedents going back to at least the 2nd century AD. Its name is an apparent reference to the fact that it was situated at the far southern and eastern end of Maya territory. The nearby modern village of Copán Ruinas itself may have anciently been known as Oxwitik. [PARAGRAPH:1]Xukpi grew into one of the most important Maya sites, becoming a regional power, and large monuments dated with hieroglyphic texts were erected in the city from 435 to 822. The development of the site was aided by a long period of stability, particularly during the long reign of Smoke Jaguar (628-695), whose 67 years on the throne was remarkable in a society where the average life expectancy was 35 years and whose stela is in the grassy courtyard of the West Court. It suffered a catastrophic defeat at the hands of its former vassal state Quirigua in 738 but, after a period of decline, Copán's rulers began to build monumental structures again within a few decades. In the ninth century Copan, like other cities in the region, withered in the as a result of unsustainable population growth bringing about the depletion of natural resources. The area continued to be occupied by squatters after the last major ceremonial structures and royal monuments were erected and the population declined from perhaps over 20,000 in the city to less than 5,000. The ceremonial center was abandoned and the surrounding valley contained only a few farming hamlets when the Spanish arrived in the 16th century.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
