<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_CATHEDRAL</Tag>
		<English>Nature Alliance</English>
		<French>Alliance avec la Nature</French>
		<Italian>Alleanza della natura</Italian>
		<Polish>Przymierze Natury</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_CATHEDRAL2</Tag>
		<English>Nature Legacy</English>
		<French>Patrimoine Naturel</French>
		<Italian>Eredità della natura</Italian>
		<Polish>Dziedzictwo Natury</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_CATHEDRAL2_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Legacy</English>
		<Italian>Eredità della natura</Italian>
		<Polish>Dziedzictwo Natury</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_CATHEDRAL2_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Legacy[COLOR_REVERT] improves health and happiness in the city. It requires Druidic Traditions as the state religion.</English>
		<Italian>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Eredità della natura[COLOR_REVERT] migliora la salute e la felicità nella tua città; è necessario che le tradizioni druidiche siano la religione di stato.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_CATHEDRAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Alliance</English>
		<French>Alliance avec la Nature</French>
		<Italian>Alleanza della natura</Italian>
		<Polish>Przymierze Natury</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_CATHEDRAL_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Alliance[COLOR_REVERT] greatly increases a city's food from grains and potatoes. It is required to build the druidic cathedral building ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Legacy[COLOR_REVERT]). It requires Druidic Traditions as the state religion.</English>
		<French>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature AllianceCOLOR_REVERT] greatly increases a city's food from grains and potatoes. It is required to build the druidic cathedral building ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Legacy[COLOR_REVERT]). It requires Druidic Traditions as the state religion.</French>
		<German>Der [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Alliance[COLOR_REVERT] greatly increases a city's food from grains and potatoes. It is required to build the druidic cathedral building ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Legacy[COLOR_REVERT]). It requires Druidic Traditions as the state religion.</German>
		<Italian>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Alleanza della natura[COLOR_REVERT] aumenta la produzione di cibo della città grazie a cereali e patate. Serve per costruire la cattedrale druidica, l'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Eredità della natura[COLOR_REVERT]. E' necessario che le tradizioni druidiche siano la tua religione di stato.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle of Power</English>
		<French>Cercle Naturel de Puissance</French>
		<Italian>Cerchio naturale del potere</Italian>
		<Polish>Krąg Mocy</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_ALMOND</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Almond)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_APPLE</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Apple)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_BANANA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Banana)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_BARLEY</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Barley God)</English>
		<French>Cercle Naturel (Orge)</French>
		<Italian>Cerchio della natura (Orzo)</Italian>
		<Polish>Krąg Mocy (Bóstwo Jęczmienia)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_COCONUT</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Coconut)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_CORN</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Maize God)</English>
		<French>Cercle Naturel (Maïs)</French>
		<Italian>Cerchio della natura (Grano)</Italian>
		<Polish>Krąg Mocy (Bóstwo Kukurydzy)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_DATES</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Dates)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_FIG</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Figs)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_GRAPES</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Grapes)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_GUAVA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Guavas)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_KAVA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Kava)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_LEMON</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Lemon)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_MANGO</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Mango)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_MELON</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Melons)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_MUSHROOMS</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Mushrooms)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_OLIVES</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Olives)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_PAPAYA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Papayas)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A monastery is a building where monks can retreat from the world and concentrate upon the divine. Usually a monastery will have strict rules of conduct to protect its unworldly members from temptation. In some monasteries, the monks are totally silent; in others no visitors are allowed inside. Monasteries usually have many daily rituals and religious services.[PARAGRAPH:1]Throughout the ages monasteries have often been centers of learning. In remote areas the monks may be the only literate people for miles around. Monks have often been employed as scribes, copying out the words of their religion's sacred scripture. Monasteries frequently have extensive libraries, holding religious, scientific, medical and philosophical texts.</English>
		<French>Un monastère est un édifice dans lequel les moines peuvent se retirer du monde et se concentrer sur le divin. Généralement, les règles de conduite y sont strictes afin de protéger ses membres, détachés du monde, de la tentation. Dans certains monastères, les moines sont totalement silencieux ; dans d'autres, les visiteurs ne sont pas autorisés à pénétrer dans leur enceinte. Les monastères ont généralement de nombreux rituels et services religieux quotidiens.[PARAGRAPH:1]A travers les siècles, les monastères ont souvent été des centres d'érudition. Dans les zones retirées, les moines étaient parfois les seules personnes sachant lire et écrire à des kilomètres à la ronde. Ils ont souvent servi de scribes, recopiant les textes sacrés de leur religion. Les monastères ont généralement de grandes bibliothèques possédant des textes religieux, scientifiques, médicaux et philosophiques.</French>
		<German>Klöster sind Gebäude, in die sich Mönche zurückziehen, um sich auf Gott zu konzentrieren. In Klöstern gelten strenge Verhaltensregeln, die die Mönche vor Versuchungen bewahren sollen. In einigen Klöstern herrscht ein strenges Redeverbot, in anderen sind keine Besucher gestattet. Die Mönche selbst gehen täglich ihren religiösen Pflichten nach.[PARAGRAPH:1]In der Vergangenheit waren Klöster stets auch Zentren des Wissens. In abgelegenen Gegenden waren die Mönche oft die einzigen gebildeten Menschen, die als Schreiber ihre religiösen Schriften kopierten. Klöster haben nicht selten Bibliotheken, in denen unzählige religiöse, wissenschaftliche, medizinische und philosophische Texte aufbewahrt werden.</German>
		<Italian>Il monastero è un edificio nel quale i monaci possono ritirarsi dal mondo e concentrarsi sul Divino. In genere, nel monastero vige un regolamento ferreo per proteggere i membri della comunità dalle tentazioni. In alcuni monasteri, i monaci erano completamente silenziosi e non erano permesse visite dall'esterno per non interrompere i rituali quotidiani e le cerimonie religiose.[PARAGRAPH:1]Nel corso dei secoli, i monasteri sono stati spesso centro di insegnamento: in alcune zone, i monaci erano sovente gli unici in grado di leggere e scrivere nel giro di diversi chilometri. Da sempre, i monaci sono stati utilizzati come scribi per copiare le parole sacre della propria religione; i monasteri ospitavano spesso delle biblioteche che contenevano testi religiosi, scientifici, medici e filosofici.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Un monasterio es un edificio en el que los monjes pueden retirarse del mundo para concentrarse en los asuntos de la divinidad. Normalmente tienen estrictas reglas de comportamiento para proteger a sus miembros de la tentación. En algunos monasterios, los monjes guardan un silencio total, mientras que en otros no se permite el acceso a los visitantes. Lo habitual es que sus miembros tengan que celebrar a diario muchos rituales y servicios religiosos.[PARAGRAPH:1]A lo largo de la historia, los monasterios han sido muchas veces centros de estudio. En las regiones remotas, los monjes podían ser las únicas personas letradas en muchos kilómetros a la redonda. A menudo han sido empleados como escribas, y se han dedicado a copiar los textos sagrados de su religión. Normalmente cuentan con grandes bibliotecas, que contienen textos religiosos, científicos, médicos y filosóficos.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Klasztor - budynek lub zespół budynków, w którym mieszkają wspólnoty religijne zakonników albo zakonnic. Klasztory są znane przede wszystkim z chrześcijaństwa i buddyzmu, choć występują lub występowały także w hinduizmie, dżinizmie, islamie i judaizmie. Nazwą tą określa się często sam zakon czy zgromadzenie zakonne.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_PISTACHIO</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Pistachio)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_POMEGRANATE</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Pomegranate)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_POTATO</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Potatoe God)</English>
		<French>Cercle Naturel (Pommes de terre)</French>
		<Italian>Cerchio della natura (Patate)</Italian>
		<Polish>Krąg Mocy (Bóstwo Ziemniaka)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_PRICKLY_PEAR</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Prickly Pear)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_PUMPKIN</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Pumpkin)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_RICE</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Rice God)</English>
		<French>Cercle Naturel (Riz)</French>
		<Italian>Cerchio della natura (Riso)</Italian>
		<Polish>Krąg Mocy (Bóstwo Ryżu)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_SQUASH</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Squash)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Druidic Monastery [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Circle of Power[COLOR_REVERT] is required to build the druidic cathedral building ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Alliance[COLOR_REVERT]) and druidic missionaries. It does not go obsolete like other monastry buildings. If Druidism is your state religion there are extennsions to this building that increase the amount of food generated from grains and potatoes.</English>
		<French>Le Monastère druidique [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Le Cercle Naturel de Puissance[COLOR_REVERT]) est requis pour construire la cathédrale druidique ([COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Alliance avec la Nature[COLOR_REVERT]) et les missionnaires druides. Il ne devient jamais obsolète comme pour les autres religions. Si les traditions druidiques est votre Religion d'Etat, Il est possible d'ajouter des extensions à ce bâtiment qui augmentent notamment la quantités de nourriture obtenue à partir de certains légumes et céréales.</French>
		<Italian>Il monastero druidico, il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Cerchio naturale del potere[COLOR_REVERT], è un prerequisito per costruire l'edificio [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Alleanza della natura[COLOR_REVERT] e per addestrare i missionari druidici; tuttavia, non diventa obsoleto come gli altri monasteri. Se il druidismo è la tua religione di stato, avendo accesso ai cereali e alle patate fornisce un bonus alla produzione di cibo.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_MONASTERY_WHEAT</Tag>
		<English>Nature Circle (Wheat God)</English>
		<French>Cercle Naturel (Céréales)</French>
		<Italian>Cerchio della natura (Frumento)</Italian>
		<Polish>Krąg Mocy (Bóstwo Pszenicy)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_SHRINE</Tag>
		<English>Nature Answer</English>
		<French>Réponse par la Nature</French>
		<Italian>Risposta della natura</Italian>
		<Polish>Zew Natury</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Druids revere many aspects of nature. The four arches of stone are a symbol for the four seasons of a year, the balance between and the annual recurrence of them. The water of the pool is a symbol for restoration and life itself. The Pool of Balance is a sacred place of meditation for the druids.</English>
		<Italian>I druidi venerano molti aspetti della natura. I quattro archi di pietra sono un simbolo delle quattro stagioni di un anno, il loro equilibrio e la loro ricorrenza annuale. L'acqua della piscina è un simbolo della rinascita e della vita stessa. La Piscina di equilibrio è un luogo sacro di meditazione per i druidi.</Italian>
		<Polish>Istniało zrzeszenie druidów o charakterze religijnym, w którym jeden z kapłanów miał władzę zwierzchnią, zaś po jego śmierci następcą zostawał ten, który był najbardziej godny i dostojny. W razie wątpliwości urządzano głosowanie lub też kandydaci odbywali święty pojedynek na słowa. Późniejsze teksty mówią natomiast o królu druidów - tzw. righ druadh, a także o naczelnym mistrzu - primus magister (łac.). Wszyscy druidzi zbierali się corocznie na terytorium Karnutów w samym środku Galii.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_SHRINE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>TBD</English>
		<Italian>Utilizza un grande profeta per costruire il santuario druidico.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar</English>
		<French>Autel de la Nature</French>
		<Italian>Altare della natura</Italian>
		<Polish>Ołtarz Natury</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_ALMOND</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Almond)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_APPLE</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Apple)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_BANANA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Banana)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_BARLEY</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Barley God)</English>
		<French>Autel de la Nature (Orge)</French>
		<Italian>Altare della natura (Orzo)</Italian>
		<Polish>Ołtarz Natury (Bóstwo Jęczmienia)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_COCONUT</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Coconut)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_CORN</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Maize God)</English>
		<French>Autel de la Nature (Maïs)</French>
		<German>Nature Altar (Maïs)</German>
		<Italian>Altare della natura (Grano)</Italian>
		<Polish>Ołtarz Natury (Bóstwo Kukurydzy)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_DATES</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Dates)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_FIG</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Figs)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_GRAPES</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Grapes)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_GUAVA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Guavas)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_KAVA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Kava)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_LEMON</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Lemon)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_MANGO</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Mango)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_MELON</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Melons)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_MUSHROOMS</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Mushrooms)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_OLIVES</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Olives)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_PAPAYA</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Papayas)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In Civilization IV, a temple is defined as a building where the faithful come to worship. Christians call their temples "churches," while Muslims call theirs "mosques," and Jews call theirs, simply, "temples." Temples are far more common than cathedrals, but much less large and ornate. Even the smallest village can possess a temple.</English>
		<French>Dans Civilization IV, un petit lieu de culte est défini comme un édifice dans lequel les fidèles viennent pratiquer leur religion: "églises" pour les chrétiens, "petites mosquées" pour les musulmans et "petites synagogues" pour les juifs. Ces petits lieux de culte sont bien plus courants que les grands lieux de culte mais sont de taille plus réduite et sont bien moins richement ornés. Même le village le plus petit peut posséder un petit lieu de culte.</French>
		<German>In Civilization IV sind Tempel Gebäude, in denen Gläubige beten. Christen nennen ihre Tempel "Kirchen", Moslems "Moscheen". Es gibt deutlich mehr Tempel als Kathedralen. Allerdings sind sie wesentlich kleiner und schlichter. Selbst das kleinste Dorf kann einen Tempel besitzen.</German>
		<Italian>In Civilization IV, il tempio è un edificio all'interno del quale i fedeli si recano a pregare. I Cristiani chiamano i loro templi "chiese", i Musulmani "moschee", gli Ebrei semplicemente "templi". I templi sono più comuni delle cattedrali, ma sono più piccoli e poco fastosi. Anche il villaggio più piccolo ospita un tempio.</Italian>
		<Spanish>En Civilization IV, un templo se define como un lugar al que los fieles acuden a venerar. Los cristianos llaman a sus templos "iglesias", mientras que para los musulmanes son "mezquitas" y para los judíos, sencillamente, "templos". Son mucho más comunes que las catedrales, pero también mucho más pequeños y humildes. Hasta la más pequeña aldea puede poseer uno.</Spanish>
		<Polish>Swiątynia - miejsce kultu religijnego. W sensie szerszym, jest to każda budowla wzniesiona w celu sprawowania w niej wszelkiego rodzaju obrzędów religijnych. W sensie węższym, świątynią może być tylko taka budowla, która spełnia przynajmniej niektóre wyższe funkcje kultowe (np. składanie ofiar), sprawowane jedynie przez kapłanów.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_PISTACHIO</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Pistachio)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_POMEGRANATE</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Pomegranate)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_POTATO</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Potato God)</English>
		<French>Autel de la Nature (Pommes de terre)</French>
		<Italian>Altare della natura (Patate)</Italian>
		<Polish>Ołtarz Natury (Bóstwo Ziemniaka)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_PRICKLY_PEAR</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Prickly Pear)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_PUMPKIN</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Pumpkin)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_RICE</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Rice God)</English>
		<French>Autel de la Nature (Riz)</French>
		<Italian>Altare della natura (Riso)</Italian>
		<Polish>Ołtarz Natury (Bóstwo Ryżu)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_SQUASH</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Squash)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Druidic Temple [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Altar[COLOR_REVERT] is required to build any of the other druidic buildings. There are extensions to this building that increase the amount of food generated from grains and potatoes.</English>
		<French>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]L'Autel de la Nature[COLOR_REVERT] (le Temple druidique) est requis pour construire les autres bâtiments de cette religion. Des extensions sont possibles, améliorant la production de nourriture.</French>
		<Italian>Il tempio druidico, l'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Altare della natura[COLOR_REVERT], è un prerequisito per tutti gli altri edifici druidici. Alcuni miglioramenti di questo edificio aumentano il cibo generato dai cereali e dalle patate.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DRUID_TEMPLE_WHEAT</Tag>
		<English>Nature Altar (Wheat God)</English>
		<French>Autel de la Nature (Céréales)</French>
		<Italian>Altare della natura (Frumento)</Italian>
		<Polish>Ołtarz Natury (Bóstwo Pszenicy)</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_DRUIDIC_TRADITIONS</Tag>
		<English>Druidic Traditions</English>
		<French>Traditions Druidiques</French>
		<German>Druidentum</German>
		<Italian>Tradizioni druidiche</Italian>
		<Polish>Tradycje Druidów</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_DRUIDIC_TRADITIONS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Druidic</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Druidique:Druidiques</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Druidisch:druidischen:druidische</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter:Neuter:Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>druidico:druidica:druidici:druidiche</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Druidic</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Druidyczny</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_DRUIDIC_TRADITIONS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A druid was a member of the high-ranking professional class in ancient Celtic cultures.[PARAGRAPH:2]While perhaps best remembered as religious leaders, they were also legal authorities, adjudicators, lorekeepers, medical professionals, and political advisors. While the druids are reported to have been literate, they are believed to have been prevented by doctrine from recording their knowledge in written form, thus they left no written accounts of themselves. They are however attested in some detail by their contemporaries from other cultures, such as the Romans and the Greeks.[PARAGRAPH:2]Druidic lore consisted of a large number of verses learned by heart, and Caesar remarked that it could take up to twenty years to complete the course of study. What was taught to druid novices anywhere is conjecture: of the druids' oral literature, not one certifiably ancient verse is known to have survived, even in translation. All instruction was communicated orally, but for ordinary purposes, Caesar reports, the Gauls had a written language in which they used Greek characters. In this he probably draws on earlier writers; by the time of Caesar, Gaulish inscriptions had moved from the Greek script to the Latin script.[PARAGRAPH:2]Greek and Roman writers frequently made reference to the druids as practitioners of human sacrifice. According to Caesar, those who had been found guilty of theft or other criminal offences were considered preferable for use as sacrificial victims, but when criminals were in short supply, innocents would be acceptable. A form of sacrifice recorded by Caesar was the burning alive of victims in a large wooden effigy, now often known as a wicker man. A differing account came from the 10th-century Commenta Bernensia, which claimed that sacrifices to the deities Teutates, Esus and Taranis were by drowning, hanging and burning, respectively.[PARAGRAPH:2]Diodorus Siculus, writing in 36 BCE, described how the druids followed "the Pythagorean doctrine", that human souls "are immortal and after a prescribed number of years they commence a new life in a new body." In 1928, folklorist Donald A. Mackenzie speculated that Buddhist missionaries had been sent by the Indian king Ashoka. Others have invoked common Indo-European parallels. Caesar noted the druidic doctrine of the original ancestor of the tribe, whom he referred to as Dispater, or Father Hades.[PARAGRAPH:2]Druids also play a prominent role in Irish Folklore, generally serving lords and kings as high ranking priest-counselors with the gift of prophecy and other assorted mystical abilities - the best example of these possibly being Cathbad. The chief druid in the court of King Conchobar mac Nessa of Ulster, Cathbad features in several tales, most of which detail his ability to foretell the future. In the tale of Deirdre of the Sorrows – the foremost tragic heroine of the Ulster Cycle – the druid prophesied before the court of Conchobar that Deirdre would grow up to be very beautiful, but that kings and lords would go to war over her, much blood would be shed because of her, and Ulster's three greatest warriors would be forced into exile for her sake. This prophecy, ignored by the king, came true.</English>
		<German>Ein Druide war ein Mitglied der priesterlichen und gelehrten Klasse in der antiken keltischen Gesellschaft in Westeuropa, Britanien und Irland. Sie wurden durch die romische Regierung unterdrückt und verschwinden aus den schriftlichen Überlieferungen im zweiten Jahrhundert nach Christi. Druiden verbanden die Aufgaben von Priestern, Richtern, Gelehrten und Lehrern. Es gibt wenige zeitgenössische Hinweise auf ihre Existenz, so dass wir heute wenig mit Sicherheit über sie sagen können, jedoch spielen sie eine wichtige Rolle in den späteren irischen Mythen und Literatur.[PARAGRAPH:2]Als die früheste Aufzeichnung des Namens druidae werden die verlorenen Werke des griechischen Doxographen Sotion von Alexandrien (frühes zweites Jahrhundert vor Christi) bezeichnet, der im dritten Jahrhundert nach Christus von Diogenes Laertius zitiert wurde.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die keltischen Gemeinschaften, in denen Druiden dienten, waren polytheistisch. Sie zeigten auch Merkmale von Animismus durch ihre Verehrung verschiedener Aspekte der Natur, so wie Land, Meer und Himmel, sowie durch die Ehrfurcht vor anderen Naturaspekten, wie heilige Bäume und Haine, (Eiche und Haselnussstrauch wurden besonders verehrt), Hügelspitzen, Wasserläufen, Seen und Pflanzen, wie zum Beispiel die Mistel. Feuer wurde als das Symbol verschiedener Götter angesehen und wurde mit Reinigung assoziert. Angebliche rituelle Tötungen und Menschenopfer waren Aspekte der druidischen Kultur, die klassische Schriftsteller schockierten.</German>
		<Italian>Un druido era un membro della classe sacerdotale e istruita nelle antiche società celtiche dell'Europa occidentale, della Gran Bretagna e dell'Irlanda. Furono soppressi dal governo romano e scomparvero dalla storia intorno al II secolo d.C; avevano le funzioni di sacerdoti, giudici, studiosi e insegnanti. Poche prove esistono di loro attualmente, e quindi poco si può dire di loro con certezza, ma continuarono a vivere nel mito e nella letteratura irlandese seguente.[PARAGRAPH:2]La prima testimonianza del nome druidae è segnalato da un'opera perduta dello scrittore greco Sozione di Alessandria (inizi del II secolo a.C.), che è stato citato da Diogene Laerzio nel III secolo d.C.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le comunità celtiche che i druidi servivano erano politeiste; mostravano anche segni di animismo, nel loro rispetto per i vari aspetti del mondo naturale, come la terra, il mare e il cielo, e del loro culto di altri aspetti della natura, come alberi e boschetti sacri (la quercia e il nocciolo erano particolarmente venerati), cime di colline, torrenti, laghi e piante come il vischio. Il fuoco era ritenuto un simbolo di diverse divinità ed è stato associato con la pulizia. Le uccisioni rituali e i sacrifici umani erano gli aspetti della cultura druidica che sconvolsero gli scrittori classici.</Italian>
		<Polish>Druid (łac. druides albo druida, z celtyckiego) - starożytny kapłan celtycki, który przewodził obrzędom i ceremoniom religijnym. Druidzi sprawowali także sądy oraz przepowiadali przyszłość z lotu ptaków lub z wnętrzności zwierząt. Jedna z trzech kast kapłańskich, obok bardów i filidów (vates), u Celtów.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_DRUIDIC_TRADITIONS_QUOTE</Tag>
		<English>So, apart from casting runes, what other hobbies do you have - forbidden rituals... human sacrifices?[PARAGRAPH:2]- Simona Panova,[PARAGRAPH:1][SPACE][SPACE]"Nightmarish Sacrifice"</English>
		<French>"Les Gaulois ont des hommes sages, experts des Dieux, qu'ils nomment Druides. A travers les entrailles et les sacrifices d'animaux, ils peuvent préduire le futur, et personne n'ose douter de leur parole. Dans ce type de divination provenant de la Nature, ces éclairés accordent la plus haute importance dans la tradition antique de l'observation." - Diodorus</French>
		<Polish>"Galowie mieli specjalnych kapłanów i mędrców zajmujących się kontaktem z bogami. To byli Druidzi." - Diodor</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_DRUIDIC_TRADITIONS_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_TECH_TEXT]Druidic Traditions[COLOR_REVERT] is a prehistoric era technology that founds said religion in the first civilization that researches it.</English>
		<French>Recherchez Druidisme pour fonder une religion</French>
		<Spanish>Investiga el Druidismo para fundar una religión.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DRUID_MISSIONARY</Tag>
		<English>Druidic Missionary</English>
		<French>Missionnaire Druidique</French>
		<German>Druidischer Missionar</German>
		<Italian>Missionario druidico</Italian>
		<Polish>Druid</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DRUID_MISSIONARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A druid was a member of the educated, professional class among the Celtic peoples of Gaul, Britain, Ireland, and possibly elsewhere during the Iron Age. The druid class included law-speakers, poets and doctors, among other learned professions, although the best known among the druids were the religious leaders.</English>
		<Polish>Druidzi sprawowali ważne funkcje społeczne, byli odpowiedzialni za sprawy wiedzy i nauczania. Młodzież nauczano o nieśmiertelności duszy, reinkarnacji, co przekazywano w formie poetyckiej do nauczenia się na pamięć - studia trwały nawet (jak twierdzi Cezar) do 20 lat, gdyż wiedza była przekazywana tylko drogą ustną. Mieli dużą wiedzę o gwiazdach i ich ruchach, o przyrodzie, mocach i nieśmiertelnych bogach. Innym ważnym zadaniem druidów było strzeżenie tradycji i wpajanie cnót moralnych.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DRUID_MISSIONARY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Use this missionary to actively spread the [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Druidic Traditions[COLOR_REVERT] in friendly cities (or rival cities with whom you have [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Open Borders[COLOR_REVERT]). This increases your income if you have the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Nature Answer[COLOR_REVERT].</English>
		<German>Verbreitet das Druidentum. Haben Sie das Becken des Gleichgewichts, erhöhen sich dadurch Ihre Einnahmen.</German>
		<Italian>Usa questo missionario per diffondere attivamente le [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Traduzioni druidiche[COLOR_REVERT] nelle città alleate, o nelle città straniere nelle quali hai un [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Diritto di passaggio[COLOR_REVERT]).</Italian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
