<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HIROHITO_1</Tag>
		<English>I am honored to meet you, [CT_NAME]. The [OUR_EMPIRE] will be a strong and resilient neighbour, resolved to endure the unendurable and suffer what is insufferable.</English>
		<French>Je suis honoré de vous rencontrer, [CT_NAME]. L'[OUR_EMPIRE] sera un voisin fort résistant, déterminé à endurer ce qui n'est pas endurable et à souffrir au-delà de toute souffrance.</French>
		<German>Ich fühle mich geehrt, Dich zu treffen, [CT_NAME]. Das [OUR_EMPIRE] wird ein starker und belastbarer Nachbar sein, entschlossen, das Unerträgliche zu ertragen.</German>
		<Spanish>Es un honor conocerte, [CT_NAME]. El [OUR_EMPIRE] será un vecino fuerte y luchador ante las adversidades, capaz de soportar lo insoportable y de sufrir lo insufrible.</Spanish>
		<Polish>To zaszczyt dla mnie spotkać [CT_NAME]. Niech [OUR_EMPIRE] będzie silnym i prężnym sąsiadem, rozwiązuje nie rozwiązalne, powstrzymuje nie powstrzymane i cierpi rzeczy nie do wycierpenia.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HIROHITO</Tag>
		<English>Hirohito</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HIROHITO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Hirohito[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of Japan[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] April 29, 1901 - January 7, 1989[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Emperor Showa was the 124th Emperor of Japan according to the traditional order of succession, reigning from December 25, 1926 until his death in 1989. In the Western World, he is most known by the name he had while he was alive, Hirohito. The word Showa is the name of the era that corresponded with the Emperor's reign, and was made the Emperor's own name upon his death.[PARAGRAPH:1]Hirohito took the throne on December 25, 1926. Shortly after Hirohito became emperor, Japan's relations with the outside world began to fall apart. In 1927 Japanese army officers, without the agreement of Emperor Hirohito, sparked conflict with Manchuria and later occupied parts of that country. Hirohito soon found his military deeply involved on the Asian mainland.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Manchurian incident ushered in a period of serious unrest within Japan. Young military officers plotted a series of unsuccessful takeovers as well as a number of successful assassinations (secretly planned murders). They hoped to overthrow parts of the government in order to establish a military regime that could govern in the name of "direct imperial rule." In other words, Hirohito would still be called emperor and would be the head of the government, but the military would actually be in control. Hirohito, however, saw himself as part of the state rather than a sole ruler and believed that the leaders of government should be men of moderation and nonmilitaristic in outlook.In July 1937 hostilities with China broke out. During the late 1930s Hirohito's advisers in the palace urged him to stay away from direct involvement in politics or be forced to compromise the position of the imperial family. The emperor followed this advice, and agreed to whatever policies the governments decided upon.[PARAGRAPH:1]There is every evidence that the emperor felt uneasy about the unfolding of events, particularly after 1940. He did not favor the alliance with Germany and Italy in World War II (1939-45), but he made no effort to oppose it. Similarly, he had grown distrustful of the judgments of the military leaders who kept assuring him of a quick end to the war in China. But when the final decision on war with the United States was made on September 6, 1941, he barely opposed it. During the war Hirohito refused to leave the imperial palace at Tokyo, even after air raids began to demolish the city and fires destroyed many buildings on the palace grounds. He wished to share the hardships of his subjects.[PARAGRAPH:1]By the summer of 1945 it was clear that defeat was at hand. But the decision to surrender did not come until after atomic bombs were dropped on the Japanese towns of Hiroshima and Nagasaki. At a historic imperial conference on August 9, 1945, the emperor made clear his opinion in favor of surrendering to the allied powers led by the United States. Following Japan's formal surrender in September 1945, there was much discussion about whether Emperor Hirohito should be punished as a war criminal. Hirohito himself frequently expressed his willingness to step down as a token of his responsibility for the war. But the U.S. authorities, including General Douglas MacArthur (1880-1964), decided that it would better serve the goals of Japanese stability to let him remain as ruler. On January 1, 1946, however, the emperor once and for all gave up any claims to being a sacred ruler by issuing a law that denied his god-like status as a descendant of the sun goddess.[PARAGRAPH:1] During the years of the occupation and afterward, every effort was made to "democratize" the throne by having the emperor mingle with the people. Even though he was personally distant and somewhat awkward in public, the emperor nevertheless became a popular figure. Pictures of the imperial family and stories of their activities became a steady part of weekly magazine and newspaper copy. A respected marine biologist with a number of books on that subject to his credit, Emperor Hirohito lived a modest, sober, and retired life when not involved in official functions. In 1972 he traveled to Europe and was met with hostile demonstrations. A 1975 trip to the United States resulted in a more friendly reception. Hirohito died on January 7, 1989, at the age of eighty-seven. Symbolic of his interest in science and in modernizing his country, Hirohito reportedly was buried with his microscope and a Mickey Mouse watch.</English>
		<Polish>[H1]Hirohito[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Cesarz Japonii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Żył: [\BOLD] 29 Kwietnia 1901 - 7 Stycznia 1989[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Tło:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]124. cesarz Japonii, panujący w latach 1926-1989. Zgodnie ze zwyczajem, cesarz Japonii po śmierci otrzymuje imię epoki, w czasie której panował. Z tego powodu obecnie nazywany jest cesarzem Showa. Hirohito został regentem w 1921, gdy jego ojciec, Yoshihito, wycofał się z życia publicznego z powodu choroby umysłowej. 25 grudnia 1926, po śmierci Yoshihito, został cesarzem. Jako nazwę okresu jego panowania przyjęto Showa (Oświecony Pokój). Był najdłużej panującym cesarzem w historii Japonii. W początkowych latach rządów Hirohito w Japonii narastały tendencje militarystyczno-nacjonalistyczne, które doprowadziły do działań mających na celu podbój Azji. W 1940 Japonia zawarła pakt z Niemcami i Włochami i zmilitaryzowała gospodarkę. Hirohito był temu przeciwny, ale realnie nie posiadał dostatecznej władzy, aby przeciwstawić się działaniom kolejnych rządów. Po kapitulacji Japonii w 1945 zachował godność cesarza, utracił jednak przysługujący mu wcześniej status boski, a jego rola została ograniczona do reprezentacyjnej. Zmarł 7 stycznia 1989 w wieku 88 lat, po 63 latach panowania.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
