<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OBATALA</Tag>
		<English>Pattaky of Obatala</English>
		<French>Pattaky d'Obatala</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Pattaky di Obatala</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pattaky Obatala</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OBATALAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A pattaky is the sum of all storys, myths, songs, dances and believes belonging to a deity, from the creator god, Olodumare, to the orishas ( greats kings of ancient times, made gods by Olodumare ).Obatala is the orisha of justice and art among others.</English>
		<Italian>Un pattaky è la somma di tutti i racconti, miti, canti, danze e credenze appartenenti a una divinità, donate dal dio creatore, Olodumare, agli Orisha (grandi re dei tempi antichi resi divinità da Olodumare). Obatala è l'orisha della giustizia e dell'arte.</Italian>
		<Polish>Obatala - u Jorubów z Nigerii boski stwórca i pan nieba, ziemi i ludzi z woli boga najwyższego Oloruna. Uważany za męża Oduduwy oraz ojca między innymi Jemandży. Jako Oriszanla ['wielkie bóstwo'] stoi na czele wszystkich innych bóstw. Jest symbolem ludzkiej świadomości. Jego kolorem jest biel. Wyznawcy, którzy uważają się za jego "dzieci" ubierają się na biało i noszą białe naszyjniki. W synkretycznej afrokubańskiej religii santeria utożsamiany zarówno z Matką Boską, jak i zmartwychwstałym Jezusem.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OBATALA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build this pattaky to increase your cities culture.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci questo pattaky per incrementare la cultura della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OGGUN</Tag>
		<English>Pattaky of Oggun</English>
		<French>Pattaky d'Oggun</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Pattaky di Oggun</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pattaky Ogoun</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OGGUN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A pattaky is the sum of all storys, myths, songs, dances and believes belonging to a deity, from the creator god, Olodumare, to the orishas ( greats kings of ancient times, made gods by Olodumare ).Oggun is the orisha of war, discoveries, science and health among others.</English>
		<German>A pattaky is the sum of all storys, myths, songs, dances and believes belonging to a deity, from the creator god, Olodumare, to the orishas ( greats kings of ancient times, made gods by Olodumare ).Oggun is the orisha of war, discoveries, science and health among others</German>
		<Italian>Un pattaky è la somma di tutti i racconti, miti, canti, danze e credenze appartenenti a una divinità, donate dal dio creatore, Olodumare, agli Orisha (grandi re dei tempi antichi resi divinità da Olodumare). Oggun è l'orisha della guerra, delle scoperte, della scienza e della salute.</Italian>
		<Polish>Ogoun, Ogun to bóg wojny w panteonie religii voodoo i candomblé. Jest panem ognia, krwi, żelaza i polityki. Patronuje kowalom, cywilizacji i technologii. Jego żoną jest bogini miłości Erzulie. Jego atrybutem jest szabla lub maczeta. Ulubionymi ofiarami są: pieczona wieprzowina, rum i tytoń. Czasami czczony pod postacią św. Jakuba Starszego. Zalicza się go zarówno do Rada Loa jak Petro Loa.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OGGUN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build this pattaky to increase your cities science and culture.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci questo pattaky per incrementare la cultura e la ricerca della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OLOFIN</Tag>
		<English>Pattaky of Olofin</English>
		<French>Pattaky d'Olofin</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Pattaky di Olofin</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pattaky Olofin</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OLOFIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A pattaky is the sum of all storys, myths, songs, dances and believes belonging to a deity, from the creator god, Olodumare, to the orishas (greats kings of ancient times, made gods by Olodumare). Olofin is the orisha sincretized to Jesus, the son of the great god, Olodumare.</English>
		<Italian>Un pattaky è la somma di tutti i racconti, miti, canti, danze e credenze appartenenti a una divinità, donate dal dio creatore, Olodumare, agli Orisha (grandi re dei tempi antichi resi divinità da Olodumare). Olofin è l'orisha sincresi di Gesù, figlio del grande Dio, Olodumare.</Italian>
		<Polish>Olofin -  bóstwa pochodzenia zachodnioafrykańskiego, bezpośrednia manifestacja najwyższego boga, nazywanego Olóňrun (Olódumŕrč).</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OLOFIN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build this pattaky to increase your cities culture.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci questo pattaky per incrementare la cultura della tua città.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OLOKUN</Tag>
		<English>Pattaky of Olokun</English>
		<French>Pattaky d'Olokun</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Pattaky di Olokun</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pattaky Olokun</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OLOKUN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A pattaky is the sum of all storys, myths, songs, dances and believes belonging to a deity, from the creator god, Olodumare, to the orishas ( greats kings of ancient times, made gods by Olodumare ).  Olokun is the orisha of sea and waters among others.</English>
		<Italian>Un pattaky è la somma di tutti i racconti, miti, canti, danze e credenze appartenenti a una divinità, donate dal dio creatore, Olodumare, agli Orisha (grandi re dei tempi antichi resi divinità da Olodumare).  Olokun è l'orisha del mare e dell'acqua.</Italian>
		<Polish>Olokun, u Jorubów z Nigerii i Beninu bóg oceanu, czczony przez rybaków. Uważany za męża swej siostry Olosy oraz Osu - bogini laguny. Według wierzeń rozsierdzony lekceważeniem ludzi miał ukarać mieszkańców ziemi potopem, jednak ludzkość została uchroniona przed zagładą przez Obatelę, który zakuł Olokuna w siedem żelaznych łańcuchów.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OLOKUN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build this pattaky to get gold and food form sea food resources.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci questo pattaky per ottenere bonus al commercio e al cibo derivanti dalle risorse di cibo marine.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OSHOSI</Tag>
		<English>Pattaky of Oshosi</English>
		<French>Pattaky d'Oshosi</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Pattaky di Oshosi</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pattaky Oshosi</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OSHOSI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A pattaky is the sum of all storys, myths, songs, dances and believes belonging to a deity, from the creator god, Olodumare, to the orishas ( greats kings of ancient times, made gods by Olodumare ).  Oshosi is the orisha of hunt among others.</English>
		<Italian>Un pattaky è la somma di tutti i racconti, miti, canti, danze e credenze appartenenti a una divinità, donate dal dio creatore, Olodumare, agli Orisha (grandi re dei tempi antichi resi divinità da Olodumare).  Oshosi è l'orisha della caccia.</Italian>
		<Polish>Oshosi to bóstwo polowań z panteonu Joruba</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OSHOSI_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build this pattaky to increase your cities get bonuses to food, gold and production from deers.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci questo pattaky per ottenere bonus alla produzione, al cibo e al commercio derivanti dai cervi.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_YORUBA_SHRINE</Tag>
		<English>Pattaky of Olodumare</English>
		<French>Pattaky d'Olodumare</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Pattaky di Olodumare</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Pattaky Olodumare</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_YORUBA_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A pattaky is the sum of all storys, myths, songs, dances and believes belonging to a deity, from the creator god, Olodumare, to the orishas ( greats kings of ancient times, made gods by Olodumare ).</English>
		<Italian>Un pattaky è la somma di tutti i racconti, miti, canti, danze e credenze appartenenti a una divinità, donate dal dio creatore, Olodumare, agli Orisha (grandi re dei tempi antichi resi divinità da Olodumare).</Italian>
		<Polish>Olodumare - w tradycyjnej teogonii Jorubów i synkretycznych religiach afrokubańskich (santeria) i afrobrazylijskich najwyższy z bogów, który zainicjował akt stworzenia, powołując do istnienia Obatalę i wszystkich innych oriszów. Jest jednocześnie źródłem zasad moralnych</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_YORUBA_SHRINE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Build this pattaky to get gold from every city in the world where Yoruba is present.</English>
		<Italian>Costruisci questo pattaky per ottenere oro da ogni città del mondo in cui è presente Yoruba.</Italian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_YORUBA</Tag>
		<English>Yoruba</English>
		<Polish>Joruba</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_YORUBA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Yoruba</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Yoruba</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Yoruba</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter:Neuter:Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Yoruba</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Yoruba</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Polish>Joruba</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_YORUBA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>RELIGION HELP: Yoruba doesn't work as usual religions does, it has a few particularities. The first is that the  missionary can only be built by first building a Pattaky of Olofin, which can be only constructed if Yoruba is your state religion and is present in the city, giving you no option but to start spreading from the founder city. Yoruba has no buildings, as the real religion never did, so they are replaced by the original form of transmission of this religion... pattakys. A pattaky is the sum of all storys, myths, songs, dances and believes belonging to a deity, from the creator god, Olodumare, to the orishas (greats kings of ancient times, made gods by Olodumare). In order to build the pattakys, you need to build first the pattaky of Olofin.The Yorùbá religion comprises religious beliefs and practices of the Yoruba people of old before the Yoruba community encountered Islam, Christianity and other faiths. It originated from Africa (chiefly in Nigeria and Benin Republic), and in the New World, where it has influenced or given birth to several Afro-American religions such as Lucumí in Cuba and Umbanda and Candomblé in Brazil in addition to the transplantation of the homeland religions. Though specific numbers are unknown, it is possibly the largest African-born religion in the world.[PARAGRAPH:2]Credits: icons by White Rabbit.</English>
		<Italian>ATTENZIONE: Yoruba non funziona come le altre religioni. La prima differenza è che i missionari possono essere addestrati solo dopo aver costruito un Pattaky di Olofin, che può essere costruito solo se Yoruba è la tua religione di stato ed è presente in città, lasciando come unica opzione il diffonderla dalla sua Città Santa. Yoruba non ha edifici, che vengono sostituiti dalla forma di trasmissione di questa religione ... i pattaky. Un pattaky è la somma di tutti i racconti, miti, canti, danze e credenze appartenenti a una divinità, donate dal dio creatore, Olodumare, agli Orisha (grandi re dei tempi antichi resi divinità da Olodumare). Per poter costruire gli altri pattaky, devi prima costruire il pattaky di Olofin.La religione Yorùbá comprende le pratiche e le credenze religiose che il popolo Yoruba aveva prima dell'incontro con l'Islam, la Cristianità e altre fedi. Ha avuto origine in Africa (principalmente in Nigeria e Benin) e si è poi diffusa nel Nuovo Mondo, dove ha influenzato o dato origine a molte teligioni afro-americane, come i Lucumí a Cuba e gli Umbanda e i Candomblé in Brasile. Anche se non esistono numeri precisi, Yoruba è probabilmente la religione afro-americana più diffusa al mondo.[PARAGRAPH:2]Crediti: icone di White Rabbit.</Italian>
		<Polish>Jorubowie - lud afrykański (populacja ok. 27 milionów osób - 2005), posługujący się językiem joruba z wielkiej rodziny nigero-kongijskiej (według niektórych klasyfikacji język ten należy do podrodziny kwa). Zamieszkują zachodnią część Afryki, największe skupiska w Nigerii, Beninie i Togo. Większość Jorubów mieszka obecnie w miastach, trudniąc się handlem i rzemiosłem (tkactwo, kowalstwo, rzeźba). Jorubowie mieszkający na wsi oprócz rolnictwa zajmują się tradycyjną sztuką ludową (rękodziełem). Jorubowie mają bogate tradycje historyczne i kulturowe. Jeszcze przed okresem kolonizacji europejskiej stworzyli cały system miast-państw, zarządzanych przez wspólnotę wodzów pod przywództwem władcy świętego według ich wierzeń miasta Ife. Sztuka Jorubów stoi na wysokim poziomie, znane są zwłaszcza wizerunki bóstw sporządzane z brązu oraz rytualne maski, dużą popularnością cieszą się ręcznie tkane makaty z motywami afrykańskimi i mitologicznymi. Spora część Jorubów oparła się zarówno chrystianizacji, jak i islamizacji, i wciąż pozostaje przy tradycyjnych wierzeniach. Ich mitologia i kultura jest obecna również na innych kontynentach, zwłaszcza w Ameryce Łacińskiej, co jest efektem wywozu z Afryki niewolników należących do tego właśnie ludu. Na Kubie, w nowych warunkach, zwłaszcza przy dużym nacisku na przyjęcie religii katolickiej, duchowość ta ewoluowała w kierunku synkretycznego kultu Santeria. W Brazylii wierzenia Jorubów stały się podstawą religii afrobrazylijskiej - candomblé, w nieznacznym stopniu synkretycznej z wierzeniami chrześcijańskimi. Jorubowie mają bardzo dobrze rozwiniętą mitologię, znani są też z należących do sfery kultowej wróżbiarstwa i zielarstwa.</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_YORUBA_QUOTE</Tag>
		<English>"A small child who is cutting a tree for the first time cannot know where the tree will fall, but an elder who has cut the tree before knows where it'll fall." - Yoruba Proverb</English>
		<French>"Un petit enfant qui coupe un arbre pour la première fois ne peut pas savoir où l'arbre va tomber, mais un aîné qui a coupé l'arbre avant sait où il va tomber." - Proverbe Yoruba</French>
		<Polish>"Małe dziecko ścinające drzewo po raz pierwszy nie wie jak to drzewo upadnie, ale starzec, który wiele razy ścinał drzewa wie jak one upadają." - przysłowie ludu Yoruba</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_YORUBA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Research Yoruba to Found a religion</English>
		<French>Recherchez Yoruba pour fonder une religion</French>
		<Spanish>Investiga la Yoruba para fundar una religión.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_YORUBA_MISSIONARY</Tag>
		<English>Yoruba Missionary</English>
		<French>Missionnaire Yoruba</French>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Missionario Yoruba</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Polish>Misjonarz Joruba</Polish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_YORUBA_MISSIONARY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Use this missionary to actively spread [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Yoruba religion[COLOR_REVERT] in friendly cities (or rival cities with whom you have [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Open Borders[COLOR_REVERT]). This increases your income if you have the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Pattaky of Olodumare[COLOR_REVERT].</English>
		<Italian>Usa questo missionario per diffondere velocemente [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Yoruba[COLOR_REVERT] nelle tue città, o nelle città straniere nelle quali hai [COLOR_HIGHLIGHT_TEXT]Diritto di passaggio[COLOR_REVERT]).</Italian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
