<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.firaxis.com ../../../Xml/Schema/Civ4Gametext.xsd">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWISS_DES</Tag>
		<English>Swiss Empire</English>
		<French>Swiss Empire</French>
		<German>Swiss Empire</German>
		<Italian>Swiss Empire</Italian>
		<Spanish>Swiss Empire</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWISS_SHORT</Tag>
		<English>Switzerland</English>
		<French>Switzerland</French>
		<German>Switzerland</German>
		<Italian>Switzerland</Italian>
		<Spanish>Switzerland</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWISS_ADJ</Tag>
		<English>Swiss</English>
		<French>Swiss</French>
		<German>Swiss</German>
		<Italian>Swiss</Italian>
		<Spanish>Swiss</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWISS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Archeological evidence suggests that hunter-gatherers were already settled in the lowlands north of the Alps in the late Paleolithic period. By the Neolithic period, the area was relatively densely populated. Remains of Bronze Age pile dwellings from as early as 3800 BC have been found in the shallow areas of many lakes. Around 1500 BC, Celtic tribes settled in the area. The Raetians lived in the eastern regions, while the west was occupied by the Helvetii.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 58 BC, the Helvetii tried to evade migratory pressure from Germanic tribes by moving into Gaul, but were defeated at Lawrenceburg by Julius Caesar's armies and then sent back. The alpine region became integrated into the Roman Empire and was extensively romanized in the course of the following centuries. The center of Roman administration was at Aventicum (Avenches). In 259, Alamanni tribes overran the Limes, putting the settlements on Swiss territory on the frontier of the Roman Empire. The first Christian bishoprics were founded in the 4th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]With the fall of the Western Roman Empire, Germanic tribes entered the area. Burgundians settled in the west; while in the north, Alamanni settlers slowly forced the earlier Celto-Roman population to retreat into the mountains. Burgundy became a part of the kingdom of the Franks in 534; two years later, the dukedom of the Alamans followed suit. In the Alaman-controlled region, only isolated Christian communities continued to exist and Irish monks re-introduced the Christian faith in the early 7th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]Under the Carolingian kings, the feudal system proliferated, and monasteries and bishoprics were important bases for maintaining the rule. The Treaty of Verdun of 843 assigned Upper Burgundy (the western part of what is today Switzerland) to Lotharingia, and Alemannia (the eastern part) to the eastern kingdom of Louis the German which would become part of the Holy Roman Empire.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 10th century, as the rule of the Carolingians waned, Magyars destroyed Basel in 917 and St. Gallen in 926. Only after the victory of King Otto I over the Magyars in 955 in the Battle of Lechfeld, were the Swiss territories reintegrated into the empire. In the 12th century, the dukes of Zähringen were given authority over part of the Burgundy territories which covered the western part of modern Switzerland. They founded many cities, including Fribourg in 1157, and Bern in 1191. The Zähringer dynasty ended with the death of Berchtold V in 1218, and their cities subsequently became reichsfrei (essentially a city-state within the Holy Roman Empire), while the dukes of Kyburg competed with the house of Habsburg over control of the rural regions of the former Zähringer territory. Under the Hohenstaufen rule, the alpine passes in Raetia and the St. Gotthard Pass gained importance. The latter especially became an important direct route through the mountains. Uri (in 1231) and Schwyz (in 1240) were accorded the Reichsfreiheit to grant the empire direct control over the mountain pass. Most of the territory of Unterwalden at this time belonged to monasteries which had previously become reichsfrei.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1291, the cantons of Uri, Schwyz, and Unterwalden united to defend the peace upon the death of Emperor Rudolf I of Habsburg. Their union, one nucleus of the Old Swiss Confederacy, is recorded in the Federal Charter, a document probably written after the fact in the early 14th century. At the battles of Morgarten in 1315 and Sempach 1386, the Swiss defeated the Habsburgs, gaining increased autonomy within the Holy Roman Empire. By 1353, the three original cantons had been joined by the cantons of Glarus and Zug and the city states of Lucerne, Zürich, and Bern, forming the "Old Federation" of eight states that persisted during much of the 15th century. Zürich was expelled from the Confederation from 1440 to 1450 due to a conflict over the territory of Toggenburg (the Old Zürich War). The Confederation's power and wealth increased significantly, with victories over Charles the Bold of Burgundy during the 1470s and the success of Swiss mercenaries.[PARAGRAPH:1]The traditional listing order of the cantons of Switzerland reflects this state, listing the eight "Old Cantons" first, with the city states preceding the founding cantons, followed by cantons that joined the Confederation after 1481, in historical order. The Swiss defeated the Swabian League in 1499 and gaining greater collective autonomy within the Holy Roman Empire, including exemption from the Imperial reforms of 1495 and immunity from most Imperial courts. In 1506. Pope Julius II engaged the Swiss Guard, which continues to serve the papacy to the present day. The expansion of the Confederation and the reputation of invincibility acquired during the earlier wars suffered a first setback in 1515 with the Swiss defeat in the Battle of Marignano.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Reformation in Switzerland began in 1523, led by Huldrych Zwingli, priest of the Great Minster church in Zürich since 1518. Zürich adopted the Protestant religion, joined by Berne, Basel, and Schaffhausen, while Lucerne, Uri, Schwyz, Nidwalden, Zug, Fribourg and Solothurn remained Catholic. Glarus and Appenzell were split. This led to inter-cantonal religious wars (Kappeler Kriege) in 1529 and 1531, because each canton usually made the opposing religion illegal, and to the formation of two diets, the Protestant one meeting in Aarau and the Catholic one in Lucerne (as well as the formal full diet still meeting usually in Baden) but the Confederation survived. During the Thirty Years' War, Switzerland was a relative "oasis of peace and prosperity" (Grimmelshausen) in war-torn Europe, mostly because all major powers in Europe depended on Swiss mercenaries, and would not let Switzerland fall in the hands of one of their rivals. Politically, they all tried to take influence, by way of mercenary commanders such as Jörg Jenatsch or Johann Rudolf Wettstein. The Drei Bünde of Grisons, at that point not yet a member of the Confederacy, were involved in the war from 1620, which led to their loss of the Valtellina in 1623.[PARAGRAPH:1]At the Treaty of Westphalia in 1648, Switzerland attained legal independence from the Holy Roman Empire. The Valtellina became a dependency of the Drei Bünde again after the Treaty and remained so until the founding of the Cisalpine Republic by Napoleon Bonaparte in 1797. In 1653, peasants of territories subject to Lucerne, Bern, Solothurn, and Basel revolted because of currency devaluation. Although the authorities prevailed in this Swiss peasant war, they did pass some tax reforms and the incident in the long term prevented an absolutist development as would occur at some other courts of Europe. The confessional tensions remained, however, and erupted again in the Battles of Villmergen in 1656 and 1712.[PARAGRAPH:1]During the French Revolutionary Wars, French armies enveloped Switzerland during their battles against Austria. In 1798 Switzerland was completely overrun by the French who turned it into the united Helvetic Republic, effectively abolishing the cantons. Having been imposed by a foreign power, and relying on French troops to survive, the Helvetic Republic was highly unpopular and encountered severe economic and political problems and uprisings. Its new constitution following not Swiss sentiment but the political philosophy of the French Revolution. Swiss resistance constitution reflects a wider European discontent with the French Revolution and conflicting Swiss notions of liberty. In 1803, Napoleon's Act of Mediation partially restored the sovereignty of the cantons, and the former tributary and allied territories of Aargau, Thurgau, Grisons, St. Gallen, Vaud and Ticino became cantons with equal rights. The Congress of Vienna of 1815 fully re-established Swiss independence and the European powers agreed to recognize permanent Swiss neutrality. At this time, Valais, Neuchatel and Geneva also joined Switzerland as new cantons, thereby extending Swiss territory for the last time.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Radical Party and liberals made up of urban bourgeoisie and burghers, which were strong in the largely Protestant cantons, obtained the majority in the Federal Diet in the early 1840s. They proposed a new Constitution for the Swiss Confederation which would draw the several cantons into a closer relationship. In 1843, the conservative city patricians and mountain or Ur-Swiss from the largely Catholic cantons were opposed to the new constitution. In addition to the centralization of the Swiss government, the new Constitution also included protections for trade and other progressive reform measures. In 1847, the Catholic cantons formed a separate union within the Confederation (the Sonderbund). This led to the Sonderbundskrieg. The Radicals, fearful of a Jesuit takeover, used their control of the national government and ordered the Sonderbund disbanded. When it refused the national army attacked in a brief civil war between the Catholic and the Protestant cantons. The Sonderbund was easily defeated in less than a month; there were about 130 killed. Apart from small riots, this was the last armed conflict on Swiss territory. As a consequence of the civil war, Switzerland adopted a federal constitution in 1848, amending it extensively in 1874 and establishing federal responsibility for defense, trade, and legal matters, leaving all other matters to the cantonal governments. From then, and over much of the 20th century, continuous political, economic, and social improvement has characterized Swiss history.[PARAGRAPH:1]During both World War I and World War II, Switzerland managed to keep a stance of armed neutrality, and was not involved militarily. However, precisely because of its neutral status, Switzerland was of considerable interest to all parties involved, as the scene for diplomacy, espionage, commerce, and as a safe haven for refugees.[PARAGRAPH:1]After the war, Swiss authorities considered the construction of a Swiss nuclear bomb. Leading nuclear physicists at the Federal Institute of Technology Zurich such as Paul Scherrer made this a realistic possibility, and in 1958 the population clearly voted in favour of the bomb. The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty of 1968 was seen as a valid alternative, however, and the bomb was never built. Opening speech by president Pascal Couchepin at the World Economic Forum, one of the many international organizations based in Switzerland From 1959, the Federal Council, elected by the parliament, is composed of members of the four major parties, the Protestant Free Democrats, the Catholic Christian Democrats, the left-wing Social Democrats and the right-wing People's Party, essentially creating a system without a sizeable parliamentary opposition (see concordance system), reflecting the powerful position of an opposition in a direct democracy.[PARAGRAPH:1]n 1963, Switzerland joined the Council of Europe. Women were granted the right to vote only in 1971, and an equal rights amendment was ratified in 1981. In 1979, parts of the canton of Bern attained independence, forming the new canton of Jura. Switzerland's role in many United Nations and international organizations helped to mitigate the country's concern for neutrality. In 2002, Switzerland was officially ratified as a member of the United Nations - the only country joining after agreement by a popular vote. Switzerland is not a member state of the EU, but has been (together with Liechtenstein) surrounded by EU territory since the joining of Austria in 1995. In 2005, Switzerland agreed to join the Schengen treaty and Dublin Convention by popular vote.</English>
		<French></French>
		<German></German>
		<Italian></Italian>
		<Spanish></Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DUFOUR</Tag>
		<English>Dufour</English>
		<French>Dufour</French>
		<German>Dufour</German>
		<Italian>Dufour</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dufour</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Dufour</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DUFOUR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Guilliaume Henri Dufour[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Swiss General, Engineer, Topographer, and President of the First Geneva Convention[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1787 - 1875 [PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Guillaume Henri Dufour was a Swiss general, bridge engineer, and topographer.  He served under Napoleon I and led the Swiss forces to victory against the Sonderbund.  He presided over the First Geneva Convention which established the international Red Cross.  He was the most famous president of the Swiss Federal Office of Topography from 1838 to 1865.  The Dufourspitze (the highest mountain in Switzerland) in Monte Rosa Massif is named for him.  Dufour's father Benedict was a Genevan watchmaker and farmer, who sent his son to school in Geneva, where he studied drawing and medicine.  In 1807, Dufour travelled to Paris to join the Ecole Polytechnique, then a military academy.  He studied descriptive geometry under Jean Nicolas Pierre Hachette, and graduated in 1809, going on to study study military engineering at the Ecole d'Application.  In 1810, he was sent to help defend Corfu against the British, and spent his time mapping the island's old fortifications.  By 1814, he had returned to France and was awarded the Croix de la Legion d'Honneur for his work repairing fortifications at Lyons.  In 1817, he returned to Geneva to become the commander of the Canton of Geneva's military engineers, as well as professor of mathematics at the University of Geneva, his duties included preparing a map of the Canton. In 1847, now-general Guillaume-Henri Dufour led a Swiss federal army of 100,000 and defeated the Sonderbund under Johan-Ulrich von Salis-Soglio in a month-long campaign.  He ordered his troops to spare the injured, anticipating the formation of the Red Cross which he presided over a few years later.</English>
		<French>[H1]Guilliaume Henri Dufour[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Swiss General, Engineer, Topographer, and President of the First Geneva Convention[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1787 - 1875 [PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Guillaume Henri Dufour was a Swiss general, bridge engineer, and topographer.  He served under Napoleon I and led the Swiss forces to victory against the Sonderbund.  He presided over the First Geneva Convention which established the international Red Cross.  He was the most famous president of the Swiss Federal Office of Topography from 1838 to 1865.  The Dufourspitze (the highest mountain in Switzerland) in Monte Rosa Massif is named for him.  Dufour's father Benedict was a Genevan watchmaker and farmer, who sent his son to school in Geneva, where he studied drawing and medicine.  In 1807, Dufour travelled to Paris to join the Ecole Polytechnique, then a military academy.  He studied descriptive geometry under Jean Nicolas Pierre Hachette, and graduated in 1809, going on to study study military engineering at the Ecole d'Application.  In 1810, he was sent to help defend Corfu against the British, and spent his time mapping the island's old fortifications.  By 1814, he had returned to France and was awarded the Croix de la Legion d'Honneur for his work repairing fortifications at Lyons.  In 1817, he returned to Geneva to become the commander of the Canton of Geneva's military engineers, as well as professor of mathematics at the University of Geneva, his duties included preparing a map of the Canton. In 1847, now-general Guillaume-Henri Dufour led a Swiss federal army of 100,000 and defeated the Sonderbund under Johan-Ulrich von Salis-Soglio in a month-long campaign.  He ordered his troops to spare the injured, anticipating the formation of the Red Cross which he presided over a few years later.</French>
		<German>[H1]Guilliaume Henri Dufour[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Swiss General, Engineer, Topographer, and President of the First Geneva Convention[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1787 - 1875 [PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Guillaume Henri Dufour was a Swiss general, bridge engineer, and topographer.  He served under Napoleon I and led the Swiss forces to victory against the Sonderbund.  He presided over the First Geneva Convention which established the international Red Cross.  He was the most famous president of the Swiss Federal Office of Topography from 1838 to 1865.  The Dufourspitze (the highest mountain in Switzerland) in Monte Rosa Massif is named for him.  Dufour's father Benedict was a Genevan watchmaker and farmer, who sent his son to school in Geneva, where he studied drawing and medicine.  In 1807, Dufour travelled to Paris to join the Ecole Polytechnique, then a military academy.  He studied descriptive geometry under Jean Nicolas Pierre Hachette, and graduated in 1809, going on to study study military engineering at the Ecole d'Application.  In 1810, he was sent to help defend Corfu against the British, and spent his time mapping the island's old fortifications.  By 1814, he had returned to France and was awarded the Croix de la Legion d'Honneur for his work repairing fortifications at Lyons.  In 1817, he returned to Geneva to become the commander of the Canton of Geneva's military engineers, as well as professor of mathematics at the University of Geneva, his duties included preparing a map of the Canton. In 1847, now-general Guillaume-Henri Dufour led a Swiss federal army of 100,000 and defeated the Sonderbund under Johan-Ulrich von Salis-Soglio in a month-long campaign.  He ordered his troops to spare the injured, anticipating the formation of the Red Cross which he presided over a few years later.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Guilliaume Henri Dufour[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Swiss General, Engineer, Topographer, and President of the First Geneva Convention[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1787 - 1875 [PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Guillaume Henri Dufour was a Swiss general, bridge engineer, and topographer.  He served under Napoleon I and led the Swiss forces to victory against the Sonderbund.  He presided over the First Geneva Convention which established the international Red Cross.  He was the most famous president of the Swiss Federal Office of Topography from 1838 to 1865.  The Dufourspitze (the highest mountain in Switzerland) in Monte Rosa Massif is named for him.  Dufour's father Benedict was a Genevan watchmaker and farmer, who sent his son to school in Geneva, where he studied drawing and medicine.  In 1807, Dufour travelled to Paris to join the Ecole Polytechnique, then a military academy.  He studied descriptive geometry under Jean Nicolas Pierre Hachette, and graduated in 1809, going on to study study military engineering at the Ecole d'Application.  In 1810, he was sent to help defend Corfu against the British, and spent his time mapping the island's old fortifications.  By 1814, he had returned to France and was awarded the Croix de la Legion d'Honneur for his work repairing fortifications at Lyons.  In 1817, he returned to Geneva to become the commander of the Canton of Geneva's military engineers, as well as professor of mathematics at the University of Geneva, his duties included preparing a map of the Canton. In 1847, now-general Guillaume-Henri Dufour led a Swiss federal army of 100,000 and defeated the Sonderbund under Johan-Ulrich von Salis-Soglio in a month-long campaign.  He ordered his troops to spare the injured, anticipating the formation of the Red Cross which he presided over a few years later.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Guilliaume Henri Dufour[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Swiss General, Engineer, Topographer, and President of the First Geneva Convention[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1787 - 1875 [PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Guillaume Henri Dufour was a Swiss general, bridge engineer, and topographer.  He served under Napoleon I and led the Swiss forces to victory against the Sonderbund.  He presided over the First Geneva Convention which established the international Red Cross.  He was the most famous president of the Swiss Federal Office of Topography from 1838 to 1865.  The Dufourspitze (the highest mountain in Switzerland) in Monte Rosa Massif is named for him.  Dufour's father Benedict was a Genevan watchmaker and farmer, who sent his son to school in Geneva, where he studied drawing and medicine.  In 1807, Dufour travelled to Paris to join the Ecole Polytechnique, then a military academy.  He studied descriptive geometry under Jean Nicolas Pierre Hachette, and graduated in 1809, going on to study study military engineering at the Ecole d'Application.  In 1810, he was sent to help defend Corfu against the British, and spent his time mapping the island's old fortifications.  By 1814, he had returned to France and was awarded the Croix de la Legion d'Honneur for his work repairing fortifications at Lyons.  In 1817, he returned to Geneva to become the commander of the Canton of Geneva's military engineers, as well as professor of mathematics at the University of Geneva, his duties included preparing a map of the Canton. In 1847, now-general Guillaume-Henri Dufour led a Swiss federal army of 100,000 and defeated the Sonderbund under Johan-Ulrich von Salis-Soglio in a month-long campaign.  He ordered his troops to spare the injured, anticipating the formation of the Red Cross which he presided over a few years later.</Spanish>
	</TEXT> 
</Civ4GameText>
